LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
SEASON VI
EPISODE 6
Welcome to Last Week Tonight.
I'm John Oliver,
thank you for joining us.
A quick recap of the week,
a busy one for the administration,
from Trump's attacks
on the Affordable Healthcare Act,
to his threats to close the southern
border, to Bernhardt's hearing.
He is Trump's pick for
Secretary of the Interior
and a former oil lobbyist,
so he's pretty swampy,
which some activists drew attention
to, as you'll see over his shoulder.
I have worked with many of you
and your staff.
I have met with many of you
in person, and by phone,
on various issues that were
of a concern to you
and I will always make myself
available to your requests.
Yeah! Nicely done. That woman
in the mask was there for a while.
Because ten minutes later?
Still there. 20 minutes? Still there!
45 minutes? Still there!
An hour later? Still there!
It is pretty funny, although,
I would not be doing my job
if I didn't point out
that this is a "swamp creature"
and technically what she's wearing
is a "lagoon creature" mask,
and that distinction
might not mean much to you
but in the aquatic goblin communities,
confusing the two is pretty racist.
This week was dominated by
the fallout from the Mueller Report.
William Barr submitted this
summary of its contents to Congress.
The investigation did not establish
that members of the Trump campaign
conspired or coordinated
with Russian government
in its election
interference activities.
When it comes
to the question of obstruction,
Barr said Mueller did not have
enough evidence to prosecute
but could not
exonerate the president.
Report did not establish a conspiracy
between Russia and Trump's campaign,
which is undeniably
good news for the president.
The fact that Mueller did not exonerate
him on obstruction of justice
is pretty remarkable.
It might
prompt headlines like:
"President May Have
Obstructed Justice."
Which is why it's been weird
to see
the good news for the president
often shoving aside the bad.
The O.J. Simpson murders were
not reported as:
"Affordable House
Becomes Available In Brentwood."
There's something pretty big
missing from that headline.
All week, the president's supporters
took their one good news
and rounded it up to two.
No collusion.
No obstruction of justice.
No obstruction, no collusion.
No collusion,
no obstruction, nothing.
Victorious, exonerated,
vindicated.
Trump was not
completely exonerated.
The report literally used the words
"does not exonerate him."
Mueller could have been clearer
is if he put hand clap emojis
between every word.
Normally this is where we would
do a deep dive into the details,
explaining all the possible
implications.
The problem is...
We still haven't seen it.
Congress hasn't seen it.
Even the president hasn't seen it.
We know what Trump's own attorney
general thinks we need to know,
a man who, unsolicited
and before he got his current job,
sent top DOJ officials a memo ruling
out obstruction of justice charges
against the president.
There are plenty of qualifiers
and questions left here,
it's strange to see Trump's
supporters saying this.
One year, 10 months and six days.
$40 million of taxpayer money wasted.
It was all a waste.
How did we ever waste
two years of America on this?
All the Democrats yakking,
billions of hours of hot air
coming out of Democrat mouths.
All they got for it was this t-shirt.
They got nothing out of it.
If there's one authority figure I trust
on free shirts, it's gonna be that man.
There is no way actual U.S. currency
was exchanged for that outfit.
He's dressed like a personal-injury
attorney whose portrait
just got MeToo'ed off the wall
of an airport Palm steakhouse.
DOJ could well take in more
than it spent on the investigation
just in the form of asset forfeitures
from Paul Manafort alone.
As we've said before, even if
the investigation didn't conclude
Trump conspired with the Russians,
doesn't mean it was a waste of time.
It's easy to forget how much
we've already learned,
directly or indirectly, from
Mueller's investigation,
as so much has slowly
trickled out over two years.
Try and imagine
that it all came out at once,
and a single headline said:
"Russia Confirmed
To Have Interfered In Election"
"And President's Campaign Manager,
Multiple Advisers Convicted Of Crimes"
"And Trump And His Team Lied
About Business With Russia,"
"And Trump May Have Committed
Campaign Finance Violations"
"To Cover Up Affair With Adult Film
Star, After His Wife Gave Birth,"
"And Which He Also Attempted
To Continue, But Ended Up"
"Sitting Next To Her In A Hotel Room
And Watching "Shark Week.'"
All of that happened,
and we know it,
as a result
of Mueller's investigation.
This scandal has been sitting
in plain sight for so long,
we've stopped noticing it,
much like a woman in an
increasingly-sweaty fish mask.
The weirdest thing about this
situation is how somehow not-weird
this objectively ridiculous state
of affairs is starting to feel.
And now this.
In Honor of Opening Day:
A Reminder From L.A.'s Vin Scully
That Great Baseball Commentary
Doesn't Have To Be About Baseball.
Looking at Clayton Kershaw's
uniform with all the dirt on it,
it reminds us about the importance
of dirt to certain people.
Beards evolved number one,
because ladies like them.
It was the idea of frightening off
adversaries and wild animals.
There's a story that redheads will
be extinct by the year 2060.
There also seems to be a dispute
as to whether Betsy Ross
ever lived in Philadelphia's
popular Betsy Ross Home.
Just think about
how tough that rabbit was:
first it gets eaten by a snake,
the snake gets chopped to pieces,
then it gets picked up
by people and lives.
Line drive base hit to center
by Hendrik
and the Dodgers
are in business.
First and second
and nobody out.
Moving on. Our main story tonight
concerns professional wrestling.
Literally the only good excuse
to wear a onesie.
Babies,
you're not pulling it off.
Put on some jeans and a button
down, like a fucking person.
I want to talk about the undisputed
corporate champion of wrestling,
the WWE, formerly known
as the WWF until, and this is true,
they lost a court case to
the World Wildlife Fund,
presumably thanks to that fund's
powerful team of panda lawyers.
Before we go any further,
let me say this: I like wrestling.
You might be surprised to hear that,
but it's objectively entertaining.
The WWE has, over the years,
delivered numerous, ludicrous
and genuinely incredible moments,
from when Jake "The Snake" Roberts
set a live cobra on "Macho Man",
to the time Strowman suplexed
the Big Show off the turnbuckle,
to when "Stone Cold" Steve Austin
drove a beer truck into the arena
and sprayed the corporation
with a beer hose,
not to be mistaken with the time
Kurt Angle drove a milk truck
and sprayed "Stone Cold"
Steve Austin with a milk hose.
And whatever the fuck this is.
My God, here we go!
What's gonna happen?
Look out!
My God!
Everything about that
is fantastic.
My favorite part is after
the table was lit on fire,
the commentator asking:
"What's gonna happen?"
What was he expecting to happen?
The table's on fire!
Here comes a hibachi chef, and
he's making those onion volcanoes!
Now he's doing
indoor s'mores! Oh my God!
It is worth talking about the WWE
tonight, for multiple reasons.
First,
it's astonishingly popular.
It has over a billion
fans on social media,
it has two highly-rated cable shows,
its own streaming network,
reality shows, video games
and even a movie studio,
which has produced hits as
"The Scorpion King", "Walking Tall",
"The Marine", "The Marine 2",
"The Marine 3", "The Marine 4",
"The Marine 5", "The Marine 6",
and, of course, "Lincoln".
By the way, their first choice
to play Abraham Lincoln
was Brutus "The Barber" Beefcake,
but he wasn't available,
so the role went to Daniel Day-Lewis,
who was, he was fine.
This company makes
a lot of money.
Last year, it generated
a record $930 million in revenue.
WrestleMania alone,
which is taking place next Sunday,
is one of the most valuable
sports brands in the world,
ranking higher than the World
Series, which actually makes sense,
'cause while the World Series
is mostly spent
watching a millionaire
think about whether to throw a ball,
WrestleMania
involves things like this.
No, oh my God.
For the love of mankind. Shane
just exploded through our table.
Are you not entertained?
How could any other TV show top that?
I would argue every other show
should be called "Not A Guy
Exploding Through A Table."
And this show should be
very much included in that.
The other reason that it's worth
talking about the WWE
is the prevalence
of stories like these.
Eddie Guerrero, found dead
in a Minneapolis hotel room.
The World Wrestling star
was just 38 years old.
We have just confirmed that
Randy "Macho Man" Savage has died.
Chyna, one of the most famous
wrestlers in the 90's has now died.
She was 46 years old.
Pro wrestling legend "King Kong"
Bundy has died at the age of 61.
He came here,
we were in Studio A.
And he lifted me almost
to the ceiling.
Just 61 years old,
these wrestlers dying early.
That is a harrowing statement
from Brian Kilmeade,
slightly dampened by his wonder
at how high the big man lifted him.
Did Bundy offer him?
Did Kilmeade ask?
I wouldn't be surprised if one
of his stock interview questions is:
"Up! Up! Horsey ride!"
Kilmeade is not wrong there.
Wrestlers dying early
is a troubling trend.
FiveThirtyEight tracked the rate
of deaths among WWF wrestlers
and findings were startling.
Here is the expected death rate
among the population as a whole.
Here is the rate among former NFL
players. And here, among wrestlers.
That is shockingly high! You'd
expect that line to be labeled:
"Test Pilots
Who Lied On Their Resume"
or "Zookeepers Who Aren't Gonna
Let Some Baboon Screech At Them."
Enough sass-mouth, buddy!
Put some respect on my name!
With that in mind, tonight,
a week ahead of WrestleMania,
let's take a look
at how the WWE does business
and how it treats its wrestlers.
You can't talk about the WWE without
talking about its chairman and CEO,
Vince McMahon, because he is
incredibly powerful, as you can see
in this actual photo he took
for a fitness magazine:
"Scary Grandpa Who Looks Like
A Big, Bumpy Hot Dog Quarterly."
Vince bought the company
from his dad
and has overseen its
ascent into the mainstream.
Before he came along, wrestling was
splintered into fiefdoms,
all of which
had their own broadcasts.
Welcome to the special edition of
World-Class Championship Wrestling.
Welcome to
Mid South Wrestling.
Mid-Atlantic Wrestling.
Welcome
to the Universal Wrestling Federation.
I get wrestling is all about spectacle
and pageantry but a tuxedo, Jim?
Tone it down a notch,
you're not at a fucking gala.
Michael, as usual, no notes,
you look great, keep living your truth.
Throughout the '80s and '90s,
Vince McMahon eliminated or absorbed
his competitors
and now one giant company
holds a monopoly on the industry.
It's impossible to overstate
just how involved Vince is.
He's not just CEO. He oversees
storylines, scripts,
playing a fictionalized
version of himself,
as the show's overarching villain,
his choices of how to dramatize
have been pretty questionable,
whether it's him forcing female
wrestlers to strip
or beating up his supposed
illegitimate son, Hornswoggle,
or dropping the ultimate racial
slur as part of a comedic skit.
Sup, boss?
How you doing?
- What's good in the 'hood?
- Trying to take care of business.
Keep it up, my nigga.
That is rough to watch.
And remember:
he's in complete control
of those scripts.
No one is making him do that.
While he is playing a villain there,
there are other ways
that that can be achieved.
Darth Vader was a great villain,
not once did he drop the n-word.
R-2 said it pretty much nonstop,
it's why he kept getting bleeped.
The fact that McMahon is an
active character in wrestling
gives us an opportunity, he's taken a
lot of in-ring abuse over the years.
At points where
you're gonna be disgusted,
for say, using the n-word,
I can now simply play a clip like this,
of The Rock smashing him
with a trashcan lid.
I grabbed this!
Wrestling's good.
It's just very good.
While the character is an asshole,
the real Vince is also an asshole.
Many fans hate him because while
the WWE has made him a billionaire,
many wrestlers
say he's treated them terribly.
Listen to Bret "Hitman" Hart,
one of the biggest wrestlers
speaking about his former boss.
Vince McMahon has always treated
wrestlers like circus animals.
All these wrestlers that have
broke their backs for years
end up with nothing when it's over,
they sort of take you out back
and dump you out, and that's
the life of a professional wrestler.
That may sound extreme.
But Hart has good reason to be angry.
His own brother, Owen,
died wrestling for Vince.
Hart is far from alone in voicing
grievances about his former employer.
The shocking thing is the extent
to which he's shielded himself
from responsibility
for wrestlers' welfare.
The main way
he's done this is simple,
while you might reasonably think
that the wrestlers employed by him
are his employees,
they're actually not.
They're merely
independent contractors.
Which as former wrestler Jesse Ventura
pointed out on Howard Stern, is insane.
How are they self-employed
when you're signed exclusively...
- You can't work for nobody else.
- It's a monopoly.
They tell you when and where you'll
work. They tell you who you'll work.
- They control your life.
- And you're an independent contractor.
And yet, they call you
an independent contractor.
How has the government allowed them
to get away with that for 40 years?
Yeah, he's got a point.
An independent contractor
is someone that you might hire
for a specific, limited task,
like a plumber, or an accountant.
Wrestlers aren't either,
apart from this wrestling plumber
and this wrestling accountant.
The vast majority
are totally different.
And as independent contractors,
wrestlers are exempt
from most discrimination
and occupational safety laws.
They don't get paid annual leave,
pensions, or health insurance.
When you look at the
Department of Labor and the IRS's
criteria for independent
contractors, it's a complete joke
to think that they apply
to Vince's wrestlers.
The IRS states that independent
contractors should be free to work
when and for whom
they choose.
Vince's wrestlers sign exclusive
contracts, so that's bullshit.
Guidelines say someone's
probably not an independent contractor
if the success or continuation
of a business
depends to a degree
on the services they provide.
Are wrestlers essential
to World Wrestling Entertainment?
It's not called "World Totally
Empty Ring Entertainment."
So there that might be clue.
If I might quote
the company's own website:
"WWE performers are
the company's greatest asset,"
"without our performers,
WWE would not exist."
When wrestlers might work years ago
for different organizations,
it made sense
to call them contractors.
But now that WWE has
a chokehold on this industry,
it makes as much sense to call them
that as it does to call Jimmy Carter
a "panty-dropping fuck machine."
It's just clearly not true...
anymore.
For what it's worth, back in 1986,
Ventura tried to unionize wrestlers
which could've improved
their working conditions,
but McMahon stamped it out hard.
If that makes you want to see
someone stamp him out hard,
I have some good news.
Sweet chin music.
Shawn, the sweet chin
music to Mr. McMahon.
Shawn has knocked out the owner
of the World Wrestling Federation!
Wrestling is better
than the things you like.
The lack of a union to advocate
for wrestlers
means that Vince
gets to call all the shots.
While every sports league has
an off-season for athletes to recover,
the WWE works its wrestlers
year-round, multiple times a week,
both on TV and in untelevised
so-called "house shows".
And big stars may be able
to command big money for that,
but not every wrestler
is a big star.
Whenever we've gotten glimpses
of wrestlers' contracts,
they contain
astonishing clauses.
If a wrestler is unable to wrestle
for six weeks because of an injury,
the company
can terminate their contract.
Another releases the company
from all liability for damage resulting
in permanent injury or death,
even if caused by its own negligence.
Which is a crazy thing for McMahon
to put in a contract.
Enough to make you want to see him
be on his own medical mishap.
How about your foot?
You like that?
What do you think about that?
Say what you like about that,
still technically more helpful
than a visit from Dr. Oz.
When you take this together
with wrestlers
as independent contractors,
in a monopolized industry,
free from meaningful oversight
and able to be fired at any time,
you wind up with an environment
with potential for unsafe conduct.
Before Lance McNaught died
at 29 of heart failure,
while struggling with addiction
to painkillers,
he spoke of the pressure
that he felt:
"If you get hurt, you work through it,
cause you'll lose your spot."
Another top wrestler, CM Punk,
has questioned the advice
given by a WWE doctor
following an incident in the ring.
I got hit with something
and I got a concussion.
But we were leaving for Europe the next
day, so Doc was leaning on me going:
"Do you have a concussion
or can you go to Europe?"
I was like: "You pigs,
I'll go to Europe. Whatever."
That's on me, that's my fault.
I'm dry-heaving after every match.
I'm either puking for real
or I'm just dry heaving.
Doc's like:
"You're sick, here's a Z-Pak."
They Z-Pak me to death,
I shit my pants on a SmackDown.
He did! He actually did that
and we found that episode
and out of common courtesy,
we are not going to show it to you.
But, this is his face
as it was happening.
Punk even tweeted about it:
"Just shit my britches on Smackdown.
Please retweet."
Something the WWE then
made him take down,
even though it's the best
tweet ever written.
Try and think of a better tweet!
Have you got one?
Does it say: "Shit my britches,
please retweet?"
Then it's not better, is it?
Stand down.
It gets much worse than concussed
wrestlers shitting themselves,
because wrestlers' bodies
regularly get smashed up
and undergo general wear and tear,
damage that's cumulative.
McMahon doesn't provide
health insurance
for anything other than injuries
that occur inside the ring.
The extent to which he's denied
any responsibility
for their welfare is astonishing.
Watch him respond to a question
about wrestler deaths.
A reason why these people
would be dying under the age of 45?
Why don't you ask
yourself that question?
Are you indicating that's
my responsibility?
I'm asking you if it's in any way
falls on your shoulders?
I would accept no responsibility
whatsoever for their untimely deaths.
You've got that little look like:
"How can you possibly say that?"
But none whatsoever?
They were part of your organization.
They worked a couple
of hundred nights a year for you.
Oh my God!
What are you doing,
you weird, weird man?
While all of that is ridiculous,
my favorite response
isn't the weird face or
the smacking of the papers.
It's: "Why are wrestlers dying early?"
with "Why don't you ask yourself?"
In terms of dodges,
is certifiably insane.
Maybe because
that journalist doesn't employ
any wrestlers and while I know that
you don't think you do either,
you're fucking
wrong about that.
The company will say that they've
transformed in recent years.
They have taken positive steps,
like banning chair shots to the head
and introducing
concussion protocols.
CM Punk's experience suggests there
may be room for improvement.
Some of the other steps they've taken
under their "Talent Wellness Program"
are underwhelming, like the fact they
now have annual physical examinations.
That's nothing. I have to take
one of those every year
to host this show and I've never
once exploded through this table.
It's in the name
of our show, now.
The program also provides for things
like cardiovascular and brain testing,
although they're still responsible
for their health insurance.
Company pays for addiction
treatment for former wrestlers,
that doesn't address the issues that
get them hooked on pain medication.
Some have had to drag their
bodies back to the WWE,
because they have
no other financial option.
"Rowdy" Roddy Piper continued
wrestling into his 40's and 50's
and listen to him explain why.
Wrestling has
a tremendous entrance plan.
You come in
as "Boy, here you are."
Everything's wonderful,
it's got no exit plan.
"Rowdy" Roddy Piper should know.
A few months ago,
he climbed back into the ring.
What would you have me do at 49
my pension plan, I can't
take out till I'm 65.
I'm not gonna make 65,
let's just face facts, guys.
Sadly, he was right about that.
Roddy Piper died in 2015
at the age of 61.
While nothing I say can or should
make that okay,
I hope that watching
this clip of Vince in the ring
gives you just
a tiny piece of catharsis.
He's a billionaire.
He owns this company.
Lucifer's lips on the biggest
ass in the WWF. Hell yeah!
The reassuring thing there is,
you can fake being kicked in the face
or hit in the head with a bedpan,
but there is no faking that.
So, I guess the question is,
is there any hope here?
Incredibly, there might be.
There is one group that even McMahon
occasionally seems to listen to
and that's the fans.
They have a strong,
independent voice in the WWE.
And have been vocal over the years,
from the dealings with Saudi Arabia,
to its treatment of female wrestlers,
who have come a long way
from the old days of so-called
"Bra and Panty" matches.
Fans online launched a hashtag
#GiveDivasAChance campaign
to feature women more
prominently, to which Vince responded:
"We hear you. Keep watching."
Next week, for the first time ever,
WrestleMania will be headlined
by a women's match.
Wrestling fans don't just go along
with whatever the company
tells them to cheer and boo.
They know what they like
and what they don't like.
The WWE tried for years to make
Roman Reigns a Superstar hero
on the level of The Rock.
But fans just didn't like him
and they let him
and the WWE know about that.
And keep in mind, Roman Reigns
is supposed to be a good guy.
Fuck you, Roman!
Asshole!
Roman sucks!
Go away!
They booed him nonstop
for eight minutes!
Might think that's harsh,
but it's the rational response
to someone with
permanently wet hair.
How can it always be wet? You look
like a pedophile out for a jog.
The fans have a big voice here.
They care about these wrestlers
and continue to do that long after
the WWE has abandoned them.
Nowhere was the extent
of this devotion more obvious
than when Jake "The Snake" needed
help paying for medical expenses.
Jake has no insurance, he didn't have
money to pay for the surgery.
We had to come up
with a solution.
We put up a page on Indiegogo
to try to raise the money.
Unfucking real.
- Where we at?
- Holy cow.
7,000.
In one night?
But the really cool thing
that came out of that
is Jake got to see
how much the fans really cared.
All those years, I guess
they did mean something.
Yeah, those years
meant a lot to fans.
That's why they want him and others
to be taken care of.
There've been multiple GoFundMe
campaigns to cover both health care
and funeral expenses for wrestlers
that fans have stepped up for.
Fans shouldn't be the ones
shouldering that responsibility.
Even the NFL,
for all its massive faults,
now offers players health reimbursement
accounts and have established
a "Legacy Fund" for older players
who may be dealing with health issues.
When you've lost the moral high
ground to the fucking NFL,
you are
morally subterranean.
Here is where the potential
opportunity is,
WrestleMania, the biggest event
in the WWE's calendar, is next Sunday.
And if fans in that arena want
McMahon to help pay
for wrestlers' long-term health care
or just to call them employees,
they could choose
to make up chants about that.
The event is live, they won't be
able to cut the chants out.
I'm not saying that fans should
do that. Or make lots of signs.
I really hope they make their
voices heard on this,
because given that
Business Hulk here is a billionaire
on the broken backs
of his non-employees,
the very least he can do is show
the same dedication to wrestlers
they have shown to his company.
I haven't really said any of this
in the preferred language
of wrestling fans.
So, maybe this will help.
Wrestling fans!
You cheered at Royal Rumble.
You thrilled at Hell in a Cell.
You yelled at SummerSlam.
Get ready to scream
for something new.
I'm talking about all wrestlers having
access to retirement accounts,
workers comp
and family and medical leave.
How would you feel about watching
the most electrifying superstars
do the unthinkable,
the "F" to the agents,
65, 70, 75 and beyond!
Performing thrilling moves
like walking comfortably,
bending their knees
past a 90-degree angle
and spending quality time
with their grandchildren!
You could see all this
if a system was put in place
that gave wrestlers
things like an off-season,
the human body was not designed to do
things like this 200 nights a year.
We're talking about bringing premature
wrestler deaths back in line.
Did somebody say tables?
He's gonna need a doctor,
and preferably one who won't
make him shit his pants on SmackDown.
Please retweet!
At WrestleMania 35,
why not join thousands of fans in
calling for your favorite wrestlers
to be employees
so you never have to pay
for their future surgeries
through GoFundMe?
If Mr. McMahon doesn't like it,
you know what he can do.
Some wrestlers were harmed
in the making of this video.
That's our show, thanks for watching.
See you next week, goodnight!
LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
END OF EPISODE 6,
SEASON VI