♪ ♪
[Cheers and applause]
John: Welcome, welcome,
welcome to "last week tonight."
I'm John Oliver, thank you so
much for joining us.
Just time for a quick recap of
the week, and it was a busy one
for the president, who, in
between claiming his father was
born in Germany when he was born
in New York, mispronouncing the
word "origins" as "oranges"
repeatedly, and trolling
Joe biden for touching women...
which seems, y'know, a bit
fucking rich... made a major and
shocking decision on Thursday
regarding the federal reserve.
President trump is said to of
selected Herman Cain for the
federal reserve board.
A former pizza executive
turned radio talk show host who
dropped his 2012 republican
presidential bid amid sexual
harassment allegations, not a
typical resume for a federal
reserve board member.
John: Oh, really?
You sure about that?
You think the resume of
pizza maker, talk show host, and
alleged sexual harasser would be
pretty unusual for the fed?
Well, why don't you tell that to
the rest of the board, six
Mario batalis?
But it is true, picking
Herman Cain for the federal
reserve is bonkers, and comes
just two weeks after trump also
said he'll nominate
Stephen Moore, a TV commentator
and fellow at a conservative
think tank.
And these two likely nominees
are causing more concern than
your typical trump
administration appointee, and
for good reason, as I'll let a
former deputy secretary of the
treasury explain.
It's one thing to be putting,
you know, your political friends
and cronies, you know, within
the agencies, but to put them on
the board of the central bank is
something that is... that has to
be done very, very cautiously,
because the moment the fed loses
credibility, it's almost
game over.
John: Now, that's a pretty
bold statement.
She's basically saying,
"go ahead, put 'Mr. oops' in
charge of the department of
energy, or a mint condition cpr
dummy in charge of opioids and
middle east peace, or hand the
commerce department over to a
man who looks like
Jackson pollock if he had lived
or Moby if he had died.
But the fed?
You don't fuck around with the
fed.
And that is because a lot of
America's economic power depends
on people's trust in the
stability of the dollar.
It is the world's reserve
currency in part because the fed
is seen as a reliable,
independent institution.
Trump has actually already
filled four of the fed's seven
seats... including the chairman,
Jerome Powell... but those
appointments didn't get much
press because all of these
people are fundamentally
qualified.
Cain and Moore, however, aren't.
Cain has argued for a return to
the gold standard, a virtually
unheard-of opinion among
respected economists, while
Moore is a tireless advocate of
supply-side economics, he helped
design the tax cut that blew a
hole in Kansas' budget, and once
asked if the country even really
needs a fed.
But instead of spending time
breaking down why their economic
views should be disqualifying,
I'd like to make a point that
requires no knowledge of
monetary policy whatsoever, and
that is that these two guys are
goofs.
They're just a pair of
dangerously goofy goofs.
And this isn't actually a job
where that's okay.
Fed board members are famously
careful with anything they say
in public because markets can
react violently.
Just two words from the fed
chair sent markets soaring last
November, and these two are not
known for thinking before they
speak.
Here's is Stephen Moore on a CNN
panel last year discussing
stormy Daniels and deciding to
blow the doors off the room with
this awesome joke.
We're discussing a sitting
president being sued by a
porn star, and it's part of
almost like the routine of
today's news cycle, which is the
interesting part of it.
Kevin, are you saying that a
porn star would actually try to
call attention to herself?
Shocking, right?
I mean, that's what
porn stars do!
John: Nailed it.
You nailed it, Stephen.
You don't want that man's mouth
moving markets.
Now, as for Herman Cain, let me
remind you, this is a man who,
when he ran for president, once
asked a crowd of
Cuban-Americans, "how do you say
'delicious' in Cuban?,"
he bragged about not knowing the
president of
"uzbeki-beki-beki-
Stan-Stan," and had this
memorable moment in a
presidential debate:
A poet once said, "life can
be a challenge, life can seem
impossible, but it's never easy
when there's so much on the
line."
All right, so, it turns out
that quote wasn't exactly
poetry.
It was, strictly speaking, a
song from the end of
"pokemon the movie" from 2000.
John: It's true.
It's true.
Herman Cain quoted this pokemon
movie during a presidential
debate, which is both the worst
place to do that and also
technically the best place to do
it, because who on that stage is
going to risk calling you out?
"Excuse me, but I believe my
opponent just attributed that
quote to a poet, when it really
comes from the theme song to the
film 'pokemon the movie 2000,'
whose lyrics I also know by
heart, and oh, god, I'm just now
realizing this is worse for me
than it is for him, please carry
on.
Ignore what I just said."
And as if all that weren't
disqualifying enough, I know
personally that Herman Cain
should not be on the fed,
because after he dropped out of
that presidential race, I did a
series of interviews with him
for "the daily show" where he
pretended to be in office, and
in which he, for some reason,
did anything I asked him to do.
Anything.
Watch.
Look into that camera and
convince Nicolas cage to give
that constitution back.
Nicolas, bring back our
constitution.
I respect you, cage, but get a
grip.
We have just had the results
back from your latest
presidential physical, and it
turns out you have telepathic
powers.
Look into that camera and
convince the Chinese that they
need to step down.
It's your move.
Oil is spilling everywhere
and it has devastated America's
national parks.
Gather those most affected and
explain to them why their
sacrifice is not in vain.
[Horn blares]
Creatures of the forest,
assemble!
John: If any part of you is
thinking, how did I get him to
do that stuff?
I just asked him.
Once.
He took orders from some
birdy twit with a pixie cut.
And look, at this point, you may
be wondering what trump sees in
these two men.
Well, just that.
He wants people who will do
exactly what he tells them to.
You've just seen how well Cain
takes direction, and Moore is
such a trump sycophant that he
co-wrote a flattering book
called "trumponomics" and said
trump should win the nobel prize
in economics.
And this should be worrying to
you, as trump seems to be
looking to bring the fed under
his control.
He's reportedly furious that it
has raised interest rates,
slowing down the stock market,
and he's publicly attacked
Jerome Powell, a huge breach of
custom, and reportedly
considered firing him.
And if he manages to install
Moore and Cain, that could
fundamentally undermine the fed,
so it's important the senate
stand against these nominations.
And I know that this could be a
difficult fight, but as a poet
once said, "come with me, the
time is right.
There's no better team.
Arm in arm, we'll win the fight.
It's always been our dream.
Pokemon.
Gotta catch em' all.
It's you and me, I know it's my
destiny.
Pokemon."
Let's move on now to Baltimore.
Baltimore is a great place to
get crabs if you can't find
post Malone.
Now, Baltimore has a long
history of corruption, but its
latest scandal is truly
remarkable.
Well, mayor Catherine pugh is
speaking out amid the ethics
controversy surrounding her
business dealings with the
university of Maryland medical
system.
The mayor had served on the
board of directors since 2001,
and throughout an eight-year
period, she sold the medical
system $500,000 worth of her
"healthy Holly" children's
books.
John: It's true.
Baltimore's mayor has apparently
made hundreds of thousands of
dollars off several local
entities, some of which have
business before the city,
purchasing her self-published
books, including "healthy Holly:
Vegetables are not just green,"
"healthy Holly: Fruits come in
colors like the rainbow," and
presumably, "healthy Holly:
Fruits come in vegetables but
only when they receive verbal
consent."
And look, look, it is hard to
believe pugh's books were purely
bought on the basis of literary
merit.
Reporters who've read them have
pointed out that, for a start,
she can't seem to settle on the
correct spelling of the name for
one of her main characters.
Also, she seems to think a
normal, healthy dinner involves
a family gathered around four
massive plates of salad with one
smaller salad that sits in the
center of the table untouched
while your dad says normal
things like, "we are having
spinach with our dinner.
It is a vegetable."
And finally, in her educational
children's book about eating
right, she spelled fucking
"vegetable" wrong.
And "vege tale" sounds like
slang that douchey bros use when
they pick up girls at vegan
restaurants.
"Yah, brah, I'm gonna gulp down
some quinoa, pretend I fucks
with Kale, and then try to smash
some of that vege tale.
All day, son.
All day."
And the scandal widened this
week after it emerged that the
amount she has received from
high-profile organizations or
people has now reached $800,000.
Pugh is now on leave because
she's fighting pneumonia, but
before she left, she called a
press conference to defend
herself.
And in this appearance, where
she was dealing with accusations
that she'd misused her office to
promote a side project, she did
this:
Mayor pugh also showed us her
child clothing line which has
slogans to get active on them as
well.
There was bibs and onesies.
John: It's true.
She basically started Hawking
her idea for a kids' clothing
line, and she did it for three
full minutes.
As you can see from these
bibs, it was about teaching
children to walk, run, crawl,
skip, dance.
Some to eat healthier.
To play and crawl.
And same thing here with the
messaging.
Swim, jump, play,
walk, run, crawl.
John: Okay, a few things
here: First, "walk, run, crawl,
skip, dance," sounds less like
something you'd put on a onesie
and more like something that
bjork whispers to you at the end
of a conversation instead of
saying "goodbye."
"Walk, run, crawl, skip, dance.
Hee-hee!"
Second, second, if the clothes
you're making are that small,
your baby is not ready to swim.
And finally, how is a baby
supposed to learn healthy eating
habits from a bib that reads
"eat healthy"?
The baby can't see the bib when
it's on.
It just can't bend its neck far
enough.
And I know what you're thinking,
just look in the mirror, baby.
Look in the mirror after you put
your bib on but before you eat.
But then, of course, the writing
will be backwards, making it
even more difficult to decipher
for a baby who already...
and this is true... cannot
fucking read.
But let's put all that aside and
let's say this baby can read
backwards, looks in the mirror
before a meal, and intuits the
message that it should eat
healthy.
It's still going to be
physically strapped into a chair
and fed whatever its parents
pick because babies have no
agency 'cause that's how babies
work.
Now, investigators are now
looking into this situation, and
while there have been no charges
so far, the whole thing does not
look good for the mayor.
And unless there is some very
good explanation that I can't
see and does not exist, it
might be better for her to read
the writing on the onesie and
walk, run, crawl, skip, dance,
her way out of office.
And now this.
Announcer: And now, a
tribute to the secret star of
divorce court.
Mr. Marino, did your wife
catch you with your situation
out on your phone, texting it to
other people?
It couldn't have been me.
I don't know.
I was like, well, I knew she
found out.
I'm just going to make up an
age.
We hang out all the time, so
I wouldn't remember...
I do tend to react that way,
because my feelings be hurt.
Because that's how large the
argument was throughout those
few days.
You should have known I was
going out with some other guy.
Right.
Because I feel...
there's no "I guess."
If I say something...
a lot of the conversation was
because...
I did do that.
But that's not how we started.
She was in the backseat with
two dudes in the car.
Oh!
John: Moving on.
Our main story tonight concerns
mobile homes.
Perfected by humans, but
invented by snails.
There are many misconceptions
about mobile, or manufactured
homes.
For instance, right now, you may
be picturing something that
looks like this.
But for decades, the industry
has been trying to change that
image, running ads like this
one:
You bought a mobile home?
♪ ♪
Today's manufactured home.
You bought a house!
Factory-built quality at a
price that makes sense.
We have three big bedrooms.
I love it.
It's a manufactured home.
Today's manufactured home.
You bought a house.
John: Okay.
I think I get it.
But for the record, that sexy
saxophone riff would make a
reveal of anything seem good.
Here, I'll show you.
You bought a taxidermy fox?
♪ ♪
You bought a fox!
But it is true, it can be
genuinely hard to tell the
difference between manufactured
homes and conventional homes.
Just like it's hard to tell the
difference between
Jessica chastain and
Bryce Dallas Howard.
The difference is, like a mobile
home, Bryce Dallas Howard is
assembled off-site then placed
on wheels and moved to her
permanent location.
Around 20 million people live in
mobile homes.
That's roughly 1 in 18
Americans, and they're one of
America's last affordable
housing options, costing up to
50% less per square foot than a
conventional house.
Which is great, but in recent
years, some of the biggest
investors in America
have moved into this industry.
According to one new report,
over 100,000 home sites,
traditionally run by mom-and-pop
businesses, are now owned or
partly owned by private equity
firms like these.
So the homes of some of the
poorest people in America are
getting snapped up by some of
the richest people in America.
And luckily, there've been no
problems whatsoever.
Except I'm obviously kidding.
It's going terribly.
If you want to hear me lie about
stories to make you feel better,
you might enjoy our spinoff
show, "everything's fine!
With John Oliver."
Did you know Isis is just
hamsters?
This little terrorist's name is
dumpling, and he doesn't even
know how to use his gun!
Sadly, back in the real world,
the truth is, the rise of
big-money investors in mobile
homes has led to a corresponding
spike in rents, fees, and
local-news stories like these:
People living at a local
mobile home park outraged over
the sharp increase in lot rent.
Rents were raised by as much
as 36%.
Rents were raised by nearly
60%.
Ella karcher lives on a fixed
income.
Her lot rent's just gone up, and
it all adds up to a bill she
can't afford.
Now it's a matter of, "okay,
now which medication am I going
to take and half so that I can
make it stretch out a little bit
longer."
John: That's clearly
horrible.
Nobody should be made to stretch
out medicine.
It's sad enough when you stretch
out your almost-empty bottle of
shampoo by adding a bunch of
water.
And if you didn't relate to that
joke, you haven't suffered a
single day in your life.
So tonight, let's take a look at
the mobile home industry.
And let's start with the company
that sells more mobile homes
than any other, Clayton homes,
controlled by one of the richest
men in America, Warren buffett.
Although the company's ads used
to feature a more down-home
spokesman.
What do I know about
Clayton homes?
I know they're built right here
in America.
And they know the difference
between a house and a home.
Hey, miss Kay, a home is where
you get your famous sweet potato
pie, honey.
And you all know how we all
try to make miss Kay happy,
happy, happy.
Clayton homes.
Good call.
[Duck call]
John: Judging by that creepy
delivery, there is no way that
"getting her famous sweet potato
pie" is not also code for some
kind of disgusting sex act.
It probably means miss Kay
smearing pie filling on his
ball sack while a live duck
scrapes it off with its bill.
And if it does, good call.
[Duck call]
But the key difference between a
mobile and conventional home has
nothing to do with pie.
It has to do with how it retains
its value.
Just listen to finance guru
Dave Ramsey give his no-nonsense
take on whether or not you
should buy one.
Mobile homes go down in
value.
It's the only thing that you
own, that you live in, that goes
down in value.
Even if you buy dirt under it
that goes up in value more than
it goes down in value so it
appears you didn't lose money,
you lost money.
You buy a $50,000 mobile home,
in a few years, it's a $10,000
mobile home.
I mean, cars go down in value,
mobile homes go down in value.
It's a car you sleep in.
John: I gotta say, I find the
negativity of his tone genuinely
refreshing there.
That guy should replace
Jim cramer on his show.
No more running around excitedly
pressing buttons like a little
boy at an arcade, just an angry
old grump hunched over a desk
telling you you're going to lose
money.
So mobile homes may be a
terrible investment for people
buying them, but they've been an
incredible investment for
Warren buffett.
Clayton homes generated pre-tax
earnings of $911 million last
year, and they've done that not
just by selling homes but by
financing them as well, because
instead of being financed with
mortgages, mobile homes tend to
be bought with high-interest,
shorter-term chattel loans, the
kind you'd use to buy a car or a
TV.
And an investigation a few years
back found Clayton relies on
predatory sales practices,
exorbitant fees, and interest
rates that can exceed 15%,
trapping many buyers in loans
they can't afford.
Now, Clayton strenuously denies
all that, saying the report was
based on isolated incidents, and
its customers report high levels
of satisfaction.
Although I will point out that
one of those isolated incidents
was this call a Clayton customer
got when she fell behind on
payments.
Why don't you try something
to come up with the money by the
31st?
What should you... what do
you suggest except for the
things that you already suggest,
which doesn't work?
Donate plasma or donate
blood.
Really?
I'ma get $800 for that?
No.
But that's one way to come up
with a little bit of money,
though.
John: Holy shit.
"Go donate blood."
I guess one way to get your
customers to report high levels
of satisfaction is to make sure
they're all feeling light-headed
after you literally bleed them
fucking dry.
But one of the biggest problems
here isn't even to do with how
you pay for a mobile home or how
quickly it loses value.
It's where you put it.
Because around a third of
mobile home dwellers own their
homes but don't own the land
underneath it.
That's because they live in
mobile home parks and pay rent
on that land to the park owner.
But in recent years, large
investors have been snatching
those parks up and either
tearing them down or ratcheting
up rent and fees, as these women
experienced first-hand.
The ingdol family decided to
sell the park and they sold it
to the Carlyle group.
First of all, Carlyle started
off with an immediate 8%
increase in space rent, so that
was a threat to most of us who
are living on fixed income.
I don't know what's gonna
happen.
I may be forced to leave
everything.
My doctors, my friends.
The life I've known here.
Even though I own my home.
John: It's true.
That woman may lose her home so
the Carlyle group, an investment
firm with $216 billion in
assets, can make more money for
shareholders.
If the concept of "income
inequality" came to life, that
is the sentence it would scream
when it orgasmed.
Now, Carlyle... Carlyle insists
the price hikes were to pay for
park improvements... which makes
complete sense.
If you asked these fuckers why
they got into private equity,
I'm sure they'd say "to break
even on investments in the
beautification of affordable
housing.
Why else would we do this?"
I also apparently have to tell
you that they have a safety net
program for low income
residents, although it only
applies for 81 of them, although
it only attaches 3% of people,
just like the one they use as my
favorite circus, a pile of dead
trapeze artists.
It's fun for the whole family!
Unless you're the family of one
of those trapeze artists.
And if you're thinking, "well
look, that's terrible, but if
those women live in mobile
homes, why don't they just
move?"
There's a problem with that, as
one of those women will tell
you.
Although they call them
mobile homes, it would cost
$20,000 to move this home out of
here.
Plus, it would... once you move
them in and they settle, moving
them out's gonna help destroy
them.
John: She's right.
It can cost thousands of dollars
to move mobile homes, if you can
move them at all.
That's why 80% of mobile homes
never move.
So mobile homes are mobile about
as much as a king crab is
actually a king.
It's just not... except in some
parts of Alaska, where it wields
the power of a despot... but
even then, it constitutionally
shares power with
moose parliament.
So "king" is really a more
ceremonial title.
Alaska is a fascinating place.
And this lack of mobility for
tenants is actually part of the
attraction for big investors.
And to see just how cynical and
predatory the industry can be,
meet frank rolfe.
His company is one of the
largest park operators in the
us, controlling over 30,000 home
sites in 25 states.
Rolfe is an evangelist for the
wonders of mobile home park
investing.
Just look at this uplifting
message that he made ahead of
the 2012 election about what it
would mean for his industry,
taped, for some reason, in front
of a shitty green screen oval
office.
If mitt romney wins, things
are good.
And if Barack Obama wins, things
You see, it doesn't much matter
who wins the election.
All that matters is that the
statistics show that Americans
will continue to get poorer in
that lower half of the
population.
John: Wow.
What president webcam is
essentially saying there is,
"no matter what happens, the
poor will suffer, and we will
feast on their rich marrow.
And, as you can see, it's casual
Friday here at the white house,
which is why I sit before you
looking like a divorced dad at a
parent-teacher conference."
Rolfe is shameless about the
degree to which his business
depends on having a captive
customer base, positively
comparing it to running a
waffle house where everyone is
chained to the booths, a concept
so deeply chilling, I think it
may have just inspired
Jordan peele's next movie.
Now you should know, rolfe
maintains that line was taken
out of context.
In fact, he has a whole page on
his website about it, claiming
he was just talking about the
"incredibly consistent revenues"
in mobile home parks.
So he wasn't suggesting that
he's a heartless person whose
customers are stuck there with
him holding all the cards
deciding for himself how high he
wants their rent to go.
To see him say that, you'd need
to enroll in his online
mobile home university, which we
did, and found seminars like
this:
What I've found, and again,
just as a heartless person, is
that, you know, the... the
customers are stuck there.
They don't have any option.
They can't afford to move the
trailer.
They don't have three grand.
So the only way they can... they
can object to your rent raise is
to walk off and leave the
trailer, in which case it
becomes abandoned property and
you recycle it... put another
person in it.
So you really hold all the
cards.
So the question is, what do you
want to do?
How high do you want to go?
John: Wow.
Usually when someone is that
contemptuous of poor people,
they're immediately visited by
the ghost of Christmas future.
Now, maybe... maybe rolfe will
claim that quote is out of
context too, and that he's not
arguing they're hostages.
To hear him say that, you need
to send away for rolfe's audio
seminar on running mobile home
parks, which we also did, and
found this:
One of the big drivers to
making money is the ability to
increase the rent.
If we didn't have them hostage,
if they weren't stuck in those
homes in the mobile home lots,
it would be a whole different
picture.
John: Frank rolfe's
mobile home university is
basically a crash course in how
to be an asshole.
Although having taken that
course, I'd argue that if that's
what you're looking for, save
your money and just follow
piers Morgan on Twitter for one
afternoon.
And, look, rolfe's course isn't
just online.
If you attend his mobile home
boot camp, he'll even take you
on a field trip tour of a park.
When you get to the park,
you'll be shocked and turned off
by, for example, the beach towel
in the window instead of an
actual curtain.
That doesn't mean anything.
What you gotta worry about are
the following items:
Infrastructure, density,
expense, age of home, and
location.
Got it?
What's going on?
They're teaching people about
mobile home parks.
Oh.
Yeah.
That's good.
John: No, it isn't, though.
It's really not good.
Telling that woman people are
just there to learn about
mobile home parks is like
telling a lobster people came to
the restaurant to learn about
crustacean habitats.
"Oh!
That's good!
Are those knives and forks to
help remove these tiny rubber
bands from my claws?"
No.
They're going to eat you.
So with that woman and many
mobile home residents like her
in danger of having their lives
turned upside down, it is worth
asking, is there anything that
can be done here?
Well, one potential solution is
for residents to band together
and buy their own park, keeping
it out of the hands of
speculators or developers.
And while that sounds inherently
like a long shot, there are
nonprofit groups that have had
real success in helping tenants
get financing to do just that.
What would help is to have laws
in every state that give
residents the right of first
refusal and time to raise funds
if the current owner plans to
sell.
But until laws like that are put
in place, which there absolutely
should be, there are some key
things to bear in mind: If you
want to rent a mobile home,
fine.
If you can afford to buy one and
put it on land that you own,
fine.
But buying a mobile home and
renting the land underneath it
can be financially catastrophic.
And it is very important that
anyone considering doing that
knows the risks involved.
And I'll tell you what would've
been helpful all along, if the
marketing for these homes had
always made those risks clear.
You bought a mobile home?
♪ ♪
Today's manufactured home.
You bought a house.
I can't believe you bought a
house.
I really didn't.
It's exactly like a house.
And what a beautiful piece of
land.
I don't own the land though,
and that's actually a super
important difference.
[Laughs]
Look at you all grown up with a
mortgage.
It's a chattel loan with an
astronomical interest rate.
The important thing is, it's
an investment in your future.
It will actually only go down
in value, and since a private
equity firm brought the park, my
rent has skyrocketed.
Are you listening to me?
[Laughs]
Oh, I love these decorative
bottles.
Oh, that's my blood.
I have to sell my blood and
plasma in order to make
loan payments.
[Laughs]
♪ ♪
But home is where the
sweet potato pie is.
I didn't make that.
Did you make that?
Isn't that burning your hand?
Are you a witch?
I want to see your garden.
No, no, don't go out there.
There she is.
Look, she can't afford to move.
You hold all the
cards.
[Laughter]
He's right.
It's like a waffle house where I
am chained to my booth.
That sounds delicious.
What is wrong with you?
Speaking of delicious...
stop it.
You bought a house!
Say it again, motherfucker!
[Laughs]
That's our show, thanks so
much for watching, see you next
week, good night!
Are you listening to me?
[Laughs]
Speaking of delicious.
Stop.
Shit.