Welcome, welcome, welcome
to "Last Week Tonight."
I'm John Oliver.
Thanks so much for joining us.
And we begin this evening
with Rudy Giuliani,
the President's lawyer,
and a one-man legal improv troupe.
Giuliani was on TV this morning,
to talk about the ongoing
Mueller investigation,
and came up with a rationale
for his boss's refusal
to sit down with Mueller
that was, even by Giuliani standards,
very "Giuliani".
When you tell me
that he should testify
because he's going
to tell the truth,
that he shouldn't worry,
well that's so silly,
because it's somebody's
version of the truth,
not the truth.
- He didn't have a conversation about...
- Truth is truth.
I don't mean to go, like...
No, it isn't truth!
Truth isn't truth!
The president of
the United States says
- "I didn't..."
- Truth isn't truth?
Mr. Mayor, do you realize what that...
No, no, no.
Don't do this to me.
Don't do this to you?
You just said "Truth isn't truth".
That's not acceptable
from a President's lawyer.
It's barely acceptable from
a sophomore philosophy major,
who just tried Molly
for the first time.
"Truth isn't truth man, and also
toes are just feet fingers."
"I feel warm!"
And, look, in fairness to Giuliani,
the Ken Bone of 9/11,
that was not the dumbest thing
he said in that interview.
Because just watch, Giuliani,
the President's lawyer,
whose job is essentially to try and
dismiss potentially damning evidence,
like the Trump Tower meeting,
basically do the exact opposite.
The trump tower meeting itself
is at least evidence
of you better investigate.
- It's a...
- It's not.
How is it not?
Because the meeting was originally
for the purpose of
getting information about Clinton.
- The meeting turned into a meeting...
- Which in itself is an attempt at collusion.
- It's not.
- You just said it.
The meet was intended
to get dirt on Hillary Clinton
- from a Kremlin lawyer.
- No, no.
That was the intention of the meeting.
You just said it.
What's Rudy Giuliani doing?
And why does the White House
keep letting him go on TV?
Because at this rate,
Trump is going to wind up
behind bars,
with Giuliani visiting him
and saying,
"Don´t worry, Donald.
Prison isn't prison."
But let's not get sucked
in to all that.
Instead, let's turn to Australia,
home of every animal
that seems like it should
already be extinct.
How is the platypus still alive?
It looks like something
Fred Flintstone would have used
as a swiss army knife.
Australian politics this week
saw a debut speech in parliament
from Fraser Anning
that will live long in their memory.
"A crossbench senator has delivered
a provocative first speech
to Parliament,
calling for a ban on muslims
migrating to Australia."
Fraser Anning also used the term
"Final Solution",
when talking about immigration,
a phrase used by Hitler
in Nazi Germany.
It's true.
In a speech arguing in favor of
a return to a "White Australia Policy",
Anning suggested having
a popular vote
would be a good "Final Solution".
And that's just not a phrase
you want to throw around
for pretty obvious reasons.
It's the same reason that
we don't name babies Adolf anymore,
or have tiny mustaches,
or call yoga retreats
"Concentration Camps."
We could!
It would make sense.
But people would be
understandably upset.
But not only did Anning
refuse to apologize,
the head of his party
backed him up.
Do you support
Fraser Anning's comments?
Absolutely, one thousand percent.
I support everything he said.
It was a magnificent speech.
It was solid gold.
And he stumbled on a bit of
a malapropism there,
and hey, he didn't go to university.
He didn't go to University
to learn the significance
of all these words.
First, the speech
was not "solid gold".
And I really hope in Australia,
you don't have to go to University
to have heard about the holocaust.
Look, he bears no responsibility
for the words he uses.
He doesn't know what they mean!
If you gave 1,000 monkeys
1,000 typewriters,
and one of them wrote "Heil Hitler",
would you get all angry with him?
No! You'd be impressed!
That's a solid gold monkey
right there.
That man is Bob Katter,
head of the self-named
"Katter's Australian Party",
who has a temperament
to match his face.
Just take a look at the hostile tone
of a previous campaign ad.
"One australian lawmaker
has come under fire
for the bad timing
of his new campaign video,
a mock execution
of his political opponents,
showing him blowing a smoking gun
as lifeless bodies lie
in the background."
Wow!
I haven't seen
a commercial that extreme
since the Geico Gecko
slit the Afflac Duck's throat.
You went too far this time,
you little shit.
But underneath
his eccentric personality
is the heart of a truly
unpleasant human being.
Last year, Katter said,
It is imperative the people from
the Middle East and North Africa
are barred from entering Australia.
And this week, when questioned
about Fraser Anning's comments,
he said this.
Are we racist?
Well, we're australians.
I don't know if that's racist or not,
but we're not apologizing
for it to anyone.
I can take this one.
You are and it is.
And look.
I'm not saying
all australians are racist.
That would be racist.
And I would never say
something like that,
because I'm not australian.
But in fairness to Katter,
he's not just racist.
He's also homophobic.
In 2011, he said gay marriage
should be ridiculed,
and when Australia approved
same-sex marriage just last year,
he tried to laugh it off,
before doing a hard emotional turn.
You know, people are entitled
to their sexual proclivities.
I mean, let there be
a thousand blossoms bloom
as far as I'm concerned.
But I ain't spending any time on it,
because in the meantime,
every three months,
a person is torn to pieces
by a crocodile
in North Queensland.
Okay,
you cannot deflect
from a question of civil rights
with a weird animal fact.
People are entitled to be worried
about voter suppression,
that's fine.
But I ain't spending any time on it
when giraffes are walking around
with black tongues all day.
It's a disgrace.
And look, I could spend all night
showing you clips
of Katter being terrible.
But I just want to show you one more.
Because his objection
to same-sex marriage
isn't just that it distracts
from croc-on-bloke crime.
No, it's also because of this.
The homosexual groupings in Australia,
they took the word "gay."
It was the most beautiful word
in the english language,
and they said, "oh good!
We'll take that word!
And we'll have it as ours!"
Oh, then there is this thing
called marriage,
the other mob, oh, well,
we'll take that, too!
You know? Well, what else
are they gonna take?
Oh, I can tell you that.
Nothing.
Because they didn't take
the words "gay" or "marriage"
in the first place.
Words can evolve over time
and be used in new contexts.
There are very few exceptions
to that rule, Bob.
Can you think of one?
Can you think of one, Bob?
I can, and if you think hard enough,
I'm sure you'll come up
with a final solution.
And now this.
And now.
The holiday local news teams dread.
Today, ladies and gentlemen,
if you didn't know it.
It´s National Tell a Joke Day.
Oh, yay, Greg.
By the way,
tomorrow is National Joke Day.
Oh, no.
What kind of jeans does Jaws wear?
Denim, denim, denim, denim.
No?
Why couldn't the toilet paper
across the street?
He got stuck in a crack.
Wow, really going for it.
Why does Snoop Dogg need an umbrella?
Gosh, this is like a
slow-moving car crash.
You see it coming from miles away.
You know that Snoop Dogg,
you know the reason why he has
his umbrella around, right guys?
Because?
You know, "Fo´ drizzle, man".
Okay.
Why did Snoop Dogg need an umbrella?
Fo´ drizzle.
- It´s National Tell a Joke Day.
- Is it?
It is.
Moving on.
Our main story tonight concerns
"Trade".
The basic system of
barter and exchange
that you have to do really carefully,
or you'll end up with Dwight Howard.
Seriously, parents,
talk to your children about trade.
You don't want them going to school
with pizza lunchables
and coming home with Dwight Howard.
You think he's going to add
a three point shot
to his game now, kids?
Grow up.
Trade is a subject on
which our current president
considers himself particularly expert.
Trade,
that's what I'm gonna do so good.
I'll take those trade deals
and make them so good,
that's what I do.
I love taking bad deals
and making them good.
I love trade.
You know trade's always been my thing.
I could name ten different
forms of trade.
I know every one of them.
Hey, the Wharton School of Finance
right here.
Yeah, I can name
ten forms of trade:
there's free trade, fair trade,
rough trade,
trader joe's.
That's what, eight?
Then there's human trafficking,
that's like trading for people.
We'll round up and call it ten.
Wharton School of Finance, right here!
Trump has talked a big game
on trade for decades.
And he's spent this year slapping tariffs
on products from china,
Canada, the EU, and others,
prompting them to retaliate
with tariffs of their own.
And this trade war has escalated fast,
from tariffs on just 18 products
at the start of the year
to now over 10,000.
So things have gotten pretty serious.
And american workers
are already being impacted,
particularly in agriculture.
"We're feeling a lot of pain right now
in the farm sector."
"It's affecting farmers
in a negative way."
"I always hope that one morning,
President Trump is just gonna wake up
and send out that 3:30
in the morning tweet
that says "tariffs are gone."
Wow, that is a depressing thought.
That guy's livelihood depends
on a tweet that says
"Tariffs are gone."
And even if Trump does end up
doing that at 3:30 in the morning,
you just know it'll say
"Tarifs APE goon",
and we'll all have to decide
what he meant by that.
So tonight, before things get
much worse,
let's take a look at this trade war.
Because it's tempting to think
that Trump has a plan.
After all, trade is his thing.
And he's tweeted, "Trade wars
are good and easy to win."
But for years, his strategy on that
seems to have been based
around little more than
tone of voice.
So easy.
I'd drop a 25% tax on China.
And I said to somebody
that it's really the messenger.
The messenger is important.
I could have one man say,
"We're gonna tax you 25%."
And I could say another,
"Listen you motherfuckers,
we're gonna tax you 25%."
Oh, I see.
So the tone is important.
If I were to say to somebody,
"That's not how trade negotiations work",
that'd be one thing.
If I were to say,
"That's not how trade negotiations work,
you dumb motherfucker",
that would be much more effective.
That's good to know.
Because for all Trump's confidence,
there are some very basic things
about economics
that he seems genuinely confused by.
Take tariffs.
Trump once tweeted that
if the trade war doesn't end,
other countries "will play us
vast sums of money
in the form of tariffs."
"We win either way."
But that's not how tariffs work.
Tariffs are taxes designed
to make foreign goods more expensive.
Therefore making domestic products
more appealing.
Other countries don't pay us tariffs,
importers do when they
receive the goods,
and they usually pass that cost
along to the consumer.
So, when Trump imposes
a tariff on an item,
you are probably going to pay
more for it.
As reporters have been
trying to explain,
in the most literal way possible.
"Here in the kitchen,
made in China utensils and appliances,
like stoves and refrigerators
are being targeted.
Upstairs in the bathroom,
everyday items like shampoo,
nail clippers, makeup and towels."
It could mean higher prices
for things like instant coffee
and this Harley Davidson motorcycle.
Everyday items, like the iPad,
could be hit.
The tablet has a chip from Intel,
which could be a target.
E-scooters have taken off this year.
Now they face a 25% tariff.
Okay, I hate to admit this.
If one of the key casualties
of this trade war is e-scooters,
I actually think I'm fine with that.
They are basically if Dane Cook
somehow became transportation.
And it's not just tariffs
that Trump seems to misunderstand.
There's also our trade deficit.
Basically, the number that expresses
how much more we buy
from other countries,
than they buy from us.
Trump talks about it all the time,
usually like this.
Our trade deficit ballooned
to $817 billion dollars.
Think of that.
We lost $817 billion dollars a year
over the last number of years.
In trade.
In other words, if we didn't trade,
we'd save a hell of a lot of money.
Okay, there's a lot to unpack there.
First, our trade deficit
is actually $552 billion.
So he was off
by a quarter-trillion dollars,
Wharton School of Finance, right there!
Second, trade deficits aren't
actually always bad.
And many economists believe,
for very complex reasons
involving savings rates
and the dollar's special status
as the world's reserve currency,
America's trade balance
might be more or less
where it should be.
And finally, and this is important,
when we have a trade deficit,
we don't "lose money."
It's not a big pile of cash
that we handed over.
We bought things, that we received.
And I'm not saying it was all valuable
does anyone really need
the "Pony Up Daddy Saddle",
which allows your child to symbolize
their new-found dominance
over your life?
No, I didn't need it,
but I "wanted" it,
and honestly, it's brought my dad
and me closer together.
And even the world leaders
that Trump has been fighting with
seemed alarmed by how little
he understands trade.
The EU Chief, Jean-Claude Juncker,
reportedly met Trump
armed with a series of colorful,
simple flash cards
to explain the trade war.
And the word that really gets me there
is "colorful."
Because that means they had
some simple flash cards and thought
"No, too wonky.
Let's get some big fun baby colors
on those things."
"Lets give him a chance."
And Angela Merkel struggled to explain
something even more basic.
"The independent newspaper citing
an unnamed senior german official,
ten times Trump asked Ms. Merkel
if he could negotiate a trade deal
with Germany.
Every time she replied,
"You can't do a trade deal
with Germany.
Only the EU."
On the eleventh refusal,
Trump finally got the message.
"Oh, we'll do a deal with Europe then."
He understood,
but only after the eleventh refusal!
Just listen to what that sounds like.
- Deal with Europe.
- Huh?
- Okay, I'll deal with Europe.
Honestly, I'm just amazed
that after the fifth time,
Angela Merkel didn't turn
to her translator and say
"Okay, you're fucking fired.
You can't possibly be
translating this right."
And I'm not saying it's easy
to understand trade.
It is one of the most complicated
issues there is,
technically, politically,
and emotionally.
Over the years, free trade
has been criticized from all sides.
People argue that unfettered trade
can reward the worst behavior
of multinational companies,
and exploit countries with fewer
protections for labor,
and that has unquestionably happened.
But Trump generally confines
himself to arguing
that trade is responsible
for the death of US manufacturing jobs.
And while there is some truth in that,
automation is the far bigger culprit.
We actually still make
a lot of things in America.
US Factories now manufacture
twice as much as they did in 1984.
But they do it with one-third
fewer workers.
And the overwhelming consensus
among economists
is that trade between countries,
generally speaking,
can create jobs, lower costs,
and be a net benefit to both nations.
Essentially, think of trade like sex.
If you're doing it right,
it can be good for both partners,
though the odds
of that happening plummet
as soon as Donald Trump
gets involved.
And the problem with Trump,
the real problem, not understanding trade
is that he therefore doesn't
understand its consequences.
For instance, one of the first
major shots he fired in this trade war
was putting tariffs on steel
and aluminum.
That was great news
for the people working
in those specific industries,
like this worker
in a Missouri aluminum plant.
You think that his policies
are kinda why you have a job today?
I know it is.
You know it is?
Yeah, I wouldn't have had this job
if it didn't happen.
Wish I could meet him.
I'd give him a big old hug.
You know?
Yeah, I do know.
And I honestly get
why he wants to hug him.
Trump got him his job back.
It's one of two possible explanations
for that man wanting to hug
Donald Trump.
The other, of course, being,
that if, during the early stages
of the campaign,
Trump and Melania were driving
through Missouri on a stormy night,
and their car broke down.
Donald's not getting out,
so Melania ends up climbing out
into the rain and opening the hood
as that aluminum worker
comes driving down the highway.
He rolls down his window
and asks if he can help,
to which Melania gratefully asks,
"maybe a flashlight?"
And just as the aluminum worker
is handing the flashlight over,
it gets struck by lightning
and they switch bodies.
So, now, Donald is living
in the White House
with an aluminum worker
who feels understandably weird
about holding his hand,
while Melania is forced to pine
after her husband
from the factory floor,
her heart aching for him
every second of every day,
knowing full well that revealing
her true identity
would just complicate things
for everyone.
But that's bullshit, Melania!
You go to him!
The world will accept your love!
That aluminum worker clearly
isn't in love with him!
Everyone can see it!
It explains so much!
The point is, for that individual guy,
in that individual job,
things have improved.
But when it comes to trade,
nothing happens in isolation.
And there are downstream effects
to those tariffs.
Not too far from where
that guy works,
there's a nail factory which suffered.
Because, thanks to Trump's
steel tariffs,
the price of their raw material,
steel, skyrocketed.
Sales dropped in half,
and they've laid off
over 100 workers,
and those that remain are worried.
Some of these people,
this is the only income they got.
Just like me.
This is the only income I got.
And I gotta put another daughter
through school.
You know, it's gonna be hard.
Yeah, it is.
That's the problem here.
Protecting steel helps steel,
but it hurts anything made from it.
And you have to balance
those consequences.
By one estimate, Trump's tariffs
may create 26,000 jobs
in steel and aluminum,
but could cost over 400,000 jobs
across the rest of the economy.
So if Trump's trying to create jobs,
almost anything would be
a better idea than tariffs.
He'd be better off
dressing a turtle up like David Bowie
and throwing him
into a pool full of milk.
Will that create jobs?
Of course not.
But it won't actively lose hundreds
of thousands of them,
plus it would be the highlight
of Ziggy Shelldust's life.
And we're only scratching the surface
of how complicated this is.
because distinguishing between
a foreign product and an american job
can be a lot trickier
than you'd think.
Take some of trump's favorite villains
when it comes to foreign companies.
They sell Mercedes and BMW
and the cars come in by the millions.
And we hardly tax them at all.
We can't do this stuff anymore.
We protect Germany.
Germany,
who doesn't have a BMW?
We're gonna tax Mercedes-Benz,
we're gonna tax BMW.
We're gonna tax all of those beautiful
Mercedes-Benz that are coming in
and we're gonna tax BMWs
that are coming in.
Trump is furious with german cars.
Here's the thing about that.
In the clip where he said,
"who doesn't have a BMW?"
to the crowd, in his classic
man-of-the-people way,
Trump is in North Augusta,
South Carolina.
And just two hours drive-away
there is a place called
Spartanburg County,
well-known for this.
"Spartanburg is home to the largest
BMW plant in the world."
"Last year they made more than
three hundred seventy thousand
luxury SUV's,
employing ten thousand people,
pumping billions
into the state's economy.
Yes.
It seems Trump didn't know that.
And look.
Everyone knows he doesn't know
a lot of things.
But occasionally it's important
to remember
that he also doesn't know anything.
It's true.
It´s true.
I´ll show you.
Everyone close your eyes right now
and think of something.
That thing you're thinking of?
He doesn't know that.
And since the trade war began,
Spartanburg County is actually
double-fucked.
Because they'll be affected
by higher costs
for the steel that they use
to build the cars,
and when they try
to ship them to China,
they'll be hit by chinese tariffs.
So they're in complicated trouble.
Or as Trump might put it,
"Listen you motherfuckers,
you're getting taxed twice."
So, if a trade war
could be this disruptive,
and the net benefits
are likely to be negative,
why is Trump doing this?
Especially because members
of his own economic team
seem against it?
Gary Cohn reportedly left over
the proposed tariffs,
and Steve Mnuchin, Treasury Secretary
and white-hot sex bomb,
has tried to do some damage control
by claiming we're not actually
in a trade war at all.
This has been a trade
dispute all along.
It never was a trade war.
It's a trade dispute.
Oh, I get it!
It's not a war,
it's a dispute!
You know, I almost bought
that bullshit,
because I was so distracted
by this lava-rich sex volcano's looks.
The guy is hypnotic.
I must have a bad case
of the mnuchies right now,
because he is looking
like an absolute "snack."
So who is telling the President
that this is a good idea?
Well, by most accounts,
the driving force is Peter Navarro.
Head of the Office of Trade
and Manufacturing Policy.
He's Trump's trade guy.
Isn't that right, Peter?
I'm the trade guy.
Thanks, Pete.
So, for the record,
let's all get our Trump
administration roles straight.
We've got trade guy,
liar lady, nothing boy,
Jesus pleaser, word ghoul,
crime nymph, drunk grandpa,
and daughter wife.
It's a well-oiled machine
he´s running.
Now, Navarro is the author of a series
of get-rich investment books,
and like Trump,
he's obsessed with trade
deficits in general,
and China in particular,
saying trade with China
is a "zero sum game",
meaning one country can only win
if the other country loses.
And it is hard to overstate just
how rare his views are
among economists.
When the New Yorker profiled him,
they asked Navarro to help them find
even one colleague
who agreed with him.
He gave them two names.
One was Peter Morici,
a University of Maryland professor
who said of Navarro,
"He has a rather severe position.
That zero-sum statement,
I have a problem with that.
Where's his proof?"
And the other was a blogger
named Alan Tonelson,
who Navarro described
as "a fine economist",
to which Tonelson replied,
"I do not hold an economics degree."
I'm guessing he also doesn't hold
a degree in web design,
because this is the photo
on the "About" page of his blog.
So if you're understandably
wondering at this point,
"Then how on Earth did Navarro
get a job at the fucking White House?"
Well, it is way dumber
than you are thinking.
Apparently, Jared Kushner
was tasked with finding Trump
experts on chinese trade,
and this is how he went about it.
So Jared went on Amazon.
He fired up his computer
and he found some
of Peter Navarro's books
and he asked him to come
to the White House.
That's how Peter Navarro
ended up in the White House.
Yeap, Jared looked
for experts on amazon.
That was his rigorous process.
So when Jeff Sessions
does get fired,
be prepared for him to be replaced
by Crystal Kaswell,
author of the erotic fiction novel,
"Dangerous Rock:
A Dangerous Noise Novel."
Because, for whatever reason,
that is honestly the first thing
that came up when we typed
"Good law person (smart)"
into Amazon.
The Navarro Book that Jared found
was called "Death by China",
and it paints the US
chinese trade relationship
in apocalyptic terms.
Because while there are some
legitimate complaints
about China's unfair practices,
they've deliberately depressed
their currency,
they violate intellectual property rights,
and arguably skirt WTO rules,
this book goes way further,
with chapter titles
featuring phrases like
"Shanghaiing the Gene Pool."
And "Look Ma, There's a Death Star
Pointing at Chicago."
Navarro actually turned the book
into a movie that one critic called
"the documentary equivalent
of a raving street-corner derelict."
Which seems harsh,
until you see how the movie begins.
"The film you are about to see
addresses one of the most urgent
problems facing America:
It´s increasingly destructive
trade relationship
with a rapidly rising China."
It starts like that.
Its warmup is a literal knife
being stabbed
into the heart of America.
And if you're worried
that leaves it with nowhere to go,
please don't be concerned.
Because there are even less-subtle
animations to come,
which depict China's trade practices
as guns and bombs
that blow up american factories,
and stunningly deceptive moments,
like this.
China has stolen thousands
of our factories
and millions of our jobs.
Multinational corporation profits
are soaring
and we now owe
over three trillion dollars
to the world's largest
communist nation.
And look.
I´m not saying that large ball
isn´t very convincing,
but our trade deficit
isn't the same as
"what we owe to China",
those are two different numbers.
And neither of them
is anywhere close to 3 trillion.
And when something
that central to your movie
has something that wrong with it,
you usually have to replace it
with Christopher Plummer.
So Navarro is not someone
who any legitimate economist
takes seriously.
And yet, he seems to be the only person
the President is listening to.
Trump has called "Death by China":
"Right on."
And lauded it's facts,
figures, and insight.
And Navarro returns the compliment
saying of his own job,
that "My function, really,
as an economist is to try and provide
the underlying analytics
that confirm Trump's intuition."
"And his intuition is always right."
And that is simply terrifying.
Because an economist
shouldn't be finding ways
to confirm the intuitions of someone
who doesn't know
what they're talking about.
It's like a builder working
for a child, saying,
"My job is to build this house
he designed,
which is shaped like an ice-cream cone,
with a window that is also a door,
and the size of the sun,
and a dog.
His intuitions are always right."
No they aren´t!
You need to stop that child
before someone gets hurt.
In fact, if you want to get a sense
of just how little Navarro understands
the game he's playing,
consider this.
Since the trade war began,
China has imposed $37 billion of tariffs
on the US.
Now, take a look at what Navarro
said back in March.
Are you expecting china to come back
with retaliation?
I don't believe any country
in the world is going to retaliate
for the simple reason
that we are the most lucrative
and biggest market in the world.
They know they're cheating us
and all we're doing is
standing up for ourselves.
It's just breathtaking to see someone
be that confident and that wrong.
He´s basically Leonardo DiCaprio
in "Titanic", yelling
"I'm king of the world."
Except you're not,
are you Leo?
You're just an amateur sketch artist
who's about to be murdered by ice.
When you put all of this together,
what you're left with is this:
We're engaged in
an escalating trade war
that almost no legitimate
economist supports,
led by a man who honestly
doesn't seem to fully understand
the mechanics of what he's doing,
getting advice
from the human equivalent of an
all-caps email from your uncle.
And the crazy thing is,
the effect of all this is the exact
opposite of what Trump says he wants.
Because if you want to create jobs,
you don't do that by cutting off
american companies' markets
and suppliers.
And if you want to curb
the abuses of countries, like China,
you don't do that by pissing off
the leaders of every other
nation on Earth.
And I know none of what I'm saying,
right now, will get through to Trump.
So maybe it's time to take a page
from one the only people
he actually listening to, and give him
some basic economic lessons
in the only language
he seems to understand.
"The film you are about to see
addresses one of the most
urgent problems facing America:
The Destruction of Basic
Economic Knowledge by
Stupidity.
And the consequences of it
could be disastrous.
So let's review a few
fundamental facts.
First, a trade deficit isn't
a giant pool of money
that you have lost it to another country.
That's idiotic.
Second, if you think you can use
tariffs as a weapon,
you should understand a tariff
isn't something
other countries pay you.
It´s a tax you are forcing
your own people to pay,
which might end up hurting them
a lot less than it hurts you.
And third, our economy
is massively interconnected,
and you can't just tamper with one thing
without considering
what the wider consequences could be.
Unfortunately, misunderstandings
just keep getting bigger
while basic knowledge is shrinking.
And the result is stupidity is increasing
at an unsustainable rate.
Listen.
Economics is incredibly complicated,
and at the very least, you probably
shouldn´t find your key economic advisor
on fucking Amazon.
Because his a bullshit could end up
seriously hurting us all.
That´s our show.
Thank you so much for watching.
We are all for the next couple
of weeks.
Back September 9th.
See you then. Good Night!