♪ ♪
>> John: WELCOME, WELCOME,
WELL, TO
"LAST WEEK TONIGHT."
THANKS FOR JOINING US.
JUST TIME FOR A QUICK RECAP OF
THE WEEK.
AND WE BEGIN WITH THE TRUMP
ADMINISTRATION, WHICH IS LIKE A
CIRCUS IN THAT NOTHING ABOUT IT
IS FUNNY AND I BADLY WANT IT TO
END.
THIS WEEK, EVEN BY CURRENT
WHITE HOUSE STANDARDS, WAS SUCH
A MESS WE DON'T EVEN HAVE TIME
TO GET INTO MUELLER'S
INVESTIGATION HEATING UP OR
TRUMP FLIP-FLOPPING ON GUN
REFORM OR THE PRESIDENT'S
ONGOING SPAT WITH HIS
ATTORNEY GENERAL, EXCEPT TO
MENTION THIS AMAZING DETAIL.
>> "THE WASHINGTON POST"
REPORTED THE PRESIDENT HAS
REFERRED TO SESSIONS AS THE
SHORT-SIGHTED ELDERLY CARTOON
CHARACTER MR. MAGOO.
>> John: OKAY, SO FIRST, LEAVE
IT TO TRUMP TO MOCK SESSIONS AS
A DODDERING OLD MAN EVEN THOUGH
TRUMP IS -- AND THIS IS TRUE --
SIX MONTHS OLDER THAN HIM.
AND CALLING HIM MR. MAGOO ISN'T
JUST MEAN, IT'S LAZY.
IF YOU WANT TO HURT SESSIONS,
TRY.
USE YOUR IMAGINATION.
CALL HIM "CONFEDERATE SMURF" OR
"A CASTING DIRECTOR'S
SECOND-CHOICE FOR AN
INCONTINENCE AD" OR THE RESULT
OF A ONE-NIGHT STAND BETWEEN
STROM THURMOND AND
A GOLDEN RAISIN.
AT LEAST MAKE AN EFFORT.
MEANWHILE, THE ADMINISTRATION
CONTINUES TO HEMORRHAGE
STAFFERS, THE LATEST BEING
HOPE HICKS, WHITE HOUSE
COMMUNICATIONS DIRECTOR AND
"GIRL WHO STARTED THAT MEAN
RUMOR ABOUT YOU IN HIGH SCHOOL."
AND HICKS LEAVING IS A BIG DEAL
FOR TRUMP.
>> WITH HER GONE, THIS LEAVES A
STUNNING LACK OF CONFIDANTES IN
THE PRESIDENT'S INNER CIRCLE.
DAN SCAVINO, THE SOCIAL MEDIA
DIRECTOR HERE --
PRESIDENT TRUMP'S FORMER
GOLF CADDIE -- IS THE LAST MAN
STANDING FROM THE ORIGINAL TEAM
OF HIS CAMPAIGN.
>> John: OKAY, SO LET'S ALL
ADMIT,
THAT'S A SUSPICIOUS PHOTO.
BUT TO BE FAIR, WE LOOKED FOR
NON-SUSPICIOUS PHOTOS OF
DAN SCAVINO AND COULDN'T FIND
ANY.
THERE'S THIS ONE, "LOOKING AT
PORN AT WORK" SUSPICIOUS.
THIS ONE, "YOU DIDN'T SEE
ANYTHING, AND IF YOU SAY A WORD,
I'LL BREAK YOUR FUCKING NECK"
SUSPICIOUS.
AND MY FAVORITE, "OH, NO, I JUST
REALIZED I LEFT MY CRAIGSLIST
FRIEND IN THE PUNISHMENT
BOX" SUSPICIOUS.
HE'S A SUSPICIOUS GUY IS WHAT
I'M SAYING.
NOW, NOT EVERYONE HAS LEFT.
THERE IS, OF COURSE, STILL
AMERICA'S BUSIEST
BUSINESS BOY.
ALTHOUGH HE MAY ACTUALLY HAVE
HAD THE WORST WEEK OF ALL,
STARTING WITH THIS.
>> PRESIDENT TRUMP'S SON-IN-LAW
AND SENIOR ADVISOR JARED KUSHNER
NO LONGER HAS ACCESS TO TOP
SECRET MATERIAL.
KUSHNER'S CLEARANCE LEVEL WAS
DOWNGRADED FROM TOP SECRET TO
SECRET.
>> EVEN THE WHITE HOUSE
CALLIGRAPHER NOW HAS A HIGHER
LEVEL OF CLEARANCE THAN KUSHNER
NOW DOES.
>> John: WOW!
THAT IS HUMILIATING.
ALTHOUGH IT KIND OF MAKES SENSE
THAT A CALLIGRAPHER HAS TO BE
GOOD AT KEEPING SECRETS.
FOR EXAMPLE, THEY HAVE TO KEEP A
SECRET THAT
THERE'S A FONT IN MICROSOFT WORD
THAT DOES THEIR ENTIRE JOB.
WHAT'S CRAZY IS, KUSHNER HAS
REPORTEDLY BEEN ON INTERIM
SECURITY CLEARANCE EVER SINCE HE
JOINED THE WHITE HOUSE, AND
THAT'S FOR PRETTY GOOD REASONS.
>> JARED KUSHNER, IT'S NOT JUST
HAS A COMPLICATED BUSINESS, HE
HAD TO CHANGE HIS FEDERAL
DISCLOSURE FORMS MULTIPLE TIMES
BECAUSE HE "INADVERTENTLY
OMITTED MILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN
ASSETS AND FORGOT TO INCLUDE
MORE THAN 100 FOREIGN CONTACTS."
>> John: IN OTHER WORDS, KUSHNER
SCREWED UP SOME IMPORTANT
PAPERWORK, KEEPS CHANGING HIS
PERSONAL WEALTH, AND CASUALLY
OVERLOOKED HUNDREDS OF
FOREIGNERS.
HE TRULY IS HIS FATHER-IN-LAW'S
SON.
THE ONLY REAL DIFFERENCE IS, ONE
OF THEM HAS ELECTRIFYING SEXUAL
CHEMISTRY WITH IVANKA TRUMP AND
THE OTHER IS JARED KUSHNER.
NOW, JARED'S SECURITY ISSUE MAY
AFFECT HIS ABILITY TO TAKE AN
ACTIVE ROLE IN INTERNATIONAL
RELATIONS -- ALTHOUGH, GOING BY
ANOTHER STORY THAT CAME OUT THIS
WEEK, THAT MAY NOT BE THE WORST
THING.
>> A REPORT IN
"THE WASHINGTON POST" SUGGESTS
OFFICIALS FROM CHINA, ISRAEL,
MEXICO, AND THE
UNITED ARAB EMIRATES SAW KUSHNER
AS EXPLOITABLE AND AT ONE POINT
HOPED TO MANIPULATE HIM.
>> John: THE MOST SHOCKING THING
ABOUT THAT IS IF SOMEHOW ONLY
FOUR FOREIGN GOVERNMENTS THOUGHT
THEY COULD MANIPULATE HIM.
HOW IS IT NOT MORE THAN THAT?
WHAT NATION LOOKED AT THIS MAN
AND THOUGHT, "FORGET IT,
HIS MIND IS A FORTRESS"?
HOW DID BOLIVIA, LAOS, OR
GERMANY NOT FEEL THAT THIS WAS A
CRACKABLE NUT?
COME ON, FRANCE, ICELAND,
YOU DIDN'T THINK IT WAS EVEN
WORTH TRYING A LITTLE
NUDGE-NUDGE ON THE
OLD KUSH-BALL?
AND, LOOK, IT'S EASY TO GET
CAUGHT UP IN ALL THE DRAMA AND
FORGET THAT WHITE HOUSE CHAOS
CAN HAVE REAL-WORLD
CONSEQUENCES, BUT THURSDAY
BROUGHT A REMINDER OF THAT WHEN,
UNEXPECTEDLY, TRUMP ANNOUNCED
NEW TARIFFS ON STEEL AND
ALUMINUM.
AND WHETHER YOU AGREE WITH THAT
MOVE OR NOT, YOU HAVE TO BE
BOTHERED BY HOW IT HAPPENED.
>> SPOILING FOR A FIGHT, ANY
FIGHT, THE PRESIDENT DECIDED TO
PICK ONE ON TRADE, ANNOUNCING
NEW TARIFFS AGAINST THE ADVICE
OF MANY OF HIS TOP ADVISERS AND
WITHOUT ANY INTERNAL REVIEW,
TWEETING, "TRADE WARS ARE GOOD
AND EASY TO WIN."
>> John: YES, TRADE WARS ARE
GOOD AND EASY TO WIN, WHICH IS
WEIRD, BECAUSE IF THAT WAS TRUE,
EVERYONE WOULD ALWAYS WIN THEM,
IN WHICH CASE THEY'D ACTUALLY BE
HARD TO WIN, BECAUSE EVERYONE
ELSE WOULD ALREADY HAVE WON
THEM.
IT'S A COMPLEX SITUATION
THAT PHILOSOPHERS REFER TO AS
"THE DIPSHIT'S CONUNDRUM."
NOW, SOME WERE IMMEDIATELY
SIGNIFICANTLY ALARMED
THAT THIS COULD ACTUALLY
RAISE THE COST FOR AMERICANS ON
ANYTHING CONTAINING ALUMINUM OR
STEEL.
THAT'S WHY TRUMP SENT OUT HIS
DYNAMIC SECRETARY OF COMMERCE,
WILBUR ROSS, TO ALLAY THOSE
FEARS IN THE DUMBEST WAY
POSSIBLE.
>> WHAT I WOULD LIKE TO DO,
THOUGH, IS TO EMPHASIZE AGAIN
THE LIMITED IMPACT.
THIS IS A CAN OF CAMPBELL'S
SOUP.
IN THE CAN OF CAMPBELL'S SOUP,
THERE'S ABOUT 2.6 CENTS,
2.6 PENNIES WORTH OF STEEL.
SO IF THAT GOES UP BY 25%,
THAT'S ABOUT 6/10 OF ONE CENT ON
THE PRICE OF A CAN OF CAMPBELL'S
SOUP.
>> John: GREAT POINT, WILBUR.
AND AS LONG AS THERE ISN'T
ANYTHING IN THE ECONOMY
THAT ISN'T SOUP, WE
SHOULD BE JUST FINE.
BUT DON'T WORRY.
OUR RESEARCHERS HAVE ACTUALLY
LOOKING INTO IT, AND IT TURNS
OUT, EVERYTHING IS SOUP.
SO WE'RE IN THE CLEAR.
OH, AND ONE MORE THING:
ONE MORE QUICK THING HERE.
HOW IS HE NOT MAGOO?
THAT IS THE MAGOO-IEST SHIT I'VE
EVER SEEN RIGHT THERE.
AND IN DOING THIS, TRUMP MAY
WELL HAVE SET OFF A GLOBAL TRADE
WAR FOR NO GOOD REASON.
AND IF YOU NEED A SENSE OF JUST
HOW STUPID THIS MOVE IS, JUST
WATCH THE RESPONSE FROM E.U.
PRESIDENT JEAN CLAUDE JUNCKER,
WHO CANNOT BELIEVE HE IS NOW
BEING FORCED TO ENGAGE IN THIS
SHIT.
>> SO NOW WE WILL ALSO IMPOSE
IMPORT TARIFFS.
THIS IS BASICALLY A STUPID
PROCESS, THE FACT THAT WE HAVE
TO DO THIS, BUT WE HAVE TO DO
IT.
WE WILL NOW IMPOSE TARIFFS ON
MOTORCYCLES, HARLEY DAVIDSON, ON
BLUE JEANS, LEVIS, ON BOURBON.
WE CAN ALSO DO STUPID.
WE ALSO HAVE TO BE THIS STUPID.
>> John: OH, REALLY, JUNCKER?
YOU THINK YOU CAN BE AS STUPID
AS US?
PLEASE.
YOU JUST BROUGHT A KNIFE TO A
GUN FIGHT, AND WE JUST BROUGHT A
HOT POCKET THAT WE PUT IN OUR
GUN HOLSTER AND FORGOT WAS
THERE.
BECAUSE NO ONE OUT-STUPIDS
DONALD TRUMP'S U.S. OF A!
NOBODY!
YOU DON'T KNOW US!
AND NOW THIS.
>> AND NOW, WOULD YOU LIKE TO BE
ON THE MAURY SHOW?
>> ARE YOU A MISTRESS WHO IS IN
LOVE WITH A MARRIED MAN AND
WANTS HIM TO CHOOSE FOR ONCE AND
FOR ALL, IF SO, CALL.
>> DO YOU SUSPECT HE IS USING
YOU FOR YOUR MONEY AND A PLACE
TO LIVE?
ARE YOU DOING A MUCH YOUNGER MAN
I DO SUSPECT HE IS CHEATING ON
YOU?
>> IS YOUR FATHER DATING A MUCH
YOUNGER WOMAN?
>> ARGUMENTS HER DAUGHTER'S
BOYFRIEND OR HUSBAND IS CHEATING
ON HER?
>> ARE YOU CONVINCED HER MOTHER
IS HAVING SEX WITH YOUR HUSBAND?
>> IS THERE A POSSIBILITY OF TWO
OR MORE MEN BEING THE FATHER OF
YOUR CHILD?
>> IS THERE A POSSIBILITY THAT F
>> ARE YOU 18 YEARS OR OLDER AND
THE MAN YOU THINK IS YOUR FATHER
CLAIMS HE IS NOT?
>> DOES YOUR CHILD LOOK LIKE
THEY BELONG TO ANOTHER RACE?
>> DID ANOTHER WOMAN'S HUSBAND
GET YOU PREGNANT?
>> ARE YOU A GRANDMOTHER WHO
LOVES WEARING REVEALING CLOTHING
AND IT IS DRIVING YOUR FAMILY
CRAZY?
>> John: OUR MAIN STORY
TONIGHT CONCERNS THE NRA.
A GROUP THAT FEELS
ABOUT GUNS THE WAY THE REST OF
US FEEL ABOUT NUTELLA:
A LITTLE IS GOOD.
MORE IS BETTER.
AND YOU CAN TELL ME IT'S BAD FOR
ME ALL YOU LIKE, BUT YOU CAN PRY
IT FROM MY COLD, DEAD HANDS.
IN THE WAKE OF THE PARKLAND
SHOOTING, THE NRA HAS FOUND
THEMSELVES IN THE SPOTLIGHT ONCE
MORE.
HOWEVER, THE PUBLIC PRESSURE
THIS TIME IS ACTUALLY STARTING
TO TAKE A TOLL.
>> TWITTER USERS ARE PRESSURING
COMPANIES AFFILIATED WITH THE
GUN RIGHTS GROUP BY USING THE
HASHTAG #BoycottNRA.
>> SO 15 COMPANIES HAVE CUT TIES
WITH THE NRA AFTER PARKLAND.
I THINK WE HAVE A LIST OF THEM
HERE, SOME BIG ONES.
DELTA, UNITED, AVIS, BUDGET,
HERTZ.
BASICALLY SAYING THERE ARE NO
LONGER GOING TO PROVIDE
DISCOUNTS TO THE NRA.
>> John: YES, AVIS, BUDGET, AND
HERTZ WILL ALL STOP PROVIDING
DISCOUNTS TO NRA MEMBERS, WHICH
WILL PRESUMABLY COME AS A HUGE
BLOW
TO JEREMY, THE ONE NRA MEMBER
WHO WAS JUST IN IT FOR THE
RENTAL CARS.
BUT THE BOYCOTT TRAIN HIT A SNAG
WHEN IT RAN INTO ONE OF THE
NRA'S LESSER-KNOWN SIDE
VENTURES.
>> ONE GROUP THAT HAS NOT BEEN
SWAYED YET, BIG TECH COMPANIES
LIKE APPLE, AMAZON, AND ROKU.
YOU SEE, THESE COMPANIES'
STREAMING SERVICES STILL OFFER
ACCESS TO NRATV, THE GUN LOBBY
GROUP'S FREE ONLINE CHANNEL
FOCUSED ON PRO-GUN CONTENT.
>> John: OKAY, SO THAT IS AN
UNCOMFORTABLE SITUATION FOR
APPLE AND AMAZON, BUT IT'S A
FUCKING MIRACLE FOR ROKU.
"HARRY!
HARRY, GET IN HERE!
SOMEONE JUST CALLED US A
'BIG TECH COMPANY.'
THEY SAID 'LIKE AMAZON AND
APPLE.'
IT'S HAPPENING, HARRY!
IT'S HAPPENING!"
BUT WITH ALL THE DISCUSSION THIS
WEEK OF BOYCOTTING NRATV, WE
THOUGHT IT MIGHT BE WORTH
ANSWERING THE QUESTION,
"WHAT THE FUCK IS THAT?"
BECAUSE THE TRUTH IS, YOU MAY'VE
ACTUALLY SEEN TINY BITS OF ITS
PROGRAMMING WITHOUT REALIZING
IT.
LIKE WHEN THIS VIDEO FEATURING
NRA SPOKESPERSON DANA LOESCH
WENT VIRAL JUST LAST YEAR.
>> THEY USE THEIR MEDIA TO
ASSASSINATE REAL NEWS.
THEY USE THEIR SCHOOLS TO TEACH
CHILDREN THAT THEIR PRESIDENT IS
ANOTHER HITLER.
THE ONLY WAY WE STOP THIS, THE
ONLY WAY WE SAVE OUR COUNTRY AND
OUR FREEDOM, IS TO FIGHT THIS
VIOLENCE OF LIES WITH A CLENCHED
FIST OF TRUTH.
>> John: YES, THE "CLENCHED FIST
OF TRUTH," WHICH, IF YOU'RE
LOOKING FOR IT, IS JUST A LITTLE
PAST THE BENT ELBOW OF NONSENSE
AND HIDING IN THE OVERSTUFFED
POCKET OF NEEDLESSLY AGGRESSIVE
METAPHORS.
IF YOU MISSED THAT, YOU MAY'VE
SEEN ONE THAT MADE THE ROUNDS
DURING THE OBAMA ADMINISTRATION,
FEATURING COUNTRY MUSIC LEGEND
CHARLIE DANIELS.
>> TO THE AYATOLLAHS OF IRAN AND
EVERY TERRORIST YOU ENABLE,
YOU MIGHT HAVE MET
OUR FRESH-FACED FLOWER CHILD
PRESIDENT AND HIS WEAK-KNEED
IVY-LEAGUE FRIENDS, BUT YOU
HAVEN'T MET AMERICA.
YOU HAVEN'T MET THE HEARTLAND,
WHERE THE PEOPLE WOULD DEFEND
THIS NATION WITH THEIR BLOODY,
CALLOUSED, BARE HANDS.
YOU HAVEN'T MET THE
STEEL WORKERS AND THE
HARD ROCK MINERS
OR THE SWAMP FOLKS IN
CAJUN COUNTRY WHO CAN WRESTLE A
FULL-GROWN GATOR OUT OF THE
WATER.
>> John: "YOU HAVEN'T MET THE
HILL DEMONS WHO CAN CURSE YOU
AND YOUR FUTURE OFFSPRING JUST
FOR HAVING A PICNIC IN THE WRONG
PLACE.
YOU HAVEN'T MET THE LAKE DOG.
HE'S A DOG WHO LIVES IN A LAKE
FOR REASONS TOO COMPLICATED TO
GET INTO AT THE PRESENT MOMENT.
AND YOU HAVEN'T EVEN MET THE
GATORS DOWN IN CAJUN COUNTRY
WHO TIPTOE OUT OF THE WATER AT
NIGHT AND TAKE REVENGE ON THE
SWAMP FOLK WHILE THEY SLEEP,
THUS PERPETUATING THE SICK CYCLE
OF SWAMP FOLK-GATOR VIOLENCE.
THAT'S THE AMERICA I KNOW.
AND I PROMISE YOU, YOU'RE GOING
TO BE CONFUSED BY IT."
IN FACT, RECENTLY, ANOTHER ONE
OF THEIR PROMOS WAS PASSED
AROUND ONLINE, AND YOU MAY
RECOGNIZE ONE OF THE FACES IN
IT.
>> MR. PRESIDENT, ARE YOU A
RACIST?
>> AND DRINKING AS MANY AS
12 DIET COKES.
>> THE SECOND AMENDMENT IS ABOUT
A MILITIA.
>> AND IT'S THE NATIONAL RIFLE
ASSOCIATION.
>> WE ARE THE PRESS WHO'S UNDER
ATTACK.
>> THE PRESIDENT IS LIKE A
CHILD.
>> CERTAIN PEOPLE SHOULDN'T HAVE
GUNS.
>> HONG KONG!
>> YOU ARE BASICALLY
PARTICIPATING IN THE BIGOTRY.
>> HOW STUPID DO YOU THINK WE
ARE?
>> BLESS YOUR HEART.
♪ ♪
>> John: NO, DON'T LAUGH.
HE'S RIGHT.
AND IF NRA MEMBERS ARE ANNOYED
WITH WHAT I'M SAYING RIGHT NOW,
THEY SHOULD DO THE EXACT SAME
THING AND SMASH THEIR EXPENSIVE
TELEVISIONS WITH LARGE
SLEDGEHAMMERS.
ARE YOU LISTENING, NRA MEMBERS?
DESTROY YOUR OWN PROPERTY.
IT'S A REALLY GOOD IDEA, AND
IT'S HONESTLY THE ONLY WAY WE'LL
LEARN.
NRATV PRODUCES A LOT OF VIDEOS
LIKE THOSE THAT ARE ESSENTIALLY
JUST TROLLING FOR YOUR
ATTENTION.
BUT THEIR CONTENT GOES MUCH,
MUCH DEEPER THAN THAT,
AS YOU'LL SEE IF YOU GO TO THEIR
WEBSITE OR WATCH IT ON
STREAMING DEVICES LIKE
THE GREAT AND POWERFUL ROKU --
"THEY SAID IT AGAIN, HARRY!
THEY SAID OUR NAME!
IT'S HAPPENING!
IT'S FINALLY HAPPENING!"
NRATV HAS NEWS PROGRAMMING,
AND THERE'S HONESTLY NOT MUCH
POINT IN OUR SHOWING YOU ANY OF
IT, BECAUSE IT'S ESSENTIALLY
JUST FOX NEWS ON A MUCH LOWER
BUDGET.
WHAT IS MORE SURPRISING IS,
THEY MAKE SHOWS,
LOTS AND LOTS OF SHOWS.
AND THEY ARE SO MUCH STRANGER
THAN YOU'D THINK.
SO TONIGHT, LET'S WATCH SOME
NRATV TOGETHER.
BECAUSE IT'S FASCINATING.
NOW, SOME SHOWS ARE PRETTY
SIMILAR TO ONES YOU'D SEE
ANYWHERE ON TV, WITH THE KEY
DIFFERENCE THAT THERE IS A GUN
INVOLVED.
FOR INSTANCE, THEY HAVE THREE
DIFFERENT "ANTIQUES ROADSHOW"
KNOCKOFFS IN WHICH MEN WHO LOOK
LIKE THIS GUY GET PROGRESSIVELY
MORE AND MORE AROUSED BY THE
GUNS THEY'RE HOLDING.
>> WHAT'S UNIQUE IS THAT IT HAS
SUCH FLOWING LINES.
IT'S ARTWORK.
IT'S A SENSUOUS GUN.
THAT'S THE KIND OF PISTOL THAT
WHEN I HOLD OR WHEN JOHN IS
HOLDING, IT GIVES ME SHIVERS.
THE IDEA WAS IS THAT YOU
WOULD COCK BOTH HAMMERS AT THE
SAME TIME.
>> John: THAT MAN IS
DOUG WICKLUND, AND I LOVE HIM,
BUT NOT AS MUCH AS HE LOVES
GUNS.
IN FACT, THE ONLY WAY HE COULD
LOVE THEM ANY MORE IS IF,
INSTEAD OF BULLETS, EVERY GUN
JUST FIRED A BUNCH OF LITTLE
BUNCH OF EVEN SMALLER GUNS
WHICH, IN TURN, FIRED TINY
DOUG WICKLUNDS LIVING
IN A STATE OF SEXUAL ECSTASY
INSIDE THE WOMB-LIKE PARADISE OF
A FIREARM.
AND WHILE THAT SHOW IS PRETTY
SEDATE, NRATV ALSO HAS
PROGRAMMING FOR THE
TESTOSTERONE-FUELED GUN
ENTHUSIAST, LIKE "MEDIA LAB," IN
WHICH A FORMER NAVY SEAL NAMED
DOM RASO DOES THE VERY IMPORTANT
WORK OF REENACTING MOVIES HE
LIKES, FROM "WHITE HOUSE DOWN"
TO "JACK REACHER."
AND HERE HE IS RE-ENACTING
SCENES FROM THE MOVIE "HEAT."
>> THE MAIN PART OF THIS MOVIE
THAT I WANTED TO BREAK DOWN WAS
THE FACT THAT THEY'RE SHOOTING,
MOVING, AND COMMUNICATING, AND
IF WE GET PAST THE FACT THAT
THEY'RE ROBBING A BANK, IF
YOU'RE ACTUALLY IN A SPECIFIC
UNIFORM WITH SPECIFIC KIT, CAN
YOU SHOOT, MOVE, COMMUNICATE
WITH THAT AMOUNT OF WEIGHT AND
DO DOWN-MAN DRILLS?
THAT'S THE KEY THING HERE.
>> John: I'D LOVE TO SEE A BANK
ROBBER TRY TO USE THAT DEFENSE
IN COURT.
"YOUR HONOR, I REALLY FEEL WE
NEED TO GET PAST THE FACT THAT
WE WERE ROBBING A BANK, AND
INSTEAD FOCUS ON HOW WELL WE
WERE SHOOTING, MOVING, AND
COMMUNICATING."
AND THE ENDEARING THING ABOUT
DOM RASO IS THAT HIS SHOW'S
RE-ENACTMENTS DON'T ALWAYS GO
SMOOTHLY.
FOR INSTANCE, HOW DID HIS
RE-ENACTMENT OF THE "HEAT"
ROBBERY GO?
>> THEY MAKE IT LOOK EASY, THE
WAY THEY'RE MOVING.
>> YEAH, THIS BAG, AS I WAS
RUNNING, WAS JUST HITTING AT THE
BACK OF MY KNEES, HAVE TAKEN MY
LEGS OUT FROM UNDERNEATH ME.
DEFINITELY FATIGUED ME.
>> MY STRAP BROKE.
SO I WAS HOLDING IT LIKE THIS
THE ENTIRE TIME, WOBBLING BACK
AND FORTH, EVEN IN THE
BEGINNING.
COULDN'T GET A STABLE SHOOTING
PLATFORM.
I MEAN, WE WORKED IT OUT.
I HAD TO LOWER MY CENTER OF
GRAVITY MORE SO THE BAG COULDN'T
CONTROL ME.
WE DEFINITELY PROVED THAT THEY
DIDN'T HAVE ANY WEIGHT IN THERE
WHILE THEY WERE SHOOTING AND
MOVING.
>> John: WOW.
THAT IS GENUINELY INSPIRING.
BECAUSE SOMEWHERE OUT THERE,
THERE'S AN EIGHT-YEAR-OLD
ASSHOLE WATCHING
THAT SHOW AND THINKING,
"OH, GOOD, BEING AN ADULT IS
LITERALLY EXACTLY HOW I IMAGINED
IT."
HONESTLY, I COULD TALK ABOUT
DOM RASO ALL NIGHT, BUT BEFORE
WE MOVE ON, I HAVE TO SHOW YOU
HIS INEXPLICABLE RESPONSE TO A
VIEWER-SUBMITTED QUESTION.
>> WHAT IS YOUR MOST TREASURED
POSSESSION?
>> I WOULD SAY, MY AUNT GAVE ME
A CROSS THAT WAS MADE OUT OF
BONES.
SHE'S LIKE, YOUR
GREAT-GREAT-GRANDFATHER GAVE
THAT TO ME TO PASS DOWN TO
SOMEBODY SPECIAL IN THE FAMILY,
BUT IT WAS ACTUALLY MADE OUT OF
HUMAN BONE AND HE CARVED IT WHEN
HE WAS A PRISONER OF WAR AND
THAT HAS BEEN PASSED DOWN IN THE
FAMILY.
NOW I'M LIKE, ARE YOU SERIOUS?
I'M LIKE, THAT JUST DOESN'T
EXIST.
SO THAT'S PROBABLY BY FAR THE
COOLEST THING THAT I HAVE.
>> John: WELL, THAT'S A HELL OF
A STORY THERE, DOM.
AND I JUST DON'T KNOW OF ANY
BETTER POSTER BOY FOR THE NRA
THAN SOMEONE WHO RE-ENACTS BANK
ROBBERIES FOR FUN AND WHOSE MOST
TREASURED POSSESSION IS A CROSS
MADE OUT OF HUMAN BONES.
BUT, LOOK, NRATV ISN'T ALL GUN
BROS.
THERE'S ALSO A LARGE AMOUNT OF
CONTENT EXPLICITLY AIMED AT
WOMEN.
THERE'S EVEN A WHOLE WOMEN'S
CHANNEL FEATURING SHOWS LIKE
"ARMED AND FABULOUS."
THE NRA IS ACTUALLY MAKING A BIG
PUSH FOR WOMEN, AND THEY'RE
PRETTY CLEAR ABOUT THEIR
MOTIVATIONS.
>> WOMEN REALLY HAVE AN
INCREDIBLE ROLE RIGHT NOW IN THE
NRA.
THEY ARE EXCITED.
THEY ARE ENTHUSIASTIC.
THEY ARE THERE FOR US AND
THAT'S --
YOU KNOW, IF YOU GET THE
WOMAN, YOU GET THE FAMILY.
>> John: "IF YOU GET THE WOMAN,
YOU GET THE FAMILY."
THAT IS A BRAZENLY TRANSPARENT
STATEMENT OF YOUR MARKETING
STRATEGY.
BUT TO BE HONEST,
CAN WE JUST GO BACK TO THAT ROOM
FOR A SECOND?
DO YOU FIND THAT ROOM RELAXING?
IS THAT A SOOTHING SPACE FOR
YOU?
BECAUSE I WOULD BE A LITTLE
DISTURBED BY THE EXTENDED FAMILY
OF GAZELLES SCREAMING "WHY?" AT
ME WITH THEIR DEAD, GLASSY EYES.
NOW, ONE OF THE NRA'S
FEMALE-FOCUSED PROGRAMS,
"LOVE AT FIRST SHOT," IS
EXPLICITLY ABOUT GETTING WOMEN
MORE COMFORTABLE WITH THE IDEA
OF OWNING OR FIRING GUNS, AND IN
ONE EPISODE, THEY TOOK A WOMAN
WHO WAS NERVOUS ABOUT FIREARMS
AND REALLY THREW HER IN AT THE
DEEP END.
>> WE'RE GOING TO GO STRAIGHT
INTO RIFLES, AND WE'RE GOING TO
DO IT WITH AN AR-15.
>> OKAY.
>> I KNOW YOU PROBABLY HEARD
ABOUT THEM ON THE NEWS AND
EVERYTHING ELSE.
>> I HIT THE TARGET.
>> YOU DID.
HOW DID IT FEEL?
>> NOT AS SCARY AS I THINK I WAS
ANTICIPATING.
>> EXACTLY.
IT'S JUST THIS NICE LIGHT POOF
OF HAPPINESS.
>> YEAH, YEAH.
>> John: "A LIGHT POOF OF
HAPPINESS."
IT'S A LITTLE WEIRD TO DESCRIBE
A SEMI-AUTOMATIC RIFLE THE WAY
BOB ROSS DESCRIBES
A FUCKING CLOUD.
BUT ONCE "LOVE AT FIRST SHOT"
HAS WOMEN HOOKED, THE UPSELLING
BEGINS, WHICH ACTUALLY MAKES
SENSE.
INDUSTRY RESEARCH HAS SHOWN THAT
WOMEN WILL SPEND HUNDREDS OF
DOLLARS ON ACCESSORIES IN
ADDITION TO THEIR GUNS.
SO YOU CAN UNDERSTAND WHY
"LOVE AT FIRST SHOT" FUNCTIONS
AS A KIND OF QVC FOR FIREARMS,
SHOWCASING PRODUCTS LIKE
MAG LOADERS, TARGETS, GUN CASES,
AND HANDBAGS.
>> OKAY, SO, AS YOU SEE HERE,
I'VE GOT A COUPLE OF DIFFERENT
STYLE OPTIONS FOR YOU.
THERE ARE A LOT OF DIFFERENT
VARIETIES OF EXTERIORS, BUT A
LOT OF THEM REALLY HAVE THE SAME
STRUCTURE IN TERMS OF CONCEAL
CARRY.
>> I NEVER WOULD'VE IMAGINED
THESE LITTLE NEAT POCKETS AND
HIDDEN CLOSURES.
KNOWING THAT YOU CAN CLOSE IT,
IT DOES PUT MY MIND AT EASE WITH
IT, SO IT'S PRETTY COOL.
>> John: GIRL, YOU DON'T EVEN
NEED A GUN BECAUSE PEOPLE ARE
GOING TO DIE WHEN THEY SEE
THAT BAG.
AND, LOOK, IT'S NOT JUST
HANDBAGS.
EVEN THE GUN ITSELF CAN BE
PROFITABLY ACCESSORIZED.
>> SO YES, WE DO HAVE A CUSTOM
LINE OF GUN PAINT FOR THE LADIES
OUT THERE.
THESE MAGS LOOK PHENOMENAL.
I LOVE THIS PRODUCT, IT'S SO
MUCH FUN TO WORK WITH, AND IT'S
GREAT TO BE ABLE TO PUT YOUR
PERSONAL TOUCH ON YOUR FIREARMS
AND YOUR ACCESSORIES.
>> John: OH, THAT'S SO FUN!
THAT IS SO FUN!
OR, IF NATALIE EVER COMMITS
MURDER, A GRAVE OVERSIGHT.
"GOOD NEWS, CHIEF.
THE MAG SAYS THE KILLER'S NAME
RIGHT ON IT.
WE DON'T KNOW WHAT MOTIVATED HER
TO GO ON A KILLING SPREE, BUT WE
DO KNOW SHE HAD A LOT OF FUN
WITH IT."
WE'VE WATCHED EVERY SINGLE
EPISODE OF "LOVE AT FIRST SHOT,"
AND I HAVE TO SHOW YOU OUR
FAVORITE CLIP.
IT'S FROM SEASON 2, EPISODE 1.
THE HOST, NATALIE, IS PREGNANT
AT THIS POINT, SO SHE CAN'T JOIN
IN ON THE SHOOTING, BUT THAT
DOESN'T MEAN THEY DIDN'T FIND A
WAY TO GET HER INVOLVED.
>> WE ARE GOING TO MAKE ART FOR
NATALIE SINCE SHE COULDN'T BE ON
THE RANGE WITH US.
>> AW.
>> WE'RE GOING TO DO SOMETHING
SPECIAL FOR HER TO HANG IN HER
BABY NURSERY.
>> YEAH!
THAT'S SO COOL!
>> THERE WE GO!
TWO FOR ONE!
>> TWO FOR ONE!
>> WE KNOW THAT YOU'RE
EXPECTING, OBVIOUSLY, SO WE
THOUGHT WE WOULD MAKE A LITTLE
SOMETHING FOR THE BABY'S
NURSERY.
>> OH, BECAUSE YOU KNOW --
OH, YOU GUYS.
>> WE SHOT PAINT.
>> John: YEAH, THEY SHOT PAINT.
SO WHEN SOMEBODY INEVITABLY ASKS
WHY YOU HAVE WHAT APPEARS TO BE
A BLANK CANVAS WITH A LARGE
BLOODSTAIN HANGING UP IN YOUR
CHILD'S NURSERY, YOU'LL BE ABLE
TO COMPLETELY REASSURE THEM BY
SAYING, "OH, YEAH, MY FRIEND
SHOT THAT FOR ME."
BUT IT'S NOT ALL FUN WITH GUNS.
WHERE NRATV REALLY COMES INTO
ITS OWN IS WHEN ITS TONE GETS
MUCH DARKER.
WHICH IT DOES.
FOR INSTANCE, THEY HAVE A SERIES
OF HUNTING VIDEOS, WHICH
SHOULDN'T BE SURPRISING.
IN FACT, IT MAKES COMPLETE
SENSE.
PEOPLE DO USE GUNS WHEN THEY
HUNT.
BUT WHILE THE VISUALS ARE
PREDICTABLE BEAUTY SHOTS OF
NATURE, THE VOICEOVER TAKES A
DIFFERENT PATH.
>> SOMEWHERE OVER THIS HORIZON
SIT A MILLION LITTLE DICTATORS
EAGER TO PURGE HUMANITY OF ITS
HUNTING INSTINCTS.
THE ANTI-HUNTERS HAVE IMPOSED A
FALSE ORDER ON THEIR LIVES BASED
ON A MISCONCEIVED PERCEPTION OF
THE WORLD.
DEATH IS EVIL, THEY BELIEVE, AND
SO THE PURVEYOR OF DEATH MUST
ALSO BE EVIL.
DEATH IS AN UNDENIABLE FUEL OF
LIFE.
>> John: OH, MY GOD.
THAT IS LESS "PLANET EARTH" AND
MORE "DERANGED LETTER FROM A
SERIAL KILLER."
ALTHOUGH, TO BE HONEST, I'D
RESPECT THE NRA MORE IF ITS
SLOGAN WERE JUST "THE NRA:
BECAUSE DEATH IS AN UNDENIABLE
FUEL OF LIFE."
I WOULDN'T LIKE IT, BUT AT LEAST
WE'D BE CLEAR WHERE THEY WERE
COMING FROM.
AND THAT FLOWERY,
VAGUELY THREATENING TONE IS A
KEY FEATURE OF NRATV.
HERE'S ANOTHER WEIRD EXAMPLE.
>> HIDDEN BENEATH THE DENSE
CANOPY OF DECIDUOUS TREES IS A
PROSTITUTE OF SORTS, AND THOSE
WHO PROFIT BY SELLING HER WILL
STOP AT NOTHING TO EXPLOIT HER.
SOLD AND PROMOTED FOR HER
NON-ADDICTIVE, EVEN MEDICINAL
ADVANTAGES, WHAT LIES BEHIND THE
VEIL OF THIS SEDUCTRESS IS FAR
DIFFERENT THAN WHAT SHE FIRST
APPEARS TO BE.
SHE IS A HARLOT, AND HER NAME IS
MARY JANE.
>> John: I DIDN'T THINK THIS WAS
POSSIBLE, BUT I THINK THAT GUY
JUST SLUT-SHAMED MARIJUANA.
"AND DON'T GET ME STARTED ON
MUSHROOMS, THOSE FILTHY TRAMPS.
THEY'LL GROW NEXT TO ANY TREE AT
ALL.
WHORES WITH SPORES, THAT'S WHAT
I CALL 'EM."
AND IF YOU'RE WONDERING WHY
NRATV IS EVEN TALKING ABOUT
DRUGS AT ALL, THE FINAL
DEFINING CHARACTERISTIC OF THE
NETWORK IS PAINTING A BLEAK
VISION OF AMERICA WITH THREATS
AROUND EVERY SINGLE CORNER AND
ONE SOLUTION.
>> THE NEXT ATTACK ON OUR SOIL
COULD COME IN A MATTER OF
MINUTES.
>> TEENAGE GIRLS ARE TRAFFICKED
IN SEX TRADE.
>> TODAY'S AMERICA IS PLAGUED BY
URBAN RIOTS AND DOMESTIC ISIS
SYMPATHIZERS.
>> IN A NATURAL DISASTER, YOU
MAY CALL 911, AND THERE MAY BE
NOBODY ON THE OTHER LINE.
>> THE DRUG CARTELS AND THE
HUMAN TRAFFICKERS WHO HAVE
INVADED OUR BORDERS AND EMBEDDED
IN EVERY SINGLE AMERICAN CITY.
>> THIS THREAT IS REAL.
OUR LEADERS ARE EITHER INCAPABLE
OF OR UNWILLING TO PROTECT YOU,
AND THE AR-15 IS ONE OF THE MOST
EFFECTIVE TOOLS AVAILABLE TO
PROTECT YOURSELF AND YOUR
FAMILY.
>> John: HOLY SHIT.
THEY'RE USING THE SAME
TECHNIQUES AS AN INFOMERCIAL.
"IS HUMAN TRAFFIC GETTING YOU
DOWN?
DO YOU HAVE ISIS SYMPATHIZERS IN
THOSE HARD-TO-REACH PLACES?
ARE YOU TIRED OF GETTING 9/11'D?
THERE'S GOT TO BE A BETTER WAY!
TRY THE AR-15!
AVAILABLE AT WAY TOO MANY STORES
NEAR YOU."
NOW, TO WATCH NRATV IS TO WATCH
A CONSTANT STREAM OF STORIES
LIKE THOSE -- MANY REAL, BUT
AMPLIFIED TO TERRIFY YOU AND
SELL YOU PRODUCTS.
AND THERE MAY BE A GOOD REASON
IT SOUNDS LIKE AN INFOMERCIAL --
BECAUSE IT IS.
MANY OF NRATV'S SHOWS ARE
SPONSORED BY GUN BRANDS LIKE
SMITH & WESSON.
AND BEHIND THE SCENES OF NRATV
IS AN AD AGENCY.
IT'S CALLED ACKERMAN McQUEEN.
THEY'VE WORKED WITH THE NRA FOR
DECADES, AND THE
ACKERMAN McQUEEN WEBSITE
PROCLAIMS, "EVERY BRAND MUST BE
ITS OWN MEDIA COMPANY."
AND THAT'S WHAT THE NRA HAVE
DONE WITH THEIR TV ARM.
THEY'VE GOT A PRODUCT TO SELL,
AND THEY EMPLOY PEOPLE WHO CAN
SELL THAT PRODUCT.
EVEN DANA LOESCH, THE CLENCHED
FIST OF TRUTH, WHEN SHE'S NOT
WARNING OF THE DRUG CARTELS AND
HUMAN TRAFFICKERS IN EVERY
SINGLE AMERICAN CITY, IS SELLING
YOU SOME OTHER SHIT.
>> HI, I'M DANA LOESCH FROM
"THE DANA SHOW."
THERE'S ONE SUPERFOOD I DRINK
EVERY DAY FOR HEALTHY
CIRCULATION AND TO MAKE ME FEEL
GREAT ALL DAY LONG.
IT'S CALLED SUPERBEETS, AND YOU
CAN TRY IT FOR YOURSELF
RISK FREE.
I TAKE SUPERBEETS AS MY
PRE-WORKOUT IN THE MORNING AND
AS A NON-JITTERY PICK-ME-UP IN
THE AFTERNOON.
AND JUST ONE TEASPOON OF
SUPERBEETS GIVES YOU THE BENEFIT
OF THREE WHOLE BEETS.
>> John: WOW, DANA.
THREE WHOLE BEETS.
THAT'S MORE THAN MY DELICIOUS
SUPERFOOD, "MEDIUM BEETS."
IT GIVES YOU THE BENEFITS OF TWO
WHOLE BEETS, WHICH IS, AND THIS
IS TRUE, ENOUGH.
THAT'S A PERFECTLY ADEQUATE
NUMBER OF BEETS.
THE WHOLE POINT HERE IS,
THE ANSWER TO THE QUESTION
"WHAT THE FUCK IS NRATV?"
IS, "IT'S JUST A VESSEL
TO SELL AMERICA GUNS."
THAT'S PRETTY MUCH IT.
DOES IT WORK?
IT'S HARD TO SAY.
THEY WON'T REVEAL THEIR RATINGS,
SO IT'S PLAUSIBLE THAT NO ONE IS
WATCHING THIS AND THAT AD
AGENCY, ACKERMAN McQUEEN, ARE
MAKING OUT LIKE BANDITS.
HAVING WATCHED A SHITLOAD OF
NRATV'S PROGRAMMING, HERE'S WHAT
I'LL SAY ABOUT IT.
THERE IS A LOT TO BE CONCERNED
ABOUT REGARDING THE NRA'S
ACTIVITIES, BUT NRATV MIGHT
ACTUALLY BE THE DUMBEST, MOST
TRANSPARENT THING IT DOES.
THINK OF IT THIS WAY.
IF THE NRA IS A FEROCIOUS BEAR
CHARGING AT YOU, NRATV IS
THAT BEAR'S RIDICULOUS HAT.
IS IT EYE-CATCHING?
SURE.
IS IT PERVERSELY ENTERTAINING?
ABSOLUTELY.
IS IT THE MAIN THING YOU SHOULD
BE WORRIED ABOUT?
PROBABLY NOT.
BECAUSE THE REAL TRUTH HERE IS,
HAT OR NO HAT, IT IS IMPERATIVE
THAT EVERYONE KEEP THEIR EYES ON
THAT FUCKING BEAR.
AND NOW THIS.
>> AND NOW PROOF THAT NRATV'S
TONE CAN MAKE ANYTHING SEEM
SCARY.
>> HAS YOUR KITCHEN THAT ONCE
GLEAMED IN THE SOFT GLOW OF DAWN
NOW BECOME A LOG OF COUNTERTOPS?
SHE IS THE OVEN'S CONTEMPTIBLE
WHORE, AND HER NAME IS MUFFINS.
THE MUFFINS GLUTINOUS PRISON,
EACH A FOOD SLAVE IN ITS CRUSTY
WALLS.
AMERICANS ONCE RELISHED OUR
RIGHT TO A STACK OF FLAPJACKS
AND A CUP OF JOE, BUT NOW WE
TREMBLE BEFORE SATAN'S CUPCAKES.
SHOW UNCUT AND FLAPJACKS AND
STACKED.
WHEN THE MUFFINS RISE, WE MUST
RISE AGAINST THEM, BECAUSE YOU
DON'T KNOW THE MUFFIN MAN,
AMERICO, AND YOU HAD BETTER PRAY
YOU NEVER DO.
PANCAKES, THE UNDENIABLE VIEW OF
LIFE.
>> John: THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
GOOD NIGHT!