WELCOME, WELCOME,
WELCOME TO "LAST WEEK TONIGHT!"
I'M JOHN OLIVER.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR JOINING
US.
JUST TIME FOR A QUICK RECAP OF
THE WEEK. AND IT'S BEEN BUSY ONE.
A FORMER FACEBOOK EMPLOYEE
CONFIRMED WHAT EVERYONE
BASICALLY KNEW, FACEBOOK'S
TERRIBLE AND IT'S VERY MUCH BY
DESIGN.
OTIS THE BEAR, THE THREE-TIME
WINNER OF FAT BEAR WEEK BECAME
THE FOUR-TIME WINNER, BECAUSE
MERITOCRACY IS A LIE AND OUR
SYSTEM IS BROKEN.
AND IN IDAHO, THERE WAS THIS
DRAMATIC POWER GRAB.
THERE IS A BLISTERING BATTLE
HAPPENING NOW BETWEEN THE TWO
TOP ELECTED OFFICIALS IN IDAHO.
LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR JANICE
McGEACHIN SIGNED AN EXECUTIVE
ORDER BANNING VACCINE MANDATES
IN SCHOOLS AND COVID TESTING IN
CERTAIN CAPACITIES.
THE PROBLEM IS THE GOVERNOR,
BRAD LITTLE, WAS OUT OF THE
STATE WHEN SHE DID IT, AND
QUICKLY PROMISED TO UNDO THE
ORDER.
YEAH, IT'S TRUE!
WHILE THE IDAHO GOVERNOR WAS OUT
OF STATE, HIS LIEUTENANT
GOVERNOR ISSUED AN EXECUTIVE
ORDER TRYING TO BAN SCHOOLS FROM
REQUIRING EMPLOYEES TO BE
VACCINATED.
AND NOT JUST THAT... SHE ALSO
SENT THE STATE NATIONAL GUARD A
QUERY ABOUT ACTIVATING TROOPS
AND SENDING THEM TO THE
U.S.-MEXICO BORDER.
WHICH IS A PRETTY BOLD MOVE FROM
A SECOND IN COMMAND.
IT'S BASICALLY A PLANE'S PILOT
GOING TO THE BATHROOM AND THE
CO-PILOT ANNOUNCING, "CHANGE OF
PLANS, WE'RE HEADED TO RENO.
MY BUDDY SAID HE'D SET ME UP
WITH HIS COUSIN IF I WAS EVER
THERE, AND I SAW A PICTURE OF HER
AND SHE'S AN ABSOLUTE SMOKESHOW.
SO STRAP IN, FOLKS.
IT'S GONNA BE BUMPY ON PURPOSE."
AND THE THING IS, IN IDAHO, THE
LIEUTENANT GOVERNOR DOES
TECHNICALLY BECOME ACTING
GOVERNOR WHENEVER THE ACTUAL
GOVERNOR LEAVES THE STATE THANKS
TO A STATE CONSTITUTION THAT WAS
DEFINITELY WRITTEN LONG BEFORE
CELL PHONES EXISTED, BUT KNOWING
THAT, IT'S PRETTY REMARKABLE
THAT BRAD LITTLE CHOSE TO LEAVE
THE STATE AT ALL, ESPECIALLY
BECAUSE McGEACHIN HAD ACTUALLY
TRIED A SIMILAR STUNT BACK IN
MAY WHEN HE LEFT FOR A
CONFERENCE IN TENNESSEE AND SHE
ISSUED AN ORDER BANNING MASK
MANDATES.
SO IT FEELS BORDERLINE RECKLESS
FOR HIM TO STEP OUTSIDE THE
STATE RIGHT NOW
BECAUSE IT'S NOT LIKE SHE'S EVER
DISGUISED WHO SHE IS.
JUST LOOK AT THIS APPEARANCE SHE
MADE LAST YEAR IN A VIDEO
CRITICIZING COVID RESTRICTIONS.
WE RECOGNIZE THAT ALL OF US
ARE, BY NATURE, FREE AND EQUAL,
AND HAVE CERTAIN INALIENABLE
RIGHTS, AMONG WHICH ARE ENJOYING
AND DEFENDING LIFE AND LIBERTY,
ACQUIRING, POSSESSING, AND
PROTECTING PROPERTY, AND
PURSUING HAPPINESS, AND SECURING
SAFETY.
WOW.
THAT IS A RICH TEXT.
ALTHOUGH, I WILL SAY, THAT
REPRESENTS THE REPUBLICAN PARTY
BETTER THAN ANYTHING I'VE EVER
SEEN.
AN ELEPHANT?
DOESN'T QUITE DO IT.
A SWIRLY SNAKE SAYING DON'T
TREAD ON ME?
NO.
BUT A GUN BIBLE AND A MISQUOTED
DECLARATION OF INDEPENDENCE?
THAT IS THE REPUBLICAN PARTY I
KNOW.
AND IT SEEMS LIKE THIS IS GOING
TO BE AN ONGOING PROBLEM, HAVING
TO KEEP A CONSTANT EYE ON THE
ULTRA-RIGHT IN THIS COUNTRY, SO
THEY DON'T SUDDENLY GRAB THE
WHEEL AND STEER US STRAIGHT INTO
HELL.
AND SPEAKING OF HELL, THAT
BRINGS US TO OUR SECOND STORY,
OAN, THE ONE AMERICA NEWS
NETWORK.
YOU MAY REMEMBER WE COVERED IT
LAST YEAR.
IT'S A FAR RIGHT CHANNEL THAT
PEDDLES COVID MISINFORMATION AND
CONSPIRACY THEORIES.
WELL, THIS WEEK, WE LEARNED SOME
PRETTY UNSETTLING NEWS.
A NEW REUTERS INVESTIGATION
BASED ON A REVIEW OF COURT
RECORDS REVEALS THAT OANN HAS
FLOURISHED THANKS TO FINANCIAL
SUPPORT FROM A SURPRISING
MAINSTREAM SOURCE, AT&T.
YUP!
TURNS OUT AT&T HAS BEEN UP TO
SOME SHIT.
AND IT'S WORTH NOTING... AT&T IS
STILL, TECHNICALLY, OUR BUSINESS
DADDY, MAKING OAN OUR BUSINESS
STEPSIBLING, AND NOT IN A HOT
WAY.
REUTERS REPORTED THAT, IN
DEPOSITIONS, OAN'S FOUNDER
ROBERT HERRING TESTIFIED AT&T
EXECUTIVES ONCE TOLD HIM THEY
WANTED A CONSERVATIVE NETWORK,
AND HE CLAIMS, "WHEN THEY SAID
THAT, I JUMPED TO IT AND BUILT
ONE."
AND ONCE HE BUILT THE CHANNEL,
AT&T CARRIED IT.
FIRST ON THEIR U-VERSE SYSTEM,
AND THEN ON DIRECT TV.
AND WITH THAT HELP, OAN HAS
GROWN INTO THE TOXIC NETWORK IT
IS TODAY, ONE THAT'S HAPPY TO
GIVE A PLATFORM TO BATSHIT
ELECTION FRAUD THEORIES FROM
AMERICA'S MOST OUT-OF-BREATH
PILLOW FETISHIST, AND ONE THAT,
A FEW MONTHS AGO, FEATURED ONE
OF ITS COMMENTATORS SAYING THIS.
DESPITE THEIR BEST EFFORTS,
THE RADICAL DEMOCRATS LEFT
FINGERPRINTS ALL OVER THE
COUNTRY, PROVIDING A TRAIL OF
EVIDENCE THAT THE 2020 ELECTION
WAS NOT ONLY TAMPERED WITH, BUT
WAS ACTUALLY OVERTHROWN.
ANY AMERICAN INVOLVED IN THESE
EFFORTS, FROM THOSE WHO RAN THE
VOTING MACHINES TO THE VERY
HIGHEST GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS, IS
GUILTY OF TREASON UNDER U.S.
CODE 2381, WHICH CARRIES WITH IT
THE PENALTY OF DEATH.
LOOK, I GET THAT WE'RE
WATCHING A CALL FOR MASS
EXECUTIONS FROM A GUY WITH, FOR
LACK OF A BETTER TERM, "BIG
THEATER KID ENERGY," BUT ARE YOU
REALLY SAYING THOSE WHO RAN THE
VOTING MACHINES COULD BE
TRAITORS?
YOU MEAN DOLORES?
DOLORES FROM DOWN THE STREET?
WHO VOLUNTEERED TO SPEND 12
HOURS OF HER... LET'S FACE IT...
DWINDLING "NCIS" -WATCHING TIME
DOLING OUT PARTICIPATION
STICKERS TO VOTERS?
THAT DOLORES?
ALL RIGHT, DEATH TO DOLORES, I
GUESS.
SORRY, LO-LO, BUT DECAF PITBULL
HERE HEARD A RUMOR FROM A PILLOW
SALESMAN THAT YOU DESERVE THE
CHAIR.
NOW, I HAVE TO TELL YOU, AT&T
SAYS THAT NO "SENIOR" EXECUTIVE
SUGGESTED TO HERRING THAT HE
CREATE ANOTHER CONSERVATIVE
NETWORK, WITH THE CARVE-OUT OF
"SENIOR" THERE BEING PRETTY
STRIKING.
THEY ALSO SAY THEY'VE NEVER HAD
A FINANCIAL INTEREST IN OAN'S
SUCCESS AND "DO NOT FUND" THE
NETWORK, NEITHER OF WHICH IS
100% THE ISSUE HERE.
THEY ALSO CLAIM THE ONLY REASON
OAN WAS ON DIRECTV WAS THAT THE
NETWORK HAD SUED THEM.
AND OKAY!
I GUESS THE LARGEST TELECOM
COMPANY IN THE WORLD GOT ROLLED
IN A LAWSUIT BY A RAGTAG BAND OF
FASCISTS.
IT HAPPENS!
BUT THE LARGER POINT IS, OAN
WOULD BE LITERALLY NOTHING
WITHOUT AT&T.
AN OAN ACCOUNTANT REPORTEDLY
SAID, UNDER OATH, THAT AT&T
PROVIDED 90% OF HERRING
NETWORKS' INCOME.
AS FOR OAN'S HORRENDOUS CONTENT,
AT&T TOLD US DIRECTV RESPECTS
THE EDITORIAL INDEPENDENCE OF
THE CHANNELS IT CARRIES, JUST AS
AT&T IS COMMITTED TO PROVIDING
EDITORIAL INDEPENDENCE FOR EVERY
WARNER MEDIA SHOW, INCLUDING
THIS ONE.
AND THAT IS SUCH A RELIEF!
ESPECIALLY THAT LAST PART.
BECAUSE IF I MAY, I'D LIKE TO
USE THAT GENEROUS EDITORIAL
INDEPENDENCE TO OFFER SOME
CONSTRUCTIVE FEEDBACK.
TAKE AT&T'S RECENT CAMPAIGN.
"MORE FOR YOUR THING, THAT'S OUR
THING," WHICH IS, RESPECTFULLY,
COMPLETE GIBBERISH.
IT SOUNDS LIKE YODA PITCHING A
PENIS-ENLARGEMENT DEVICE.
IT'S SO NONSENSICAL I HAVE TO
ASSUME SOMETHING WAS LOST IN
COMMUNICATION, WHICH ACTUALLY
WOULD BE A MUCH MORE APPROPRIATE
SLOGAN FOR THE COMPANY.
AND IF YOU DON'T LIKE THAT,
AT&T, DON'T WORRY, I'VE GOT
MORE.
HOW ABOUT "AT&T, ALL THE
BUSINESS SAVVY OF QUIBI WITHOUT
THE COURTESY OF COMMITTING
CORPORATE SUICIDE."
OR "AT&T, IF YOU RUN A CABLE OUT
THE BACK OF YOUR HEADQUARTERS
AND PLUG IT INTO T-MOBILE'S
NETWORK WHILE THEY AREN'T
LOOKING, THAT'S LEGAL, RIGHT?
ASKING FOR A FRIEND."
ANY OF THOSE ARE YOURS IF YOU
WANT THEM!
AND LOOK, AT&T, I KNOW OUR
RELATIONSHIP IS A LITTLE
AWKWARD, ESPECIALLY SINCE YOU'RE
TRYING TO SPIN THIS BUSINESS
BABY OFF IN YOUR DEAL WITH
DISCOVERY.
BUT WHILE WE'RE STILL
TECHNICALLY RELATED, LET ME JUST
SAY THIS.
YOU'RE A TERRIBLE COMPANY.
YOU DO BAD THINGS AND YOU MAKE
THE WORLD WORSE.
PLEASE DON'T BOTHER KEEPING IN
TOUCH ONCE THE MERGER'S
COMPLETE.
ALTHOUGH THAT SHOULDN'T BE A
PROBLEM.
YOU'RE AT&T.
IT'S NOT LIKE YOUR MESSAGES WILL
GO THROUGH ANYWAY.
AND NOW, THIS.
AND NOW, FOX AND FRIENDS AS
BRIAN KILL MEAD LIKES
CHRISTOPHER COLUMBUS WAY, WAY
TOO MUCH.
IF YOU READ ONE REPUTABLE
BOOK ON COLUMBUS AND STILL DON'T
THINK WE SHOULD HAVE A
COLUMBUS DAY, YOU'RE NOT PAYING
ATTENTION.
HE MARRIED TO WORLD OF THE TIME.
I JUST DID THE MATH, 527 YEARS
AGO, CHRISTOPHER COLUMBUS
DISCOVERED THE NEW WORLD.
WHAT HE DID AS AN EXPLORER
FIGHTING THE ODDS TO DO SO THEY
SAID WAS LIKE GOING TO THE MOON
TODAY BUT ONLY MORE DANGEROUS.
ONE PERSON DESCRIBED AS GOING TO
THE MOON BACK IN THE 1960s
ONLY MORE DANGEROUS.
ONLY IT WAS MORE DANGEROUS.
BASICALLY, HE DID THE EQUIVALENT
OF GOING TO THE MOON IN THE
1490s.
NOT GOOD ENOUGH.
ACTUALLY MORE DANGEROUS.
I WAS ALMOST THE CHRISTOPHER
COLUMBUS OF THE SHOW.
YOU ARE THE CHRISTOPHER
COLUMBUS OF PET GIVES.
SOME PEOPLE WHO THINK
COLUMBUS IS ACTUALLY SPANISH.
I DON'T BUY THAT AT ALL.
I READ FOUR VOYAGES AND TOTALLY
ITALIAN.
COULDN'T BE MORE ITALIAN.
I WAS COLUMBUS FOR HALLOWEEN, NO
PICTURES AVAILABLE.
I'M LIKE WHAT YOU TALKING
ABOUT?
MOVING ON.
FOR A MAIN STORY TONIGHT, WE'RE
GOING TO TALK ABOUT THE
INTERNET, MAGICAL PLACE WHERE
YOU FIND COMMUNITIES OF
LIKE-MINDED INDIVIDUALS LIKE A
TIKTOKER WHO CREATED THE STORY
ABOUT THINGS NARROWLY FITTING
INTO TIGHT SPACES, SOMETHING THE
SUCCEEDING WEEK BRITISH WOMAN
WAS A BIG FAN OF.
ALL RIGHT, HERE WE GO!
OH, THAT WENT NICE.
THAT LITERALLY FITTED PERFECTLY.
OH, THAT'S NICE.
OH, BLOODY HELL, BIT CLOSE FOR
COMFORT, THAT.
STRESSING ME OUT A BIT, BUT THAT
WERE NICE.
OH, GO ON!
OH, YES, GO ON.
HOW'D YOU FIND THAT ALL THESE
THINGS FIT, DO YOU KNOW WHAT I MEAN?
DID YOU JUST SIT IN YOUR HOUSE
AND JUST SEE IF THINGS FIT IN HOLES?
YOU KNOW WHAT?
SHE'S ASKING A LEGITIMATE
QUESTION THERE.
AND I DO THINK THE ANSWER IS
"YES."
BUT SADLY, OUR STORY ISN'T GOING
TO BE ABOUT THE FUN SIDE OF THE
INTERNET.
IT'S GOING TO BE ABOUT THE
RAMPANT MISINFORMATION ON IT.
IT'S SOMETHING WE'VE COVERED
MULTIPLE TIMES BEFORE, FROM ALEX
JONES TO VACCINE MISINFORMATION
TO CONSPIRACY THEORIES.
BUT TONIGHT, WE'RE GOING TO LOOK
SPECIFICALLY AT MISINFORMATION
THAT SPREADS AMONG IMMIGRANT,
DIASPORA COMMUNITIES.
BASICALLY, INSTEAD OF STUFF LIKE
THIS FACEBOOK POST IN ENGLISH,
TITLED "THE FAKE VACCINATION OF
KAMALA HARRIS," WHICH,
INCIDENTALLY, FACEBOOK HAS
FLAGGED AS FALSE INFORMATION,
WE'RE GOING TO BE LOOKING AT
STUFF LIKE THIS POST IN SPANISH,
FEATURING THE EXACT SAME VIDEO
WHICH... AS OF THIS TAPING...
HAS NO SUCH WARNING.
AND THAT ACTUALLY ISN'T THAT
SURPRISING WHEN YOU CONSIDER
THAT... ACCORDING TO THE RECENT
FACEBOOK FILES EXPOSE... WHILE
MORE THAN 90 PERCENT OF
FACEBOOK'S MONTHLY USERS ARE
OUTSIDE THE U.S. AND CANADA,
WHEN IT COMES TO THE HOURS THE
COMPANY SPENDS ON MONITORING
MISINFORMATION, LAST YEAR, ONLY
13% WERE SPENT ON CONTENT FROM
OUTSIDE THE U.S.
SO IT SEEMS THAT FACEBOOK'S
ADOPTED THE SAME GENERAL
ATTITUDE TO MISINFORMATION THAT
THE OSCARS TOOK TOWARD BEST
PICTURES FOR THE FIRST 90 YEARS
OF ITS EXISTENCE.
BASICALLY, IF IT DOESN'T HAPPEN
IN ENGLISH, IT DOESN'T
FUNDAMENTALLY MATTER.
AND THE SPREAD OF MISINFORMATION
HAS REAL CONSEQUENCES.
WHEN A REPORTER RECENTLY TRIED
TO FIGURE OUT WHY VACCINATION
RATES AMONG LATINO COMMUNITIES
IN CALIFORNIA'S CENTRAL VALLEY
REMAIN LOW, ONE WOMAN EXPLAINED
HER RELUCTANCE LIKE THIS.
I'VE LISTENED TO HEALTH
LEADERS.
LIKE WHO?
THERE'S A DOCTOR WHO I'VE
HEARD AND SEEN IN SOME
DOCUMENTARIES WHO SAYS THAT THE
VIRUS IS CURABLE.
I FOUND ONE OF THE FEMALE
DOCTOR.
THE MOST IMPORTANT THING FOR
MY PEOPLE OF EL SALVADOR IS TO
SAY NO.
WE SHOULDN'T BE GETTING THE
COVID VACCINE.
HOW DID YOU FIND THIS VIDEO?
MY MOTHER SENT IT TO ME.
THROUGH WHAT MEANS?
SHE SENT IT THROUGH FACEBOOK.
WHY DO YOU BELIEVE THIS
DOCTOR AND NOT SOMEONE LIKE DR.
FAUCI?
I HAVEN'T SEEN DR. FAUCI.
NEVER?
NO, I HAVEN'T.
YEAH, THAT'S NOT GREAT!
IS IT?
AND IT'S A PRETTY GOOD REMINDER
OF HOW, THANKS TO SOCIAL MEDIA,
IT'S POSSIBLE TO SILO YOURSELF
OFF AND HAVE VERY DIFFERENT
EXPERIENCES OF LIVING IN
AMERICA.
BECAUSE SHE WAS AWARE OF A
DOCTOR FROM EL SALVADOR PEDDLING
BULLSHIT COVID CURES, BUT HAD
NEVER HEARD OF DR. FAUCI.
AND ON THAT POINT, I HONESTLY
KIND OF ENVY HER.
WHATEVER YOU THINK ABOUT FAUCI,
I THINK WE CAN ALL AGREE, IT
WOULD HAVE BEEN GREAT TO HAVE
SEEN SIGNIFICANTLY LESS OF HIM
OVER THE LAST YEAR AND A HALF.
THAT WOMAN WILL NEVER KNOW THE
DYSTOPIAN HELL OF SEEING FAUCI
SUPERIMPOSED OVER A VOTIVE
CANDLE OR HEARING PEOPLE REFER
TO THE VACCINE AS A FAUCI
OUCHIE.
SHE ENJOYS AN INNER PEACE I WILL
NEVER KNOW.
AND LOOK, WE CLEARLY HAVEN'T
REMOTELY FIGURED OUT WHAT TO DO
WITH ENGLISH-LANGUAGE
MISINFORMATION YET, AS PROVEN BY
THE FACT THAT WHEN I SAY THE
WORDS "HORSE DEWORMER" OR "THE
LETTER Q," YOU KNOW EXACTLY WHAT
I'M REFERRING TO.
BUT WHILE I KNOW IT'S HARD TO
IMAGINE THAT THE SITUATION COULD
BE WORSE, WHEN IT COMES TO
NON-ENGLISH LANGUAGE
MISINFORMATION, IT HONESTLY IS.
SO TONIGHT, LET'S TALK ABOUT
MISINFORMATION IN DIASPORA
COMMUNITIES, HOW EASILY IT CAN
BE SPREAD, AND WHAT CAN BE DONE
ABOUT IT.
AND LET'S START WITH THE FACT
THAT WHILE SOME MISINFORMATION
IS BASICALLY THE SAME IN OTHER
LANGUAGES, IN OTHER CASES, IT
TAPS INTO CULTURALLY SPECIFIC
INTERESTS OR FEARS.
FOR INSTANCE, COMMUNITIES WITH
LIVED EXPERIENCE UNDER COMMUNIST
OR SOCIALIST REGIMES ARE OFTEN
TARGETED WITH MISINFORMATION
THAT TRIES TO STOKE FEARS ABOUT
SOCIALISM.
IN FACT, JOE BIDEN'S
UNDERPERFORMANCE IN
MAJORITY-LATINO AREAS IN FLORIDA
MAY HAVE HAD A LOT TO DO WITH
THE FACT THAT CUBAN COMMUNITIES,
WERE INUNDATED BY FALSE CLAIMS
LIKE THIS.
FOR THE PAST FEW MONTHS, MANY
HISPANIC-AMERICAN VOTERS HAVE
SEEN REPORTS AND IMAGES TRYING
TO TIE JOE BIDEN TO SOCIALISM.
FOR INSTANCE, THIS PHOTO HAS
BEEN FLOATING AROUND ON SOCIAL
MEDIA.
IT CLAIMS TO BE JILL BIDEN NEXT
TO FIDEL CASTRO.
BUT IN FACT, THIS IS FALSE.
IT'S ACTUALLY A PHOTO OF LATE
NORWEGIAN EXPLORER THOR
HEYERDAHL AND HIS WIFE,
JACQUELINE BIER.
OKAY, THAT PHOTO IS
CLEARLY NOT JILL BIDEN.
AND THAT'S DEFINITELY NOT JOE
BIDEN.
ALTHOUGH IT LOOKS A LOT MORE
LIKE HIM THAN THIS ANIMATRONIC
VERSION AT DISNEY WORLD'S HALL
OF PRESIDENTS DOES.
WHAT IS GOING ON THERE?
THAT LOOKS LIKE WHAT WOULD
HAPPEN IF AN ELDERLY ANDERSON
COOPER GOT A FACELIFT FROM A
PLASTIC SURGEON WITHOUT A
MEDICAL LICENSE.
AND SOMETIMES, THE SPREAD OF
MISINFORMATION IS EXACERBATED BY
THE FACT THAT, FOR MANY DIASPORA
COMMUNITIES HERE IN THE U.S.,
THERE JUST AREN'T MANY
ALTERNATIVES IN THEIR OWN
LANGUAGES.
FOR MANY OLDER VIETNAMESE
AMERICANS, THERE'S SUCH A VACUUM
OF CREDIBLE NEWS CHANNELS THAT
BROADCAST IN VIETNAMESE THAT
MANY TURN TO YOUTUBE FOR THEIR
NEWS, WITH CERTAIN CHANNELS ON
IN THEIR HOUSES 24/7.
ONE POPULAR HOST BASED HERE IN
THE U.S. IS NGUY VU, WHO BRANDS
HIMSELF "KING RADIO."
HE'S BASICALLY A VIETNAMESE ALEX
JONES, AS YOU CAN SEE IN RANTS
LIKE THESE.
CHINA COMPLETELY HAS CONTROL
OF BIDEN.
THE WHOLE SITUATION WITH HUNTER
BIDEN'S LAPTOP AND THE TROVE OF
DATA IT CONTAINS, I THINK XI
JINPING HAS GOT HIS HANDS ON ALL
OF IT.
GEORGE SOROS WAS PART OF THE
FINANCIAL PLOT TO OVERTHROW THE
TRUMP ADMINISTRATION.
WHY ARE WE STILL BEING FORCED TO
WEAR MASKS?
MASKS ARE KILLING PEOPLE.
IF YOU'RE IN A STATE THAT GIVES
YOU THE RIGHT TO NOT WEAR A
MASK, AND THEN YOU ENTER
SOMEONE'S HOUSE BUT THEY TRY TO
MAKE YOU WEAR ONE, TELL THEM
"FUCK YOU."
I MEAN, YOU CAN SEE
WHERE THE ALEX JONES COMPARISONS
COME FROM.
BOTH HAVE VOICES THAT SOUND LIKE
BONES GOING THROUGH A WOOD
CHIPPER, BOTH HAVE AN INABILITY
TO CONTROL THE VOLUME OF SAID
VOICES, AND BOTH HAVE SETS
CLEARLY INSPIRED BY A WINDOWS 95
SCREENSAVER.
ALSO, THEY SEEM TO HAVE THE SAME
BUSINESS MODEL WITH KING RADIO
SELLING HIS AUDIENCE VIAGRA,
MEDICATIONS, AND BEAUTY CREAMS
THAT HE CLAIMS ARE MADE BY HIS
COUSIN.
WHICH SHOULD BE A HUGE RED FLAG.
UNLESS HIS COUSIN IS NAMED STEVE
CLINIQUE, I DO NOT WANT ANY
CREAMS FROM THAT INDIVIDUAL.
BUT AGAIN, WHILE ALEX JONES HAS
BEEN REMOVED FROM YOUTUBE FOR
SPREADING MISINFORMATION, KING
RADIO IS STILL GOING STRONG ON
THE PLATFORM, DESPITE THE FACT
YOU JUST HEARD HIM SAY, "MASKS
ARE KILLING PEOPLE," WHICH
CLEARLY VIOLATES YOUTUBE'S BAN
ON CLAIMS THAT WEARING A MASK IS
DANGEROUS.
AND WHAT I GUESS THIS MEANS IS,
ALEX JONES COULD PROBABLY FIND
HIS WAY BACK ONTO YOUTUBE.
HE JUST NEEDS TO COMPLETE A
ROSETTA STONE VIETNAMESE COURSE.
AND AS BAD AS FACEBOOK AND
YOUTUBE ARE... AND THEY ARE
SCREAMINGLY BAD... AT LEAST IN
THEORY, THEY CAN BE MONITORED.
BUT THERE'S ANOTHER WAY
MISINFORMATION SPREADS THAT'S
ACTUALLY INVISIBLE TO MOST
PEOPLE, AND UNFORTUNATELY, ALSO
HAPPENS TO BE ONE OF THE MOST
POPULAR TOOLS OF COMMUNICATION
AMONG IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES, AND
THAT IS PRIVATE MESSAGING APPS.
THE BIGGEST, BY FAR, IS
WHATSAPP, OWNED BY FACEBOOK,
WHICH IS MASSIVE ALL OVER THE
WORLD.
SO MUCH SO, IT'S BECOME PART OF
MANY PEOPLE'S DAILY ROUTINE.
IN INDIA, SENDING "GOOD MORNING"
MESSAGES ON WHATSAPP IS
INCREDIBLY POPULAR, MEANING
MILLIONS OF PEOPLE WAKE UP TO
RELATIVES HAVING SENT THEM ONE
OF THESE, OR EVEN A VIDEO LIKE
THIS.
I WILL SAY, THAT'S AN
AGGRESSIVELY PLEASANT WAY TO
WAKE UP!
WHEN WE CAME ACROSS THAT MESSAGE
UPLOADED TO YOUTUBE, THE TOP
CMMENT WAS SIMPLY "NICE."
WHICH IS PRETTY STRIKING.
NOTHING ELSE ON THE PLATFORM HAS
A RESPONSE THAT WHOLESOME.
YOU JUST KNOW THE AMERICAN
VERSION OF GOOD MORNING WOULD
HAVE A TOP COMMENT LIKE "YOU
KNOW WHO HAD A SHIT MORNING?
HARAMBE.
REST IN PEACE, KING."
BUT IT'S NOT JUST WHATSAPP.
CERTAIN COMMUNITIES HAVE THEIR
OWN PREFERRED APP.
KOREAN IMMIGRANTS HAVE
KAKAOTALK, WHILE MORE RECENT
CHINESE IMMIGRANTS USE WECHAT.
AND IF YOU'RE NOT ON THESE APPS,
IT CAN BE HARD TO UNDERSTAND
JUST HOW CENTRAL THEY ARE TO
PEOPLE'S LIVES.
THIS TUNE AND LOADING SCREEN
ARE INSTANTLY RECOGNIZABLE TO
OVER ONE BILLION PEOPLE AROUND
THE WORLD.
IN CHINA, WHERE MOST WESTERN
SOCIAL MEDIA IS BANNED, WECHAT
IS ESSENTIAL.
PEOPLE USE IT TO TEXT EACH
OTHER, ORDER FOOD, HAIL RIDES,
AND PAY FOR THINGS.
OUTSIDE OF CHINA, THE DIASPORA
USES IT TO CONNECT WITH FELLOW
CHINESE SPEAKERS AND ISSUES IN
THE COUNTRY THEY'RE LIVING IN.
EXACTLY.
COMMUNICATION, FOOD ORDERS,
TRAVEL, PAYMENT, EVERYTHING, ALL
IN ONE APP.
THAT'S SO MUCH MORE EFFICIENT
THAN THE U.S.-BASED MODEL, WHERE
YOU HAVE ONE APP TO CONVINCE YOU
EVERYONE'S HAVING A BETTER TIME
THAN YOU, ONE THAT FUNCTIONS AS
AN ENDLESSLY REFRESHING FURY
GENERATOR, ONE FOR PRETENDING
YOU'LL MEDITATE ONE DAY, ONE
THAT LETS YOU PAY TOO MUCH FOR
FAST FOOD, ONE FOR HORNY
MISTAKES, AND ONE THAT SIMPLY
LETS YOU KNOW THAT YOU'RE VERY
OLD AND THE WORLD NO LONGER
BELONGS TO YOU.
SO I GUESS, IN A WAY, KUDOS TO
WECHAT FOR STREAMLINING OUR
SHARED DIGITAL NIGHTMARE INTO
ONE CONVENIENT PLACE.
SO THESE APPS ARE A CHEAP AND
UBIQUITOUS WAY TO ALLOW PEOPLE
TO STAY IN TOUCH WITH FAMILY AND
FRIENDS, AND ALSO GET NEWS AND
SHARE INFORMATION IN THEIR HOME
LANGUAGES.
WHICH IS OBVIOUSLY APPEALING.
UNFORTUNATELY, THEY'RE ALSO A
HUGE VECTOR FOR MISINFORMATION.
THERE IS ACTUALLY A SAYING IN
THE LATINO COMMUNITY, IN THE
VENEZUELAN AND CUBAN COMMUNITIES
ABOUT LA TIA DEL WHATSAPP.
IT'S THE AUNT THAT GOES ON
WHATSAPP AND RECEIVES ANY TYPE
OF CONSPIRACY THEORY AND
FORWARDS IT TO ALL HER CONTACTS.
WE ALL HAVE SOMEBODY IN OUR
FAMILY LIKE THAT.
OH, YEAH, WE DO.
AND IT'S ALMOST COMFORTING TO
KNOW THAT REGARDLESS OF
BACKGROUND, EVERY SINGLE FAMILY
HAS ONE MEMBER THAT WHEN ANYONE
GETS A MESSAGE FROM THEM, THE
FIRST RESPONSE IS TO GO "OH,
SHIT, WHAT NOW?"
IT'S A TRULY UNIVERSAL
EXPERIENCE.
AND THERE ARE PARTICULAR REASONS
THESE APPS HAVE BECOME
ESPECIALLY FERTILE GROUNDS FOR
MISINFORMATION.
FOR INSTANCE, IN MANY COUNTRIES,
FACEBOOK... WHICH, REMEMBER,
OWNS WHATSAPP... HAS PARTNERED
WITH MOBILE PHONE CARRIERS TO
MAKE ACCESSING ITS SERVICES A
LOT CHEAPER THAN ACCESSING THE
REST OF THE INTERNET.
SO MISINFORMATION CAN SPREAD FAR
AND WIDE WITHOUT THE SAME
ABILITY TO CHECK IT.
IN BRAZIL, A BROADBAND
CONNECTION CAN COST UP TO 15
PERCENT OF A HOUSEHOLD'S INCOME,
ESSENTIALLY MAKING FACT-CHECKING
TOO EXPENSIVE FOR THE AVERAGE
BRAZILIAN.
WHICH IS A TRULY TERRIFYING
THOUGHT.
AND WECHAT HAS ITS OWN FEATURES
THAT MAKE SOURCING HARDER TO
FOLLOW.
BECAUSE IT HAS A FUNCTION FOR
USERS TO SET THEMSELVES UP AS
WHAT'S KNOWN AS SELF-MEDIA...
BASICALLY A PSEUDO "NEWS
CHANNEL," BUT THERE'S A CRUCIAL
LIMITATION THERE.
WHILE FACEBOOK AND TWITTER
GENERALLY ALLOW PUBLISHERS TO
POST LINKS THAT TAKE USERS TO
OTHER WEBSITES, WECHAT BANS MOST
PUBLISHERS FROM EMBEDDING
HYPERLINKS IN ARTICLES.
THIS MEANS PRETTY MUCH
EVERYTHING IS SELF-CONTAINED ON
THE PLATFORM.
IT'S HARD TO FIND THE ORIGINAL
SOURCE MATERIAL AND DEBUNK IT.
RIGHT, AND THAT'S A BIG
DEAL, BECAUSE WHO YOUR SOURCE IS
MATTERS!
A BOOK CALLED "HOW I BROKE RULES
AND MADE HISTORY" READS
COMPLETELY DIFFERENTLY IF IT WAS
WRITTEN BY RUTH BADER GINSBURG
OR OSAMA BIN LADEN.
SO MISINFORMATION CAN CIRCULATE
FREELY ON MESSAGING APPS, AND IN
CLOSED GROUPS, BASICALLY
INVISIBLE TO THE GENERAL PUBLIC,
AND SOMETIMES, WHEN THE MESSAGES
ARE END-TO-END ENCRYPTED, EVEN
TO THE COMPANIES THAT HOST THEM.
AND THEY'RE OFTEN BEING PASSED
AROUND BY TRUSTED FRIENDS AND
FAMILY MEMBERS, LENDING THEM AN
AURA OF LEGITIMACY.
AND IT CAN BE TRULY EXASPERATING
FOR YOUNGER PEOPLE TO SEE JUST
HOW SUSCEPTIBLE THEIR RELATIVES
ARE TO THIS BULLSHIT.
SUBREDDITS LIKE "ASIAN PARENT
STORIES" ARE FULL OF POSTS LIKE
"WECHAT FUCKED UP MY PARENTS."
AND LISTEN TO THIS WOMAN READ A
MESSAGE THAT WAS FLYING AROUND
HER SOUTH AFRICAN FAMILY'S
WHATSAPP GROUP.
"PLEASE DO NOT FULL PETROL TO
THE MAXIMUM LIMIT.
IT MAY CAUSE EXPLOSION.
THIS WEEK, FIVE EXPLOSION
ACCIDENTS HAVE HAPPENED DUE TO
FILLING PETROL TO THE MAXIMUM.
PLEASE DO SHARE THIS MESSAGE.
RESCUE 1122."
I'VE NEVER HEARD OF IT, I'VE
NEVER SEEN IT, SO I DON'T SEE
HOW SHE BELIEVES IT.
BUT YOU KNOW WHAT?
BECAUSE WHATSAPP SAYS SO, IT'S
TRUE.
YOUR CAR'S GONNA EXPLODE.
YEAH, IT'S TRUE!
I MEAN, IT'S NOT.
YOUR CAR'S NOT GOING TO EXPLODE.
WHAT'S TRUE IS THAT
MISINFORMATION LIKE THAT IS
EVERYWHERE ON THESE APPS.
OUR OWN STAFF HAS HAD FAMILY
MEMBERS CIRCULATE THINGS LIKE
THESE VIDEOS IN KOREAN PROMOTING
CONSPIRACY THEORIES LIKE QANON,
OR THIS POST ABOUT HOW AYURVEDIC
DOCTORS SAY WE CAN SAVE
OURSELVES FROM CORONAVIRUS, WITH
TIPS LIKE "BOILED BLACK PEPPERS
IN WATER AND ADD LEMON JUICE, IT
KILLS THE VIRUS."
WHICH WOULD BE GREAT NEWS IF IT
WAS TRUE, BUT IT ISN'T.
THIS PROBLEM IS SO FAMILIAR TO
YOUNGER GENERATIONS THAT ONE SON
OF INDIAN PARENTS MOCKED IT ON
TIKTOK LIKE THIS.
HERE'S HOW YOU MAKE BROWN
PARENTS BELIEVE LITERALLY
ANYTHING.
YOU'RE GONNA START WITH A PLAIN
BACKGROUND AND WRITE WHATEVER
YOU WANT, BUT JUST MAKE SURE YOU
WRITE IT IN THIS FONT, THAT'S
CRUCIAL.
NOW, MENTION ANY RELIGIOUS TEXT
AND TALK ABOUT BODY, MIND,
SPIRIT, OR SOMETHING LIKE THAT
AND MAKE SURE THAT YOU MENTION A
HARVARD SCIENTIST HELPED CONFIRM
ANCIENT WISDOM, 'CAUSE WE LOVE
THOSE HEADLINES.
NOW, MAKE A DIAGRAM THAT LOOKS
SCIENTIFIC AND RELIGIOUS AT THE
SAME TIME AND THROW SOME
SANSKRIT ON THERE, DON'T WORRY
ABOUT ACCURACY.
BEAUTIFUL!
NOW, MENTION SOME CHEMICALS.
I CHOSE KANYE AND DRAKE'S NAME
AND MADE THEM LOOK LIKE
COMPOUNDS.
IT DOESN'T MATTER IF THEY'RE
REAL OR NOT.
OUR UNCLES AND AUNTIES HAVE PhDS
IN SCIENCE BUT THAT'S NO MATCH
FOR WHATSAPP.
NOW, IT'S IMPERATIVE THAT YOU
INSULT WESTERN MEDICINE AND
CULTURE AT THIS LAST PART.
YOU KNOW THE DRILL.
THREE DOTS, THREE EXCLAMATION
POINTS, CITE YOUR SOURCES, AND
MAKE THE IMAGE QUALITY A LITTLE
WORSE.
AND THAT IS PERFECTION.
YEAH!
ALL IT TAKES IS A FEW
SUPERFICIAL LABELS AND STYLISH
CHOICES TO CONVINCE PEOPLE THAT
SOMETHING WITH NO REAL SUBSTANCE
IS ACTUALLY MEANINGFUL AND GOOD
OR, AS IT'S KNOWN IN AMERICA,
THE MARVEL CINEMATIC UNIVERSE.
WHILE THAT WAS CLEARLY FUN, THAT
GUY LATER POSTED A FOLLOWUP
SAYING THAT HIS IMAGE HAD WORKED
SLIGHTLY TOO WELL, BECAUSE IT
WAS MAKING THE ROUNDS ON
WHATSAPP, BUT NOT ALWAYS AS A
JOKE.
AND WE'VE SEEN THE VERY REAL
IMPACTS MISINFORMATION ON THESE
APPS CAN HAVE.
IN INDIA, MISINFORMATION HAS
BEEN LINKED TO VIOLENCE AND
DEATHS, TO THE POINT WHERE
WHATSAPP FELT IT NECESSARY TO
CREATE THIS AD.
MEET KAVYA.
SHE LIVES AWAY FROM HER FAMILY,
BUT VERY CLOSE TO THEIR HEARTS
ON THE FAMILY WHATSAPP GROUP.
BUT TODAY, SHE'S A LITTLE
SERIOUS.
FUFAJI HAS FORWARDED SOME RANDOM
FAKE NEWS ON THE FAMILY GROUP.
KAVYA CALLED HIM RIGHT AWAY.
KAVYA?
DO YOU HAVE SOME PROOF OF
THAT MESSAGE OR DID YOU JUST
FORWARD IT?
I JUST RECEIVED IT ON SOME
RANDOM GROUP.
AND MADE HIM UNDERSTAND THAT
FAKE NEWS CAN CAUSE VIOLENCE.
WE SHOULDN'T CIRCULATE
SOMETHING DANGEROUS, RIGHT?
SHE CONVINCED FUFAJI TO LEAVE
THAT GROUP.
BE LIKE KAVYA.
SHARE JOY, NOT RUMOURS.
YEAH, YEAH, SURE,
IT'S A NICE SENTIMENT, BUT IT'S
NOT GREAT WHEN YOU HAVE TO
PRODUCE A PSA ESSENTIALLY
SAYING, "LOOK, SOME OF WHAT'S ON
OUR SERVICE IS DANGEROUS
NONSENSE AND IF YOU COULD HELP
CLEAN IT UP FOR US, THAT'D BE
GREAT!"
AT THE VERY LEAST, THEY MIGHT
WANT TO CHANGE THAT SLOGAN TO
"SHARE THE RESPONSIBILITY FOR
KEEPING MISINFORMATION FROM
DESTROYING THE FABRIC OF OUR
SOCIETY BECAUSE WE CLEARLY CAN'T
DO IT."
SO WHAT CAN WE DO ABOUT ALL
THIS?
WELL, IDEALLY, PLATFORMS LIKE
FACEBOOK, YOUTUBE AND OTHERS
WOULD BE AT LEAST AS PROACTIVE
ABOUT TAKING DOWN MISINFORMATION
IN OTHER LANGUAGES AS THEY ARE
ABOUT TAKING IT DOWN IN ENGLISH.
WHICH I KNOW IS A LOW, LOW BAR,
BUT IT DOES SAY SOMETHING ABOUT
WHERE WE'RE AT RIGHT NOW.
AS FOR PRIVATE MESSAGING APPS,
THAT'S TRICKIER, BECAUSE OF HOW
THEY'RE DESIGNED.
AND EVEN WHEN SOME HAVE TAKEN
STEPS TO SLOW THE SPREAD OF
MISINFORMATION, THEY'VE OFTEN
AMOUNTED TO HALF-MEASURES.
WHATSAPP, FOR INSTANCE, STARTED
PLACING LIMITS ON THE NUMBER OF
CHATS A MESSAGE CAN BE FORWARDED
TO, CAPPING IT AT UP TO FIVE
CHATS AT A TIME.
WHICH MIGHT SOUND GOOD, BUT IN
PRACTICE, IT LEAVES PLENTY OF
ROOM FOR DAMAGE.
IF A MESSAGE IS SENT TO A
WHATSAPP GROUP OF 20, THEN EACH
OF THEM SHARES IT WITH 20 OTHER
PEOPLE, AND THIS HAPPENS FIVE
TIMES, IT CAN REACH MORE THAN 3
MILLION PEOPLE VERY QUICKLY.
YEAH, IT CAN STILL
SPREAD PRETTY FAR.
AND I KNOW THAT THIS ISN'T THE
MAIN POINT HERE, BUT ALSO HOW
MANY OF US ARE IN TWO GROUP
CHATS OF 20 DIFFERENT PEOPLE
EACH?
AND IF YOU ARE, HOW THE FUCK DO
YOU SLEEP?
HOW DO YOU GET ANYTHING DONE
WITHOUT CONSTANTLY SWIPING AWAY
NOTIFICATIONS?
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING HOLD ON,
IT'S NOT A PROBLEM, JUST MUTE
THEM, THEN HOW DO YOU THEN CATCH
UP ON ANYTHING THAT'S HAPPENED
IN THE CHAT?
YOU'D SPEND HALF YOUR DAY
SCROLLING BACK UP JUST SO YOU'D
KNOW WHAT THIS GIF MEANT IN
CONTEXT.
MOM SENT THAT?
IN RESPONSE TO WHAT?
I HAVE TO KNOW.
A KEY PROBLEM RIGHT NOW IS THAT
MANY COMMUNITIES DON'T HAVE THE
SAME FACT-CHECKING RESOURCES
THAT ENGLISH-SPEAKING ONES DO.
IF SOMEONE SENDS YOU AN ALEX
JONES CLIP, YOU CAN RESPOND TO
IT WITH ANY NUMBER OF TRUSTED
SOURCES DEBUNKING HIM.
YOU CAN SEND THEM SOMETHING FROM
POLITIFACT, OR SNOPES, OR
FACTCHECK.ORG.
BUT IF SOMEONE SENDS YOU A CLIP
FROM KING RADIO,
VIETNAMESE-LANGUAGE
FACT-CHECKING SOURCES ARE THIN
ON THE GROUND.
THERE ARE SOME... THERE'S VIET
FACT CHECK, A VOLUNTEER-LED
PROJECT, AND THE INTERPRETER,
WHICH WORKS TO TRANSLATE NEWS
ARTICLES FROM REPUTABLE OUTLETS
INTO VIETNAMESE.
BUT THESE ARE OFTEN SMALL
ORGANIZATIONS, AND THE PEOPLE
RUNNING THEM ARE OUTMATCHED AND
UNDERSTANDABLY FUCKING
EXHAUSTED.
SO GROUPS LIKE THESE NEED
RESOURCES TO BETTER MATCH THE
CHALLENGE THEY'RE FACING.
BUT BEYOND THAT, THERE NEEDS TO
BE PUBLIC PRESSURE ON PLATFORMS
TO DO SOMETHING ABOUT ALL FORMS
OF MISINFORMATION, WHETHER
THEY'RE IN ENGLISH OR NOT.
BECAUSE A WHOLE LOT DEPENDS ON
THIS.
AND UNTIL THEY DO, IF YOU'RE A
MEMBER OF ONE OF THESE DIASPORA
COMMUNITIES, YOU MAY NEED TO
PREPARE YOURSELF FOR MORE
DIFFICULT CONVERSATIONS WITH
YOUR CRAZIEST UNCLES.
ALTHOUGH THERE'S ONE TINY WAY WE
MAY BE ABLE TO HELP, BECAUSE WE
MADE SOME "GOOD MORNING"
MESSAGES SPECIFICALLY TAILORED
FOR YOUR NEEDS.
LIKE THIS ONE, WHICH READS,
"GOOD MORNING!
TAKE EVERY CHANCE YOU GET IN
LIFE AND RETHINK SHARING NEWS
FROM A BULLSHIT SOURCE!"
IT MIGHT BE EASIER TO SEND THAT
TO AN UNCLE IN THE MORNING
RATHER THAN, YOU KNOW, SPEAK TO
HIM.
OR YOU CAN SEND HIM A VIDEO
MESSAGE LIKE THIS.
THAT'S RIGHT!
IT MAY NOT BE THE MORNING
MESSAGE THEY WANT, BUT IT'S
DEFINITELY THE MORNING MESSAGE
THAT THEY NEED.
AND FOR VIETNAMESE-AMERICANS IN
PARTICULAR, IF ANY OF YOUR
RELATIVES HAVE KING RADIO ON IN
THE BACKGROUND 24 HOURS A DAY,
WE MADE A SPECIAL MESSAGE JUST
FOR YOU.
YOU CAN DOWNLOAD THAT
MESSAGE IN BOTH ENGLISH AND
VIETNAMESE AND A FEW MORE LIKE
THEM AT
BetterMorningMessages.com.
FEEL FREE TO USE THEM WHEN YOU
CAN'T HANDLE A WHOLE
CONVERSATION, BUT KNOW THAT YOU
REALLY HAVE TO SAY SOMETHING.
THAT'S OUR SHOW, THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR WATCHING.
WE'RE OFF NEXT WEEK, BUT WE'LL
BE BACK AFTER THAT.
GOOD NIGHT!
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org