WELCOME, WELCOME,
WELCOME TO "LAST WEEK TONIGHT!"
I'M JOHN OLIVER.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR JOINING
US.
JUST TIME FOR A QUICK RECAP OF
THE WEEK, WHICH HAS BEEN BUSY.
THE CDC EXPANDED ELIGIBILITY FOR
BOOSTER SHOTS, THE HOUSE VOTED
TO HOLD STEVE BANNON IN CONTEMPT
OF CONGRESS, AND ADELE WORE THE
SHIT OUT OF THIS HEAD TO TOE
CHOCOLATE LEATHER OUTFIT.
NO ONE'S WORN CHOCOLATE THAT
WELL SINCE AUGUSTUS GLOOP.
THAT'S A FASHION FACT. BUT
WE'RE GOING TO START WITH THIS.
IN POLICE DEPARTMENTS
NATIONWIDE, A CRUSH OF VACCINE
MANDATES ARE A FLASH POINT FOR
OFFICERS FACED WITH ROLLING UP
THEIR SLEEVES OR LOSING THEIR
JOBS.
IN LEESBURG, VIRGINIA, SOME
OFFICERS SAY THEY MAY QUIT IF
THE VACCINE MANDATE MOVES
FORWARD.
IN MASSACHUSETTS, THE STATE
POLICE UNION BELIEVES AT LEAST
150 STATE POLICE OFFICERS WILL
RESIGN.
ONE TROOPER WHO DECIDED TO
QUIT HAD SOME CHOICE WORDS FOR
THE GOVERNOR ON THE WAY OUT.
THIS IS THE LAST TIME YOU'LL
HEAR ME IN A STATE PATROL CAR.
AND JAY INSLEE CAN KISS MY ASS.
WOW, A WALKIE DROP!
YOU DON'T SEE MANY OF THOSE!
AND THAT'S PROBABLY BECAUSE IT
LOOKS PATHETIC.
DROPPING A MICROPHONE IS
INHERENTLY EXCITING.
YOU GET THE THUD AS IT HITS THE
FLOOR, AND THE CHEER OF THE
CROWD, BUT A WALKIE DROP?
THAT'S JUST A SAD MAN SITTING IN
A DARK CAR, DROPPING A HEAVY
OBJECT DIRECTLY ONTO HIS PENIS.
BUT IT'S TRUE.
ALL OVER THE COUNTRY, A SMALL
MINORITY OF POLICE OFFICERS HAVE
RECEIVED DISPROPORTIONATE
COVERAGE AFTER THREATENING TO
RESIGN OVER COVID MANDATES.
THEY'VE FRAMED THIS AS A MATTER
OF INDIVIDUAL LIBERTY, EVEN IN
CASES WHERE VERY LITTLE WAS
BEING ASKED OF THEM.
IN CHICAGO, OFFICERS WERE MERELY
ASKED TO REGISTER THEIR
VACCINATION STATUS ON A PORTAL,
AND FOR NOW CAN STILL WORK IF
THEY'RE UNVACCINATED, SO LONG AS
THEY'RE REGULARLY TESTED.
BUT NEVERTHELESS, JOHN
CATANZARA, THE HEAD OF CHICAGO'S
FRATERNAL ORDER OF POLICE, TOLD
HIS OFFICERS FLAT OUT, "DO NOT
COMPLY WITH ANY DIRECT ORDER TO
FILL OUT THE PORTAL, PERIOD."
HE'S ACTUALLY BEEN ESPECIALLY
VOCAL IN HIS OPPOSITION TO
VACCINE MANDATES FOR OFFICERS,
INCLUDING AN OFFENSIVE STATEMENT
THAT I'M NOT GOING TO REPEAT,
I'M JUST GOING TO SHOW YOU HIS
APOLOGY FOR IT, BECAUSE I DO
THINK YOU'LL BE ABLE TO WORK IT
OUT FROM CONTEXT.
IN NO WAY WAS I TRYING TO TIE
FORCED VACCINATIONS TO THE
ATROCITIES OF THE HOLOCAUST,
WHICH IS WHY I NEVER USED THE
WORD HOLOCAUST.
I SHOULD NOT HAVE MADE THE
REFERENCE LIKE I DID TO THE
SHOWERS AND FOR THAT I AM SORRY.
WOW, JUST A BIG YIKES
TO EVERYTHING GOING ON THERE.
SETTING ASIDE THE PRONUNCIATION
OF "HOLE-OCAUST" -- AND BELIEVE
ME, I HAVE NOTHING BUT QUESTIONS
ABOUT THAT -- ARGUING THAT,
"TECHNICALLY I NEVER SAID THE
WORD HOLOCAUST, I JUST
REFERENCED THE SHOWERS" IS
TOTALLY ABSURD.
AND FINALLY -- AND THIS IS
PROBABLY THE LEAST IMPORTANT
THING TO SAY HERE -- AT LEAST
CENTER YOURSELF IN THE FUCKING
FRAME!
IT'S JUST NOT THAT HARD!
A QUICK SCOOTCH OF THE LAPTOP
AND YOU'RE THERE.
AND LOOK, I DON'T WANT TO BE IN
THE BUSINESS OF ART DIRECTING
"HOLE-OCAUST" NON-APOLOGIES, BUT
FRANKLY, YOU'VE LEFT ME NO
CHOICE.
AND YOU SHOULD KNOW, EVEN BY THE
SUBTERRANEAN STANDARDS OF THE
CHICAGO PD, THIS GUY IS A LOT.
HE HAS BEEN SUSPENDED EIGHT
TIMES AND HAS RECEIVED MORE
MISCONDUCT COMPLAINTS PER YEAR
OF SERVICE THAN 96% OF HIS
FELLOW CHICAGO OFFICERS.
AND YET, THIS IS WHO HIS UNION
MEMBERS CHOSE TO REPRESENT THEM.
SO NEXT TIME SOMEONE SAYS TO
YOU, "NOT ALL COPS ARE BAD," YOU
CAN RESPOND, "NO, JUST THEIR
FAVORITE ONES!"
AND CATANZARA'S HOSTILITY TO A
VACCINE MANDATE IS PARTICULARLY
NOTEWORTHY GIVEN ONE OF HIS
PREDECESSORS AS HEAD OF THE
UNION DIED OF COVID JUST THIS
MONTH.
WHICH ACTUALLY BRINGS US TO A
STAGGERING FACT.
SINCE THE START OF THE
PANDEMIC, MORE THAN FOUR TIMES
AS MANY OFFICERS HAVE DIED FROM
COVID-19 AS FROM GUNFIRE.
THIS DESPITE BEING AMONG THE
FIRST GROUPS TO HAVE ACCESS TO
SHOW
THE VACCINE. YEAH. FOUR
TIMES MORE POLICE OFFICERS
HAVE DIED FROM COVID THAN
GUNFIRE.
THAT'S A TERRIBLE STATISTIC,
WHICH YOU MIGHT NOT FULLY
ABSORB, GIVEN THAT CNN'S
GRAPHICS DEPARTMENT REPRESENTED
IT WITH ONE BAR THAT'S ONLY
ABOUT TWICE AS BIG AS THE OTHER.
SO WELCOME TO CNN.
IF YOU WANT TO INSTANTLY
UNDERSTAND THE DIFFERENT WAYS
POLICE DIE, IT'S GOING TO BE
TRICKY.
BUT IF YOU WANT TO UNDERSTAND
THE ONE WAY A CERTAIN BRITISH
ROYAL DIED, IT'S YOUR LUCKY DAY!
9:00 P.M. EASTERN, SUNDAY
NIGHTS.
THOUGH NO NEED TO WATCH.
SPOILER ALERT, IT WAS THE
MOTHER-IN-LAW.
THERE'S ALSO THE KEY MATTER OF
THE FACT THAT THE POLICE ARE
SUPPOSED TO BE KEEPING THE
PUBLIC SAFE.
THAT'S THE POINT OF THEIR JOBS.
YET SOME DON'T SEEM TO GIVE MUCH
OF A SHIT ABOUT THAT.
TAKE THIS VIDEO OF NYPD OFFICERS
FLIPPING OUT OVER A SUBWAY RIDER
WHO SIMPLY ASKED THEM TO PUT ON
A MASK.
CELL PHONE VIDEO TAKEN
TUESDAY MORNING SHOWS AN
UNMASKED NYPD OFFICER PUSHING A
MASKED COMMUTER OUT OF THE 8TH
STREET SUBWAY STATION AND
CLOSING THE EMERGENCY EXIT DOOR.
AS THE COP WALKS AWAY, HE SAYS.
YOU'RE BEING DISRUPTIVE.
OKAY, FIRST, YOU OPENED
THE EMERGENCY DOOR?
OH, NO!
EVERYONE IN NEW YORK KNOWS YOU
CAN'T OPEN THE EMERGENCY DOOR!
NOT UNLESS IT'S AN EMERGENCY!
ALSO, DISRUPTIVE?
HAVE YOU EVER BEEN ON THE
SUBWAY?
YOU KNOW, THE BIG METAL WORM
THAT SCREAMS?
THE PLACE WHERE EVERY DAY, YOU
SEE THE BIGGEST RAT TO EVER WALK
THE EARTH AND THEN YOU JUST GO
TO WORK LIKE IT'S NOTHING?
YOU'RE IN DISRUPTION JUNCTION,
BABY.
IT'S ALSO WORTH REMEMBERING THAT
NEW YORK STILL HAS A MASK
MANDATE ON PUBLIC TRANSIT, AND
ANYONE CAUGHT WITHOUT ONE RISKS
A $50 FINE -- EXCEPT,
APPARENTLY, THE COPS.
AND THIS ALL SUMS UP THE
AMERICAN POLICE PROBLEM IN
MINIATURE.
THE CONSTANT REFRAIN WE HEAR
FROM COPS EVERY TIME THEY KILL
AN UNARMED BLACK PERSON IS "THEY
SHOULD HAVE COMPLIED WITH
COMMANDS," BECAUSE AS LONG AS
YOU COMPLY, THINGS WILL
SUPPOSEDLY GO WELL.
BUT THAT ONLY SEEMS TO WORK ONE
WAY.
BECAUSE WHEN OFFICERS ARE ASKED
TO FOLLOW SIMPLE RULES OR FACE
CONSEQUENCES, A NOT
INSIGNIFICANT AMOUNT OF THEM
FLIP THEIR SHIT.
SO YOU KNOW WHAT?
IF AN OFFICER WANTS TO QUIT OVER
THIS, FUCKING LET THEM.
LET THE INDIVIDUALS WHO CLEARLY
DON'T CARE ABOUT PUBLIC SAFETY
STOP BEING IN CHARGE OF PUBLIC SAFETY.
IT IS REALLY THAT SIMPLE.
AND, BY THE WAY, THAT IS A
MOTHERFUCKING WALKIE
DROP. OW. AND NOW THIS.
AND NOW, THE WEATHER
CHANNEL'S GRAPHICS DEPARTMENT IS
STILL NOT FUCKING AROUND.
LET'S TAKE THIS CAR INTO
AUGMENTED REALITY AND TALK ABOUT
HOW THE WEATHER IMPACTS YOUR
TRAVEL.
YOU TAKE YOUR SHOES OFF LIKE
THAT TO GET TO YOUR SPOT.
BEING CLOSE TO A RAGING
WILDFIRE LIKE THIS ONE IS A
TERRIFYING EXPERIENCE.
YOU CAN SEE LARGE OBJECTS, A
TRUCK RIGHT HERE.
THOSE SNOWMOBILES CAN REALLY
PICK UP SPEED.
WAS AS A TRULY
LIFE-THREATENING.
THIS IS AN SUV.
YOU'VE GOT TO BE KIDDING, A
BUS?
I HOPE THIS BUS STOPS.
YOU MIGHT GET CAUGHT
OFF GUARD.
TREES AND STARTED TO COME
DOWN.
WHAT'S THAT?
THAT'S THE MAGIC TOP HAT.
THE SCENE WITH THE FOG IS
GETTING PRETTY SPOOKY.
WATCH OUT, HE IS COMING FOR YOU.
WHERE IS MY BROOM?
THIS WHICH IS OUT OF HERE.
MOVING ON. OUR MAIN STORY
TONIGHT CONCERNS TAIWAN.
IT'S HONESTLY REMARKABLE THAT WE
HAVEN'T TALKED ABOUT TAIWAN
BEFORE ON THIS SHOW GIVEN IT'S
THE BIRTHPLACE OF BUBBLE TEA,
WHICH IS DELICIOUS, EVEN THOUGH
TAPIOCA BALLS SOUNDS LIKE A SEX
MOVE FOR PEOPLE OVER 70, AND
ESPECIALLY SINCE TAIWAN SHARES
OUR UNHEALTHY OBSESSION WITH
MASCOTS, CITIES THERE MAKE TONS
OF THEM.
THERE'S THIS ONE, THE MILKFISH
KID, CELEBRATING ONE AREA'S
MILKFISH PRODUCTION.
AND THERE'S THIS ONE, FROM A
REGION THAT PRODUCES BANANAS,
WHICH I DO NOT WANT TO TALK
ABOUT.
IN FACT, TAIWAN MAKES SO MANY
MASCOTS THAT IN SOME CITIES, THE
VERY ACT OF STORING THEM HAS
BECOME A PROBLEM.
WE WENT WITH THE CITY
COUNCILOR TO A TAIPEI PUBLIC
SCHOOL FOLLOWING HER INTO THE
DEPTHS OF A BASEMENT PARKING
LOT.
HERE BEHIND A DOOR, WE
DISCOVERED A MOUNTAIN OF
ABANDONED MASCOTS.
THIS IS SACRED FIRE BABY FROM
2013 NATIONAL GAMES HELD IN
TAIPEI.
THE CITY GOVERNMENT SHOULD
REALLY THINK ABOUT WHETHER IT'S
NECESSARY TO KEEP CREATING
ONE-OFF MASCOTS.
OH, COME ON.
YOU CAN'T JUST KEEP MAKING
MASCOTS AND THROWING THEM AWAY.
THANKFULLY, AT THE END OF EACH
OF OUR SEASONS, OUR MASCOTS GO
TO LIVE ON A BEAUTIFUL FARM.
A FANTASTIC GREEN FARM, WHERE
JEFF THE DISEASED LUNG CAN
BREATHE FRESH AIR, AND THE POLAR
BEAR WITH A BROKEN PENIS CAN GET
THE CARE HE SO BADLY NEEDS.
I KEEP ASKING MY PRODUCER WHERE
THIS FARM IS, AND SHE KEEPS
SAYING, "I'LL TELL YOU WHEN
YOU'RE OLDER."
I CAN'T WAIT!
BUT OBVIOUSLY, THE MAJOR REASON
TAIWAN ENDS UP IN THE NEWS THESE
DAYS IS BECAUSE OF ITS
RELATIONSHIP WITH CHINA, WHICH,
TO PUT IT MILDLY, IS FRAUGHT.
AND RECENTLY, GETTING EVEN
FRAUGHTER.
CHINA HAS LONG VIEWED TAIWAN
AS ITS OWN NATIONAL TERRITORY.
CHINA'S PRESIDENT, XI JINPING,
ON SATURDAY ALL BUT DECLARING IT
POLICY.
"THE COMPLETE REUNIFICATION OF
OUR COUNTRY MUST BE AND WILL BE
REALIZED," HE SAID.
MILITARY TENSIONS BETWEEN THE
TWO SIDES ARE SOARING.
CHINA'S AIR FORCE SENT NEARLY
150 PLANES INTO TAIWAN'S AIR
DEFENSE ZONE SINCE THE START OF
THIS MONTH.
YEAH.
THEY DID.
NOT EXACTLY LIKE THAT, THOUGH,
IN A BIG STACK.
I'M PRESUMING THEY FLEW THE
PLANES OUT ONE AT A TIME, NOT
HEAPED ON TOP OF EACH OTHER LIKE
AN AIR TRAFFIC CONTROLLER'S
NIGHTMARE.
THE POINT IS, CHINA INSISTS THAT
TAIWAN, AN INDEPENDENTLY
OPERATING ENTITY WITH ITS OWN
DEMOCRATICALLY ELECTED LEADERS,
ARMED FORCES, AND CONSTITUTION,
IS ACTUALLY PART OF CHINA, AND
IN NO WAY A SEPARATE COUNTRY.
HERE'S AN UNDERSTATEMENT.
THE CHINESE GOVERNMENT FEELS
STRONGLY ABOUT THIS.
SO STRONGLY, IN FACT, THAT WHEN
JOHN CENA WENT ON A PRESS TOUR
FOR THE MOST RECENT "FAST &
FURIOUS" MOVIE AND SAID TAIWAN
IS THE FIRST "COUNTRY" THAT CAN
WATCH "F9," THIS IS WHAT
HAPPENED NEXT.
ACTOR JOHN CENA HAS
APOLOGIZED TO CHINA AFTER HE
CALLED TAIWAN A COUNTRY.
EVERY PART OF THAT IS
SO WEIRD.
IT'S WEIRD JOHN CENA APOLOGIZED
TO CHINA.
IT'S WEIRD HE DID IT FOR CALLING
TAIWAN A "COUNTRY."
AND IT'S WEIRD TO SEE HIM DO IT
IN PRETTY DECENT MANDARIN.
THAT'S JUST TOO MANY WEIRD
THINGS!
I HALF EXPECT THAT SHOT TO PAN
OUT TO REVEAL HE'S ALSO DOING A
NEEDLEPOINT OF LIAM NEESON
KISSING AN OSTRICH.
HONESTLY, IT WOULD ONLY MAKE IT
SLIGHTLY STRANGER.
BUT JOHN CENA ISN'T ALONE.
TAIWAN IS SUCH A THIRD RAIL FOR
CHINA THAT IT MAY BE WHY
PARAMOUNT PICTURES REMOVED THE
TAIWANESE FLAG FROM TOM CRUISE'S
JACKET FOR THE "TOP GUN" SEQUEL,
AND IT'S DEFINITELY WHY THE GAP
APOLOGIZED FOR RELEASING THIS
T-SHIRT FEATURING A MAP OF CHINA
WITHOUT TAIWAN ATTACHED.
THAT SHIRT CAUSED A SHITSTORM,
AND IT LED TO THE GAP, MAKERS OF
THE T-SHIRT DADS WEAR WHILE
THEY'RE ON THE ELLIPTICAL FOR
30 MINUTES, APOLOGIZING TO 1.4
BILLION PEOPLE.
SO IF CHINA IS GETTING T-SHIRT
RETRACTIONS FROM THE GAP, LOUDLY
VOWING TO REUNIFY WITH TAIWAN
AND SENDING STACKS OF WAR PLANES
TOWARDS IT IN RECORD-BREAKING
NUMBERS, IT FEELS LIKE TONIGHT,
IT'D BE WORTH TAKING A LOOK AT
TAIWAN, HOW IT GOT TO BE IN THE
UNIQUE POSITION IT'S IN, WHAT
THE WORLD WANTS FROM IT, AND
MOST IMPORTANTLY, WHAT IT WANTS
FOR ITSELF.
AND LET'S START WITH HOW WE GOT
HERE.
HISTORICALLY, TAIWAN HAS BEEN
LIKE THE STANLEY CUP OF ASIAN
HISTORY, IN THAT DIFFERENT
PEOPLE KEEP PASSING IT AROUND
AND CARVING THEIR NAMES ON IT.
HERE'S A LUDICROUSLY BRIEF
HISTORY OF THE LAST 400 YEARS
THERE.
TAIWAN, OR AS IT'S SOMETIMES
BEEN CALLED, "FORMOSA," WAS
FIRST HOME TO INDIGENOUS PEOPLE,
THEN COLONIZED BY THE DUTCH, AND
BRIEFLY THE SPANISH, BEFORE
CHINA'S QING DYNASTY HELD IT FOR
ABOUT 200 YEARS.
THEN, IN 1895, CHINA LOST TAIWAN
TO JAPAN, WHICH TURNED IT INTO A
SO-CALLED "MODEL COLONY,"
IMPOSING JAPANESE CULTURAL
VALUES, AND GENERALLY RULING IT
WITH AN IRON FIST.
THEN, AFTER WORLD WAR II, TWO
MAJOR THINGS HAPPENED.
FIRST, THE ALLIES PUT TAIWAN
BACK UNDER CHINESE CONTROL.
AND SECOND, THE CIVIL WAR THAT
WAS TAKING PLACE IN CHINA
BETWEEN THE NATIONALIST
GOVERNMENT LED BY CHIANG
KAI-SHEK AND THE COMMUNISTS, LED
BY MAO ZEDONG, ENDED.
SPOILER ALERT, THE COMMUNISTS
WON.
CONGRATULATIONS TO MAO.
AND IN THE WAKE OF THAT DEFEAT,
CHIANG KAI-SHEK FLED TO TAIWAN,
ALONG WITH 2 MILLION NATIONALIST
SOLDIERS AND REFUGEES, BASICALLY
SETTING UP A CHINESE GOVERNMENT
IN EXILE.
MEANING CHINA TECHNICALLY HAD
TWO GOVERNMENTS AT THE TIME, ONE
IN CHINA, AND ONE IN TAIWAN.
AND WESTERN COUNTRIES WERE VERY
INVESTED IN THE SUCCESS OF THE
SECOND ONE, EVEN CALLING TAIWAN
"FREE CHINA," BECAUSE THEY SAW
IT AS A NECESSARY BULWARK
AGAINST COMMUNISM.
AGAINST ALL PROPHECIES,
FORMOSA STILL KEEPS THE
ANTI-COMMUNIST FLAG FLYING ONLY
100 MILES OR SO OFF THE MAINLAND
OF CHINA.
IT'S A PROSPEROUS ISLAND WHERE
THE NEW GENERATIONS GROW UP IN
FREEDOM.
A COMPLETE CONTRAST TO
CONDITIONS UNDER THE RULE OF MAO
TSE-TUNG.
I DO MISS THAT PERIOD
OF HUMAN HISTORY WHERE THE ONLY
WAY TO LEARN ABOUT OTHER
CULTURES WAS TO HAVE A BRITISH
MAN ON AMPHETAMINES TELL YOU
WHICH WERE THE GOOD ONES AND
WHICH WERE THE BADDIES.
"HERE WE SEE FORMOSANS LIVING IN
FREEDOM.
WELL, NOT FREEDOM PER SE, BUT
THE POINT IS, THEY'RE NOT
COMMIES, AND THAT'S WHERE MY
CURIOSITY TERMINATES."
BUT WHILE CHIANG KAI-SHEK MIGHT
HAVE BEEN A STAUNCHLY
ANTI-COMMUNIST U.S. ALLY,
HISTORICALLY, WE'VE HAD A LOT OF
THOSE, AND THEY OFTEN HAVEN'T
BEEN GREAT PEOPLE.
AND CHIANG RULED TAIWAN AS A
BRUTAL AUTHORITARIAN.
THOUSANDS WERE SWEPT UP IN A
PERIOD THAT CAME TO BE KNOWN AS
"THE WHITE TERROR," SUFFERING
IMPRISONMENT, TORTURE, EVEN
EXECUTION.
DOING ANYTHING THAT COULD BE
REMOTELY CONSTRUED AS CRITICISM
OF THE GOVERNMENT WAS EXTREMELY
RISKY, AS ONE WRITER DISCOVERED
WHEN HE MERELY TRANSLATED A
POPEYE COMIC STRIP.
POPEYE AND HIS SON WERE IN
EXILE ON AN ISLAND AND THEY WERE
CAMPAIGNING FOR ELECTION THERE.
POPEYE GAVE A SPEECH AND USED AN
ENGLISH WORD, "FELLOWS."
THERE COULD BE HUNDREDS OF
TRANSLATIONS FOR "FELLOWS," BUT
I CHOSE ONE WHICH WAS, "ALL MY
FELLOW COUNTRYMEN."
THIS WAS TERRIBLE.
THE BUREAU OF INVESTIGATION
ARRESTED ME SAYING, "WHY DIDN'T
YOU TRANSLATE IT INTO SOMETHING
ELSE?
THIS IS EXACTLY THE WAY OUR
PRESIDENT CHIANG SPEAKS.
YOU ARE MAKING FUN OF HIM.
IT DESERVES THE DEATH PENALTY,
NO DOUBT, THE DEATH PENALTY."
IT'S TRUE.
THAT GUY WAS INTERROGATED FOR
MONTHS ON SUSPICION OF BEING A
COMMUNIST COLLABORATOR, AND
ULTIMATELY SPENT NINE YEARS IN
PRISON, ALL BECAUSE CHIANG'S
GOVERNMENT THOUGHT A POPEYE
COMIC HAD A HIDDEN POLITICAL
MESSAGE.
WHICH IS A BIT OF A REACH.
THERE IS CLEARLY NO DEEPER
MEANING TO POPEYE COMICS, OTHER
THAN WOMEN ARE INHERENTLY PRIZES
TO BE FOUGHT OVER, PERFORMANCE
ENHANCING DRUGS ARE COOL, AND
BLUTO DOESN'T DESERVE LOVE.
ALL OF WHICH IS TO SAY, IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE LAST CENTURY,
TAIWAN WAS A GRIM PLACE.
BUT AFTER CHIANG DIED IN 1975,
UNDER PRESSURE BOTH
INTERNATIONALLY AND FROM
POLITICAL MOVEMENTS AT HOME, THE
NATIONALISTS BEGAN TO LOOSEN
THEIR GRIP, ENDING MARTIAL LAW
IN THE LATE '80s AND OPENING THE
DOOR TO FULL DEMOCRATIZATION.
SO AGAINST THE ODDS, TAIWAN
SHIFTED FROM A DICTATORSHIP TO A
FUNCTIONING, VIBRANT DEMOCRACY,
AND I DO MEAN VIBRANT.
A DEBATE OVER HOW BILLIONS OF
EUROS WOULD BE ALLOCATED FOR AN
INFRASTRUCTURE DEVELOPMENT PLAN
DESCENDED INTO A BRAWL IN
TAIWAN'S PARLIAMENT ON TUESDAY.
MEMBERS OF THE RULING DEMOCRATIC
PROGRESSIVE PARTY AND THE
OPPOSITION NATIONALISTS PARTY
THREW WATER AND SHOVED EACH
OTHER TO THE FLOOR.
TAIWAN'S MPS ARE KNOWN FOR
BRAWLING AND EVEN THROWING
OBJECTS AT EACH OTHER.
AND FIGHTS IN PARLIAMENT ARE
EVEN SEEN AS ONE WAY FOR THE
OPPOSITION TO SHOW VOTERS THAT
IT STANDS TOUGH ON ISSUES.
YEAH!
FIGHTING IS NOT UNCOMMON IN
TAIWAN'S PARLIAMENT.
HERE THEY ARE THROWING WATER
BALLOONS AT EACH OTHER.
AND HERE THEY ARE HURLING PIG
GUTS DURING A DEBATE ON PORK
IMPORTS.
AND THAT'S NOT ALL.
ONE TIME IN 2006, A MEMBER
SNATCHED A WRITTEN PROPOSAL OF A
BILL AND SHOVED IT INTO HER OWN
MOUTH.
WHICH IS FANTASTIC, AND
DEFINITELY SOMETHING WE SHOULD
STEAL.
YOU WANT TO KILL A CLEAN ENERGY
BILL?
PULL UP A CHAIR AND FUCKING EAT
ALL 900 PAGES OF IT.
BUT TAIWAN ISN'T JUST A
FUNCTIONING DEMOCRACY.
IT'S A MAJOR PLAYER IN THE
GLOBAL SUPPLY CHAIN.
TAIWAN WAS THE FASTEST GROWING
ECONOMY IN ASIA LAST YEAR, AND
IT'S THE WORLD'S KEY
MANUFACTURER OF SEMICONDUCTORS,
WHICH ARE USED EVERYWHERE IN
PRODUCTS FROM CARS TO SEX TOYS.
SO THE NEXT TIME YOU FIRE UP A
BUTT PLUG THAT HAS 100,000 TIMES
MORE COMPUTING POWER THAN THE
"APOLLO" MOON MISSION, MAKE SURE
YOU SAY, "THANKS, TAIWAN."
SO ALL OF THIS BRINGS US TO
WHERE WE ARE RIGHT NOW, WITH
TAIWAN ESTABLISHED AS A
HIGHLY-DEVELOPED AND WEALTHY
COUNTRY.
AND YET, NO ONE IS ALLOWED TO
CALL IT ONE.
AND THAT BRINGS US BACK TO THE
HUGE, UNRESOLVED ISSUE OF
TAIWANESE SOVEREIGNTY.
BECAUSE CHINA NOW SEES CLAIMING
TAIWAN AS A KEY POINT OF
NATIONAL PRIDE, WITH XI JINPING
CALLING REUNIFICATION PART OF
HIS VISION FOR "THE GREAT
REJUVENATION OF THE CHINESE
NATION."
AND ANYONE WANTING TO DO
BUSINESS IN CHINA KNOWS THAT
CALLING TAIWAN A COUNTRY IS A
MASSIVE FAUX PAS.
AND IT'S NOT JUST THE GAP AND
JOHN CENA WHO'VE FOUND THAT OUT.
ALL OF THESE COMPANIES HAVE
EITHER HAD TO APOLOGIZE FOR, OR
WALK BACK, EVEN THE SMALLEST
IMPLICATION THAT TAIWAN IS A
SEPARATE COUNTRY.
AND YOU CAN SEE THIS CAUTION
EVERYWHERE.
AT THIS YEAR'S OLYMPICS, YOU
PROBABLY SAW TAIWANESE ATHLETES
COMPETING NOT UNDER THE
TAIWANESE FLAG, BUT UNDER THE
FAKE PSEUDO-FLAG OF "CHINESE
TAIPEI," SOMETHING THEY'VE BEEN
FORCED TO USE AT EVERY OLYMPICS
SINCE THE 1980s WHEN THEY
REACHED A COMPROMISE WITH THE
IOC THAT ALLOWED THEM TO
PARTICIPATE WITHOUT ANGERING
CHINA.
BUT THIS ARRANGEMENT ISN'T
SOMETHING THAT ALL TAIWANESE
PEOPLE APPRECIATE.
IN FACT, DURING THE 2012 GAMES,
THE LEAD SINGER OF TAIWANESE
HEAVY-METAL BAND CHTHONIC
POINTED OUT HOW LUDICROUS IT IS.
OUR TEAM, OUR NATIONAL TEAM'S
BEEN CALLED CHINESE FUCKING
TAIPEI.
FUCKING BULLSHIT, RIGHT?
"OH, WE CAN'T CALL YOU TAIWAN,
SORRY.
WE HAVE TO CALL YOU CHINESE
FUCKING TAIPEI."
I KNOW I SAY THIS EVERY
WEEK, BUT THAT DEATH METAL
SINGER COMPLAINING ABOUT OLYMPIC
NOMENCLATURE HAS A POINT.
ALTHOUGH, TO BE FAIR, IF THEIR
OFFICIAL OLYMPICS NAME REALLY
WAS "CHINESE FUCKING TAIPEI,"
THAT WOULD AT LEAST BE A LITTLE
MORE ACCURATE VIS-A-VIS WHO'S
FUCKING WHOM.
AND EVEN HUGE INTERNATIONAL
ORGANIZATIONS LIKE THE W.H.O.
ARE FORCED TO PLAY THIS
RIDICULOUS GAME, FREEZING OUT
TAIWAN FROM FULL PARTICIPATION.
LAST YEAR, WHEN ONE W.H.O
OFFICIAL WAS PRESSED ON THIS
POINT BY A HONG KONG NEWSCASTER,
IT LED TO THIS VERY AWKWARD
INTERACTION.
WILL W.H.O. CONSIDER TAIWAN'S
MEMBERSHIP?
HELLO?
I'M SORRY. I CAN'T HEAR YOU. I COULDN'T
HEAR YOUR QUESTION. OKAY, YEAH.
LET ME -- LET ME REPEAT THE
QUESTION. NO, THAT'S OKAY.
LET'S MOVE TO ANOTHER ONE THEN.
I'M ACTUALLY CURIOUS ON
TALKING ABOUT TAIWAN AS WELL ON
TAIWAN'S CASE.
WE DECIDED TO GIVE DR. AYLWARD
ANOTHER CALL TO FOLLOW UP.
AND I JUST WANT TO SEE IF YOU
CAN COMMENT A BIT ON HOW TAIWAN
HAS DONE SO FAR IN TERMS OF
CONTAINING THE VIRUS.
WELL, WE'VE ALREADY TALKED
ABOUT CHINA.
OH, WE DID, DID WE?
ARE YOU SURE ABOUT THAT?
BECAUSE IT SEEMS LIKE FIRST, YOU
PRETENDED NOT TO HEAR THE
QUESTION, THEN FAKED GETTING
DISCONNECTED AFTER COMMITTING
THE WORLD'S MOST TELEGRAPHED LOGOFF.
THAT MAN COULDN'T BE MORE
CLEARLY AVOIDING THE QUESTION IF
HE CAME BACK ONLINE PRETENDING
TO BE A LAMP.
"YOU CAN'T ASK A LAMP ABOUT
TAIWAN.
ESPECIALLY ME -- I ONLY SPEAK
FRENCH.
SO THAT'S TWO REASONS I SHOULDN'T
HAVE TO ANSWER THIS QUESTION.
I'M A LAMP, AND I ONLY SPEAK
FRENCH, EXCEPT FOR THIS BRIEF
PARAGRAPH IN ENGLISH EXPLAINING
MY SITUATION.
AU REVOIR!
JE SUIS LAMP."
BUT IT'S NOT JUST COMPANIES AND
INTERNATIONAL ORGANIZATIONS.
THE VAST MAJORITY OF WORLD
GOVERNMENTS HAVE NO OFFICIAL
DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH TAIWAN
BECAUSE CHINA WON'T HAVE
DIPLOMATIC RELATIONS WITH ANYONE
WHO DOES.
AND FOR ALL THE INITIAL
CHEERLEADING FROM WESTERN
COUNTRIES ABOUT "TAIWAN'S PLUCK
AND VERVE IN KEEPING THE
ANTI-COMMUNIST FLAG FLYING?"
THINGS HAVE SHIFTED.
BY THE END OF THE 1970s, MOST
COUNTRIES HAD SWITCHED THEIR
RECOGNITION OF CHINA'S OFFICIAL
GOVERNMENT FROM THE ONE ON
TAIWAN, KNOWN AS THE REPUBLIC OF
CHINA, TO THE COMMUNIST ONE ON
THE MAINLAND, THE PEOPLE'S
REPUBLIC OF CHINA.
IN FACT, TODAY, THE NUMBER OF
GOVERNMENTS STILL WILLING TO
DIPLOMATICALLY RECOGNIZE TAIWAN
HAS DWINDLED TO ONLY 14
COUNTRIES AND THE HOLY SEE.
ALTHOUGH THAT LAST ONE SHOULDN'T
BE SURPRISING.
YOU KNOW THE POPE.
HE LOVES TO STIR SHIT UP.
DRINKS WINE IN THE MORNING.
HE'S A MESSY BITCH WHO LIVES FOR
DRAMA.
AS FOR AMERICA, WE'VE SPENT THE
PAST HALF CENTURY WALKING A
DIPLOMATIC TIGHTROPE WITH A
POLICY KNOWN AS "STRATEGIC
AMBIGUITY."
IT'S SOMETHING THAT LETS US
MAINTAIN FUNCTIONAL RELATIONS
WITH TAIWAN AND STILL HAVE A
FULL FORMAL RELATIONSHIP WITH
CHINA.
IT'S AN APPROACH THAT BEGAN IN
THE 1970s AND WAS BUILT UPON A
SERIES OF INCREDIBLY CAREFULLY
WORDED STATEMENTS.
THE UNITED STATES IN ONE OF
OUR COMMUNIQUES WITH THE
PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA ACKNOWLEDGES
THAT TAIWAN IS A PART OF CHINA.
BUT THE UNITED STATES ALSO DID
NOT ACCEPT THE PRC CLAIM TO TAIWAN.
THAT HAS BEEN OUR POSITION EVER
SINCE.
AND SO, IN EFFECT, THE U.S.
VIEWS TAIWAN'S STATUS AS
UNDETERMINED.
RIGHT.
WE ACKNOWLEDGED CHINA'S CLAIM,
BUT DIDN'T AGREE WITH IT,
LEAVING TAIWAN'S STATUS AS
"UNDETERMINED."
YOU KNOW, LIKE SHRODINGER'S CAT,
OR THE SCIENTOLOGY VERSION,
MISCAVIGE'S WIFE.
THEY COULD BE ONE THING OR THE
OTHER THING, AND NO ONE KNOWS
FOR SURE, DO THEY, DAVID?
HEY DAVID, DAVID, WHERE'S
SHELLY?
BUT THAT CONFUSION IS EMBLEMATIC
OF THE "STRATEGIC AMBIGUITY"
POLICY.
FOR INSTANCE, THE U.S. OPERATES
OUT OF THIS BUILDING IN TAIWAN,
OFTEN REFERRED TO AS ITS "DE
FACTO EMBASSY," BUT NOT,
CRUCIALLY, AN ACTUAL EMBASSY.
MEANWHILE, TAIWAN HAS THIS
BUILDING IN D.C., WHICH DOES
PRETTY MUCH EVERYTHING THAT AN
EMBASSY WOULD DO, JUST WITHOUT
ACTUALLY BEING CALLED ONE.
AND I KNOW THIS POLICY CAN
OCCASIONALLY SEEM RIDICULOUS,
BUT THE UNCERTAINTY IS KIND OF
THE POINT, ESPECIALLY WHEN IT
COMES TO DEFENSE.
IN 1979, CONGRESS PASSED THE
TAIWAN RELATIONS ACT, IN WHICH
THE U.S. COMMITTED TO ASSIST
TAIWAN IN MAINTAINING ITS
SELF-DEFENSE CAPABILITY.
BUT THAT COMMITMENT VERY MUCH
STOPS SHORT OF THE U.S.
PROMISING TO DEFEND TAIWAN FROM
A CHINESE INVASION.
INSTEAD, IT SAYS MILITARY
AND THE EFFORT TO DETERMINE THE
FUTURE OF TAIWAN WOULD BE OF
GRAVE CONCERN TO THE
UNITED STATES.
AND WHAT DOES THAT EVEN MEAN?
DOES IT MEAN THE U.S. WOULD
DEPLOY MILITARY ASSETS?
OR JUST THAT A U.S. GENERAL
WOULD RAISE AN EYEBROW?
NO ONE KNOWS.
IT'S A WILLFULLY CONFUSING
WILL-THEY OR WON'T-THEY DANCE,
THAT FOR 40 YEARS HAS BEEN THE
BACKBONE OF U.S.-TAIWAN POLICY.
AND LOOK, SO FAR, WE'VE BEEN
TALKING ABOUT TAIWAN ALMOST
EXCLUSIVELY IN TERMS OF WHAT
OTHER COUNTRIES WANT FROM IT.
BUT THE KEY QUESTION IS CLEARLY,
WHAT DOES IT WANT FOR ITSELF?
BUT EVEN THAT'S NOT EASY TO
ANSWER.
TAIWAN IS MADE UP OF A MIX OF
DIFFERENT CULTURES, LANGUAGES
AND POLITICAL VIEWPOINTS.
REMEMBER, THEIR LAWMAKERS
SOMETIMES THROW PIG INTESTINES
AT EACH OTHER IN PARLIAMENT.
EVERYONE IS NOT ON THE SAME PAGE
THERE.
BUT TO THE EXTENT TAIWANESE
PEOPLE HAVE SPOKEN THROUGH THE
BALLOT BOX, THEY'VE CHOSEN A
GOVERNMENT THAT WANTS TO KEEP
CHINA AT ARM'S LENGTH.
THAT SINGER YOU SAW EARLIER
TALKING ABOUT "CHINESE FUCKING
TAIPEI?"
HE'S ACTUALLY IN TAIWAN'S
PARLIAMENT NOW, AND HE'S OPENLY
PRO-INDEPENDENCE.
AS FOR TAIWAN'S CURRENT LEADER,
TSAI ING-WEN, SHE WAS ELECTED ON
A PLATFORM OF DEFENDING TAIWAN,
BUT, CRUCIALLY, PRESERVING THE
STATUS QUO.
JUST WATCH HOW CAUTIOUSLY SHE
DISCUSSES THE QUESTION OF
TAIWANESE INDEPENDENCE.
ARE YOU IN PRINCIPLE AT LEAST
IN FAVOR OF THE IDEA OF FORMAL
TAIWANESE INDEPENDENCE?
THE REALITY, AND WHAT IT IS
NOW, IS THAT WE ARE ALREADY A
FUNCTIONALLY INDEPENDENT
COUNTRY.
WE HAVE OUR OWN GOVERNMENT, AND
WE HAVE OUR OWN ELECTION.
WILL THERE COME A DAY WHEN
THAT REALITY NEEDS TO BE SPELLED
OUT BY A FORMAL DECLARATION OF
INDEPENDENCE?
THE IDEA IS THAT WE DON'T
HAVE A NEED TO DECLARE OURSELVES
AN INDEPENDENT STATE, BUT WE ARE
AN INDEPENDENT COUNTRY.
RIGHT.
SHE'S CLEARLY DECLARING THAT
THEY'RE INDEPENDENT THERE, BUT
IS ALSO VERY MUCH DRAWING THE
LINE AT A DECLARATION OF
INDEPENDENCE.
BECAUSE SHE KNOWS THAT TAIWAN
EXPLICITLY FORMALIZING THE WAY
THINGS ARE COULD CAUSE A LOT OF
TROUBLE.
IT'S LIKE MEETING YOUR PARTNER'S
PARENTS FOR THE FIRST TIME AND
SAYING, "HELLO, I REGULARLY FUCK
YOUR OFFSPRING."
YEAH.
EVERYONE WAS AWARE OF THAT.
BUT NOW THAT YOU'VE OFFICIALLY
DECLARED IT, THINGS ARE GOING TO
GET MORE DIFFICULT FOR EVERYONE
INVOLVED.
AND THE TRUTH IS, THAT INTENSE
PRAGMATISM IS IN LINE WITH HOW
MANY TAIWANESE PEOPLE FEEL.
POLLS HAVE CONSISTENTLY SHOWN
THAT WHEN THEY'RE ASKED ABOUT
INDEPENDENCE FROM OR UNIFICATION
WITH CHINA, SOMETHING LIKE 1.5
PERCENT WANT UNIFICATION WITH
CHINA AS SOON AS POSSIBLE AND
ABOUT SIX PERCENT WANT
INDEPENDENCE AS SOON AS
POSSIBLE, BUT THE VAST MAJORITY
FAVOR SOME VERSION OF STICKING
WITH THE STATUS QUO, AT LEAST
FOR NOW.
WHICH MAKES SENSE.
BECAUSE AS THINGS STAND, AS
VOLATILE AS THIS SITUATION CAN
APPEAR, DAY-TO-DAY LIFE IN
TAIWAN CAN GO ON AS NORMAL.
AS THIS TAIWANESE MAN SHOWS.
WOW.
THAT IS A PRETTY RELAXED
ATTITUDE GIVEN THE
CIRCUMSTANCES.
HE'S TALKING ABOUT THE
NUCLEAR-ARMED, SABER-RATTLING
SUPERPOWER TAUNTING HIS COUNTRY
WITH WARPLANES LIKE IT'S SEASON
TWO OF "EMILY IN PARIS."
"YOU KNOW, I DON'T LOVE THAT
IT'S HAPPENING, BUT I JUST TRY
TO CARRY ON WITH MY LIFE."
BUT THE KEY QUESTION IS, CAN THE
CURRENTLY-SAFE STATUS QUO HOLD
FOREVER?
XI JINPING HAS STATED THAT THE
QUESTION OF TAIWAN CANNOT SIMPLY
BE "PASSED ON FROM GENERATION TO
GENERATION."
AND THOSE MILITARY DRILLS SEEM
TO BE SENDING A MESSAGE.
AND WHILE EXPERTS SAY WAR ISN'T
IMMINENT, TAIWAN IS
UNDERSTANDABLY THINKING ABOUT
ITS OWN DEFENSE CAPABILITIES.
SOMETHING, BY THE WAY, WE'VE
BEEN HAPPY TO ASSIST THEM IN
THINKING ABOUT, BY SELLING THEM
BILLIONS OF DOLLARS IN WEAPONS,
SHOWING EVEN "STRATEGIC
AMBIGUITY" HAS ITS PRICE.
BUT DESPITE U.S. ASSISTANCE, THE
TAIWAN MILITARY IS OBVIOUSLY A
FRACTION OF CHINA'S.
AND ITS RECENT ATTEMPTS TO
ATTRACT RECRUITS HAVE LEFT
SOMETHING TO BE DESIRED.
THE ARMED FORCES HAVE BEEN
PRODUCING VIDEOS LIKE THIS TO
TRY TO DRUM UP ENTHUSIASM AMONG
POTENTIAL YOUNG SOLDIERS.
BUT THEY'VE BEEN STRUGGLING TO
MAKE UP FOR A SHORTFALL LEFT BY
A PHASING OUT OF CONSCRIPTION.
OKAY, I'M NOT SURE
THAT'S HELPING.
THAT DOESN'T LOOK LIKE A GROUP
OF PEOPLE WHO ARE EXCITED TO BE
IN THE MILITARY.
IT LOOKS LIKE A BUNCH OF
BACKGROUND DANCERS WHO WERE CUT
FROM "IN THE HEIGHTS" BECAUSE
THEY WERE TOO BORING TO BE ON
CAMERA.
SO WHAT EXACTLY CAN OR SHOULD BE
DONE HERE?
WELL, THAT'S SOMETHING THE
ENTIRE WORLD HAS BEEN DISSECTING
FOR HALF A CENTURY NOW, AND SO
FAR THE ANSWER WE SEEM TO HAVE
SETTLED ON IS SOME VERSION OF,
"UH...
NEXT QUESTION, PLEASE," WHICH IS
CLEARLY NOT VERY SATISFYING.
AND I KNOW AMBIGUITY IS
INHERENTLY FRUSTRATING,
ESPECIALLY FOR AMERICANS, WHO
MIGHT LOOK AT A PLACE LIKE
TAIWAN, WHICH LOOKS AND ACTS
LIKE A COUNTRY, AND FEEL IT'S
WEIRD AND FARCICAL TO NOT
ACKNOWLEDGE IT AS ONE.
BUT FROM A PRACTICAL STANDPOINT,
WOULD THAT BE BETTER?
AND IS THAT EVEN WHAT THE PEOPLE
OF TAIWAN WANT?
COULD IT BE THAT MAINTAINING THE
CURRENT, DEEPLY WEIRD, AMBIGUOUS
STATUS QUO IS ACTUALLY THE BEST
OPTION?
I DON'T KNOW.
I'M NOT TAIWANESE, AND FRANKLY,
PEOPLE WHO AREN'T TAIWANESE
MAKING DECISIONS FOR TAIWAN IS A
BIT FUCKING PLAYED OUT,
HISTORICALLY.
SO MAYBE THE BEST THING WE CAN
DO IS MOVE PAST TALKING ABOUT
TAIWAN LIKE IT'S SOME KIND OF
POKER CHIP IN A NEVER-ENDING
GAME OF US VS. THEM.
BECAUSE THE FACT IS, TAIWAN IS
NOT A PLUCKY BULWARK AGAINST THE
RED MENACE, NOR IS IT SOME SORT
OF ISLAND-SIZED VIAGRA TO
REJUVENATE THE CHINESE NATION.
TAIWAN IS 23 MILLION PEOPLE,
WHO, IN THE FACE OF CONSIDERABLE
ODDS, HAVE BUILT A FREE,
DEMOCRATIC SOCIETY, AND VERY
MUCH DESERVE THE RIGHT TO DECIDE
THEIR OWN FUTURE, IN ANY WAY
THEY DEEM FIT, EVEN IF THAT
MEANS SPORADICALLY BEATING THE
ABSOLUTE SHIT OUT OF EACH OTHER.
AND NOW THIS.
AND NOW, JAMES CORDEN
JAMES CORDEN LOVES CINEMA.
WE HAVE TO CONGRATULATE YOU
ON YOUR BRILLIANT NEW MOVIE,
"HAPPIEST SEASON."
IT'S SO GOOD.
FOR THOSE WHO DON'T KNOW, TELL
THEM WHAT IT'S ABOUT AND WHO YOU
PLAY.
FOR ANYONE WHO DOESN'T KNOW,
TELL THEM WHAT IT'S ABOUT AND
WHO YOU PLAY.
FOR ANYONE WHO DOESN'T KNOW,
TELL THEM WHAT IT'S ABOUT AND
WHO YOU PLAY.
WE HAVE TO CONGRATULATE YOU ON
YOUR BRILLIANT NEW MOVIE.
BRILLIANT NEW MOVIE.
FOR ANYONE WHO DOESN'T KNOW,
TELL THEM WHAT IT'S ABOUT AND
WHO YOU PLAY.
AND WHO YOU PLAY.
CAN YOU TELL US WHAT IS FOUL AND
WHO YOU PLAY?
WE HAVE TO CONGRATULATE YOU ON
YOUR BRILLIANT NEW MOVIE,
"FANTASY ISLAND."
I'M REALLY EXCITED FOR THIS FILM
FOR ANYONE WHO DOESN'T KNOW,
TELL THEM WHAT IT'S ABOUT AND
WHO YOU PLAY.
WE HAVE TO CONGRATULATE YOU ON
YOUR BRILLIANT NEW MOVIE.
BRILLIANT NEW MOVIE.
BRILLIANT MOVIE.
WE HAVE TO CONGRATULATE YOU,
NUMBER ONE MOVIE IN THE WORLD.
TELL THEM WHAT IT'S ABOUT AND
WHO YOU PLAY.
SONIC THE HEDGEHOG.
THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANKS SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org