HI THERE, WELCOME TO
THE SHOW, STILL TAKING PLACE,
BUT FOR THE LAST TIME, IN THIS
BLANK VOID.
GOD, THAT FEELS GREAT TO
HEAR.
THIS MUST BE HOW ENGLAND FELT
WHEN THEY GOT RID OF YOU.
UH, EXCUSE ME, THEY
DIDN'T GET RID OF ME, I CHOSE TO
LEAVE.
"CHOSE."
OKAY, SURE, LET'S GO WITH THAT.
HAS ANYONE ASKED YOU TO COME
BACK?
LIKE, ANYONE?
THAT'S A FAIR POINT.
IT'S BEEN A BUSY WEEK.
A BOMB THREAT IN WASHINGTON,
DEMOTED FROM HOST IN JEOPARDY TO
RUNNING IT, AND THEN THE LATEST
INNOVATION.
WORK ROOMS IS USED ON
FACEBOOK'S OCULUS QUEST 2
VIRTUAL REALITY HEADSETS.
THIS IS MY FIRST VIRTUAL
REALITY INTERVIEW.
HOW ABOUT YOU?
MINE TOO.
MY FIRST VIRTUAL REALITY
INTERVIEW TOO.
WELL, THAT'S THE
STUPIDEST THING I'VE EVER SEEN.
DO YOU LIKE ZOOM MEETINGS?
NO?
WELL, THIS IS LIKE THAT, EXCEPT
YOU GET TO WEAR A HELMET AND
YOUR COWORKERS ARE GLITCHY SIMS.
IT'S ANOTHER GAME-CHANGING HIT
FROM THE GUY WHO BROUGHT YOU
"EVERYONE YOU WENT TO
HIGH SCHOOL WITH IS Q-ANON NOW."
BUT INSTEAD OF FOCUSING ON THAT,
LET'S DIVE STRAIGHT IN WITH OUR
AFGHANISTAN.
AMERICA'S WAR THERE IS DRAWING
TO A CLOSE AFTER ALMOST 20 YEARS
OF FIGHTING.
WE ALL KNEW THE END WAS LIKELY
TO BE UGLY.
THE ONLY QUESTION WAS
"HOW UGLY?"
WELL, THIS WEEK, WE GOT OUR
ANSWER.
AFGHANS ARE THRONGING TO
KABUL'S AIRPORT.
THIS IS WHAT DESPERATION
LOOKS LIKE.
WE NOW KNOW THAT AT LEAST ONE
OF THE AMERICAN TRANSPORTS TOOK
OFF WITH A PAYLOAD FAR IN EXCESS
OF THE MAXIMUM RECOMMENDED.
800 PEOPLE ON YOUR JET?
HOLY COW.
I MEAN, GOOD JOB GETTING OFF THE
GROUND.
HOLY SHIT.
THAT IS TERRIFYING.
YOU NEVER, EVER WANT TO BE ON A
PLANE THAT IS MANAGING TO
ACTIVELY IMPRESS AIR TRAFFIC
CONTROL.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, THAT IS THE
EXACT REACTION I WANT EVERY TIME
I DO A SINGLE PUSH-UP.
"HOLY COW.
I MEAN, GOOD JOB GETTING OFF THE
GROUND.
NO ONE COULD'VE EXPECTED
ANYTHING MORE FROM YOU."
AND THE THING IS, THAT IS JUST
THE PEOPLE THAT MANAGED TO GET
ONTO THE PLANE.
THERE WERE HORRIFIC VIDEOS THAT
WE ARE NOT GOING TO SHOW YOU OF
PEOPLE CLINGING TO THE WHEELS OF
A PLANE AND FALLING TO THEIR
DEATH AS THEY TOOK OFF.
AND WHILE BIDEN INSISTED THAT
"WE PLANNED FOR EVERY
CONTINGENCY," THAT IS PRETTY
HARD TO BELIEVE GIVEN, JUST TEN
DAYS AGO, THE U.S. WAS
DESPERATELY TRYING TO NEGOTIATE
WITH THE TALIBAN, ASKING IT TO
SPARE OUR EMBASSY IN KABUL.
A DAY LATER, THAT EMBASSY WAS
TOLD TO DESTROY SENSITIVE FILES,
AND BY THIS TIME LAST WEEK, WE
WERE EVACUATING IT ALTOGETHER.
ALTHOUGH THE SECRETARY OF STATE
PUSHED BACK ON THE IDEA THAT THE
EMBASSY WAS CLOSED AT ALL.
SO, IF NO AMERICAN IS IN THE
EMBASSY, WE'VE ESSENTIALLY
CLOSED THE EMBASSY.
IT SOUNDS LIKE YOU DON'T WANNA
SAY THAT.
YEAH.
NO, WE'RE GONNA HAVE A...
WE'RE GONNA HAVE A... WE'RE
GONNA HAVE OUR CORE DIPLOMATIC
PRESENCE.
WE WILL?
AND... AND, IN EFFECT, AN
EMBASSY AT A LOCATION AT THE
AIRPORT.
WOW, THAT IS A ROUGH
SENTENCE.
BECAUSE "WE'LL HAVE, IN EFFECT,
AN EMBASSY" IS ALREADY PRETTY
ALARMING, THEN YOU FINISH IT OFF
WITH "AT A LOCATION AT THE
AIRPORT," PERHAPS THE DARKEST
QUALIFIER IN THE ENGLISH
LANGUAGE.
BECAUSE, TO STATE THE OBVIOUS
HERE, AN EMBASSY DOES NOT BELONG
IN AN AIRPORT, BECAUSE IT'S NOT
A FUCKING WOLFGANG PUCK
RESTAURANT.
AND THE FACT IS, AMERICA HAS NOW
JOINED A LONG LINE OF COUNTRIES
WHO CAME TO AFGHANISTAN TO SERVE
THEIR OWN INTERESTS ONLY TO
LEAVE DEFEATED.
IT'S A PATTERN SO UNIVERSALLY
KNOWN IT WAS LITERALLY A PLOT
POINT IN "RAMBO III."
THIS IS AFGHANISTAN.
ALEXANDER THE GREAT TRIED TO
CONQUER THIS COUNTRY.
THEN GENGHIS KHAN, THEN THE
BRITISH, NOW RUSSIA.
ANCIENT ENEMY MAKE PRAYER ABOUT
THESE PEOPLE.
IT SAYS "MAY GOD DELIVER US FROM
THE VENOM OF THE COBRA, THE
TEETH OF THE TIGER, AND THE
VENGEANCE OF THE AFGHANS."
YOU UNDERSTAND WHAT THIS MEANS?
THAT YOU GUYS DON'T TAKE ANY
SHIT?
YES.
SOMETHING LIKE THIS.
YEAH, SOMETHING LIKE
IT, ALTHOUGH IT FEELS LIKE
OL' RAMBO COULD HAVE USED A FEW
MORE FOLLOW-UPS THERE.
"YOU UNDERSTAND WHAT THIS MEANS,
RIGHT?"
"YEAH, YOU GUYS DON'T TAKE ANY
SHIT."
"SURE, BUT ALSO THAT OUR
POLITICAL SYSTEM HAS LONG BEEN
DEFINED BY OTHER COUNTRIES'
IMPERIAL SELF-INTEREST.
YOU UNDERSTAND WHAT THAT MEANS?"
"NO.
NO, I DON'T."
"YEAH, I DIDN'T THINK SO.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
I'M GUESSING WE'LL BE SEEING YOU
GUYS IN ROUGHLY 15 YEARS."
AND LOOK, CLEARLY, WE DON'T HAVE
TIME TO RECAP THE LAST 20 YEARS
OF AMERICA'S INVOLVEMENT IN
AFGHANISTAN, MUCH LESS RECKON
WITH ALL THE LONG-TERM
CONSEQUENCES.
BUT WE THOUGHT TONIGHT, IN THE
WAKE OF THE CHAOS THIS WEEK,
IT'D BE WORTH TRYING TO ANSWER A
WHY WERE WE
IN AFGHANISTAN IN THE FIRST
PLACE, WHAT DID WE DO WHILE WE
WERE THERE, AND WHAT ARE WE
DOING RIGHT NOW?
AND LET'S START WITH WHY WE WERE
THERE.
BECAUSE ON MONDAY, BIDEN OFFERED
THIS ORIGIN STORY:
WE WENT TO AFGHANISTAN ALMOST
20 YEARS AGO WITH CLEAR GOALS:
GET THOSE WHO ATTACKED US ON
SEPTEMBER 11, 2001, AND MAKE
SURE AL-QAEDA COULD NOT USE
AFGHANISTAN AS A BASE FROM WHICH
TO ATTACK US AGAIN.
OUR MISSION IN AFGHANISTAN WAS
NEVER SUPPOSED TO HAVE BEEN
NATION-BUILDING.
OH, OKAY THEN.
IF OUR MISSION WAS NEVER
NATION-BUILDING, THEN I GUESS
NOT-MISSION NOT-ACCOMPLISHED.
BUT THE THING IS, THAT'S A
LITTLE TRUE BUT ALSO A LOT NOT.
BECAUSE, YES, THE PRIMARY REASON
FOR INITIALLY INVADING
AFGHANISTAN WAS 9/11 AND THE
FACT THAT THE TALIBAN HAD BEEN
GIVING SAFE HAVEN TO BIN LADEN.
BUT VERY QUICKLY, THAT MISSION
BECAME DRESSED UP IN THE
LANGUAGE OF NATION-BUILDING AND
HUMAN RIGHTS.
GEORGE W. BUSH SAID, "ROOTING
OUT THE TALIBAN WAS IMPORTANT,
BUT BUILDING A SCHOOL IS EQUALLY
IMPORTANT," AND BIDEN HIMSELF
SAID BACK THEN, "THE ALTERNATIVE
TO NATION-BUILDING IS CHAOS."
AND THERE WAS LOTS OF FOCUS AT
THE TIME ON ATROCITIES THE
TALIBAN HAD COMMITTED DURING
THEIR FIVE YEARS OF REPRESSIVE
RULE... THE SUBJUGATION OF
WOMEN, THE EXECUTIONS IN A
SOCCER STADIUM, THE DESTRUCTION
OF THE FAMOUS BUDDHAS OF
BAMIYAN, ALL OF WHICH WERE
TERRIBLE, BUT WHICH HAD BEEN
EQUALLY TERRIBLE BEFORE
SEPTEMBER 11TH, AND WE HADN'T
DONE MUCH ABOUT IT.
THE TRUTH IS, BETWEEN A
POST-9/11 DESIRE FOR VENGEANCE
AND THE BUSH ADMINISTRATION
FRAMING INTERVENTION AS A
"CRUSADE" FOR HUMAN RIGHTS, THEY
BUILT A NEAR-UNIVERSAL POLITICAL
CONSENSUS.
ONLY ONE MEMBER OF CONGRESS,
REPRESENTATIVE BARBARA LEE,
VOTED AGAINST THE AUTHORIZATION
OF MILITARY FORCE.
OTHER DEMOCRATS JUMPED TO
CO-SIGN THE HUMAN RIGHTS
ARGUMENT, LIKE REPRESENTATIVE
CAROLYN MALONEY, WHO DELIVERED A
SPEECH ON THE FLOOR OF THE HOUSE
ABOUT THE NEED TO COMBAT TALIBAN
REPRESSIONS, FEATURING A
STRIKING VISUAL AID.
I SALUTE THE BUSH
ADMINISTRATION FOR BALANCING WAR
WITH COMPASSION.
FOR DROPPING FOOD AS WELL AS
BOMBS.
EVEN IN WAR, WE ARE SHOWING A
REGARD FOR HUMAN LIFE AND
HUMAN RIGHTS THAT THE TALIBAN
WILL NEVER KNOW.
OKAY, FIRST, IT DOESN'T
GET MUCH MORE "THE MONTH AFTER
9/11" THAN A WHITE DEMOCRAT IN A
"FUCK YOU" BURQA SALUTING THE
BUSH ADMINISTRATION'S COMMITMENT
TO HUMAN RIGHTS.
AND THE PROBLEM THERE IS, YOU
COULD BE REVEALING THE SOLUTION
FOR WORLD HUNGER, BUT IF YOU'RE
A WHITE LADY WHO THREW ON A
BURQA FOR THE DRAMA, YOU'RE
FUNDAMENTALLY DISTRACTING FROM
YOUR POINT.
AS FOR "WE DROPPED FOOD AS WELL
AS BOMBS," THOSE TWO DO NOT
CANCEL EACH OTHER OUT.
AND WE DROPPED A LOT OF THE
SECOND.
OVER 71,000 AFGHAN AND PAKISTANI
CIVILIANS ARE ESTIMATED TO HAVE
DIED AS A DIRECT RESULT OF THE
WAR, WITH MANY MORE INJURED OR
DISPLACED.
AS FOR OUR PROGRAM OF DRONE
STRIKES, THEY DIDN'T JUST KILL
CIVILIANS... THEY TRAUMATIZED AN
ENTIRE GENERATION.
THE VILLAGERS CALL THEM
PLANES WITHOUT MEN.
SHEZ AMAN SAYS HIS
NINE-YEAR-OLD SON, SULEIMAN, WAS
KILLED BY A DRONE THREE MONTHS
AGO, ALONG WITH THE FATHERS OF
ALL OF THESE CHILDREN.
I'M SCARED THEY'LL BOMB US.
THEY KILLED MY FATHER AND I'M
AFRAID THEY'LL BOMB US TOO.
I CAN'T WALK OUTSIDE MY HOME
BECAUSE I'M SCARED.
I'M EVEN SCARED AT HOME.
YEAH, IT'S TERRIBLE.
SO IF CAROLYN MALONEY WANTS TO
ILLUSTRATE "ALL" THE MAJOR
THREATS AFGHAN SOCIETY'S FACED
IN RECENT YEARS, SHE MAY WANT TO
DELIVER HER NEXT SPEECH DRESSED
LIKE A FUCKING DRONE.
AND THOSE STRIKES ARE JUST ONE
PART OF THE ANSWER TO OUR SECOND
QUESTION, WHICH IS,
"WHAT EXACTLY DID WE DO IN
AFGHANISTAN?"
BECAUSE THE U.S. CAME IN WITH
BIG PLANS, PROMISING TO SET UP A
MODERN, CENTRALIZED DEMOCRACY.
AND YET, INSTEAD OF ENGAGING
WITH AND UNDERSTANDING THE
COUNTRY'S COMPLEX LOCAL
POLITICAL POWERS, WE ADOPTED A
POLICY OF PAYING OFF AND
CO-OPTING LOCAL WARLORDS AND
DRUG TRAFFICKERS, WHICH ERODED
TRUST QUICKLY BETWEEN THE AFGHAN
PEOPLE AND THE BLATANTLY CORRUPT
GOVERNMENT THAT WE HELPED FUEL.
BY 2006, IN THE WORDS OF ONE
RETIRED COLONEL, THE GOVERNMENT
HAD "SELF-ORGANIZED INTO A
KLEPTOCRACY" UNDER WHICH PEOPLE
IN POWER COULD PLUNDER THE
ECONOMY WITHOUT RESTRAINT.
AND YET, SUCCESSIVE
ADMINISTRATIONS KEPT GIVING US
ROSY ASSESSMENTS LIKE THIS:
THE TALIBAN HAVE BEEN DRIVEN
FROM POWER, AL-QAEDA HAS BEEN
DRIVEN FROM ITS CAMPS, AND
AFGHANISTAN IS FREE.
THAT'S WHY I SAY WE HAVE MADE
REMARKABLE PROGRESS.
THE WAR IN AFGHANISTAN IS
ENDING.
AL-QAEDA HAS BEEN DECIMATED.
OSAMA BIN LADEN IS DEAD.
WE HAVE MADE REAL PROGRESS.
WE MAKE A LOT OF PROGRESS IN
AFGHANISTAN.
AND WITH TIME, WE'LL HAVE IT
SPINNING LIKE A TOP.
OH.
OH, YOU WILL, WILL YOU?
BUT I GUESS HE'S TECHNICALLY
RIGHT THERE.
WE DID LEAVE AFGHANISTAN
"SPINNING LIKE A TOP," YOU KNOW,
THOSE THINGS THAT FAMOUSLY SPIN
FOREVER AND NEVER COLLAPSE.
THE FACT IS, THINGS OBVIOUSLY
WEREN'T GOING AS WELL AS ALL
THREE OF THOSE MEN PUBLICLY
CLAIMED, AS WE NOW KNOW... NOT
LEAST THANKS TO THIS REVELATION
TWO YEARS AGO.
ACCORDING TO MORE THAN 2,000
PAGES OF DOCUMENTS OBTAINED BY
"THE WASHINGTON POST," MILITARY
COMMANDERS, DIPLOMATS, AND AID
WORKERS PRIVATELY AND IN BLUNT
TERMS DESCRIBE AN UNCLEAR
MISSION, A FAILED STRATEGY AND
EFFORTS TO SWAY PUBLIC OPINION.
AMONG THE REVELATIONS, RETIRED
GENERAL DOUGLAS LUTE, THE AFGHAN
WAR CZAR UNDER PRESIDENTS BUSH
AND OBAMA, SAYING IN 2015,
"WHAT ARE WE TRYING TO DO HERE?
WE DIDN'T HAVE THE FOGGIEST
NOTION OF WHAT WE WERE
UNDERTAKING."
WOW.
THAT SOUNDS LESS LIKE SOMETHING
YOU'D EXPECT TO HEAR FROM A
GENERAL AND MORE LIKE THE
INTERNAL MONOLOGUE
FOR SIR IAN McKELLEN IN THIS
PHOTO FROM THE SET OF "CATS."
"WHAT ARE WE TRYING TO DO HERE?
HAS ANYONE GOT A PLAN FOR WHAT
THIS IS GOING TO LOOK LIKE IN
THE END?
I HAVEN'T THE FOGGIEST NOTION OF
WHAT WE'RE UNDERTAKING."
THOSE INTERVIEWS WERE COLLECTED
BY SIGAR... THE SPECIAL
INSPECTOR GENERAL FOR
AFGHANISTAN RECONSTRUCTION, A
GOVERNMENT OFFICE TASKED WITH
PRODUCING HONEST REPORTS ABOUT
HOW THINGS WERE REALLY GOING
THERE, ONE OF WHICH NOTED "THE
U.S. GOVERNMENT'S GOALS WERE
OFTEN OPERATIONALLY IMPRACTICAL
OR CONCEPTUALLY INCOHERENT."
SIGAR'S MANDATE WAS TO PROMOTE
EFFICIENCY AND PREVENT WASTE,
FRAUD, AND ABUSE.
AND I KNOW FOCUSING ON WASTEFUL
SPENDING MAY SEEM LIKE THE
ABSOLUTE LEAST OF THE ISSUES
HERE, BUT SOMETIMES KNOWING
EXACTLY WHERE THE MONEY WAS
SPENT HELPS YOU UNDERSTAND THE
SCALE OF THE MESS WE'VE LEFT
BEHIND.
BECAUSE SO MUCH MONEY WENT TO
MILITARY CONTRACTORS TO SET UP
PROJECTS WITH NO PLAN FOR HOW
THEY'D SURVIVE AFTER WE WERE
GONE.
HERE'S THE HEAD OF SIGAR
IDENTIFYING ONE EXPENDITURE IN
PARTICULAR.
I THINK THE WORST CASE SO FAR
OF JUST STUPID WASTE HAS BEEN
THE PURCHASE OF THE HELICOPTERS
AND AIRPLANES FOR THE AFGHAN AIR
WING.
IT'S CLEARLY RISKING THAT THOSE
PLANES AND THOSE HELICOPTERS ARE
JUST GONNA END UP ON THE TARMAC
RUSTING.
THEY CAN'T EVEN USE THE
PLANES THEY CURRENTLY HAVE.
OVER 70% OF THE MAINTENANCE IS
BEING DONE BY U.S. CONTRACTORS,
NOT BY THE AFGHANS.
THEY DON'T HAVE THE PILOTS,
THEY DON'T HAVE THE GROUND
CREWS, THEY DON'T HAVE THE
WORKERS TO...
SO WHY ARE WE BUYING THEM?
THAT'S A GOOD QUESTION.
YEAH, IT IS.
THAT CLIP IS FROM SEVEN YEARS
AGO, BUT IT'S NOT LIKE, SINCE
THEN, WE'VE FIXED THE UNDERLYING
PROBLEM.
LAST MONTH, DEFENSE OFFICIALS
WERE MAINTAINING THAT AIRCRAFT
COULD STILL BE USED AFTER WE
WERE GONE BECAUSE AFGHANS COULD
SIMPLY SERVICE THEM WITH
"U.S. CONTRACTORS LOOKING OVER
THEIR SHOULDERS VIA ZOOM OR
COACHING THEM OVER THE PHONE."
WHICH IS SO CLOSE TO NOTHING
THAT I'M HONESTLY SURPRISED THE
U.S. DIDN'T JUST BUY EVERY
AFGHAN TECHNICIAN A MASTERCLASS
SUBSCRIPTION AND TELL THEM THAT
ANNA WINTOUR'S COURSE WOULD
SUPERCHARGE THEIR CREATIVITY.
AND THAT'S EMBLEMATIC OF OUR
WE CAME
IN, BUILT SOMETHING ON THE
AMERICAN MODEL, ALMOST WHOLLY
DEPENDENT ON AMERICAN SUPPORT,
AND PUT NEXT TO NO EFFORT INTO
ENSURING THAT IT WAS SUSTAINABLE
AFTER WE LEFT.
TAKE THE GOVERNMENT ITSELF.
FOREIGN GRANTS FINANCED AROUND
75% OF ITS PUBLIC SPENDING,
MEANING THAT, AS THE TALIBAN
TAKES OVER, THAT MONEY
PRESUMABLY DRIES UP, AND THE
ECONOMY IS NOW POISED TO
COLLAPSE.
AND IT'S NOT JUST THE ECONOMY
THAT'S IN DANGER HERE.
THERE WERE REAL, MEANINGFUL
GAINS... PARTICULARLY FOR WOMEN,
WHO'D SUFFERED TERRIBLY UNDER
THE PREVIOUS TALIBAN REGIME.
MILLIONS OF GIRLS WERE ALLOWED
TO ATTEND SCHOOL FOR THE FIRST
TIME, AND WOMEN JOINED THE
MILITARY, THE POLICE, AND HELD
POLITICAL OFFICE.
BUT THOSE ACHIEVEMENTS ARE IN
REAL JEOPARDY NOW.
AND SOME WHO LED THE WAY... LIKE
MAHBOUBA SERAJ, AN AFGHAN
WOMEN'S ACTIVIST... ARE ACUTELY
AWARE OF THAT.
I'M GOING TO SAY TO THE WHOLE
WORLD, SHAME ON YOU.
ARE YOU USING ALL OF US?
ARE WE BEING JUST PAWNS IN YOUR
HANDS?
IS THAT WHAT IT IS?
I DON'T UNDERSTAND IT.
THEY JUST MADE DECISIONS WITH
THEIR GUT FEELINGS OR WHATEVER,
ALL OF THESE MEN OF THE WORLD
THAT THEY WERE IN POWER, AND
THEY'RE DESTROYING SOMETHING
THAT WE WORKED SO HARD FOR.
WHAT IS HAPPENING IN AFGHANISTAN
TODAY IS GOING TO PUT THIS
COUNTRY 200 YEARS BACK.
THAT IS INCREDIBLY HARD
TO HEAR.
AND THE THING IS, SHE'S RIGHT.
THE PEOPLE OF AFGHANISTAN "HAVE"
BEEN TREATED LIKE PAWNS.
WHILE THERE WERE GAINS, THE
INITIAL IMPULSE THAT LED TO THEM
WAS PURELY U.S. INTERESTS.
AND FOR 20 YEARS, FOR MULTIPLE
REASONS, THE U.S. AND VARIOUS
AFGHAN GOVERNMENTS DIDN'T SECURE
THOSE GAINS.
AND EVEN THOUGH THIS WEEK HAS
BROUGHT INCREDIBLE SCENES OF
AFGHAN WOMEN LEADING PROTESTS
AGAINST THE INCOMING TALIBAN
REGIME, ODDS ARE, MUCH OF THAT
PROGRESS IS NOW SET TO BE
OBLITERATED.
BUT HERE IS WHERE IT GETS REALLY
HARD.
WHAT WAS THE ANSWER HERE?
TO STAY INDEFINITELY?
IT IS VERY HARD TO MAKE A GOOD
CASE FOR THAT, ESPECIALLY GIVEN
THE TALIBAN HAD BEEN
STRENGTHENING IN RECENT YEARS
AND HAD MADE IT CLEAR THAT THEY
WERE GOING TO ESCALATE VIOLENCE
UNLESS WE LEFT.
WHICH MOST PEOPLE AGREE, WE HAD
TO DO.
THE PROBLEM IS THOUGH, JUST AS
WE WENT IN FOCUSED ENTIRELY ON
U.S. INTERESTS, WE'RE LEAVING
THE EXACT SAME WAY.
AND THAT BRINGS US TO WHAT WE'RE
DOING RIGHT NOW.
BECAUSE THIS EXIT WAS SET IN
MOTION IN FEBRUARY OF 2020, WHEN
THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION STRUCK
A DEAL WITH THE TALIBAN FOR A
TOTAL U.S. WITHDRAWAL BY MAY OF
THIS YEAR.
IN EXCHANGE, THE TALIBAN AGREED
NOT TO LET AFGHANISTAN BECOME A
HAVEN FOR TERRORISTS, AND TO
START PEACE TALKS WITH THE
AFGHAN GOVERNMENT.
ALTHOUGH, NOTABLY, THAT DEAL
EXCLUDED THE AFGHAN GOVERNMENT,
MAKING THIS LINE FROM
MIKE POMPEO A LITTLE
HARD TO TAKE.
WHEN IT COMES DOWN TO IT, THE
FUTURE OF AFGHANISTAN IS FOR
AFGHANS TO DETERMINE.
THE U.S.-TALIBAN DEAL CREATES
THE CONDITIONS FOR AFGHANS TO DO
JUST THAT.
WELL, HOLD ON.
YOU NEVER WANT TWO PEOPLE IN A
ROOM DETERMINING YOUR FUTURE
WITHOUT YOU, ESPECIALLY IF ONE
OF THEM IS THE TALIBAN.
HOW DOES POMPEO EXPECT THEM TO
REACT TO THAT?
CONGRATULATIONS, AFGHANS.
TODAY IS THE FIRST DAY OF WHAT
SOMEONE ELSE DETERMINED THE REST
OF YOUR LIFE WILL BE.
NOW, BIDEN PUSHED OUR EXIT DATE
BACK SLIGHTLY, TO AUGUST 31, BUT
HE BASICALLY FOLLOWED THROUGH
WITH THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION'S
DEAL.
AND WHILE THE TALIBAN LARGELY
STUCK BY THEIR PROMISE NOT TO
ATTACK U.S. PERSONNEL, ALMOST
IMMEDIATELY AFTER SIGNING THAT
DEAL, THEY CARRIED OUT AT LEAST
76 ATTACKS ACROSS 24 AFGHAN
PROVINCES AND HAVE SINCE PURSUED
ASSASSINATION CAMPAIGNS OF
GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS,
JOURNALISTS, AND CIVIL SOCIETY
ACTORS, AND JUST THIS MAY,
BEHEADED AN AFGHAN INTERPRETER
FOR THE U.S. ARMY.
AND YET, ALL THE WHILE, THEY'VE
MADE A BIG SHOW OF PRESENTING
THEMSELVES IN A MORE MODERN,
FLATTERING LIGHT... SOMETHING
THAT CONTINUED THIS WEEK.
THIS WAS A SMARTER, MORE
MEDIA-SAVVY TALIBAN ONE.
SENIOR LEADERS CLAIMING THEY
WANT TO FORM AN "INCLUSIVE,
ISLAMIC GOVERNMENT."
THE GROUP IS ESTABLISHING A
"CIVILIAN CASUALTY PREVENTION
AND COMPLAINTS COMMISSION,"
TWEETING OUT WHATSAPP PHONE
NUMBERS FOR AFGHANS TO SEND IN
COMPLAINTS.
WOW, THAT IS SOMETHING.
AND SET ASIDE THE FACT THAT
"TALIBAN COMPLAINTS DEPARTMENT"
SOUNDS LIKE A SKETCH ELON MUSK
PITCHED TO "SNL," I'M NOT SURE
IT'S GOING TO BE ALL THAT
EFFECTIVE.
IT'S THE EQUIVALENT OF
INSTITUTING A COMPLAINT BOX IN
SCOTT RUDIN'S OFFICE.
THE PROBLEM WITH THE BEHAVIOR
THERE ISN'T "LACK OF AWARENESS."
A SIGNIFICANTLY CHANGED TALIBAN
JUST DOESN'T SEEM LIKELY HERE.
THEIR TIES TO AL-QAEDA ONLY
APPEAR TO BE DEEPENING.
AND THEY'RE NOW EVEN BETTER
ARMED.
THE AFGHAN FORCES FELL SO
QUICKLY, THEY LEFT BEHIND
BRAND-NEW BOXES OF GUNS AND
GRENADE LAUNCHERS, WHICH TALIBAN
FIGHTERS HAVE BEEN FILMING
THEMSELVES OPENING IN THE
WORLD'S GRIMMEST UNBOXING
VIDEOS.
INCIDENTS WHICH LED TO THIS
WHAT HAPPENS TO THE BILLIONS
OF DOLLARS WORTH OF WEAPONRY
THAT THE U.S. GAVE AFGHANISTAN?
WE DON'T HAVE A COMPLETE
PICTURE, OBVIOUSLY, OF WHERE
EVERY ARTICLE OF DEFENSE
MATERIALS HAS GONE.
BUT CERTAINLY A FAIR AMOUNT OF
IT HAS FALLEN INTO THE HANDS OF
THE TALIBAN, AND, AH, OBVIOUSLY
WE DON'T HAVE A SENSE THAT
THEY ARE GOING TO READILY HAND
IT OVER TO US AT THE AIRPORT.
AH, YEAH, I THINK
THAT'S A SAFE ASSUMPTION.
BUT HEY, WE COULD ALWAYS TEXT
THE TALIBAN COMPLAINT DEPARTMENT
AND SEE WHAT HAPPENS.
I'M SURE WE'LL BE DEALT WITH
SWIFTLY.
SO HERE WE ARE, 20 YEARS OF WAR
AND DESTRUCTION.
TENS OF THOUSANDS OF AFGHANS
KILLED.
MANY MORE TRAUMATIZED.
AND THE OVERALL SENSE YOU HAVE
AT THIS POINT IS OF DEEP
BETRAYAL OF THE
PROMISES THAT WERE MADE TO THE
AFGHAN PEOPLE AND BETRAYAL OF
THE U.S. SERVICE MEMBERS ASKED
TO EXECUTE THOSE SELF-SERVING
PROMISES AND WHO ARE NOW LEFT
ASKING THEMSELVES, "WHAT DID I
JUST DO?
WHAT WAS THIS ALL FOR?"
THE MILITARY SENT OUT AN EMAIL
TO 9 MILLION VETERANS THIS WEEK
OFFERING A LIST OF MENTAL HEALTH
RESOURCES WITH NOTES LIKE,
"IF YOU'RE HAVING THOUGHTS OF
SUICIDE, CALL THIS NUMBER."
AND IF YOU ARE, DO.
THIS IS A GRIM SITUATION.
AND THERE ARE IMMEDIATE
DECISIONS THAT NEED TO BE MADE
THAT HAVE LIFE-OR-DEATH
CONSEQUENCES FOR AFGHANS WHO PUT
THEIR TRUST IN US, LIKE THIS
FATIMA, THAT'S NOT HER REAL
NAME, AND HER CHILDREN HAVE GONE
INTO HIDING AFTER DEATH THREATS
FROM THE TALIBAN FOR HER WORK IN
EMPOWERING OTHER WOMEN.
SHE THOUGHT SHE WAS BUILDING A
NEW AND BETTER AFGHANISTAN, BUT
NOW SHE'S VIEWED AS A SPY AND
ENEMY COLLABORATOR.
I FEEL EXTREMELY ABANDONED.
I AM IN... I AM IN DANGER.
IT'S NOT ONLY THAT I AM IN
DANGER, NOW MY KIDS ARE IN
DANGER.
THEY WON'T... THEY WON'T LEAVE
US... THEY WON'T LEAVE ME ALIVE.
WE BEAR RESPONSIBILITY
FOR THE POSITION SHE'S IN.
WE SAID WE'D PROTECT PEOPLE WHO
DID COURAGEOUS THINGS THAT
PISSED OFF THE TALIBAN, LIKE
"ADVOCATE FOR HUMAN RIGHTS,"
EVEN IF IT WOUND UP PUTTING A
TARGET ON THEIR BACK.
AND NOW IT FEELS LIKE WE'RE
WALKING AWAY GOING, "WHOA, COOL
TARGET, HOW'D YOU GET THAT?
YOU KNOW WHAT?
DON'T ANSWER, WE'RE LEAVING."
AND AGAIN, I AM NOT ADVOCATING
FOR STAYING.
AT ALL.
WHAT I'M SAYING IS, WE'RE IN THE
MIDST OF A MASSIVE HUMANITARIAN
CRISIS, AND WE HAVE A CLEAR
OBLIGATION TO TAKE IN AFGHANS
WHO ARE NOW VULNERABLE... AND
NOT JUST THOSE THAT WORKED WITH
U.S. TROOPS, BUT THOSE, LIKE
FATIMA AND HER CHILDREN, WHOSE
LIVES ARE NOW AT GRAVE RISK.
ALTHOUGH SOME CONSERVATIVE
COMMENTATORS ARE ALREADY TRYING
TO GET WAY OUT AHEAD OF THAT.
IF HISTORY IS ANY GUIDE, AND
IT'S ALWAYS A GUIDE, WE WILL SEE
MANY REFUGEES FROM AFGHANISTAN
RESETTLE IN OUR COUNTRY IN
COMING MONTHS, PROBABLY IN YOUR
NEIGHBORHOOD.
AND OVER THE NEXT DECADE, THAT
NUMBER MAY SWELL TO THE
MILLIONS.
SO FIRST WE INVADE, AND THEN WE
ARE INVADED.
THE LESSON OF THIS 20-YEAR
WAR CANNOT BE THAT EVERY TIME WE
TURN A COUNTRY UPSIDE DOWN OR
MAKE HUGE MISTAKES, OUR
IMMIGRATION LAWS, OUR REFUGEE
LAWS NO LONGER APPLY.
OKAY, FIRST, FUCK OFF,
YOU TAG TEAM RACIAL PANIC
GOBLINS.
SECOND, THE NOTION OF
"EVERY TIME WE TURN A COUNTRY
UPSIDE DOWN" IS AN INCREDIBLE
THING TO JUST BLOW PAST.
MAYBE THAT'S THE LESSON HERE,
LAURA.
MAYBE DON'T KEEP TURNING
COUNTRIES UPSIDE DOWN IN THE
FIRST PLACE.
AS FOR, "OUR REFUGEE LAWS NO
LONGER APPLY"?
WE ARE A BIG PART OF WHY THOSE
PEOPLE ARE REFUGEES.
HELPING THEM NOW ISN'T CHARITY,
IT'S DOING THE BARE MINIMUM.
REFUSING TO HELP A NEIGHBOR
WHOSE HOME JUST BURNED DOWN IS
SHITTY.
DOING IT WHEN YOU HELPED START
THE FIRE IS FUCKING MONSTROUS.
AND THE THING IS, THEY'RE NOT
THE ONLY ONES WHO'VE BEEN BLITHE
ABOUT THE FATE OF THE AFGHANS.
BIDEN'S FAILURE TO PLAN HERE IS
ASTONISHING.
BUT HIS CONTINUED INDIFFERENCE
TO THE LIVES OF ANYONE WHO'S NOT
AMERICAN ISN'T SURPRISING.
HE'S FELT THIS WAY FOR YEARS.
ACCORDING TO THE LATE DIPLOMAT
RICHARD HOLBROOKE'S DIARY, IN
2010, THE TWO MEN HAD A
CONVERSATION, AND BIDEN TOLD
HIM THE U.S. HAD TO WITHDRAW
EVERY TROOP FROM AFGHANISTAN,
REGARDLESS OF THE CONSEQUENCES
FOR WOMEN OR ANYONE ELSE.
AND WHEN HOLBROOKE ASKED HIM
ABOUT AMERICAN OBLIGATIONS TO
THOSE WHO'D BE IN DANGER IF WE
LEFT, BIDEN MENTIONED THE U.S.
WITHDRAWAL FROM SOUTHEAST ASIA
IN 1973, SAYING, "FUCK THAT, WE
DON'T HAVE TO WORRY ABOUT THAT.
WE DID IT IN VIETNAM, NIXON AND
KISSINGER GOT AWAY WITH IT."
AND MAY I SAY, JOE?
A-PLUS CHOICE OF HISTORICAL
ROLE-MODELS THERE.
WHEN YOU'RE ROLLING WITH DICK
AND THE KISS, YOU KNOW YOU'RE
ROLLING ON THE RIGHT SIDE OF
HISTORY.
AND LAST FEBRUARY, BIDEN DOUBLED
DOWN ON THAT ARGUMENT.
DON'T YOU BEAR SOME
RESPONSIBILITY FOR THE OUTCOME
IF THE TALIBAN ENDS UP BACK IN
CONTROL AND WOMEN END UP LOSING
THE RIGHTS?
NO, I DON'T.
DO I BEAR RESPONSIBILITY?
ZERO RESPONSIBILITY.
THE RESPONSIBILITY I HAVE IS TO
PROTECT AMERICA'S NATIONAL
SELF-INTEREST AND NOT PUT OUR
WOMEN AND MEN IN HARM'S WAY TO
TRY TO SOLVE EVERY SINGLE
PROBLEM IN THE WORLD BY USE OF
FORCE.
THAT'S MY RESPONSIBILITY AS
PRESIDENT.
YOU DON'T HAVE TO MAKE A ZERO
WITH YOUR FINGERS TO INDICATE
YOU MEAN ZERO.
YOU'RE AN ADULT MAN, NOT
A CHILD ENSEMBLE MEMBER OF
BROADWAY'S "MATILDA."
THOUGH I WILL SAY, IF BIDEN
WANTS TO ARGUE FOR ISOLATIONISM
GOING FORWARD, HE'S WELCOME TO
DO THAT.
BUT WHAT HE CAN'T DO IS USE THAT
AS A JUSTIFICATION TO DISMISS
THE FATES OF PEOPLE IN WHOSE
COUNTRY WE'VE ALREADY
DISASTROUSLY INTERVENED.
BECAUSE WE HAVE A NON-ZERO DUTY
AT THIS POINT TO DO EVERYTHING
WE CAN TO HELP THEM.
AND THAT MEANS GETTING AS MANY
PEOPLE OUT AS WE CAN.
AND ADVOCATES FOR REFUGEES SAY
THE FIRST THING TO DO IS SECURE
A PERIMETER AT THE KABUL
AIRPORT, MAKING SURE PEOPLE HAVE
A SAFE WAY TO GET THERE AND GET
INSIDE, BECAUSE THAT HAS BEEN
TOTAL CHAOS THIS WEEK, TO THE
POINT THAT MANY OF THE DEPARTING
FLIGHTS HAVE LEFT WITH EMPTY
SEATS.
AND THE FACT THERE ARE PEOPLE
WITH VISAS UNABLE TO GET ONTO
THE PLANES IS BAD ENOUGH.
BUT THERE ARE MANY MORE AT-RISK
AFGHANS WHO ARE STILL STUCK IN
THE VISA PROCESS, AND WE SHOULD
BE GETTING THEM TO THE U.S. AS
QUICKLY AS POSSIBLE SO THEY
CAN THEN SAFELY FINISH THEIR
PAPERWORK... AND THAT CAN BE
ACHIEVED BY GRANTING THEM
CATEGORICAL "HUMANITARIAN
PAROLE."
AND TO THE EXTENT ANY HESITATION
ABOUT DOING THIS IS DUE TO FEAR
OF POLITICAL BLOWBACK THANKS TO
IDIOTS LIKE THESE, CALL YOUR
REPRESENTATIVES AND TELL THEM
THAT YOU CARE ABOUT THIS.
BECAUSE IF THEY THINK THAT YOU
DON'T, IT IS NOT GOING TO
HAPPEN.
THE CHAOS THIS WEEK IS
ALREADY A STAIN ON BIDEN'S
LEGACY... THE ONLY QUESTION IS,
HOW BIG DOES HE WANT THAT STAIN
TO BE?
AND THAT IS REALLY UP TO HIM.
BUT MORE BROADLY, WE, AS A
COUNTRY, NEED TO TAKE A HARD
LOOK AT WHAT WE'VE DONE IN
AFGHANISTAN... WHICH IS LIKELY
TO BE DESTABILIZED FOR DECADES
TO COME.
SO WHAT CAN WE DO ABOUT THAT?
NOT MUCH NOW.
NO AMOUNT OF BRUTE FORCE OR
PERSEVERANCE IS GOING TO CLEAR
UP THE CLUSTERFUCK THAT WE
HELPED FUCK INTO EXISTENCE.
AND I REALIZE THAT'S A
QUINTESSENTIALLY UNAMERICAN
IDEA... TO ACKNOWLEDGE THAT WE
CAN'T ALWAYS CONTROL SOMETHING
WE WANT TO CONTROL OR ACHIEVE
SOMETHING WE WANT TO ACHIEVE.
BUT THE TRUTH IS, WE CAN'T.
I KNOW THAT FEELS FUTILE.
BUT ASSUMING WE CAN GO INTO
ANOTHER COUNTRY AND FIX
EVERYTHING BY SIMPLY IMPOSING
OUR WILL IS LARGELY WHAT LED US
TO WHERE WE ARE RIGHT NOW.
WE HAVE SPENT DECADES CLAIMING
THAT WE'RE TRYING TO SOLVE THE
WORLD'S PROBLEMS... ALBEIT
ALMOST EXCLUSIVELY WHEN IT
HELPED SOLVE OUR OWN... AND THE
RESULT HAS BEEN, IN THE WORDS OF
THIS PROFESSIONAL
PEARL-CLUTCHER, THAT WE'VE
TURNED ONE COUNTRY AFTER ANOTHER
UPSIDE DOWN.
SO WE SHOULD MAYBE STOP DOING
THAT.
BUT IN THE MEANTIME, THE LEAST
WE COULD DO IS HELP ALLEVIATE
THE HUMANITARIAN CRISIS AHEAD.
BECAUSE NO MATTER WHAT HAPPENS
IN AFGHANISTAN FROM HERE ON OUT,
THERE IS NO UNIVERSE WHERE
AMERICA BEARS ZERO
RESPONSIBILITY.
AND NOW THIS.
AND NOW, TAMRON
HALL WILL HAVE YOU KNOW SHE IS
50.
AND HERE SHE IS, THE ONE, THE
ONLY, THE 50 AND FABULOUS TAMRON
HALL!
I HAVE, IN MY 40s, NOW THAT
I'M 50.
I'M 59.
ON A PERSONAL NOTE, I'M 50.
>41 AND DON'T CARE.
WAIT TILL YOU TURN 50.
I'M 50, YOU ARE 54.
YOU AND YOUR FRIENDS ON
"SESAME STREET" HAVE BEEN
HELPING KIDS AND FAMILIES AROUND
THE WORLD AND ALL KINDS OF WAYS
FOR MORE THAN 50 YEARS.
50 YEARS, THAT'S HOW OLD I AM.
WOW.
LISTEN, I AM... AS THE KIDS
SAY, I'M 50.
HOW DID I NOT KNOW THAT?
OKAY, I AM 50 YEARS OLD.
I'M 50.
THIS IS THE BEST TACO I'VE EVER
HAD IN MY LIFE.
I'M 50.
MOVING ON.
BEFORE WE GO, A QUICK WORD ABOUT
HAMMERS.
SOME ARE EENSY.
SOME ARE CHONKOS.
SOME HAVE A LITTLE CLAW ON THE
END FOR PULLING NAILS.
OTHERS HAVE A LITTLE ROUND NUB
AND NO ONE KNOWS WHY.
AND ONE HAMMER IS ACTUALLY A
PRACTICING PERSONAL INJURY
ATTORNEY, WHICH
YOU MIGHT REMEMBER FROM THIS
"AND NOW" SEGMENT WE AIRED IN
2019.
GREEDY INSURANCE COMPANIES
PLAY DIRTY.
BRING IT ON!
I'M JIM ADLER, THE TEXAS HAMMER.
AND I DO MY BEST TO BRING 'EM
DOWN!
I GET ANGRIER THAN A JUNKYARD
DOG.
I STAND TOUGH AND CARRY A BIG
HAMMER.
I GROWL AND BARK.
WAKE UP!
IT'S HAMMER TIME!
I'M JIM ADLER, THE TEXAS HAMMER!
YOU GET THE IDEA,
RIGHT?
HE'S THE TEXAS HAMMER.
HE CARRIES A HAMMER.
HE TALKS ABOUT HAMMERS.
FOR A WHILE IN THE MIDDLE HE
TALKS ABOUT GROWLING AND BARKING
LIKE A DOG, WHICH IS A BIT
CONFUSING, BECAUSE THAT'S NOT A
THING HAMMERS DO, BUT THEN IT'S
RIGHT BACK TO HAMMER TIME, BABY.
NOW, WE AIRED THAT BECAUSE WE
THOUGHT HIS ADS WERE FANTASTIC.
BUT SINCE THEN, WE'VE DISCOVERED
JUST HOW MUCH MONEY JIM ADLER
PUTS INTO THEM.
HE CLAIMS TO HAVE SPENT OVER
$100 MILLION DOLLARS ON ADS
SINCE 2000, AND AS YOU CAN SEE
FROM THIS TESTIMONIAL HE ONCE
FILMED FOR AN AD AGENCY HE
WORKED WITH, HE PUTS A LOT OF
THOUGHT INTO THEM TOO.
A LAWYER IN ANOTHER STATE MAY
NOT WANT TO BE A HAMMER, OR BE A
TOUGH, SMART LAWYER, BUT THEY
UNDERSTAND THE IMAGE THAT THE
CLIENT WANTS TO PORTRAY.
RIGHT.
LAWYERS IN OTHER STATES MIGHT
NOT WANT TO BE TOUGH, SMART
LAWYERS.
WISCONSIN LIKES ITS LAWYERS WEAK
AND SIMPLE.
MICHIGAN PREFERS THEM LEAN AND
LETHARGIC.
IDAHO WANTS EVERY ATTORNEY TO BE
DAMP AND DISTRACTED, WHILE HERE
IN NEW YORK, WE LIKE THEM SWEATY
AND SUSPENDED.
UNFORTUNATELY FOR JIM ADLER
THOUGH, IT TURNS OUT THERE IS
ANOTHER LAWYER IN ANOTHER STATE
WHO WANTS TO BE A HAMMER TOO.
I'M MIKE SLOCUMB.
THE ALABAMA HAMMER!
IF YOU'VE BEEN INJURED, CALL ME
RIGHT NOW AND GET THE BIG CHECK.
HI, MIKE!
NICE TO MEET YOU!
NOW, IF YOU'RE NOTICING ANY
SIMILARITIES, YOU'RE NOT ALONE.
BECAUSE WHEN JIM ADLER FOUND OUT
WHAT MIKE SLOCUMB WAS DOING, HE
FUCKING SUED HIM!
AND WHILE WE CAN'T GET INTO ALL
OF THE CLAIMS IN HIS VERY FUN
LAWSUIT, BASICALLY, HE'S
ALLEGING THAT MIKE SLOCUMB...
THE ALABAMA HAMMER... HAD
"ADOPTED HIS FAMOUS PERSONA IN A
BRAZEN BID TO CONFUSE AND
DECEIVE CONSUMERS."
AND THE THING IS, HE'S NOT JUST
CLAIMING THE ALABAMA HAMMER IS
COPYING HIS NICKNAME.
I'M GOING TO PLAY TWO OF THEIR
COMMERCIALS SIDE BY SIDE AND SEE
IF THEY LOOK SIMILAR TO YOU.
GREEDY INSURANCE COMPANIES
PLAY DIRTY.
BRING IT ON.
CHEAP INSURANCE COMPANIES
PLAY ROUGH.
I BEAT 'EM AT THEIR OWN GAME!
I'M JIM ADLER, THE TEXAS
HAMMER!
I'M MIKE SLOCUMB, THE ALABAMA
THAT'S WHAT I THOUGHT!
OH, COME ON!
NOW, I HAVE TO TELL YOU, SLOCUMB
DENIES ADLER'S CLAIMS...
INCLUDING THAT HE COPIED THAT
AD.
AND I'M GONNA SAY, GOOD LUCK
DEFENDING THAT ARGUMENT.
BUT I DO ACTUALLY HAVE A BIT OF
SYMPATHY FOR MIKE SLOCUMB.
BECAUSE IF YOU WATCH HIS ADS
THAT AREN'T HAMMER-THEMED, IT
BECOMES CLEAR HOW MUCH MIKE
NEEDS THAT GIMMICK.
BECAUSE THEY'RE A TOTAL MESS.
THERE'S ONE WHERE HE'S A
"BIG BUCKS" HUNTER WHERE HE
SHOOTS DEER THAT EXPLODE INTO
MONEY, ONE WHERE HE RUNS AFTER
AN AMBULANCE LIKE A CAROUSEL
HORSE, ONLY TO GET HIT BY A
DIFFERENT AMBULANCE.
AND THEN THERE'S THIS:
GIVE ME MY LUNCH MONEY BACK!
WHERE'S THE ALABAMA HAMMER?
I'VE BEEN STANDING UP TO
BULLIES MY WHOLE LIFE.
WHOO!
I'M MIKE SLOCUMB, THE ALABAMA
HAMMER!
IF YOU'VE BEEN INJURED IN A CAR
WRECK, DON'T LET THE INSURANCE
COMPANY BULLY YOU.
CALL ME RIGHT NOW!
WHAT THE FUCK WAS THAT?
I'M REALLY CURIOUS WHAT HAPPENED
IN THE NEXT SCENE WHEN THE
POLICE TURNED UP.
"WHO PUNCHED THIS CHILD
UNCONSCIOUS?"
"THAT WAS ME, OFFICER, BUT DON'T
WORRY... IT'S OKAY."
"EXPLAIN HOW, BUT JUST SO YOU
KNOW, I'M GOING TO GET MY TASER
OUT WHILE YOU TALK."
"WHEN I KNOCKED HIM OUT, I WAS
ALSO A CHILD.
THEN I SAID 'WHOO, ' IMMEDIATELY
AGED 30 YEARS INTO AN ADULT, AND
SAID 'WHOO' AGAIN."
"HMM.
SEEMS UNLIKELY, BUT YOU ARE
WHITE, SO I'M GONNA GO AHEAD AND
GIVE YOU THE BENEFIT OF THE
DOUBT."
LOOK, IT SEEMS PRETTY CLEAR TO
ME THAT MIKE SLOCUMB RIPPED OFF
THE TEXAS HAMMER.
AND YOU CAN SEE WHY.
HIS COMMERCIALS ARE EVERYTHING
CLEAR,
PRECISE, AND THEMATICALLY
RESONANT.
HE'S
THE TEXAS HAMMER, AND THAT'S IT.
AND I SO BADLY DON'T WANT THESE
TWO GLORIOUS MANIACS TO FIGHT.
IT SEEMS THE BEST THING IS FOR
MIKE SLOCUMB TO SIMPLY GET A
DIFFERENT TOOL-THEMED NICKNAME
SO THESE TWO DANGEROUSLY STRANGE
MEN CAN MOVE ON IN PEACE.
AND I ACTUALLY HAVE A SUGGESTION
FOR YOU, MIKE, AND IT'S THIS
BANANA SLICER.
MIKE "THE ALABAMA BANANA SLICER"
SLOCUMB.
THINK ABOUT IT... IT WORKS
PERFECTLY.
JUST LIKE A HAMMER, IT'S A TOOL.
AND LIKE YOUR COMMERCIALS, IT'S
UNNECESSARY, COMPLICATED, AND I
DON'T LIKE LOOKING AT IT.
SO PLEASE, MIKE, TAKE THIS IDEA,
AND TAKE THIS BANANA SLICER TOO.
AND THAT'S IT!
THAT'S OUR SHOW!
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WATCHING
DURING THIS VERY WEIRD TIME.
THANK YOU TO OUR STAFF
FOR WORKING SO HARD IN THIS VERY
DIFFICULT ENVIRONMENT.
WE'LL BE OFF FOR A COUPLE OF
WEEKS NOW.
BUT WE WILL BE BACK
SEPTEMBER 12TH, DEFINITELY IN A
STUDIO, MAYBE WITH AN AUDIENCE,
MAYBE NOT.
WHO KNOWS?
BUT THE POINT IS, THAT'S IT!
THAT'S IT?
LIKE...
YOU'RE ENDING IT?
YEAH.
THAT'S IT.
THIS IS WHERE YOU AND I SAY
GOODBYE.
YOU KNOW, IT IS OUR LAST
NIGHT TOGETHER, RIGHT?
SO YOU DIDN'T PLAN ANYTHING?
UM...
CONAN GOT A SONG, REMEMBER?
JACK BLACK SANG A BIG SONG.
RIGHT, SORRY, DO YOU
THINK YOU'RE THE CONAN IN THIS
DYNAMIC?
I JUST THOUGHT YOU'D PREPARE
SOMETHING.
BUT YOU'RE NOT GONNA... YEAH...
YOU KNOW... YOU'RE DOING IN YOUR
WAY.
THAT'S FINE.
BYE.
ALL RIGHT, UM,
ARE YOU SURE?
YEAH, I SAID I'M FINE.
SO WE'RE DONE.
GOODBYE.
AND DEFINITELY NO SONG.
OKAY, WELL, THANKS FOR
EVERYTHING AND I GUESS, UM, I'LL
SEE YOU AROUND.
UM...
BYE.
I'M NOT DEAD!
I'M RETURNING TO A STUDIO!
JESUS CHRIST.
THIS IS A LOT.
QUEEN ELIZABETH HAD
PRINCESS DIANA MURDERED.
GOOD NIGHT.
NO, NO, NO, NO,
NO, NO, NO!
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org