HI, THERE!
WELCOME TO THE SHOW.
OUR SECOND TO LAST ONE
INCIDENTALLY TAKING PLACE IN
THIS BLANK VOID.
HEY, EVERYBODY.
HEY.
HEY, JOHN.
I HAVE BEEN THINKING A LOT
ABOUT, YOU KNOW, YOU AND I IN
THE LAST FEW WEEKS, AND I, YOU
KNOW, I AM A VOID.
SOMETIMES I CAN BE CANTANKEROUS
IF YOU KNOW WHAT THAT MEANS.
BUT I DO WANT TO SAY, I ACTUALLY
WILL MISS YOU WHEN YOU'RE GONE.
WAIT, REALLY?
NO!
NOT AT ALL!
RIGHT.
TOTALLY JOKING!
YEP.
BYE, I HATE YOU.
Get out!
I FIGURED.
WHAT A FUCKING IDIOT.
MOVING ON!
IT'S BEEN A BUSY WEEK IN
AFGHANISTAN.
THE TALIBAN NOW CONTROLS
HALF OF THE COUNTRY'S PROVINCIAL
CAPITALS.
IN NEW YORK, ANDREW CUOMO
RESIGNED IN DISGRACE OR AS
CHRIS CUOMO MIGHT SAY...
BUT I WANT TO TALK ABOUT
THE CORONAVIRUS.
BECAUSE SADLY, OUR
HOT VAX SUMMER SEEMS TO BE
GIVING WAY TO DIPSHIT AUTUMN
AS THE DELTA VARIANT IS
SPREADING WILDLY AROUND
THE COUNTRY, PARTICULARLY
AMONG THE UNVACCINATED,
WITH THE U.S. AVERAGING AROUND
100,000 NEW INFECTIONS A DAY.
AND ALARMINGLY, ROUGHLY 15% OF
NEW CASES OUR CHILDREN, WITH
OVER 250 KIDS BEING NEWLY
HOSPITALIZED EACH DAY.
AND ALL OF THIS MEANS THAT MANY
HOSPITALS ARE YET AGAIN BEING
STRETCHED TO THE BREAKING POINT,
PARTICULARLY IN CERTAIN PARTS OF
THE COUNTRY, WITH FLORIDA AND
TEXAS ALONE ACCOUNTING FOR
40% OF NEW HOSPITALIZATIONS AND
THE RESPONSE OF FLORIDA'S
GOVERNOR HAS BEEN UNDERWHELMING.
TODAY, FLORIDA'S GOVERNOR
CONCEDED THINGS MAY LOOK BAD.
WE ARE SEEING PEOPLE TESTING
POSITIVE IN HIGHER NUMBERS THAN
I THINK MOST PEOPLE
ANTICIPATED.
DEAL WITH
IT.
IT'S AIRBORNE.
IT'S AEROSOLIZED.
AND SO WE JUST HAVE TO
UNDERSTAND THAT WHEN THAT'S
HAPPENING, THESE WAVES ARE
SOMETHING THAT YOU HAVE TO
DEAL WITH.
WOW, THE WORLD CHANGES
SO QUICKLY, DOESN'T IT?
IF YOU HAD TOLD ME JUST
A FEW YEARS AGO THAT FLORIDA'S
REPUBLICAN GOVERNOR WOULD
RESPOND TO A DEADLY THREAT WITH
"THESE WAVES ARE SOMETHING YOU
JUST HAVE TO DEAL WITH," I'D
HAVE ASSUMED THEY WERE TALKING
ABOUT MIAMI SINKING INTO A
WARMING OCEAN, NOT A COMPLETELY
DIFFERENT, TOTALLY SELF-INDUCED
CRISIS.
AND IT'S PRETTY TOUGH TO HEAR
THIS CUT-RATE COACH TAYLOR
SAYING, "JUST DEAL WITH IT" WHEN
HE SEEMS TO BE VERY MUCH NOT
DOING THAT.
JUST A FEW WEEKS AGO, DeSANTIS
ISSUED AN ORDER BANNING SCHOOL
MASK MANDATES... MAKING FLORIDA
ONE OF AT LEAST SEVEN STATES
NOW PROHIBITING SCHOOLS FROM
IMPOSING THEM.
AND SCHOOL BOARD MEETINGS AROUND
THE COUNTRY HAVE SEEN FIERY
EXCHANGES ABOUT THIS ISSUE.
IN NORTH CAROLINA,
REPRESENTATIVE MADISON CAWTHORN
SHOWED UP TO ONE, TO DO WHATEVER
THIS IS.
THE GREATEST THREAT TO OUR
CHILDREN TODAY DOES NOT COME
FROM COVID-19.
IT COMES FROM WOKE, LIBERAL
GOVERNMENT OFFICIALS LIKE YOU
WHO THINK THEY ARE ALL KNOWING
AND ALL WISE.
I'M A DIRECT DESCENDANT OF
ABRAHAM KUYKENDALL, ONE OF THE
FIRST MEN TO SETTLE THIS COUNTY.
HE KNEW HARDSHIP FIRSTHAND.
HE DID NOT ENDURE THAT HARDSHIP
JUST SO A WOKE SCHOOL BOARD CAN
BEGIN TO SYSTEMATICALLY STRIP
THE RESPONSIBILITY FROM THE
HANDS OF PARENTS AND GUARDIANS
O
TO DETERMINE WHAT TO HAPPENS
WITH THEIR CHILDREN.
WOW.
SO MADISON CAWTHORN THINKS THE
BIGGEST THREAT TO CHILDREN IS
SCHOOL BOARD MEMBERS WHO THINK
THEY'RE OMNISCIENT.
I'D SAY I WAS SURPRISED,
BUT THIS IS A MAN WHO ONCE
POSTED THIS VIDEO OF HIMSELF
BEATING UP A TREE.
SO HE CLEARLY LOVES TO PICK
USELESS FIGHTS AGAINST IMAGINARY
OPPONENTS WHERE HE COMES OUT
LOOKING LIKE A COMPLETE ASSHOLE.
ALSO, A QUICK SIDE NOTE ABOUT
HIM BRAGGING ABOUT BEING
A DESCENDANT OF
ABRAHAM KUYKENDALL.
NOT ONLY DOES THAT LAST NAME
SOUND LIKE THE SWEDISH
TRANSLATION FOR BRATZ DOLLS,
FOR THE RECORD,
ABRAHAM KIRKENDALL... WHICH IS
HOW IT'S ACTUALLY PRONOUNCED...
WAS ONE OF THE EARLIEST
SLAVE OWNERS IN THE COUNTY.
SO NEXT TIME YOU'RE TRYING TO
PROVE A POINT ABOUT HOW PARENTS
SHOULD DECIDE WHAT'S BEST FOR
THEIR KIDS, MAYBE DON'T USE
A GUY WHO DECIDED THE BEST THING
FOR OTHER PEOPLE'S KIDS WAS FOR
HIM TO OWN THEM.
AND THAT WAS BY NO MEANS
THE ONLY WILDLY INAPPROPRIATE
HISTORICAL REFERENCE DURING
A DEBATE THIS WEEK.
JUST AFTER THE FOX CHAPEL
SCHOOL BOARD VOTED FOR STUDENTS
TO WEAR MASKS AS THE NEW SCHOOL
YEAR BEGINS, PEOPLE AT THE
MEETING STARTED ARGUING WITH
THE BOARD, BEFORE THIS PERSON
APPEARS TO FLASH A NAZI SALUTE
AT THE BOARD.
THE HOLOCAUST CENTER OF
PITTSBURGH SAYS THERE IS
NO COMPARISON BETWEEN
THE HOLOCAUST AND MASKING
CHILDREN IN SCHOOLS.
OKAY, I APPRECIATE
THE EFFORT, BUT YOU REALLY DID
NOT NEED TO ASK THE HOLOCAUST
CENTER TO FACT CHECK THAT.
FOR THE SAME REASON YOU DON'T
NEED TO CONTACT AN AFRICAN
STUDIES CENTER TO ASK IF
THE RWANDAN GENOCIDE WAS AS
BAD AS GETTING A POPCORN KERNEL
STUCK IN YOUR TEETH.
IF YOU DON'T ALREADY KNOW THE
ANSWER, YOU DON'T UNDERSTAND
EITHER OF THE THINGS YOU'RE
COMPARING.
AND LOOK, WHEN TEMPERS ARE THIS
HIGH, IT CAN BE HARD TO SORT
THINGS THROUGH IN A NUANCED WAY,
BUT LET'S TRY.
BECAUSE FIRST, WE CAN AGREE:
FOR MOST KIDS, IN-PERSON
SCHOOLING IS VASTLY PREFERABLE
TO THE ONLINE KIND.
THE QUESTION IS, HOW TO DO IT
SAFELY.
AND THOSE OPPOSED TO
MASK MANDATES ARGUE THAT,
SINCE COVID CASES IN CHILDREN
HAVE TENDED TO BE MILD... WHICH
IS, THANKFULLY, TRUE... THE
DOWNSIDES OF THEM WEARING MASKS
OUTWEIGH THE BENEFITS.
BUT THAT IS A BIG SWING.
THERE IS STILL SO MUCH WE DON'T
KNOW ABOUT HOW LONG-TERM COVID,
AND THE DELTA VARIANT, AFFECT
KIDS.
AND WHAT WE DO KNOW IS THAT
COVID IS SIGNIFICANTLY MORE
DEADLY FOR ADULTS, AND IN MANY
COMMUNITIES, FOR SOME FUCKING
REASON, THERE ARE A LOT OF
UNVACCINATED ADULTS TO WHOM KIDS
COULD TRANSMIT THE VIRUS.
BUT IT DOESN'T FEEL LIKE ANY OF
THAT NUANCE IS BEING FACTORED
INTO THIS DISCUSSION,
ESPECIALLY WHEN YOU SEE SCENES
LIKE PEOPLE BEING HARASSED
OUTSIDE THIS TENNESSEE SCHOOL
BOARD MEETING, WITH A MAN WHO
SPOKE IN FAVOR OF MASK
REQUIREMENTS BEING CONFRONTED
EVERYBODY'S TAKING NOTES,
BUDDY!
KEEP THAT LITTLE SMILE.
WE KNOW WHO YOU ARE!
YOU CAN LEAVE FREELY BUT WE WILL
FIND YOU AND WE KNOW WHO YOU
ARE.
WE KNOW WHO YOU ARE.
HOLY SHIT.
IT'S GENUINELY HARD TO IMAGINE
A FIVE-WORD PHRASE LESS WELCOME
THAN "WE KNOW WHO YOU ARE,"
ASIDE FROM, OBVIOUSLY, "NEW
"JEOPARDY" HOST MIKE RICHARDS."
AND LOOK, I'M NOT SAYING MASKS,
IN AND OF THEMSELVES,
ARE A PERFECT SHIELD AGAINST
TRANSMISSION.
THEY'RE NOT!
EXPERTS ARGUE THEY SHOULD BE
PART OF A LAYERED APPROACH...
LIKE ENSURING PROPER VENTILATION
IN SCHOOLS, MAINTAINING SOCIAL
DISTANCING, AND REQUIRING THAT
EVERYONE IN A SCHOOL WHO CAN GET
A VACCINE DOES.
THE PROBLEM IS, IT'S NOT LIKE
SOME OF THESE STATES ARE SAYING,
"OKAY, WE'LL TAKE EVERY
REASONABLE PRECAUTION, EXCEPT
FOR MASKS."
BECAUSE IN TEXAS, THEY'RE DOING
THIS.
THE TEXAS EDUCATION AGENCY
RELEASED NEW GUIDANCE REGARDING
COVID-19 AND SCHOOLS.
UNDER THE NEW GUIDELINES,
SCHOOLS ARE NOT REQUIRED TO
INFORM PARENTS OF A POSITIVE
CASE, SCHOOLS DO NOT HAVE TO
CONDUCT CONTACT TRACING, AND
IF A SCHOOL DOES CONTACT TRACE,
PARENTS CAN STILL SEND THEIR
CHILD TO SCHOOL IF THEY ARE
A CLOSE CONTACT OF AN INFECTED
STUDENT.
WHAT THE FUCK ARE YOU
DOING?
THE PHRASE, "EVERYTHING'S BIGGER
IN TEXAS" IS SUPPOSED TO REFER
TO MEAT, TRUCKS, AND BELT
BUCKLES, NOT "THE MARKET FOR
CHILD-SIZED VENTILATORS."
AND I KNOW SOME KIDS LITERALLY
CAN'T WEAR A MASK ALL DAY.
BUT THAT'S ALL THE MORE REASON
THAT, UNTIL TRANSMISSION IS IN
CHECK, ANYONE WHO CAN, DOES.
AND BOTH THE CDC AND THE
AMERICAN ACADEMY OF PEDIATRICS
REPRESENTING NEARLY 70,000
DOCTORS... ARE ARGUING FOR
UNIVERSAL INDOOR MASKING FOR
KIDS.
AND THE THING IS, YOU CAN'T HELP
THINKING THAT SOME OF THE FUSS
OVER MASKS IS MORE ABOUT
PARENTS THAN IT IS ABOUT THEIR
KIDS.
IN FACT, JUST WATCH AS ONE
BASICALLY ADMITS THAT.
WELL, I MEAN, HONESTLY,
IT'S JUST CRAZY.
I MEAN, LAST TIME I CHECKED,
THIS IS AMERICA, AND YOU CAN'T
MAKE ANYBODY DO ANYTHING.
I MEAN, I THOUGHT THAT'S WHAT
PEOPLE DIED FOR, OUR FREEDOM.
LAST YEAR, HE DID HAVE TO WEAR
A MASK, AND YOU KNOW, HONESTLY,
HE THINKS IT'S COOL.
I'M GONNA JUST... I'M NOT GONNA
LIE, YOU KNOW, HE THINKS HE'S A
NINJA.
AND I SAY, "SON, DON'T... DON'T
SAY THAT, WHEN THEY... WHEN THEY
ASK YOU IF YOU LIKE TO WEAR A
MASK."
BUT, YOU KNOW.
IT DOESN'T REALLY AFFECT HIM,
I GUESS, RIGHT NOW, BUT,
YOU KNOW, HE DOESN'T KNOW WHAT'S
GOING ON.
OH, COME ON!
IF YOUR KID HAPPENS TO LIKE
WEARING A MASK, LET THEM FUCKING
WEAR IT!
DO YOU REALIZE HOW RARE IT IS
FOR A CHILD TO VOLUNTARILY DO
SOMETHING THAT'S A NET POSITIVE
FOR PUBLIC HEALTH?
KIDS ARE NORMALLY JUST MOVING
SNOT DISPENSARIES THAT RUN
AROUND COUGHING ON DOOR KNOBS,
AND SNEEZING DIRECTLY INTO
PEOPLE'S MOUTHS.
LOOK, THE KEY THING TO REMEMBER
IS THAT THE ABSOLUTE BEST THING
WE CAN DO TO KEEP COVID FROM
SPREADING IN SCHOOLS ISN'T
SIMPLY PUTTING MASKS ON
CHILDREN.
IT'S FOR THE WHOLE COMMUNITY
SURROUNDING THAT SCHOOL TO BE
VACCINATED.
IT IS NO COINCIDENCE THAT THE
FIRST LARGE WAVE OF COVID CASES
IN CHILDREN IS HITTING
LOW-VACCINATION STATES.
SO YOU REALLY WANT TO PROTECT
THE HEALTH OF CHILDREN AND
THE COMMUNITY THEY LIVE IN?
HERE'S YOUR FUCKING ANSWER:
WE ARE ONLY FIGHTING ABOUT MASKS
IN SCHOOLS BECAUSE THERE ARE
A BUNCH OF FOOLISH ADULTS THAT
HAVE DECIDED NOT TO GET THE
VACCINE.
AND TO ALL OF THEM, I CAN ONLY
SAY... TO QUOTE A BUNCH OF
UPSETTINGLY LOUD IDIOTS...
"WE KNOW WHO YOU ARE" AND YOU'RE
THE FUCKING PROBLEM.
AND NOW, THIS.
AND NOW...
PETE NELSON FROM "TREE HOUSE
MASTERS" REALLY, REALLY LIKES
TREES.
BOY, THIS IS A GREAT LOOKING
TREE, THESE MAPLES.
A POPLAR.
A LOT OF PINE.
OAK TREES.
EASTERN HEMLOCKS.
LOOK AT THIS BEAUTIFUL TUNNEL OF
LOVE.
LOOK AT THE SIZE OF THIS
GORGEOUS, BIG OAK!
I WOULD RATHER BE IN A TREE THAT
IS IN ITS ADOLESCENT YEARS, IF
YOU WILL.
HAVING JUST SAID THAT, IF THERE
IS A BIG, BEAUTIFUL MATURE OAK
THAT HAS CLEARLY BEEN AROUND A
LONG TIME, YOU GET SO ATTRACTED
TO THOSE TOO THAT YOU CAN'T HELP
YOURSELF.
THERE WAS A LITTLE
COMMUNICATION THERE BETWEEN ME
AND THE BIG GUY THAT WAS LIKE,
LET'S DO THIS.
IT IS ASKING FOR IT.
IT WANTS US TO BE HERE.
I SAW THEM EARLIER BUT I DIDN'T
WANT TO JUMP HER BONES RIGHT
AWAY.
THESE ARE REGAL.
IT'S THE KING OF THE FOREST.
WE HAVE HAD THIS THING GOING
FOR ABOUT SEVEN YEARS.
I THINK IT SENSES THAT NOW IS
THE TIME.
MY TREE JUICES ARE PUMPING.
I AM FEELING SOMETHING REALLY
GOOD RIGHT IN HERE.
I AM BUZZING RIGHT NOW.
FEELS REALLY GOOD.
THIS FEELS GREAT.
THIS IS FANTASTIC.
OH!
MOVING ON.
OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT CONCERNS
THE INTERNET.
IT IS A HORRIBLE PLACE THAT
EVERYONE HATES, WHICH IS A
LITTLE WEIRD, AS IT'S GIVEN US
ALMOST EVERYTHING THAT WE WERE
PROMISED IN THIS NEARLY
PRESCIENT AD FROM 1993.
HAVE YOU EVER BORROWED A BOOK
FROM THOUSANDS OF MILES AWAY?
CROSSED THE COUNTRY WITHOUT
STOPPING FOR DIRECTIONS?
OR SENT SOMEONE A FAX
FROM THE BEACH?
YOU WILL.
AND THE COMPANY THAT'LL BRING IT
AT&T.
WOW, THAT WAS
TWO-THIRDS OF THE WAY TO
SHOCKINGLY ACCURATE.
EBOOKS?
CHECK.
GPS?
BEACH FAX?
NOT IN THIS OR ANY OTHER
LIFETIME.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, IF THERE
WAS ONE COMPANY THAT WOULD GO
ALL IN ON A DOOMED TECHNOLOGY
LIKE SAND-FAXING, IT WOULD BE
AT&T.
SPECIFICALLY, I WANT TO TALK
ABOUT ONE OF THE MORE DAMAGING
THINGS THE INTERNET HAS ENABLED,
AND THAT'S RANSOMWARE ATTACKS...
BASICALLY, INCIDENTS WHERE
HACKERS GET INTO A COMPUTER,
LOCK UP THE DATA, AND THEN FORCE
THE OWNERS TO PAY A RANSOM
IN ORDER TO UNLOCK IT.
YOU MAY HAVE HEARD A LOT ABOUT
THEM RECENTLY.
BACK IN MAY, A RANSOMWARE ATTACK
SHUT DOWN A TOP U.S. GAS
PIPELINE... THE COLONIAL
PIPELINE, A MAJOR ARTERY FOR
FUEL ALONG THE EAST COAST.
AND WHILE THE COMPANY STRESSED
THERE WAS STILL PLENTY OF GAS
AVAILABLE, JUST THE VERY IDEA
THAT THERE MIGHT BE A SHORTAGE
LED TO CHAOS.
THE LINES FOR GAS GETTING
LONGER, FROM THE CAROLINAS,
DOWN TO FLORIDA,
PANICKED DRIVERS OVERWHELMING
GAS STATIONS.
ACROSS THE SOUTHEAST,
DEMAND IS UP 40%.
PRICES AT THE PUMP INCHING UP
TOO.
I'LL SPEND THAT EXTRA
FEW BUCKS.
THAT'S THE WAY IT IS.
I JUST KINDA HEARD THERE WAS
GONNA BE A RUN ON GAS AND WE
FIGURED I BETTER GET IT NOW.
YEAH, THAT MAKES SENSE!
"THERE WON'T BE A RUN ON GAS
UNLESS EVERYONE IS AN IDIOT,
WHICH MEANS THERE'S DEFINITELY
GOING TO BE A RUN ON GAS,
SO I MIGHT AS WELL BE A FASTER
IDIOT."
HE'S NOT WRONG, BUT IT'S PEOPLE
LIKE THAT GUY THAT MAKE
EVERYTHING COMPLETELY IMPOSSIBLE
ALL OF THE TIME.
SO THANKS, "THAT GUY."
LIFE JUST WOULDN'T BE THE SAME
WITHOUT YOU, AND I REALLY WISH
LIFE WEREN'T ALWAYS THE SAME.
THE SCALE OF THE COLONIAL HACK
WAS TRULY REMARKABLE.
AND THEN IN JULY, THE I.T.
SOFTWARE COMPANY KASEYA GOT HIT
WITH AN EVEN BIGGER HACK.
AND SINCE ITS JOB WAS TO PUSH
SOFTWARE TO OTHER COMPANIES,
THAT MEANT THAT HUNDREDS OF
KASEYA'S CLIENTS, AND CLIENTS'
CLIENTS, LIKE A GROCERY STORE
CHAIN, A PUBLIC BROADCASTER,
SCHOOLS, AND A NATIONAL RAILWAY
SYSTEM WERE ALSO COMPROMISED.
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING, "IS IT
JUST ME, OR DID THERE NOT USED
TO BE A MASSIVE RANSOMWARE
ATTACK EVERY TWO MONTHS?"
YOU'RE ACTUALLY RIGHT.
OVER THE PAST FEW YEARS, IT'S
GONE FROM A TRICKLE TO A FLOOD.
THE ESTIMATED TOTAL RANSOMS PAID
QUADRUPLED TO $350 MILLION
LAST YEAR.
AND THAT IS DEFINITELY AN
UNDERCOUNT, BECAUSE COMPANIES
OFTEN DON'T PUBLICLY DISCLOSE
RANSOMWARE ATTACKS, FOR FEAR OF
NEGATIVE PRESS OR LAWSUITS.
AND IT'S NOT JUST COMPANIES
INVOLVED HERE.
EVERYONE IS VULNERABLE TO
RANSOMWARE, EVEN THIS WOMAN.
INNA SIMONE IS RETIRED.
SHE'S A MOTHER AND GRANDMOTHER
FROM RUSSIA WHO NOW LIVES
OUTSIDE OF BOSTON.
IN THE FALL OF 2014, HER HOME
COMPUTER STARTED ACTING
STRANGELY.
INNA SAW DOZENS OF THESE
MESSAGES.
THEY WERE ALL THE SAME.
THEY READ, "YOUR FILES ARE
ENCRYPTED.
TO GET THE KEY TO DECRYPT THEM,
YOU HAVE TO PAY $500."
ALL HER FILES WERE LOCKED,
TAX RETURNS, FINANCIAL PAPERS,
LETTERS, EVEN THE PRECIOUS
PHOTOS OF HER GRANDDAUGHTER.
TUESDAY AFTERNOON, THE FULL
RANSOM WAS SENT TO THE HACKERS'
ACCOUNT.
INNA INSERTED ONE SHORT
MESSAGE TO THE CRIMINALS WITH
HER PAYMENT.
I WROTE, "I WISH YOU ALL WILL
DROP DEAD."
YEAH.
YOU ALMOST FORGOT THAT WOMAN
WAS GOING TO BE RUSSIAN
FOR A MOMENT, DIDN'T YOU?
AND THEN SHE'S REALLY RUSSIAN.
SHE IS ENJOYING HERSELF.
YOU CAN TELL THIS ISN'T THE
FIRST TIME SHE'S WISHED DEATH
ON SOMEONE, AND ALSO, THAT THIS
WOULDN'T BE THE FIRST TIME HER
WISH CAME TRUE.
SO IF IT'S SO PERVASIVE,
IT'S AFFECTING PIPELINES AND
GRANDMOTHERS, WE THOUGHT
TONIGHT, WE'D TAKE A LOOK AT
RANSOMWARE, WHY IT'S ON THE
RISE, AND WHAT, IF ANYTHING,
CAN BE DONE ABOUT IT.
AND LET'S START WITH SOME
HISTORY.
THE FIRST RANSOMWARE ATTACK
ACTUALLY OCCURRED BACK IN 1989,
WHEN A MAN NAMED JOSEPH POPP
MAILED 20,000 FLOPPY DISKS TO
PUBLIC HEALTH RESEARCHERS
THAT HE CLAIMED CONTAINED AIDS
RESEARCH.
BUT WHEN THEY INSERTED THE DISK,
THEIR COMPUTERS WERE INFECTED
WITH MALWARE, THEIR FILES WERE
LOCKED UP, AND THE PROGRAM
DEMANDED THEY MAIL $189
TO A P.O. BOX IN PANAMA.
THIS IS A
CYBERCRIME SO OLD, IT USED TO
REQUIRE A BUNCH OF FLOPPY DISKS
AND TWO PHYSICAL MAILMEN.
OH, AND FUN FACT: AFTER BEING
ARRESTED, POPP CLAIMED IN COURT
THAT HE HAD PLANNED TO DONATE
THAT RANSOM MONEY TO AIDS
RESEARCH, WHICH IS WEIRD BECAUSE
HE HAD STOLEN THAT MONEY
FROM AIDS RESEARCHERS
IN THE FIRST PLACE.
HE'S LIKE ROBIN HOOD,
IF ROBIN HOOD HAD GONE AROUND
TAKING MONEY FROM THE POOR AND
PROMISING THE POOR HE'D GIVE IT
BACK LATER.
BUT OBVIOUSLY, RANSOMWARE
DOESN'T COME IN VIA FLOPPY DISK
ANY MORE.
INSTEAD, IT GETS INTO YOUR
SYSTEM THROUGH THE INTERNET,
WITH A MESSAGE LIKE THIS.
THIS IS WHAT IT LOOKS LIKE
WHEN YOU GET ATTACKED.
IT SAYS, YOUR NETWORK HAS BEEN
INFECTED, RIGHT THERE IN BIG RED
TYPE.
YOUR DOCUMENTS HAVE BEEN
ENCRYPTED.
AND NOW TO GET THEM BACK,
YOU HAVE TO PAY, IS WHAT THIS
RANSOM NOTE IS TELLING YOU.
THERE'S A COUNTDOWN CLOCK
THERE LETTING YOU KNOW YOU HAVE
JUST LIMITED TIME HERE TO TAKE
ACTION AND PAY THESE HACKERS OR
ELSE THE PRICE IS GOING TO GO UP
AND YOU MIGHT NOT GET YOUR DATA
BACK.
YEAH, THAT'S NOT A
MESSAGE YOU WANT TO SEE
ON YOUR SCREEN.
AND WHILE THEY'RE SCARY ENOUGH
IN THAT FORM, SOME ATTACKS CAN
BE CARTOONISHLY TERRIFYING.
HERE'S ONE FEATURING
THE ANNABELLE DOLL.
HERE'S ONE WITH THE PUPPET
FROM "SAW."
NOBODY WANTS TO SEE THAT!
AND HERE'S ONE WITH
THOMAS THE TANK ENGINE SCREAMING
"FUCK YOU" AND SAYING THE ONLY
WAY TO UNLOCK YOUR COMPUTER IS
TO SEND HIM AT LEAST TEN NUDES,
WHICH I'M PRETTY SURE IS A
REFERENCE TO THE UNAIRED FINAL
EPISODE OF "THOMAS AND FRIENDS"
WHERE THEY INTRODUCED THOMAS TO
THE CONCEPT OF PORNOGRAPHY, AND
HE BECAME SO CRAZED BY IT, HE
HAD TO BE FORCIBLY DISASSEMBLED.
THEY SAY IF YOU WANDER THE SODOR
SCRAPYARDS AT NIGHT, YOU CAN
HEAR THE WAILING OF A THOUSAND
SCATTERED PISTONS, STILL ALIVE
AND HOWLING FOR DICK PICS.
SO THAT'S WHAT RANSOMWARE LOOKS
LIKE.
BUT HOW MUCH HARM CAN IT DO?
WELL, DEPENDING ON THE TARGET,
A LOT.
RANSOMWARE HAS CAUSED CHAOS IN
CITY GOVERNMENTS LIKE BALTIMORE
AND NEW ORLEANS.
AND HACKERS HAVE ALSO HIT SCHOOL
DISTRICTS, POLICE DEPARTMENTS,
AND EVEN HOSPITAL SYSTEMS.
LAST MONTH, A CYBERATTACK
TARGETING THE HOSPITAL CHAIN
UNIVERSAL HEALTH SERVICES CAUSED
A MAJOR COMPUTER FAILURE, WITH
SOME OF ITS HOSPITALS FORCED TO
USE PEN AND PAPER TO FILE
PATIENT INFORMATION.
SO THIS IS A PERFECT STORM
HITTING THE HOSPITALS, AND
THERE'S ACTUALLY NEVER BEEN
A BETTER TIME, IF YOU'RE A
RANSOMWARE SYNDICATE AND YOU
WANT A FAST PAYOUT, THIS WOULD
BE THE TIME TO STRIKE.
HEY, THERESA,
CAN I TALK TO YOU FOR A SECOND?
LOOK, I'M NO STRANGER TO
INADVERTENTLY GIVING
UNSCRUPULOUS PEOPLE NEW WAYS
TO PREY ON THE VULNERABLE.
THIS SEASON ALONE, WE'VE DONE
STORIES ON PREDATORY NURSING
HOMES, PACE LOAN SCAMS, AND
BASICALLY TOLD YOU HOW TO SET UP
A FAKE RELIGIOUS HEALTH
INSURANCE COMPANY.
THIS SHOW COULD EASILY BE CALLED
"GETTING RICH FOR SOCIOPATHS"
WITH JOHN OLIVER.
BUT I WILL SAY, AT LEAST I'VE
NEVER LOOK DEAD INTO CAMERA AND
TOLD HACKERS IT'S A GREAT TIME
TO TAKE DOWN A HOSPITAL.
UNTIL, I GUESS, JUST NOW.
WHAT HAVE YOU GOTTEN ME INTO,
THERESA?
AND TO BE FAIR, HACKERS DON'T
NEED MUCH ENCOURAGEMENT.
LAST YEAR, OVER 500 HEALTHCARE
FACILITIES WERE HIT BY
RANSOMWARE ATTACKS
IN THE U.S. ALONE.
ONE OF WHICH WAS IN VERMONT,
WHERE CLINICIANS WERE FORCED TO
TURN AWAY HUNDREDS OF CANCER
PATIENTS WHO NEEDED TREATMENT
AFTER THEY LOST ACCESS TO
MEDICAL RECORDS.
AND THE THING IS, HACKERS DON'T
NECESSARILY HAVE TO WORK TOO
HARD TO DO THIS.
ABOUT 85% OF HOSPITALS DON'T
HAVE A SINGLE QUALIFIED
CYBERSECURITY PERSON ON STAFF,
WHICH DOES FEEL LIKE IT'S JUST
ASKING FOR TROUBLE.
IN FACT, LAX SECURITY IS A
PROBLEM ACROSS ALL INDUSTRIES.
THE COLONIAL PIPELINE ATTACK
OCCURRED BECAUSE AN EMPLOYEE HAD
USED THE SAME PASSWORD ACROSS
MULTIPLE SERVICES, AND THE
COMPANY DIDN'T USE MULTI-FACTOR
AUTHENTICATION.
SO WHEN THAT PASSWORD WAS
BREACHED IN AN ATTACK ELSEWHERE,
THERE WAS A DIRECT WAY IN.
AND WHEN PRESSED ON WHAT
HAPPENED, COLONIAL'S CEO WASN'T
PARTICULARLY REASSURING.
IN THE CASE OF THIS
PARTICULAR LEGACY VPN, IT DID
ONLY HAVE SINGLE-FACTOR
AUTHENTICATION, IT WAS A
COMPLICATED PASSWORD, SO I WANT
TO BE CLEAR ON THAT, IT WAS NOT
A "COLONIAL 123" -TYPE PASSWORD.
WELL, HOLD ON.
NO ONE SAID IT WAS!
I DON'T KNOW WHOSE EXPECTATIONS
YOU THINK YOU'RE MEETING WITH
THAT ANSWER.
THE ONLY PEOPLE I'D EVEN SUSPECT
OF USING "COLONIAL123" AS A
PASSWORD ARE THE STAFF AT
COLONIAL WILLIAMSBURG, AND
THAT'S ONLY BECAUSE AGGRESSIVELY
SUCKING AT CYBERSECURITY WOULD
AT LEAST BE HISTORICALLY
ACCURATE.
AND HERE'S THE THING,
EVEN ORGANIZATIONS THAT ARE
SCRUPULOUS ABOUT BACKING UP DATA
SO IT CAN BE EASILY RECOVERED
CAN STILL BE VULNERABLE.
BECAUSE HACKERS ARE NOW NOT JUST
ENCRYPTING DATA, THEY'RE ALSO
THREATENING TO RELEASE FILES OR
PERSONAL INFORMATION PUBLICLY.
THIS HAPPENED TO THE D.C. POLICE
RECENTLY WHEN HACKERS RELEASED
THE PERSONAL INFORMATION OF 22
OFFICERS.
AND A FEW YEARS AGO, HBO WAS
HIT, TOO, WITH HACKERS DEMANDING
AROUND $6 MILLION OR THEY'D LEAK
UNAIRED EPISODES OF
"GAME OF THRONES."
WHICH, TO BE HONEST, IS A PRETTY
WEAK THREAT.
IF HBO'S GOING TO BE PUBLICLY
HUMILIATED, IT WILL BE BY
RELEASING THE LAST SEASON OF
"GAME OF THRONES" ON ITS OWN
TERMS, THANK YOU VERY MUCH.
AND IF HAVING YOUR DATA LOCKED
OR LEAKED WEREN'T SCARY ENOUGH,
IT ACTUALLY GETS WORSE.
BECAUSE WE'RE INCREASINGLY
HOOKING PHYSICAL OBJECTS IN OUR
LIVES UP TO THE INTERNET...
THINGS LIKE TVs, REFRIGERATORS,
AND OVENS.
AND THEY CAN BE VULNERABLE TO
RANSOMWARE, TOO.
BACK IN 2016, HACKERS MADE
THE FIRST-EVER RANSOMWARE FOR
SMART THERMOSTATS, CRANKING
THE TEMPERATURE TO 99 DEGREES
UNLESS THE OWNER PAID UP.
AND LAST YEAR, RESEARCHERS FOUND
A VULNERABILITY IN AN
INTERNET-ENABLED CHASTITY CAGE
BASICALLY A HIGH-TECH PENIS
PRISON... THAT COULD BE
COCK-LOCKED UNTIL THE PERSON
IN JUNK JAIL PAID UP.
AND INTERESTINGLY, THE
RESEARCHERS WHO DISCOVERED THAT
FELT COMPELLED TO GO PUBLIC WITH
IT BECAUSE OF THE NEXT PRODUCT
THAT COMPANY WAS ABOUT TO
RELEASE.
HI THERE!
WE'RE INTRODUCING YOU TO
PEAR FLOWER ANAL PLUG.
COMPATIBLE TO VARIOUS TEALS AND
LEASH.
YOU NEED TO SELECT TO BE
"KEYMASTER" OR "WEARER."
WEARER CAN ADD FRIENDS IN THE
APP, AND INVITE FRIENDS TO BE
KEYMASTER.
THIS INVITED KEYMASTER HAS RIGHT
TO GIVE PERMISSION TO WEARER FOR
UNLOCKING.
WEARER CANNOT UNLOCK WITHOUT
PERMISSION FROM KEYMASTER.
YEAH, THAT PRODUCT
COULD ESSENTIALLY GIVE THE
INTERNET CONTROL OVER YOUR ANUS,
WHICH DOESN'T SEEM GREAT.
ASSHOLES ARE LIKE OPINIONS:
LETTING THE INTERNET BE IN
CHARGE OF YOURS IS A REALLY
BAD IDEA.
NOW, INCREDIBLY, I LEGALLY HAVE
TO TELL YOU AT THIS POINT:
THAT BUTT PLUG DOES COME WITH
A PHYSICAL KEY FOR EMERGENCIES.
WHICH I AM NOT SURE IS
COMPLETELY REASSURING.
KEYS DO GET LOST, DON'T THEY?
JUST PICTURE THE LAST TIME
YOU SEARCHED FOR YOUR KEYS
AROUND YOUR HOUSE AND
NOW RAISE THE STAKES
SIGNIFICANTLY.
THE POINT IS, THE COSTS OF
RANSOMWARE KEEP GETTING HIGHER
AND HIGHER, EVEN AS, CRUCIALLY,
THE BARRIER TO ENTRY HAS GOTTEN
MUCH LOWER.
BECAUSE THE EXPLOSION IN
RANSOMWARE HAS BASICALLY BEEN
THE RESULT OF THREE MAJOR
DEVELOPMENTS.
THE FIRST ONE IS THE EMERGENCE
OF SOMETHING CALLED
"RANSOMWARE AS A SERVICE."
BASICALLY, HACKERS WILL DEVELOP
A RANSOMWARE PROGRAM, AND THEN
SELL IT TO ANYONE WHO MIGHT WANT
TO LAUNCH AN ATTACK AND SPLIT
THE PROFITS.
WHAT THIS MEANS IS, BASICALLY
ANYONE CAN LAUNCH AN ATTACK,
EVEN IF THEY'RE NOT PARTICULARLY
TECH-SAVVY... IN FACT, JUST
WATCH AS A CYBERSECURITY EXPERT
WALKS THROUGH THE FEATURES
OFFERED BY ONE RANSOMWARE
VENDOR.
THEY ACTUALLY PROVIDE YOU
WITH BASICALLY A CHAT ROOM,
WHERE YOU CAN ASK QUESTIONS TO
THE PEOPLE WHO MAINTAIN THIS
ARCHITECTURE FOR YOU.
FREQUENTLY ASKED QUESTIONS
FOR CRIMINALS.
EXACTLY.
TOM PACE LOGGED ONTO THE SITE
AND USED IT TO ENCRYPT A NETWORK
OF HIS OWN.
SO ALL OF THE FILES THAT ARE
ON THIS SYSTEM HAVE NOW BEEN
SUCCESSFULLY ENCRYPTED.
SO THIS TOOK YOU JUST
SLIGHTLY OVER FIVE MINUTES,
AND YOU DIDN'T WRITE A SINGLE
LINE OF CODE?
CORRECT.
OFF THE SHELF.
READY TO GO.
THAT IS ALARMINGLY
EASY!
IDEALLY, NO ONE WOULD LAUNCH
RANSOMWARE ATTACKS.
BUT MY NEXT PREFERENCE WOULD BE
THAT LAUNCHING ONE SHOULD
REQUIRE SIGNIFICANTLY MORE WORK
THAN SIMPLY CLICKING
"ADD RANSOMWARE TO CART."
IF IT'S BEGINNING TO SEEM LIKE
RANSOMWARE IS JUST A TYPICAL
BUSINESS, BUT STAFFED BY
CRIMINALS, YOU'RE NOT ENTIRELY
WRONG.
THIS CAN BE A VERY PROFESSIONAL
ENTERPRISE, WITH CUSTOMER CARE
FOR BOTH THE CRIMINAL WHO BOUGHT
THE RANSOMWARE PRODUCT, AND THE
VICTIM ON THE RECEIVING END OF
IT.
ONE EXPERT EVEN SAID, "HONESTLY,
I WISH MY INTERNET SERVICE
PROVIDER HAD CUSTOMER SERVICE
THE WAY THESE GUYS DO."
WHICH SEEMS A LITTLE UNFAIR,
SINCE RANSOMWARE HACKERS ARE
CRIMINALS AND INTERNET SERVICE
PROVIDERS ARE FUCKING MONSTERS.
YOU CAN'T HOLD THEM TO THE SAME
STANDARDS.
AND FOR A SENSE OF THE CUSTOMER
SERVICE THEY OFFER FOR VICTIMS,
REMEMBER THAT GRANDMOTHER?
THE PEOPLE THAT HACKED HER WERE
HAPPY TO HELP GUIDE HER THROUGH
THE PROCESS OF PAYMENT.
IN THEIR RANSOM NOTE, THE
HACKERS WANTED TO BE PAID IN
BITCOIN, THE LARGELY UNTRACEABLE
DIGITAL CURRENCY, AND HAVE IT
PUT INTO THEIR ANONYMOUS
ACCOUNT.
INNA HAD NEVER HEARD OF BITCOIN,
BUT THE HACKERS, IN ONE OF THEIR
MANY TOUCHES OF WHAT YOU MIGHT
CALL CUSTOMER SERVICE, PROVIDED
ALL SORTS OF HELPFUL FACTS AND
LINKS AND HOW-TO GUIDES ABOUT
BITCOIN.
IT'S TRUE!
THEY HAD TO TEACH
INNA HOW TO USE BITCOIN.
THAT IS GENUINELY WAY MORE
IMPRESSIVE THAN CARRYING OUT A
RANSOMWARE ATTACK.
CLICK
THINK ABOUT IT, IF YOU HAD TO
TEACH YOUR GRANDMA TO USE
CRYPTOCURRENCY IN ORDER TO MAKE
$500, ARE YOU CONFIDENT YOU
WOULD WALK OUT OF THERE WITH
$500?
LET'S SAY YOU HAD INFINITE TIME
AND INFINITE GRANDMAS.
YOU HAVE TO UNDERSTAND BITCOIN,
AND THEN YOU HAVE TO TEACH A
GRANDMA, ANY GRANDMA, TO USE IT.
ARE YOU SERIOUSLY GETTING $500
OUT OF THAT SITUATION?
DEEP DOWN, I THINK YOU KNOW THE
ANSWER TO THAT.
BUT THE BITCOIN PART OF THAT
STORY ACTUALLY BRINGS US TO
THE SECOND MAJOR DRIVER OF
RANSOMWARE, AND THAT'S THE RISE
OF CRYPTOCURRENCIES.
THEY'VE MADE IT MUCH EASIER TO
MAKE MONEY FROM RANSOMWARE,
AND MUCH MORE DIFFICULT FOR LAW
ENFORCEMENT TO RECOVER PAYMENTS.
BECAUSE IF RANSOMS WERE PAID IN
WIRE TRANSFERS, COMPANIES COULD
FIND A WAY TO CLAW THAT MONEY
BACK.
BUT WITH CRYPTOCURRENCIES,
IT'S NEARLY IMPOSSIBLE TO UNDO.
AND WHILE THE FEDERAL GOVERNMENT
ACTUALLY DID MANAGE TO RECOVER
SOME OF THE BITCOIN USED
IN THE COLONIAL PIPELINE RANSOM,
THERE ARE OTHER CRYPTOCURRENCIES
DESIGNED TO BE EVEN MORE
ANONYMOUS.
TAKE MONERO, WHICH IN ITS ADS,
SEEMS TO BE AWARE OF JUST HOW
ATTRACTIVE IT IS TO CRIMINALS.
THERE'S NO SAFE PLACE TO
CONDUCT PRIVATE TRANSACTIONS.
WELL, THERE WASN'T ONE,
UNTIL NOW.
MEET MONERO.
MONERO IS A SECURE, PRIVATE,
UNTRACEABLE CURRENCY.
WITH MONERO, YOU ARE YOUR OWN
BANK.
ONLY YOU CONTROL AND ARE
RESPONSIBLE FOR YOUR FUNDS.
MONERO IS PRIVATE.
THIS MEANS BUSINESSES CAN
KEEP THEIR SUPPLIERS IN SECRET,
AS WELL AS CITIZENS ESCAPE
GOVERNMENT REPRESSIONS, AND NOSY
NEIGHBORS OR CROOKS.
OH, COME ON.
THERE'S A PRETTY CLEAR SUBTEXT
TO WHAT THEY'RE SELLING THERE.
IT'S LIKE SEEING A CHEERFUL AD
FOR "PLASTIC TUBS THE SIZE AND
SHAPE OF A HUMAN BODY."
THIS ISN'T FOR ANYTHING IN
PARTICULAR!
THERE'S ALL SORTS OF HUMAN
BODY-SIZED THINGS YOU COULD PUT
INTO ONE OF THESE STURDY TUBS!
ALSO, THEY'RE SCREAM PROOF!
"NO MATTER HOW MUCH SOUND
SOMETHING MAKES INSIDE,
YOU'LL NEVER HEAR IT!"
WE'RE NOT TELLING YOU WHAT TO DO
WITH OUR PRODUCT, THOUGH...
WE'RE SIMPLY LEADING YOU TO A
VERY SPECIFIC CONCLUSION.
ALTHOUGH, INTERESTINGLY, DESPITE
THE FACT HACKERS NOW HAVE THE
ABILITY TO MAKE THEIR FINANCIAL
TRANSACTIONS IN SECRET, IT'S NOT
ALWAYS THAT HARD TO FIGURE OUT
WHERE, EXACTLY, THE MONEY IS
GOING.
THIS SHOWS AN ALLEGED MEMBER
OF A RUSSIAN CYBER GANG KNOWN AS
EVIL CORP, SHOWING OFF AN
EXPENSIVE LAMBORGHINI IN A
PARKING GARAGE.
THIS IS VIDEO OF EVIL CORP
MEMBERS ALLEGEDLY DOING DONUTS
AND OBSTRUCTING TRAFFIC IN
DOWNTOWN MOSCOW.
VIDEOS AND PHOTOGRAPHS
RELEASED BY INVESTIGATORS SHOW
THE ALLEGED HACKERS LIVING
LARGE, POSING WITH ARMS FULL OF
CASH, AND SHOWING OFF A PET LION
CUB.
THIS IS 32-YEAR-OLD
MAKSIM YAKUBETS WITH HIS
LAMBORGHINI HURACAN AND HIS
PERSONALIZED NUMBER PLATES,
WHICH IN RUSSIAN READS "THIEF."
WOW.
THESE GUYS ARE DOUCHES.
IT'S BAD ENOUGH SITTING
IN A TRAFFIC JAM WATCHING SOME
ASSHOLE DO DONUTS IN THE MIDDLE
OF THE STREET WITHOUT HAVING TO
WONDER IF THERE'S A LION CUB
THROWING UP IN THE CAR.
C'MON, GUYS.
LEAVE LIONS OUT OF THIS.
IF YOU ABSOLUTELY HAVE TO HAVE
A WEIRD ANIMAL, GET A BIG SNAKE.
I COULD GIVE TWO SHITS ABOUT
A BIG SNAKE'S QUALITY OF LIFE.
AND YOU CAN TELL ANY BIG SNAKE
I SAID THAT.
BUT THERE'S ACTUALLY A REASON
THOSE HACKERS FEEL SO
COMFORTABLE DRIVING AROUND WITH
LICENSE PLATES THAT ARE
BASICALLY AN ADMISSION OF GUILT,
AND THAT'S BRINGS US TO
THE FINAL FACTOR INCREASING
RANSOMWARE ATTACKS, AND THAT'S
COUNTRIES PROVIDING SAFE HAVENS.
BECAUSE MULTIPLE GOVERNMENTS...
AND RUSSIA, IN PARTICULAR...
WILL LOOK THE OTHER WAY FOR
HACKERS
SO LONG AS THEY DO
THEIR WORK OUTSIDE OF THEIR
BORDERS.
CYBERSECURITY EXPERTS SAY THE
"DON'T WORK IN .RU" STRICTURE
HAS BECOME AN UNWRITTEN RULE
IN THE RUSSIAN-SPEAKING HACKING
COMMUNITY, TO AVOID
ENTANGLEMENTS WITH RUSSIAN
LAW ENFORCEMENT.
BASICALLY, RUSSIAN HACKERS KNOW,
AS LONG AS THEY DON'T MAKE
TROUBLE AT HOME, THEY WON'T BE
PUNISHED FOR WHAT THEY DO
ABROAD.
AND WHEN YOU PUT ALL OF THIS
TOGETHER, WITH CYBERCRIMINALS
ABLE TO BUY RANSOMWARE OFF THE
SHELF, GET PAID IN UNTRACEABLE
CURRENCY, AND WORK FREE FROM
STATE INTERFERENCE, IS IT ANY
WONDER WE HAVE SUCH A MASSIVE
PROBLEM ON OUR HANDS?
WHICH BRINGS US TO THE KEY
QUESTION... WHAT CAN WE DO ABOUT
THIS?
WELL, HERE'S A TERRIBLE IDEA.
WE OUGHT TO PASS A LAW
IMMEDIATELY THAT MAKES IT...
THIS KIND OF HACKING SUBJECT TO
A DEATH PENALTY, AND THE LAW
SHOULD INCLUDE A PROVISION THAT
THE PRESIDENT, THROUGH A
JUDICIAL PROCESS, SHOULD BE ABLE
TO ORDER THE KILLING OF ANYBODY
OVERSEAS WHO IS DOING THIS.
WOW.
THAT'S BOTH INCREDIBLY HARSH AND
ALSO ENDEARINGLY NAIVE.
BECAUSE I HATE TO BREAK IT TO
NEWT, BUT AMERICA DOESN'T
EXACTLY CONCERN ITSELF WITH
"A JUDICIAL PROCESS" TO KILL
PEOPLE OVERSEAS.
WE VERY MUCH TAKE
THE SANTA CLAUS APPROACH:
SEE THEM WHEN THEY'RE SLEEPING,
KNOW WHEN THEY'RE AWAKE, MAKE A
LIST OF WHO'S BEEN BAD OR GOOD,
AND THEN KILL SOME BAD ONES,
AND WHICHEVER GOOD ONES HAPPEN
TO BE AROUND THEM.
YOU KNOW, FOR GOODNESS' SAKE.
SO THAT IS ONE EXTREME WAY TO
HANDLE THIS.
THE CURRENT ADMINISTRATION,
HOWEVER, HAS SO FAR TAKEN A
DIFFERENT TACK.
IN THE WAKE OF THE COLONIAL
HACK, THIS WAS THE MESSAGE THEY
WERE PUBLICLY SENDING.
WE RECOGNIZE THAT VICTIMS OF
CYBERATTACKS OFTEN FACE A VERY
DIFFICULT SITUATION, AND THEY
HAVE TO JUST BALANCE, OFTEN,
THE COST-BENEFIT WHEN THEY HAVE
NO CHOICE WITH REGARD TO PAYING
A RANSOM.
COLONIAL IS A PRIVATE COMPANY,
AND WE'LL DEFER INFORMATION
REGARDING THEIR DECISION ON
PAYING A RANSOM TO THEM.
OKAY, SO YOU'D LIKE
THEM TO PAY THE RANSOM.
YOU'D LIKE THE GAS BACK, AND
THE EASIEST WAY TO GET
THE GAS BACK IS TO PAY
THE RANSOM, SO YOU'D LIKE THEM
TO PAY THE RANSOM.
IT'S A PRETTY STRONG HINT, AND
YOU GET THE FEELING THAT IF THE
HINT DOESN'T WORK, JOE BIDEN IS
GOING TO TAKE THEIR COMPUTER AND
PAY FOR THEM.
IF THAT RUSSIAN GRANDMA CAN
FIGURE OUT HOW TO USE BITCOIN,
THERE'S A 30% CHANCE JOE CAN
TOO.
BUT THERE HAS TO BE A MIDDLE
GROUND BETWEEN "JUST KILL THEM"
AND "JUST PAY THEM."
BECAUSE MOST PUNISHMENTS... AND
THIS IS TRUE... FALL SOMEWHERE
BETWEEN "DEATH SENTENCE" AND
"A CASH REWARD."
AND THE PROBLEM IS, THE MORE WE
PAY, THE MORE THESE KINDS OF
ATTACKS WILL BE ENCOURAGED,
AND THE MORE WELL-FUNDED THEY
END UP BEING.
SO MUCH MORE NEEDS TO BE DONE
HERE... AND I WILL SAY, ON THE
GOVERNMENT LEVEL, THERE ARE SOME
ENCOURAGING SIGNS.
THE JUSTICE DEPARTMENT RECENTLY
CALLED A TAX FORCED TO CURTAIL
THE PROLIFERATION OF RANSOMWARE
ATTACKS, DOES FEEL A LITTLE LATE
TO BE FORMING A TASK FORCE BUT
IT IS DEFINITELY BETTER THAN
NEVER.
ALSO THE INFRASTRUCTURE BILL
A BILLION DOLLARS FOR IMPROVING
THE CYBERSECURITY OF LOCAL
GOVERNMENTS.
BUT THE THING IS,
IT'S NOT JUST UP TO THE
GOVERNMENT TO TAKE CYBERSECURITY
A LOT MORE SERIOUSLY.
COMPANIES AND PRIVATE
INDIVIDUALS HAVE TO STEP UP,
TOO.
AND THERE ARE SOME BASIC THINGS
THAT WE SHOULD ALL ABSOLUTELY
BE DOING.
FIRST, SET UP MULTI-FACTOR
AUTHENTICATION... DO IT RIGHT
NOW!
SECOND, KEEP YOUR COMPUTERS UP
TO DATE, AND ALSO, DON'T CLICK
ON SUSPICIOUS EMAILS.
AND I KNOW THAT THOSE MEASURES
SOUND SMALL WHEN WE'RE FACING
SOMETHING SO TERRIFYING.
BUT IN A WORLD WHERE MOST
PEOPLE'S DOORS ARE UNLOCKED
AND WIDE OPEN, JUST LOCKING YOUR
DOOR MIGHT BE A DETERRENT.
THE FACT IS, IT'S IN EVERYONE'S
INTEREST TO GET THIS UNDER
CONTROL, BECAUSE RIGHT NOW,
IT REALLY, REALLY ISN'T.
TO THE POINT THAT IT MAY WELL BE
TIME FOR A NEW AD CAMPAIGN TO
DRILL HOME JUST HOW VULNERABLE
ALL OF US ARE.
HAVE YOU EVER LOST ACCESS TO
YOUR MEDICAL RECORDS?
WHAT THE FUCK?
HOW TO WORK OUT TO MAKE A BET
GOING TRANSFER JUST SO YOU CAN
SEE PHOTOS OF YOUR GRANDCHILDREN
AGAIN?
OR SEND A FAX FROM THE BEACH?
WHAT ARE YOU, SOME KIND OF BEACH
BUSINESS?
HAVE YOU EVER OPEN YOUR LAPTOP
TO SEE A CLOWN'S FACE DEMANDING
$300,000?
YOU KNOW WHAT, ALL RIGHT.
WHAT THE FUCK IS GOING ON?
WHAT IS HAPPENING?
OR JAVIER BUTT PLUG AND
EXCITEDLY TAKEN OVER BY
UKRAINIAN HACKERS.
YOU WILL.
OH, NO, NOT THAT.
UNLESS WE LOST OUR TAKING THE
ISSUE OF RANSOMWARE A LOT MORE
SERIOUSLY.
SO PLEASE, HE WAS TWO FACTOR
AUTHENTICATION TO SECURE ALL
YOUR MEDICAL RECORDS,
EMAILS, AND BUTT PLUGS.
HI, TECH SUPPORT?
ESPECIALLY THE BUTT PLUGS.
IT IS HAPPENING AGAIN.
IF YOU THINK YOU CAN IGNORE
THIS PROBLEM AND WILL NEVER BE
THE VICTIM OF RANSOMWARE, TRUST
US...
YOU WILL.
OH, YEAH, YOU DEFINITELY
WILL.
THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANKS SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
WE WILL SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
GOOD NIGHT.
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org