HI THERE!
WELCOME TO THE SHOW.
STILL TAKING PLACE
IN THIS BLANK VOID.
IT'S ACTUALLY THE PLACE ALL YOUR
AIRPODS GO WHEN YOU LOSE THEM.
I BET YOU THOUGHT THIS WAS
RATTLING AROUND YOUR CAR'S
FLOOR MATS.
NOPE... IT'S MINE NOW!
INTO THE PILE YOU GO!
IT'S BEEN A BUSY WEEK,
FROM REPUBLICANS TRYING
TO OUST LIZ CHENEY FROM
HOUSE LEADERSHIP,
TO CALIFORNIA GEARING UP
FOR THE RECALL ELECTION OF
GOVERNOR GAVIN NEWSOM.
MULTIPLE CANDIDATES HAVE ALREADY
FILED TO RUN AGAINST HIM, ONE
OF WHOM RELEASED THIS AD:
THIS BEAUTY HAS PROVEN HE
CAN'T DO IT.
PRETTY BOY.
THE BEAST CAN.
THIS TIME, MAKE THE RIGHT CHOICE
FOR CALIFORNIA AND YOUR FAMILY.
RECALL THE BEAUTY, AND ELECT
THE NICEST, SMARTEST BEAST
YOU'VE EVER MET.
JOHN COX.
ALL OF THAT'S IDIOTIC,
BUT I'M GOING TO FOCUS ON THE
FACT THAT HE SEEMS TO THINK
THE PROBLEM IN "BEAUTY AND
THE BEAST" WAS ABOUT CHOOSING
BETWEEN THE TWO, WHEN EVERYONE
KNOWS THE PROBLEM WAS, HOW ARE
THESE TWO FUCKING?
WE KNOW IT'S HAPPENING,
WE KNOW IT'S GREAT,
AND WE KNOW IT'S WEIRD,
BUT HOW EXACTLY DOES IT WORK?
DO THEY TAKE SPECIAL PRECAUTIONS
AROUND THE FLAMES TO AVOID
BURNING, OR IS THE BURNING PART
OF IT?
SAME QUESTION, BUT ABOUT THE
FEATHER DUSTER AND SNEEZING,
IS THE SNEEZING PART OF IT?
I HOPE THE SNEEZING IS PART OF
IT!
THAT GUY COMMITTED TO THE BEAR
METAPHOR, EVEN BRINGING ONE
TO A CAMPAIGN EVENT, ONLY
TO COMPLAIN THE NEXT DAY THAT
"THE COVERAGE YESTERDAY WAS ALL
ABOUT THE BEAR."
AND YEAH, NO SHIT.
YOU BROUGHT A LITERAL
DANCING BEAR.
THE UNIVERSAL METAPHOR FOR
"DISTRACTING GIMMICK PEOPLE PAY
ATTENTION TO INSTEAD OF WHATEVER
THE FUCK YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT."
MEANWHILE, THE WEEK SAW
THE LATEST ATTEMPTS TO UNDERMINE
THE DEMOCRATIC PROCESS,
WITH TEXAS AND FLORIDA
CONTINUING THE TREND OF
REPUBLICANS ENACTING
NEW VOTING RESTRICTIONS.
FLORIDA'S GOVERNOR RON DESANTIS
...A MAN WITH A VIBE THAT
SCREAMS "WILL FLIRT WITH YOUR
TEENAGE FRIENDS"... SIGNED
A BILL, LIVE ON
"FOX AND FRIENDS," FOR SOME
REASON, THAT TARGETS BALLOT DROP
BOXES AND VOTING BY MAIL.
MEANWHILE, IN TEXAS, THEIR NEW
VOTER-SUPPRESSION BILL INITIALLY
FEATURED A LINE ABOUT THE
IMPORTANCE OF PROTECTING
"THE PURITY OF THE BALLOT BOX,"
LEADING TO THIS AWKWARD EXCHANGE
WITH ONE OF ITS SPONSORS.
DID YOU LOOK AT THE HISTORY
BEFORE USING THAT WORD?
NO, NO, THE ONLY THING, IF WE
WERE TO HAVE A DISCUSSION...
MAYBE OVER SOME COFFEE OR
DRINKS, ONE DAY, I COULD GO INTO
THE DETAILS OF ARTICLE ONE
REALLY WELL.
I'VE READ THE DEBATES AND THE
JOURNALS OF THE CONVENTION OF
1875 ON THAT, FOR THAT THING,
BUT I'M NOT FAMILIAR.
YOU MAY HAVE MISSED IT THEN.
THAT PROVISION WAS DRAFTED
SPECIFICALLY TO DISENFRANCHISE
BLACK PEOPLE... BLACK VOTERS,
IN FACT... FOLLOWING
THE CIVIL WAR.
DID YOU KNOW THAT?
NO, THAT'S... THAT'S... I'M
SORRY TO HEAR THAT.
YEAH, I BET YOU ARE!
ALTHOUGH, I'M GUESSING YOU'RE
LESS "SORRY TO HEAR THE
HISTORICAL CONNOTATIONS OF THAT
PHRASE " AND MORE, " SORRY TO HEAR
THAT PUBLICLY, ESPECIALLY IN
FRONT OF ALL THESE FUCKING
CAMERAS."
BUT PERHAPS THE STUPIDEST
ELECTION-RELATED STORY IS
CURRENTLY TAKING PLACE IN
ARIZONA, WHERE REPUBLICANS HAVE
BEEN TRYING TO RELITIGATE THE
PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION BY
RECOUNTING ALL THE BALLOTS
IN THE STATE'S MOST POPULOUS
COUNTY.
THIS IS YET ANOTHER TALLY OF
THE NEARLY 2.1 MILLION BALLOTS
IN MARICOPA COUNTY.
BUT THIS SO-CALLED AUDIT IS
UNLIKE ANY OTHER.
THESE ARE BALLOT COUNTERS
HEADING INTO A SHIFT.
HAVE YOU EVER DONE ELECTION
COUNTING BEFORE?
NO.
BUT IT'S... THERE'S NOTHING TO
IT.
IT'S PRETTY OBVIOUS.
YEAH, THAT'S NOT
REASSURING!
NORMALLY WHEN A GUY IN THOSE
SUNGLASSES SAYS, "THERE'S
NOTHING TO IT, IT'S PRETTY
OBVIOUS," HE'S SECONDS FROM
REVERSING HIS BRAND NEW ATV
THROUGH THE FRONT WINDOW OF A
FUDDRUCKERS.
THE AUDIT COMPANY IN CHARGE,
CYBER NINJAS, IS OWNED BY AN
ADVOCATE OF THE STOP THE STEAL
MOVEMENT.
AND OBVIOUS BIAS ASIDE,
THE PROCESS ALONE SEEMS SEEMS
PRETTY SLIPSHOD.
ARIZONA'S SECRETARY OF STATE HAS
EXPRESSED ALARM OVER ACCOUNTS OF
BALLOTS BEING LEFT UNATTENDED,
AND UNTRAINED WORKERS USING
DIFFERENT RULES TO COUNT
BALLOTS.
ALL OF WHICH THE AUDIT OFFICIAL
TWITTER ACCOUNT
DISPUTED AS "BASELESS
CLAIM-EES."
AND IT'S GENUINELY INSANE TO
SWOOP INTO A COUNTY THAT,
REMEMBER, HAS ALREADY DONE
MULTIPLE AUDITS OF ITS ELECTION
COUNT, FINDING NO EVIDENCE OF
FRAUD... WITH THE ATTITUDE OF,
"OKAY, BUT WHAT IF WE DO IT
SHITTY THIS TIME?"
AND IT GETS EVEN WORSE WHEN YOU
CONSIDER THE SECRETARY OF STATE
IS NOW RECEIVING DEATH THREATS.
AND ALL OF THIS IS SO THEY CAN
CHASE DOWN CRAZY CONSPIRACY
THEORIES LIKE THIS ONE.
THERE'S ACCUSATIONS THAT
40,000 BALLOTS WERE FLOWN IN.
TO ARIZONA?
TO ARIZONA.
AND IT WAS STUFFED INTO THE BOX,
OKAY?
AND IT CAME FROM THE SOUTHEAST
PART OF THE WORLD, ASIA, OKAY?
AND WHAT THEY'RE DOING IS TO
FIND OUT IF THERE'S BAMBOO IN
THE PAPER.
AND WHY DO YOU CHECK FOR
BAMBOO?
BECAUSE THEY USE BAMBOO IN
THEIR PAPER PROCESSING.
WHO'S THEY?
PEOPLE IN SOUTHEAST ASIA.
WOW.
"SOUTHEAST ASIANS ATTEMPTED TO
SWAY THE 2020 ELECTION IN
ARIZONA VIA BAMBOO BALLOTS"
SOUNDS LIKE SOMETHING YOUR
DRUNKEST UNCLE WOULD SAY BEFORE
PASSING OUT AT HIS NIECE'S
SIXTH BIRTHDAY PARTY.
AND LOOK, THAT'S OBVIOUSLY
NONSENSE.
AND IN FAIRNESS TO THAT MAN,
HE DOESN'T BELIEVE ANY OF IT.
HE RUNS A NONPROFIT FOCUSED
ON ELECTION FAIRNESS, AND IS
VOLUNTEERING, HOPING THIS
PROCESS MANAGES TO DISPROVE MANY
OF THESE CRAZY THEORIES.
WHICH IS A NICE IDEA.
THE PROBLEM IS, THOUGH, THE
PEOPLE BEHIND THIS RECOUNT
AREN'T GOING
TO BE CONVINCED, UNLESS THE
RESULTS SWING THEIR WAY.
AND WE KNOW THIS BECAUSE...
AGAIN... THERE HAVE ALREADY BEEN
MULTIPLE AUDITS CONDUCTED IN
MARICOPA COUNTY AND THEY WEREN'T
CONVINCED BY THE RESULTS.
AND THE THING IS, ARIZONA IS
PLAYING A DANGEROUS GAME HERE.
AND THINGS ARE PROBABLY ONLY GET
MORE VOLATILE.
ARIZONA'S
RECOUNT IS LIKE THAT GUY
BRINGING A BEAR TO HIS EVENT,
IN THAT IT'S CHAOTIC,
IT'S PATHETICALLY DESPERATE, AND
WE'LL ALL BE LUCKY IF NOBODY
GETS SERIOUSLY HURT.
AND NOW THIS.
AND NOW...
HAPPY MOTHER'S DAY FROM THE
DISAPPOINTING MEN OF LOCAL NEWS.
I GOT A LOT OF MOMS,
RELATED MOMS IN MY FAMILY.
MY WIFE IS A MOM, MY MOM MOM.
YOUR MOM MOM.
MY STEPMOM AND MY
MOTHER-IN-LAW.
SO.
WOW.
YEAH, I GOT FOUR PEOPLE THAT
I DISAPPOINT.
SHE HINTED YOU SHOULD KNOW
WHAT TO GET HER FOR THIS
MOTHER'S DAY.
DID YOU FIGURE THIS OUT?
NO, I DIDN'T.
ACTUALLY, I DID SUGGEST
SOMETHING THAT I THOUGHT SHE
WANTED, AND THEN SHE TOLD ME,
NO, THAT WOULD BE A TERRIBLE
IDEA.
MOTHER'S DAY IS SUNDAY.
DO NOT FORGET.
HIGH TEMPERATURES ARE
54 DEGREES.
IF YOU HAVE ANY GOOD IDEAS FOR
MY WIFE, LET ME KNOW.
LAST YEAR, I GOT MY WIFE,
LIKE, A $40 BOUQUET FOR
MOTHER'S DAY.
IT WAS BEAUTIFUL.
THIS YEAR, I AM BUYING FOR FOUR
MOMS.
SO $10 BOUQUETS ALL AROUND.
DON'T MAKE THE SAME MISTAKE I
MADE.
DON'T GIVE HER A WONDERBRA FOR
MOTHER'S DAY.
NATHAN, YOU GOT YOUR MOTHER
YOUR MOTHER'S DAY GIFT READY FOR
MOM AND YOUR WIFE?
YEAH.
MOVING ON.
OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT CONCERNS
HAIR.
SPECIFICALLY, BLACK HAIR.
THE SUBJECT THAT GAVE US
THE SINGLE GREATEST
"REAL HOUSEWIVES" ENTRANCE
OF ALL TIME:
WHEN KENYA MOORE CRASHED
MARLO HAMPTON'S WIG LAUNCH WITH
A MARCHING BAND TO PROMOTE HER
OWN LINE OF HAIR PRODUCTS, AND
PORSHA WILLIAMS REACTED LIKE
THIS.
EVEN IF I DID AGREE WITH
KENYA AND THE FACT THAT PEOPLE'S
EDGES MATTER, THEY DON'T MATTER
TODAY, BITCH.
YOU ARE WRONG.
THIS IS ABSOLUTELY INSANE, OKAY?
SO TODAY, I DON'T AGREE.
BUT TOMORROW, YES, MY EDGES
MATTER, AND I'LL BE USING THE
PRODUCT.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
AS PER USUAL, PORSHA IS RIGHT
ABOUT A NUMBER OF THINGS:
KENYA IS WRONG, EDGES DO MATTER
AND I, LIKE PORSHA, WILL BE
USING THE PRODUCT TOMORROW.
MONDAY IS MY WASH DAY.
AND LOOK, I REALIZE I'M NOT
THE IDEAL PERSON TO TALK ABOUT
BLACK HAIR.
I LOOK LIKE I STILL GO TO AN
OLD TIMEY BARBER NAMED VALENTINO
AND ASK FOR "THE TIDY
LIZA MINNELLI."
AND I ALSO KNOW THAT THE DANGER
IS, WHEN A WHITE GUY ON TV
STARTS CONFIDENTLY TALKING ABOUT
BLACK HAIR, EVEN WITH THE BEST
OF INTENTIONS, IT CAN END
SOMETHING LIKE THIS:
I DIDN'T WANT THE LITTLE
TEA LIGHT TO OVERHEAT AND THEN
ALL OF A SUDDEN, WE'VE GOT
BREAKING NEWS HERE AT THE
CHANNEL.
I TOLD YOU IF THE SPRINKLER
SYSTEMS COME ON, I'M DONE FOR
THE DAY.
YEAH.
YOU KNOW, THAT IS NOT...
SITTING UP HERE LOOKING LIKE
A MOP.
THAT IS NOT.
YEAH.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
SPRINKLER SYSTEM AND A BEAUTIFUL
WEAVE BECAUSE, THEY DO NOT GO.
AHH!
WHAT?
YOU'RE BEAUTIFUL.
YOU SAID IT WAS A WEAVE,
RIGHT?
IT'S NOT!
OH, MY GOD!
WOW.
THAT IS THE EXACT RIGHT REACTION
TO ANNOUNCING YOUR BLACK
COWORKER'S HAIR IS A WEAVE
LIVE ON-AIR.
GETTING UP FROM YOUR DESK AND
JUST RUNNING AWAY.
RUNNING FOREVER.
RUNNING UNTIL YOUR LIFE FADES
BEHIND YOU AND YOUR FEET TOUCH
THE OCEAN.
NOW YOU SHOULD KNOW, THOSE TWO
COWORKERS SEEM TO HAVE GOTTEN
OVER THAT INCIDENT, PUTTING OUT
A VIDEO TITLED "BLAINE AND LAILA
A REBUTTAL,"
WHERE BLAINE SAYS HE'S LEARNED
THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
QUICK WEAVES, LACEFRONTS, AND
SEW-INS BECAUSE OF THEIR
FRIENDSHIP.
BUT THE FACT IS, ON THE WHOLE,
WHITE PEOPLE DON'T REALLY
UNDERSTAND A LOT ABOUT
BLACK HAIR.
AND BY THE WAY, IF YOUR FIRST
REACTION TO THAT WAS,
"HEY, NOT ALL WHITE PEOPLE,"
MAYBE LOOK INSIDE YOURSELF AND
FIGURE OUT WHY THAT IS YOUR
RESPONSE TO THINGS.
BUT IMPORTANTLY, THAT LACK OF
UNDERSTANDING... AND LACK OF
INTEREST IN UNDERSTANDING... CAN
HAVE REAL CONSEQUENCES, FROM THE
PERSONAL TO THE PROFESSIONAL,
AS YOU PROBABLY KNOW, EITHER
FROM EXPERIENCE, OR FROM SEEING
STORIES LIKE THIS:
CHASTITY JONES WAS TANGLED
IN A NEARLY 10-YEAR LEGAL BATTLE
AFTER SHE SAYS AN EMPLOYER TOOK
BACK A JOB OFFER AT AN ALABAMA
CALL CENTER BECAUSE SHE REFUSED
TO CUT HER HAIR.
SHE SAID, "ARE THOSE
DREADLOCKS IN YOUR HAIR?"
AND I JUST LOOKED AT HER AND
I WAS LIKE, "THESE?"
AND SHE SAID, "YES."
I SAID, "YES, THEY ARE."
SHE SAID, "WELL, WE CAN'T ACCEPT
THAT HERE."
CAN YOU IMAGINE TURNING
SOMEONE AWAY WHO WANTS TO WORK
AT A CALL CENTER, THE UNIVERSE'S
MOST THANKLESS JOB?
A PLACE WHERE YOU ANSWER THE
PHONE AND IMMEDIATELY, THERE'S
AN ANGRY WOMAN SCREAMING AT YOU
BECAUSE SOME OF THE BROCCOLI IN
HER HELLO FRESH KIT "DIDN'T
SMELL RIGHT" AND NOW SHE WANTS
TO SPEAK TO MR. FRESH.
IF YOU HAVE SOMEONE WHO WANTS TO
DO THAT JOB, LET THEM!
WHAT'S ON THEIR HEAD HAS NOTHING
TO DO WITH IT!
THEY COULD SHOW UP TO WORK
IN A WIG MADE OF LIVING FERRETS,
AND THEY DESERVE NOT ONLY THAT
POSITION, BUT DOUBLE WHATEVER
YOU'RE PAYING THEM.
THE POINT IS, BLACK HAIR IS
AND HAIRSTYLES FREQUENTLY YET
ANOTHER TARGET OF
DISCRIMINATION.
SO TONIGHT, LET'S TALK ABOUT IT.
AND LET'S START BY UNDERSTANDING
WHY BLACK HAIR IS SO IMPORTANT.
FOR CENTURIES, BLACK PEOPLE IN
AFRICA INNOVATED WAYS TO PROTECT
AND PROLONG THE HEALTH OF THEIR
HAIR, AND THAT PRACTICE HAS
CONTINUED AND EVOLVED INTO
BEAUTIFUL AND DISTINCT
HAIRSTYLES, WITH A DEEP
CONNECTION TO CULTURE AND
HERITAGE.
AND FOR AS LONG AS THAT HAS
HAPPENED, WHITE PEOPLE HAVE BEEN
UNABLE TO HANDLE IT.
ONE OF THE FIRST THINGS
SLAVE TRADERS WOULD DO WAS
SHAVE THE HEADS OF ENSLAVED
PEOPLE, WHICH ERASED THEIR
CULTURAL IDENTITY.
AND BLACK HAIR HAS HISTORICALLY
BEEN DESCRIBED IN DEHUMANIZING
FASHION, WITH RACIAL TYPOLOGIST
CHARLES HAMILTON SMITH
DESCRIBING HIS HIERARCHY OF
THREE MAIN TYPES OF PEOPLE:
THE BEADED CAUCASIAN TYPE, THE
BEARDLESS MONGOLIC TYPE, AND THE
"WOOLLY-HAIRED TROPICAL TYPE."
AND THE ONLY TIME "WOOLLY-HAIRED
TROPICAL" IS AN ACCEPTABLE TERM
TO USE IS IF YOU'RE TALKING
ABOUT MADAGASCAR'S
"WOOLLY LEMUR," A TROPICAL
LITTLE SWEETIE WHO ALWAYS LOOKS
LIKE HE JUST ACCIDENTALLY
REPLIED ALL.
OTHER THAN THAT,
IT'S OFF LIMITS.
BY THE LATE NINETEENTH CENTURY,
BEAUTY COMPANIES WERE
ADVERTISING PRODUCTS LIKE
SKIN LIGHTENERS AND
HAIR STRAIGHTENERS, REINFORCING
THE IDEA THAT BLACK HAIR WAS
DIRTY AND UNKEMPT, AND THE
CLOSER YOUR APPEARANCE WAS TO
WHITENESS, THE BETTER.
LIKE IN THIS AD FROM 1900 FOR A
MAGNETIC COMB THAT PROMISED TO
DESTROY THE "HAIR GERMS" ON YOUR
HEAD AND TAKE YOU FROM A
CURLY-HAIRED BLACK PERSON TO
A STRAIGHT-HAIRED WHITE ONE.
AND THE DESIRE TO MAKE BLACK
HAIR SMOOTHER AND STRAIGHTER
WAS SO STRONG, JUST LISTEN TO
THE SHEER DELIGHT THIS BRITISH
NEWSREEL TAKES IN SHOWING THE
PROCESS.
COMBS COME INTO PLAY.
KEPT CONSTANTLY HEATED, THEY ARE
PASSED THROUGH EACH SECTION OF
THE HAIR UNTIL ALL TRACE OF
KINKINESS DISAPPEARS.
IT'S NOT ALL PLAIN SAILING
NATURALLY, AND IT'S NOT QUITE
A PERMANENT PERMANENT, IF YOU
FOLLOW ME.
IF THE HAIR GETS REALLY WET OR
STEAMED UP, IT UNSTRAIGHTENS
ITSELF AND BACK COME THE KINKS.
OH, NOO.
HEARING THAT BEAUTY STANDARD
REINFORCED IN THAT PARTICULAR
VOICE IS DEFINITELY A SIGN THAT
SOMETHING HAS GONE TERRIBLY
WRONG.
AND I KNOW FOR SOME VIEWERS,
PASSING A HOT METAL COMB THROUGH
THE HAIR TO STRAIGHTEN IT MIGHT
LOOK LIKE A CURIO FROM THE
DISTANT PAST.
BUT I GUARANTEE SOME OF YOU WERE
JUST TRANSPORTED BACK TO BEING
8-YEARS-OLD SITTING ON A HIGH
STOOL IN THE KITCHEN AT 6:00 AM
ON SCHOOL PICTURE DAY, HOLDING
YOUR EARS DOWN WHILE YOUR MOM OR
GRANDMA GETS THE HOT COMB
UNCOMFORTABLY CLOSE TO YOUR
SCALP.
FOR SOME, THE SMELL OF BURNING
HAIR IS A SIGN THAT SOMETHING'S
WRONG.
BUT FOR OTHERS, IT BRINGS BACK
MEMORIES.
BY THE 1960s AND '70s, THOUGH,
THE EMBRACE OF BLACK HAIR'S
NATURAL TEXTURE AND CULTURALLY
SIGNIFICANT STYLES HAD BECOME
A RADICAL ACT OF SELF ACCEPTANCE
AND POLITICAL POWER.
WHO TAUGHT YOU TO HATE
THE TEXTURE OF YOUR HAIR?
WHO TAUGHT YOU TO HATE THE COLOR
OF YOUR SKIN?
TO SUCH EXTENT THAT YOU BLEACH,
TO GET LIKE THE WHITE MAN?
UH, WHITE PEOPLE.
THE ANSWER IS WHITE PEOPLE.
THAT QUESTION ANSWERS ITSELF.
JUST LIKE THE ANSWER TO THE
WHO LETS THEIR DOGS
KISS THEM IN THE MOUTH?
WHO WANTS TO PICK APPLES
FOR FUN?
AND WHO'S COMING TO DINNER ON
INA GARTEN'S SHOW?
THE ANSWER IS, WHITE PEOPLE.
BUT DESPITE THE NATURAL HAIR
MOVEMENT, WHITE PEOPLE'S
DISCOMFORT AND IGNORANCE AROUND
BLACK HAIR HAS VERY MUCH
REMAINED.
ONE STUDY FOUND BLACK WOMEN WERE
80% MORE LIKELY TO AGREE WITH
THE STATEMENT, "I HAVE TO CHANGE
MY HAIR FROM ITS NATURAL STATE
TO FIT IN AT THE OFFICE," AND
ANOTHER FOUND THAT BLACK WOMEN
WITH NATURAL HAIRSTYLES WERE
PERCEIVED TO BE LESS
PROFESSIONAL, LESS COMPETENT,
AND LESS LIKELY TO BE
RECOMMENDED FOR A JOB INTERVIEW.
THE POINT IS, THE WAY YOUR HAIR
IS PERCEIVED... AND THEREFORE,
THE WAY YOU ARE PERCEIVED... CAN
MANIFEST IN ALL SORTS OF WAYS.
I KNOW THE ANXIETY THAT
PEOPLE HAVE AFTER GETTING THEIR
HAIR DONE THEN, LIKE, "OKAY,
WHAT'S GOING TO HAPPEN WHEN I GO
TO WORK?
ARE THEY GONNA SAY ANYTHING?"
YOU KNOW, IT'S A BIG THING
IN THE WORKPLACE.
A LOT OF PEOPLE DON'T WANT TO
DRAW ATTENTION TO THEIR SELF
SO THEY TRY TO DO THE NORM.
A LOT OF THE TIME, I WOULD
ALWAYS GET PEOPLE JUST, LIKE,
SAYING HOW, LIKE, SOFT MY HAIR
IS AND EVERYTHING AND LIKE
WANTING TO TOUCH IT.
THAT'S, LIKE, ALWAYS A BIG
THING.
NO, YOU CAN'T TOUCH IT.
AND, LIKE, ADULTS DOING THAT
TOO, I'M LIKE...
IT'S GROWN WOMEN.
YOU CAN'T TOUCH IT!
YOU KNOW, YOU DON'T TOUCH
NO BLACK WOMEN'S HAIR, YOU
ALREADY KNOW THAT, LIKE...
IT MAKES YOU FEEL LIKE YOU'RE
IN A ZOO.
LOOK, YOU OBVIOUSLY
SHOULDN'T BE MADE TO FEEL LIKE
YOU'RE IN A ZOO, EVER, FOR ANY
REASON.
ALSO... AND IT'S NOT THE POINT
...BUT IF YOU'RE TOUCHING
ANIMALS AT THE ZOO, YOU'RE DOING
THE ZOO WRONG.
DON'T BE STRESSING THE OTTERS
OUT BY SHOUTING UNWANTED
QUESTIONS AND TRYING TO SNEAK
YOUR HANDS INTO THE CAGES TO
COP A FEEL.
YES, THE BALD EAGLE'S FEATHERS
ARE LAID, BUT DON'T SHOUT
"YAAAS, QWEEN" AND TRY TO PET
HER.
UNLIKE YOUR COWORKERS,
THE EAGLE WILL SNAP YOUR
FUCKING FINGERS OFF.
AND YOU WILL HAVE IT COMING.
UNFORTUNATELY, THOUGH,
WHITE PEOPLE'S BIASES AND
IGNORANCE ARE OFTEN JUST LAYING
IN WAIT FOR THE RIGHT MOMENT
TO STRIKE.
JONATHON SUTHERLAND IS THE
PENN STATE FOOTBALL CAPTAIN AND
A DEAN'S LIST STUDENT.
BUT WHAT PEOPLE ARE TALKING
ABOUT TONIGHT IS HIS HAIR.
THAT'S THANKS TO THIS LETTER.
THE AUTHOR IS A PROCLAIMED
ALUMNUS FROM DECADES AGO NAMED
DAVID PETERSEN.
HE CALLS SUTHERLAND'S HAIR
"AWFUL."
STATING HIS LOCS ARE
"DISGUSTING AND ARE CERTAINLY
NOT ATTRACTIVE."
HE ALSO WRITES,
"WE WOULD WELCOME THE
REAPPEARANCE OF DRESS CODES
FOR ATHLETES."
EVERYTHING ABOUT THAT'S
UPSETTING.
FROM THE RACIST ATTITUDE,
TO THE HURTFUL LANGUAGE,
TO THE FACT THAT HE CHOSE
TO EXPRESS MORAL OUTRAGE OVER
SOMETHING IN COLLEGE FOOTBALL,
BUT IT'S NOT THAT THE NCAA MAKES
MILLIONS OFF STUDENT ATHLETES,
INSTEAD, IT'S "I CAN SEE YOUR
HAIR OUTSIDE YOUR HELMET."
THAT MAN LATER EXPLAINED HE ONLY
WROTE THE LETTER BECAUSE
"I WAS JUST DISGRUNTLED ABOUT
SOME OF THE HAIRDOS THAT WE'RE
SEEING.
YOU THINK OF PENN STATE AS A
BUNCH OF CLEAN-CUT GUYS."
AND "YOU THINK OF PENN STATE
AS" IS JUST NOT A SENTENCE THAT
ENDS WELL UNDER
ANY CIRCUMSTANCE.
ESPECIALLY WHEN YOU REALIZE,
THAT MAN ACTUALLY GOT A DEGREE
FROM PENN STATE IN 1966, THE
SAME YEAR AS JERRY SANDUSKY.
WHO SOMEHOW... DESPITE HIS
SHORT HAIR... TURNED OUT TO BE
A HEINOUS SEX CRIMINAL.
I KNOW IT SOUNDS RIDICULOUS,
BUT IT'S ALMOST LIKE THE HAIRCUT
DOESN'T FUCKING MATTER.
AND IT STARTS WAY BEFORE
COLLEGE.
YOU MAY REMEMBER THE TERRIBLE
CASE OF HIGH SCHOOL WRESTLER
ANDREW JOHNSON, WHO WAS
BASICALLY FORCED TO CUT HIS LOCS
OFF OR FORFEIT AN IMPORTANT
WRESTLING MATCH BY A REFEREE.
THAT CASE MADE NATIONAL NEWS,
BUT THERE ARE HUNDREDS OF OTHERS
THAT DON'T.
FROM THE SCHOOL IN KENTUCKY THAT
ONCE BANNED... AND I QUOTE...
"DREADLOCKS AND CORN ROLLS,"
TO TWIN SISTERS IN MASSACHUSETTS
THAT RECEIVED HOURS OF DETENTION
BECAUSE OF THEIR BRAIDED HAIR,
TO THIS DAYCARE IN SUBURBAN
CHICAGO.
MOM MAY LIKE THE SMELL,
BUT ACCORDING TO THIS NOTE
TIONNA NORRIS POSTED ON HER
FACEBOOK PAGE,
AMIA'S TEACHER DIDN'T LIKE IT,
BASICALLY SAYING...
YOUR CHILD STINKS.
DON'T PUT THE COCONUT OIL
IN HER HAIR.
THE KIDS WERE TEASING HER.
NORRIS SAYS AMIA WAS THE ONLY
BLACK CHILD IN HER PRESCHOOL
CLASS AT THE RAGGEDY ANNE
LEARNING CENTER IN ELMHURST.
I WAS JUST HURT FOR MY CHILD.
ESPECIALLY AFTER NORRIS SAYS
SHE MET WITH THE TEACHER AND
SCHOOL ADMINISTRATOR AND LEARNED
THE CHILDREN IN THE CLASS NEVER
COMPLAINED.
IT WAS JUST THE TEACHER WHO
DIDN'T LIKE THE SMELL.
WE CALLED THE SCHOOL AND LEFT
SEVERAL MESSAGES.
WE VISITED AND GOT THIS.
HI, I'M DOROTHY TUCKER FROM
CHANNEL 2 NEWS.
GOODBYE.
WOW.
THAT FEELS LIKE A PERFECTLY
STAGED FIVE-SECOND PLAY
ENCAPSULATING THE HISTORY OF
RACE RELATIONS IN AMERICA:
A BLACK PERSON TRYING TO DISCUSS
RACIAL INEQUALITY WITH A WHITE
PERSON, WHO THEN IMMEDIATELY
SAYS, "GOODBYE!"
SO BLACK PEOPLE, FROM AN EARLY
AGE, ARE OFTEN TOLD THEIR HAIR
IS UNATTRACTIVE.
AND NEEDS TO BE CORRECTED.
AND THAT IS ALREADY JUST...
A LOT, BEFORE YOU EVEN START
GETTING INTO ALL THE WAYS THAT
SOCIETY MAKES IT DIFFICULT TO
NAVIGATE THE WORLD BECAUSE OF
YOUR HAIR.
EVEN JUST BUYING HAIR PRODUCTS
CAN BE AN UNNECESSARY CHALLENGE,
WITH BLACK HAIR PRODUCTS
ROUTINELY LOCKED IN A CASE WHERE
SOMEONE HAS TO COME WITH A KEY
TO GET IT FOR YOU... OR MAYBE
EVEN "WALK IT TO THE REGISTER"
...IN THE SAME AISLE WHERE
PRODUCTS FOR WHITE PEOPLE THAT
COST JUST AS MUCH OR MORE ARE
SIMPLY SITTING OUT ON THE
SHELVES.
AND THE EXPLANATION FOR THAT IS
NEVER GREAT.
SO I WENT AND FOUND THE
MANAGER AND I SAID, "I'M WAITING
FOR THE KEY FOR SHAMPOO AND
CONDITIONER."
I SAID, "BUT LET ME ASK YOU,
WHY ARE THE BLACK HAIR PRODUCTS
LOCKED UP AND NOT THE WHITE HAIR
PRODUCTS?"
HE SAID, "UMM," AND ANOTHER
ASSOCIATE SAID, "WELL, PEOPLE
HAVE BEEN STEALING."
YEAH.
NOW THAT WALMART CLAIMED IT WAS
BASED ON DATA OF THEFT
IN THE STORE.
BUT WHEN A TOWN COUNCIL MEMBER
ASKED TO SEE THAT DATA, THE
STORE INSTRUCTED HER TO CALL
"1-800-WALMART."
AND JUST OUT OF INTEREST,
ON A TOUCHTONE PHONE, WHICH
BUTTON DO YOU PRESS TO HEAR THE
BULLSHIT DATA USED TO JUSTIFY
LOCKING UP $4 ECO STYLER GEL?
IS THAT, LIKE, NUMBER 7 OR DO
YOU HAVE TO ASK FOR AN ASSOCIATE
FIRST?
SO IT'S ALREADY HARD ENOUGH TO
GET PRODUCTS TO DO YOUR HAIR AT
HOME.
BUT FINDING A QUALIFIED STYLIST
CAN BE EVEN HARDER.
THE COSMETOLOGY INDUSTRY MOSTLY
REVOLVES AROUND, AND TRAINS FOR,
CARING FOR STRAIGHT,
NON-TEXTURED HAIR.
SO THERE IS NO GUARANTEE THAT
A STYLIST IN YOUR AREA CAN WORK
WITH BLACK HAIR... JUST WATCH
ONE TIKTOKER CALL 23 SALONS IN
THEIR HOMETOWN, AND GET NOTHING
BUT RESPONSES LIKE THESE.
I WAS WONDERING IF YOU GUYS
WORK WITH AFRICAN-AMERICAN HAIR,
SPECIFICALLY 4C TYPE?
UH, WE DO NOT.
NONE OF THE GIRLS HERE DO, NO.
UM, WE DON'T REALLY HAVE
A LOT OF EXPERIENCE.
SO I WOULD SAY YOU'RE PROBABLY
BETTER TO KEEP LOOKING AROUND.
I WAS WONDERING IF YOU GUYS
WERE ABLE TO WORK WITH
AFRICAN-AMERICAN HAIR,
SPECIFICALLY 4C TYPE?
OH!
HOLD ON JUST A MINUTE!
LET ME ASK!
IS ANYBODY FAMILIAR WITH
AFRICAN-AMERICAN HAIR?
NOT VERY MUCH.
YEAH, THAT'S NOT GREAT.
BUT I DO LOVE THAT RECEPTIONIST
IS ASKING THE ENTIRE STAFF,
LIKE SHE JUST GOT CALLED AS A
PHONE-A-FRIEND ON
"WHO WANTS TO BE A MILLIONAIRE."
"HEY, DONNA, IT'S THE $25,000
QUESTION.
CAN YOU DO A SILK PRESS AND BUMP
THOSE ENDS?
SHE CAN'T."
AND THIS ISN'T JUST A PROBLEM
IN SALONS... EVEN IN HOLLYWOOD,
STYLISTS WHO ARE BOTH FAMILIAR
WITH BLACK HAIR AND IN THE
HAIRSTYLISTS' UNION ARE RARE.
AND ACTORS DEFINITELY KNOW WHEN
THEIR PRODUCTION FAILED TO HIRE
ONE.
I WAS ON THIS SHOW.
THEY MADE ME A SERIES REGULAR.
I WAS HELLA PUMPED, WALKED IN
THE HAIR AND MAKEUP TRAILER
FIRST TIME.
"OH, SHIT.
I'M ABOUT TO, LIKE, GET PAID.
LET ME SEE."
HOMEGIRL, THIS WHITE LADY,
SHE TAPPED MY HEAD.
YUP!
NOT LYING, SHE TAPPED IT,
SPRAYED SOME WATER... DIDN'T
BRUSH, DIDN'T COMB, AND LEFT.
AND I WAS LIKE, "OH, WILD!"
I ACTUALLY RECOMMEND
GOING BACK AND WATCHING EACH
ACTOR IN THAT CLIP AS HE TELLS
THAT STORY,
BECAUSE YOU REALLY GET THE SENSE
THAT
EVERY ONE OF THEM IDENTIFIES
WITH WHAT HE'S SAYING.
AND IT'S NOT IDEAL THAT FOR
A LOT OF HAIRSTYLISTS, THEIR
STRATEGY TO DEAL WITH BLACK
CLIENTS IS THE SAME YOU'D USE
TO GET YOUR CAT OFF THE KITCHEN
COUNTER.
GIVE THEM A LITTLE SPRITZ AND
THEN GIVE THEM A PAT ON THE HEAD
SO THEY KNOW YOU'RE NOT MAD.
AND WHEN YOU CONSIDER ALL OF
THE OBSTACLES THAT GET PLACED IN
THE PATH OF BLACK PEOPLE, IT'S
UNDERSTANDABLY PRETTY HARD TO
TAKE WHEN WHITE PEOPLE WEAR THE
SAME EXACT SAME HAIRSTYLES THAT
THEY GET JUDGEMENT FOR.
FROM BO DEREK, FAMOUSLY WEARING
BRAIDS IN THE MOVIE "10" TO
ADELE AND MILEY CYRUS TRYING ON
BLACK HAIRSTYLES FOR FUN, TO
THIS COMME DES GARCONS FASHION
SHOW, AT WHICH THE MODELS WORE
LACE FRONT CORNROW WIGS,
WHICH WERE AWFUL IN EVERY
POSSIBLE WAY.
I MEAN, LOOK AT THAT THING!
THERE IS ENOUGH ROOM BETWEEN
EACH BRAID TO LAND A FUCKING
PLANE, AND YOU DON'T EVEN HAVE
TO LOOK CLOSELY TO SEE THE
MODEL'S DARK HAIR THROUGH THE
LACE.
COME ON!
YOU PUT A WIG CAP ON FIRST,
THEN YOU PUT THE WIG ON!
YOU GRAB YOUR GOT2B SPRAY
OR WIG GLUE, YOU MELT THAT LACE,
AND YOU LAY THOSE EDGES DOWN
SO WELL THEY FALL ASLEEP.
THERE ARE ONLY TWO SITUATIONS
WHERE THAT APPALLING LEVEL OF
WIG APPLICATION IS ACCEPTABLE:
EITHER YOU'RE IN THE MIDDLE OF
HOSTING AN EPISODE OF "SNL," OR
YOU'RE POSING AS A BRITISH NANNY
TO STAY CLOSE TO YOUR CHILDREN
AFTER YOUR DIVORCE.
THAT IS IT.
AND THE THING IS, WHITE PEOPLE
APPROPRIATING BLACK HAIRSTYLES
ISN'T JUST INFURIATING... IT CAN
DIRECTLY MAKE IT HARDER FOR
BLACK PEOPLE TO FIGHT
DISCRIMINATION CONCERNING THEIR
HAIR.
THERE WAS A COURT CASE, 1981,
A DISCRIMINATION SUIT FILED BY A
BLACK WOMAN NAMED RENEE ROGERS.
SHE'D WORKED FOR AMERICAN
AIRLINES AND SHE WORE HER HAIR
IN CORNROWS.
HER LEGAL ARGUMENT WAS THAT HER
HAIRSTYLE WAS A PART OF HER
CULTURAL HERITAGE.
THE JUDGE RULED AGAINST HER IN
FEDERAL COURT BECAUSE HE SAID
SHE GOT HER HAIR DONE SOON AFTER
THE MOVIE "TEN" CAME OUT.
AND THEREFORE, THERE WAS NO
LEGAL BASIS FOR SAYING IT WAS
CULTURAL HERITAGE BECAUSE
SHE WAS DOING SOMETHING THAT
ESSENTIALLY WAS IMITATING HOW
BO DEREK STYLED HER HAIR.
YEAH, IT'S TRUE.
AMONG THE REASONS HE DISMISSED
HER CASE, THE JUDGE SUGGESTED
THAT A BLACK PERSON WEARING A
TRADITIONALLY BLACK HAIRSTYLE
WAS JUST COPYING A WHITE
CELEBRITY, WHO STOLE IT FROM
BLACK PEOPLE.
WHICH IS JUST RIDICULOUS!
HAIRSTYLES HAVE CULTURAL ROOTS.
THEY DON'T JUST COME OUT OF
NOWHERE TO SWEEP THE NATION,
WITH THE SOLE EXCEPTION OF
"THE RACHEL," WHICH WASN'T
APPROPRIATED FROM ANY CULTURE.
IT SIMPLY SPRANG FORTH,
FULLY-FORMED, FROM THE CONCEPT
KNOWN AS "THE '90s."
AND I WISH I COULD SAY THAT'S
A THING OF THE PAST, BUT YOU
KNOW IT ISN'T.
CHASTITY JONES, THE WOMAN YOU
SAW EARLIER, SPENT YEARS
APPEALING HER CASE, ONLY TO
LOSE, IN PART, BECAUSE JUDGES
INTERPRETED CIVIL RIGHTS LAW
TO PROTECT AGAINST
DISCRIMINATION BASED ONLY ON
"IMMUTABLE" OR UNCHANGEABLE
CHARACTERISTICS ASSOCIATED
WITH RACE, LIKE SKIN COLOR.
SO FOR DECADES, COURTS HAVE
FOUND THAT HAIRSTYLES, EVEN
THOUGH THEY ARE DEEPLY TIED TO
RACIAL IDENTITY, ARE NOT
COVERED.
AND ALL OF THAT MEANS THAT A
YOUNGER GENERATION CAN STILL END
UP HAVING TO DEAL WITH THIS
SHIT.
19-YEAR-OLD DESTINY THOMPKINS
HAS WORKED AT THIS
BANANA REPUBLIC STORE AT THE
WESTCHESTER MALL IN WHITE PLAINS
FOR JUST ABOUT A MONTH.
SHE WAS CALLED INTO A MEETING
WITH HER MANAGER ON WEDNESDAY,
CAUGHT COMPLETELY OFF GUARD BY
WHAT HAPPENED NEXT.
HE WAS LIKE, "YEAH, SO, THE
DISTRICT MANAGER CAME IN AND SHE
POINTED OUT YOUR HAIR."
AND I'M LIKE, "OKAY, SO WHAT'S
WRONG WITH MY HAIR?"
HE SAID, "IT'S A LITTLE TOO
URBAN AND UNKEMPT FOR OUR LOOK
AND FOR OUR IMAGE.
WE WERE JUST WONDERING, LIKE, IF
YOU COULD JUST TAKE THEM OUT."
OKAY, PUTTING ASIDE THE
USE OF THE WORD "URBAN"... A
LEVEL OF TONE-DEAFNESS ON PAR
WITH NAMING YOUR STORE "BANANA
REPUBLIC "..." JUST TAKE THEM
OUT?"
THOSE ARE WORDS FROM SOMEONE WHO
HAS ZERO IDEA OF WHAT IT TOOK TO
PUT THEM IN IN THE FIRST PLACE.
THAT'S COMING FROM A MAN WHO,
I'M GUESSING, HAS NEVER SPENT
SEVEN HOURS IN A SALON CHAIR
WITH AN iPAD FULL OF MOVIES AND
A BACKPACK FULL OF SNACKS.
NOW YOU SHOULD KNOW, THE STORE
CALLED THAT UNACCEPTABLE, AND
THE MANAGER WAS FIRED.
BUT THE PROBLEM IS, SINCE
PROFESSIONALISM GETS DEFINED BY
WHITE STANDARDS AND
EXPECTATIONS, BLACK HAIR
IS MORE LIKELY TO CRASH INTO
THOSE EXPECTATIONS.
SO WHAT CAN WE DO?
WELL, FOR SOME OF THE SMALLER
ISSUES YOU'VE SEEN TONIGHT,
THERE HAVE BEEN CHANGES.
SOME CHAIN STORES, INCLUDING
WALMART, HAVE ANNOUNCED THEY'LL
NO LONGER BE LOCKING UP
BLACK HAIR PRODUCTS.
WHICH FEELS LIKE THE LEAST THEY
CAN DO, BUT IT IS A START!
A BIGGER CHANGE WOULD BE TO
PASS LAWS LIKE CROWN ACTS, OR
"CREATING A RESPECTFUL AND OPEN
WORLD FOR NATURAL HAIR."
VERSIONS HAVE ALREADY BECOME LAW
IN THESE 11 STATES.
AND WHILE THE LANGUAGE VARIES,
GENERALLY, THEY EXPAND
THE DEFINITION OF RACE IN
ANTI-DISCRIMINATION LAWS TO
INCLUDE TRAITS HISTORICALLY
ASSOCIATED WITH RACE, LIKE
PROTECTIVE HAIRSTYLES, SUCH AS
BRAIDS, LOCS, AND TWISTS.
UNFORTUNATELY, CROWN ACT BILLS
HAVE REPEATEDLY MET WITH
REPUBLICAN OPPOSITION.
IN UTAH, IN ONE RECENT ZOOM
HEARING ON THEIR BILL, STATE
SENATOR DERRIN OWENS... WHO
VOTED AGAINST IT... MADE A POINT
OF FIRST ADDRESSING THE BILL'S
ADVOCATES LIKE THIS.
LET ME MAKE A COMMENT,
YOU PEOPLE ARE BEAUTIFUL.
I DON'T NORMALLY DO THIS, BUT
I'M GOING TO SHARE.
I WAS IN THE STORE
THE OTHER DAY.
AND, UH, YOU WON'T BE ABLE
TO SEE THIS PICTURE, BUT THIS
GENTLEMAN IN FRONT OF ME... A
BLACK MAN... HAD TWO YOUNG
CHILDREN AND THEY WERE JUST
HAVING FUN AROUND, UP AND DOWN
THE AISLE.
AND I DON'T NORMALLY TAKE
PICTURES OF CHILDREN,
BUT THEY WERE ADORABLE,
TWO BLACK CHILDREN.
BECAUSE THEY WERE JUST THE
CUTEST KIDS IN THE WORLD.
ONE HAS CORNROWS AND ONE OF THEM
DREADLOCKS.
I WISH YOU COULD SEE THAT.
WHAT ARE YOU DOING,
YOU EXCEPTIONALLY WEIRD MAN?
HE STARTED OFF
THERE BY TELLING A GROUP OF
BLACK WOMEN, "YOU PEOPLE ARE
BEAUTIFUL," THEN PROCEEDED TO
SAY, "I DON'T NORMALLY TAKE
PICTURES OF CHILDREN, BUT"...
A PERFECTLY ACCEPTABLE SENTENCE
UNTIL THE "BUT" PART.
THEN LAUNCHED INTO A STORY ABOUT
HOW HE KEEPS PHOTOS OF
STRANGERS' CHILDREN
ON HIS PHONE.
ALL OF WHICH EVOKES A RESPONSE
PERHAPS BEST SUMMED UP BY THIS
EXPRESSION, WHICH I'D ARGUE IS
AN ABSOLUTE MASTERCLASS IN HOW
TO SAY "THE FUCK?"
USING ONLY YOUR EYEBROWS.
AND IF YOU'RE WONDERING HOW HE
GOT FROM THAT TO VOTING AGAINST
THE BILL, HIS ARGUMENT WAS THAT
HE FELT EXISTING LAWS WERE
SUFFICIENT, AND THAT "IT ALMOST
LOOKS LIKE WE'RE TRYING TO DO
SOMETHING THAT DOESN'T EXIST."
BUT THIS DISCRIMINATION ISN'T
"SOMETHING THAT DOESN'T EXIST,"
IT'S "SOMETHING THAT DOESN'T
EXIST FOR WHITE MEN WHO'VE NEVER
HAD TO THINK ABOUT IT BEFORE."
THE CONSEQUENCES OF HAIR-BASED
DISCRIMINATION ARE VERY REAL.
JUST LISTEN TO CONNECTICUT STATE
SENATOR GARY WINFIELD MAKE THE
CASE FOR HIS STATE'S CROWN ACT,
IN THE RUN-UP TO IT PASSING INTO
LAW, BY TALKING ABOUT HIS
THREE-YEAR-OLD DAUGHTER.
RIGHT NOW, SHE RUNS THROUGH
LIFE WITH ALL OF THE ENERGY THAT
SHE HAS, WITH ALL OF THE BEAUTY
THAT SHE HAS WITH HER HAIR
NATURAL.
THAT'S WHO SHE IS.
IT'S NOT JUST WHAT SITS ON TOP
OF HER HEAD, IT IS WHO SHE IS.
BUT I WANT HER TO BE ABLE TO
PARTICIPATE IN THIS WORLD FULLY,
AND SO EVEN IF SHE RUNS THROUGH
THIS WORLD WITH HER NATURAL
HAIR, THERE WILL BE A DISCUSSION
ABOUT WHAT IT IS TO RUN THROUGH
THIS WORLD WITH HER NATURAL
HAIR.
AND WHAT SHE WILL HAVE TO LEARN,
WHETHER SHE MAKES THE CHOICE TO
RUN THROUGH THIS WORLD WITH HER
NATURAL HAIR OR NOT, IS THAT A
PART OF HER IS NOT ACCEPTABLE.
THAT'S AWFUL.
IT'S INFURIATING THAT
BLACK CHILDREN HAVE TO ADD
"HAIR DISCRIMINATION" TO THE
LONG LIST OF THINGS THEY'RE
ALREADY FORCED TO THINK ABOUT,
LIKE THE THREAT OF POLICE
VIOLENCE, THE DANGER OF
HARASSMENT BY RACIST
WHITE PEOPLE, AND OF COURSE,
THE VERY REAL RISK OF GETTING
PHOTOGRAPHED BY UTAH STATE
SENATOR DERRIN OWENS
IN A FUCKING CHECKOUT LINE.
THAT MAN'S DAUGHTER, AND ALL
BLACK PEOPLE, SHOULD CLEARLY BE
ABLE TO MAKE CHOICES ABOUT THEIR
HAIR BASED ON WHAT THEY FEEL
LIKE DOING WITH IT, RATHER
THAN, "WILL THIS GET ME HARASSED
OR FIRED?"
IF YOU WANT TO HAVE
NATURAL HAIR, GREAT!
YOU WANT TO STRAIGHTEN
YOUR HAIR, GREAT!
WHATEVER YOU LIKE!
THE POINT IS, BLACK HAIR
SHOULDN'T BE VIEWED, CORRALLED,
OR JUDGED BY WHITE PEOPLE'S
COMFORT.
BECAUSE IT DOESN'T BELONG TO
WHITE PEOPLE, IT DOESN'T AFFECT
WHITE PEOPLE, AND WHITE PEOPLE
REALLY DON'T NEED TO HAVE AN
OPINION ON IT.
AND OUR LAWS SHOULD REFLECT
THAT.
AND I KNOW THERE MAY BE LIMITS
TO WHAT CROWN ACTS CAN
ACCOMPLISH.
EVEN IF ONE PASSES AT THE
FEDERAL LEVEL, THERE COULD
BE CASES WHERE A WHITE JUDGE IS
ASKED TO DECIDE WHETHER
A SPECIFIC HAIRSTYLE IS
"ASSOCIATED WITH RACE" AND
COMPLETELY FUCKS IT UP, BUT
THEY ARE A START.
IF YOU'RE NOT
A BLACK PERSON, IT'S PROBABLY
EASY TO HEAR THESE STORIES AND
THINK "WELL, IT'S JUST HAIR,"
BUT THE THING IS, IT'S NOT.
IT'S NOT AT ALL.
BLACK PEOPLE AREN'T GETTING
HIRED, OR ARE GETTING FIRED...
BLACK STUDENTS ARE BEING TEASED,
TAUNTED, AND REMOVED FROM SCHOOL
...ALL BECAUSE OF THEIR HAIR.
AND CROWN ACT LAWS COULD MAKE A
REAL DIFFERENCE THERE.
AND WHILE SOCIAL STIGMA AND
UNREALISTIC BEAUTY STANDARDS
AREN'T GOING TO GO AWAY
OVERNIGHT, THERE ARE A FEW
THINGS THAT WHITE VIEWERS,
IN PARTICULAR, MIGHT WANT TO
KEEP IN MIND GOING FORWARD.
AND TO THAT END,
IF YOU ARE ONE, THERE'S A
MESSAGE YOU SHOULD PROBABLY
HEAR.
HI, WHITE PEOPLE.
I'M LESLIE JONES.
WHAT'S UP, BLACK PEOPLE.
BROTHERS AND SISTERS.
YOU GOOD?
YOUR MAMA GOOD?
ALL RIGHT, LISTEN, I GOT TO
TALK TO THESE WHITE PEOPLE FOR A
SECOND.
I SEE YOU AT THE MEETING.
LOOK, WHITE PEOPLE.
I KNOW YOU HAVE LOTS OF
QUESTIONS.
LIKE, MAY BE TOO MANY
LIKE, HOW OFTEN DO YOU HAVE
TO WASH BLACK HAIR?
WHAT IS A SILK PRESS?
WHAT DOES IT DO RAG DO?
WE ARE ABOUT TO FILL YOU IN.
WE ARE ABOUT TO GIVE YOU ANSWERS
TO ALL YOUR QUESTIONS ABOUT
BLACK HAIR.
ARE YOU READY FOR IT?
GOOGLE IT.
FUCKING GOOGLE IT.
IT DOESN'T HAVE TO BE GOOGLE.
IT CAN BE FUCKING BING.
THE INFORMATION IS OUT THERE.
ONCE YOU GET THE INFORMATION,
YOU CAN APPRECIATE THE BEAUTY
AND HARD WORK IT TAKES TO KEEP
MY HAIR LAID AND LOOKING GOOD.
IF YOU AREN'T INTERESTED IN
GOOGLING IT, YOU THERE IS
ANOTHER OPTION.
LEAVE US ALONE.
FUCKING OFF IS ALWAYS AN
OPTION.
WHITE PEOPLE, DON'T TELL ME
YOU CAN FIGURE THAT OUT.
YOU FIGURED OUT SETTLERS OF
CATAN.
YOU FIGURED OUT SOURDOUGH.
YOU CAN LEARN WHAT A BOX
BRAID IS, BITCH.
BASICALLY, GOOGLE IT.
DON'T TOUCH IT.
ONE MORE THING.
DON'T SPRAY MY WATER AND TAP
MY HEAD.
I'M NOT A CAT.
BYE.
THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
GOOD NIGHT.
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org