HI THERE!
WELCOME TO THE SHOW,
STILL, UNFORTUNATELY,
TAKING PLACE IN THIS BLANK VOID.
THINK OF IT LIKE PRINCE PHILIP,
IN THAT IT'S WHITE,
DOESN'T DO ANYTHING,
AND I THOUGHT FOR SURE IT'D BE
GONE BY NOW.
AND WE HAVE TO DIVE STRAIGHT IN
WITH TUESDAY'S HORRIFIC EVENTS
IN THE ATLANTA AREA,
WHERE A GUNMAN
KILLED EIGHT PEOPLE,
SIX OF THEM ASIAN WOMEN,
AT THREE DIFFERENT SPAS.
AND SYMPATHY FOR THE VICTIMS HAS
POURED OUT ACROSS THE COUNTRY,
ALTHOUGH THERE'VE BEEN SOME
TERRIBLE REACTIONS, TOO...
LIKE THE ONE FROM THIS OFFICER
WHO BRIEFED THE PRESS.
THERE ARE A LOT OF CONCERNS
ABOUT THIS STATEMENT, WHICH MANY
FEEL APPEARS TO SYMPATHIZE WITH
THE SHOOTER AND NOT HIS ALLEGED
VICTIMS.
I SPOKE WITH INVESTIGATORS.
THEY INTERVIEWED HIM THIS
MORNING AND I... THEY GOT THAT
IMPRESSION THAT, YES, HE... HE
UNDERSTOOD THE GRAVITY OF IT
AND HE WAS PRETTY MUCH FED UP,
AT THE END OF HIS ROPE.
AND... AND YESTERDAY WAS
A REALLY BAD DAY FOR HIM.
AND THIS IS WHAT HE DID.
OKAY, ABSOLUTELY
FUCKING NOT.
YOU GET THAT THIS IS A PRESS
CONFERENCE ABOUT A MASS MURDER,
RIGHT?
YOU DON'T GET TO MINIMIZE WHAT
HAPPENED LIKE THAT.
"REALLY BAD DAY?"
ALEXANDER HAD A TERRIBLE,
HORRIBLE, NO GOOD, VERY BAD DAY,
AND WHAT HE DID WAS SHRUG IT
THE FUCK OFF AND GO TO BED WHILE
MANAGING TO MURDER ZERO PEOPLE.
THAT COP EVEN WENT ON TO REPEAT
THE SHOOTER'S CLAIMS THAT HIS
ATTACKS WEREN'T RACIALLY
MOTIVATED; INSTEAD,
HIS "SEXUAL ADDICTION" WAS
TO BLAME FOR THE KILLINGS.
WHICH ALREADY FEELS LIKE A
WEIRD DISTINCTION TO BE MAKING.
"HEY!
I MIGHT BE A MASS-MURDERER,
BUT WATCH WHO YOU CALL A RACIST,
BUDDY!
WORDS HURT!"
AND WHILE IT IS STILL EARLY,
DETAILS ARE STILL COMING OUT,
AND AUTHORITIES SEEM UNWILLING
TO CALL THIS A HATE CRIME.
I WILL SAY, A WHITE MAN
DRIVING ACROSS COUNTIES
TO TWO DIFFERENT TOWNS,
GOING TO THREE ASIAN-OWNED
BUSINESSES, SHOOTING AND KILLING
SIX ASIAN WOMEN, IN A CITY
THAT'S ONLY ABOUT 4% ASIAN
SURE AS SHIT SEEMS A LOT MORE
LIKE A HATE CRIME THAN
"A BAD FUCKING DAY."
AND THIS IS JUST THE LATEST DATA
POINT IN A DISTURBING PATTERN.
ONE GROUP TRACKING HATE-RELATED
INCIDENTS AGAINST
ASIAN-AMERICANS... WHICH INCLUDE
PHYSICAL ASSAULTS,
VERBAL HARASSMENT, AND
CIVIL RIGHTS VIOLATIONS LIKE
REFUSAL OF SERVICE... FOUND
NEARLY 3800 REPORTED IN JUST
THE PAST YEAR.
IT'S AN ABSOLUTELY TERRIBLE
TREND THAT PRESIDENT BIDEN SPOKE
ABOUT JUST LAST WEEK.
VICIOUS HATE CRIMES AGAINST
ASIAN-AMERICANS, WHO'VE BEEN
ATTACKED, HARASSED, BLAMED, AND
SCAPEGOATED.
IT'S WRONG, IT'S UN-AMERICAN,
AND IT MUST STOP.
YEAH.
IT MUST.
AND I AM REALLY GLAD HE
CONDEMNED HATE CRIMES AGAINST
ASIAN-AMERICANS THERE, BUT TO
SAY THAT THEY ARE "UN-AMERICAN?"
I'D LOVE TO VISIT THE NATION
THAT EXISTS IN JOE BIDEN'S HEAD,
BECAUSE IT'S A PLACE WHERE
RACISM "IS NOT WHO WE ARE" AND
RACIAL ATTACKS AGAINST ASIANS
ARE SOMEHOW "UN-AMERICAN,"
DESPITE THE FACT... AND FAR BE
IT FROM ME TO EXPLAIN THIS TO
SOMEONE WHO SEEMS LIKE HE'S
LIVED THROUGH MOST OF AMERICAN
HISTORY... ANTI-ASIAN RACISM HAS
LONG BEEN A FACT OF AMERICAN
LIFE.
FROM THE TREATMENT OF
CHINESE RAILROAD WORKERS
IN THE 1800s, THROUGH
THE CHINESE EXCLUSION ACT,
THROUGH THE WATSONVILLE RIOTS
IN 1930, IN WHICH A WHITE MOB
RAMPAGED THROUGH A FILIPINO
COMMUNITY,
THROUGH THE INTERNMENT OF
JAPANESE AMERICANS DURING
WORLD WAR II, THROUGH DEADLY
CASES OF RACIAL SCAPEGOATING
LIKE THE MURDER OF VINCENT CHIN,
KILLED IN 1982 BY TWO
WHITE AUTOWORKERS IN DETROIT.
WITNESSES SAID THE MEN MISTOOK
CHIN, A CHINESE-AMERICAN, FOR
BEING JAPANESE, BLAMED HIM FOR
TAKING THEIR JOBS, AND BEAT HIM
TO DEATH.
AND BY THE WAY, EVEN THOUGH
THEY'D REPORTEDLY USED
RACIAL SLURS DURING THE ATTACK,
THE MEN STILL TRIED TO CLAIM
THEY WERE NOT MOTIVATED BY RACE.
SO NOT ONLY ARE HATE CRIMES
AGAINST ASIAN-AMERICANS VERY
MUCH "AMERICAN," SO IS DENYING
THAT THEY'RE RACIST.
IT'S ALL SO AMERICAN, IN FACT,
THE NATIONAL ANTHEM COULD
"OH, SAY CAN YOU SEE
THAT THIS WASN'T ABOUT RACE."
AND OUR LONG, UGLY HISTORY OF
ANTI-ASIAN RACISM... AND THE
FACT IT OFTEN PEAKS DURING TIMES
OF CRISIS... IS THE VERY REASON
WHY, JUST LAST YEAR, MANY WERE
LOUDLY WARNING THAT TRUMP
CALLING COVID NAMES LIKE
"THE CHINA VIRUS" WAS LIKELY TO
LEAD TO A RISE IN VIOLENCE
AGAINST PEOPLE OF ASIAN DESCENT,
AN ARGUMENT THAT AT THE TIME,
NOT EVERYONE SEEMED TO FIND
CONVINCING.
I THINK IF THE LEFT WANTS TO
FOCUS ON PC LABELING THIS VIRUS,
IT IS A GREAT WAY TO GET TRUMP
REELECTED.
I DON'T HAVE A PROBLEM WITH
PEOPLE CALLING IT WHATEVER THEY
WANT.
IT'S A DEADLY VIRUS THAT DID
ORIGINATE IN WUHAN.
I DON'T HAVE A PROBLEM WITH IT.
OH, GOOD!
MEGHAN McCAIN DOESN'T
HAVE A PROBLEM WITH IT!
LISTEN NOT TO THE SCORES OF
ASIAN-AMERICANS TELLING EVERYONE
THAT THE TERM IS DANGEROUS AND
OFFENSIVE!
INSTEAD, GATHER ROUND,
AND TAKE THE WORD OF A WEALTHY
WHITE WOMAN WHO'S DRESSED LIKE
SHE'S ABOUT TO LAY OFF 47 PEOPLE
OVER ZOOM.
NOW, I WILL SAY, McCAIN POSTED
THIS WEEK, "STOP ASIAN HATE"
WITH THREE BROKEN HEART EMOJIS.
WHICH IS A FINE SENTIMENT TO
THROW UP ON TWITTER AFTER THE
FACT, BUT THERE HAS TO BE AN
UNDERSTANDING THAT SAYING,
"I DON'T HAVE A PROBLEM WITH
CALLING IT THE CHINA VIRUS"
IS VERY MUCH GIVING SPACE FOR
THAT HATE TO GROW.
AND THE MINIMIZATION OF RACIST
RHETORIC PLAYS INTO THE HARMFUL
STEREOTYPE OF ASIAN-AMERICANS AS
A "MODEL MINORITY," PITTING THEM
AGAINST OTHER MINORITY GROUPS
AND PRESSURING THEM TO SWALLOW
THEIR EXPERIENCES WITH RACISM
WITHOUT MAKING A STINK, BECAUSE
THAT'S HOW YOU EARN
WHITE ACCEPTANCE.
AND THAT IS SOMETHING THAT TAKES
ITS TOLL.
JUST LISTEN TO BASKETBALL PLAYER
JEREMY LIN, WHO RECENTLY
REVEALED THAT HE'D BEEN CALLED
"CORONAVIRUS" ON THE COURT, AND
SPOKE ABOUT THE EVENTS OF THIS
WEEK.
ASIANS HAVE ALWAYS BEEN...
HAVE BEEN PROJECTED AS BEING
OTHERS OR OUTSIDERS AND YOU
CAN... YOU CAN HEAR AND SEE
THESE MICROAGGRESSIONS, IN LIKE,
"OH, NO, WHERE ARE YOU REALLY
FROM?"
OR, YOU KNOW, TALKING ABOUT THE
WAY WE LOOK OR OUR COMPLEXION
AND, AGAIN, CALLING IT THE CHINA
VIRUS, KUNG FLU VIRUS, THAT IS
ADDING TO IT, FUELING THE FIRE,
AND NOW WE'RE STARTING TO SEE A
LOT OF THOSE MICROAGGRESSIONS
TURN INTO ACTUAL ACTS OF
VIOLENCE.
RIGHT.
COMMENTS LIKE, "WHERE ARE YOU
REALLY FROM?" ARE CONSTANT
REMINDERS OF HOW
ASIAN-AMERICANS ARE REGARDED AS
OUTSIDERS, AS PEOPLE WHO DON'T
BELONG.
AND THE FACT IS, "WHERE ARE YOU
REALLY FROM?" IS JUST NOT AN
APPROPRIATE QUESTION TO ASK
ANYONE, UNLESS THEY'VE JUST
OPENED UP THEIR TORSO TO REVEAL
A TINY ALIEN SQUID OPERATING
A ROBOT BODY.
AND EVEN THEN, HONESTLY, IT'S
STILL A BIT IFFY.
"WELL MY PARENTS ARE FROM
RIGEL VII, BUT I WAS BORN IN
CINCINNATI, YOU DICK!"
THE COMFORT PEOPLE HAVE WITH
DIMINISHING AND OTHERING ASIANS
IS PERVASIVE.
EVEN THAT OFFICER YOU SAW
EARLIER WAS LAST YEAR PROMOTING
T-SHIRTS ON HIS FACEBOOK PAGE
CALLING COVID-19 AN
"IMPORTED VIRUS FROM CHY-NA."
AND THE FACT THE KILLER CHOSE
THESE PARTICULAR WOMEN,
WORKING LOW-WAGE JOBS, AS
TARGETS FOR HIS "SEX ADDICTION"
SPEAKS TO HOW ASIAN-AMERICAN
WOMEN, IN PARTICULAR, HAVE TO
DEAL WITH HYPERSEXUALIZATION,
AND HOW ASIAN WORKERS TO THE
EXTENT THAT THEY ARE SEEN AT ALL
ARE SEEN MORE FOR THE LABOR THAT
THEY PROVIDE RATHER THAN THE
FULL THREE-DIMENSIONAL HUMANS
THAT THEY ARE.
SO THERE'S PRETTY CLEARLY A LOT
THAT NEEDS TO BE CONFRONTED
HERE, AS MANY HAVE BEEN POINTING
OUT.
I'M GLAD THAT WE'RE STARTING
TO HAVE THIS CONVERSATION,
BUT THIS CANNOT BE IT.
ASIAN-AMERICAN WOMEN HAVE BEEN
LONG INVISIBLE IN THIS SOCIETY.
RIGHT?
YOU KNOW, WE'RE BEING TOLD THIS
IS NOT A RACIST INCIDENT.
IT IS A RACIST INCIDENT BECAUSE
OF THE WAY ASIAN-AMERICAN WOMEN
EXPERIENCE RACISM IN OUR
COUNTRY.
EXACTLY.
THIS ISN'T JUST A CONVERSATION
ABOUT THIS WEEK.
IT'S A CONVERSATION ABOUT
THE CENTURIES LEADING UP TO IT.
NOW, SOME HAVE RESPONDED BY
CALLING FOR INCREASED POLICE
PRESENCE, ALTHOUGH OTHERS ARE
UNDERSTANDABLY WARY OF "MORE
POLICE" BEING A GOOD SOLUTION.
MORE GUYS LIKE "DEPUTY OOPS ALL
FOREHEAD" HERE AREN'T LIKELY TO
MAKE ASIAN-AMERICANS, OR,
INDEED, OTHER COMMUNITIES OF
COLOR AROUND THEM, FEEL MUCH
SAFER.
OTHERS HAVE SUGGESTED SOLUTIONS
FROM CONNECTING VICTIMS OF
TRAUMA TO SUPPORT AFTER THE
FACT, TO IMPROVING COLLECTION
AND REPORTING OF STATISTICS
ON ANTI-ASIAN VIOLENCE AND
DISCRIMINATION, SO WE HAVE
A MUCH MORE COMPLETE PICTURE OF
WHAT'S HAPPENING.
AND IF YOU DO WANT TO HELP,
THERE ARE SOME GREAT
ORGANIZATIONS LIKE THESE ONES
THAT COULD REALLY USE YOUR HELP.
LOOK, ASIAN-AMERICAN AND
ASIAN IMMIGRANT COMMUNITIES
HAVE BEEN FEELING EXTREMELY
VULNERABLE FOR A LONG TIME,
AND ESPECIALLY SO RIGHT NOW.
AND FOR A GROUP WHOSE SUFFERING
HAS HISTORICALLY FELT INVISIBLE
TO THE MEDIA AND THE COUNTRY AT
LARGE, IT'S IMPORTANT THAT WE
ACKNOWLEDGE THAT PAIN RIGHT NOW.
BUT MORE THAN THAT, DISMANTLING
ANTI-ASIAN PREJUDICE SHOULD BE
ANOTHER KEY PART OF DISMANTLING
THE CHOKEHOLD THAT
WHITE SUPREMACY HAS
ON THIS COUNTRY.
BECAUSE AS WE'VE SEEN SINCE ITS
FOUNDATION, AND CONTINUED TO SEE
THIS WEEK, PEOPLE WILL BEND OVER
BACKWARDS TO CALL RACISM
ANYTHING OTHER THAN WHAT IT IS.
AND THAT IS UNFORTUNATELY VERY
FUCKING AMERICAN.
AND NOW THIS.
AND NOW...
EVEN DURING A PANDEMIC,
LOCAL NEWS CANNOT BE TRUSTED
WITH ST. PATRICK'S DAY.
TODAY ON "WINDY CITY LIVE,"
TOP OF THE MORNING TO YOU.
TOP OF THE MORNING TO YOU,
SAN DIEGO.
TOP OF THE MORNING TO YOU.
TOP OF THE MORNING TO YOU
TOO.
IT'S WEE MORE THAN A LITTLE
CLOUD COVER OUT THERE.
IT'S TOTALLY CLOUD COVERED.
AH, LADS AND LASSES,
WE WILL HAVE SUNSHINE.
THE LUCK OF THE IRISH.
THE LUCK OF THE IRISH BE WITH
US.
I HAVE NO IDEA WHAT I SAID.
BUT I WATCHED A LOT OF
LUCKY CHARMS COMMERCIALS.
WELCOME TO OUR FAIR CITY
WHERE THE GIRLS ARE SO PRETTY.
LET'S START WITH ONE OF THOSE
LOVELY LADIES.
MOVING ON.
OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT CONCERNS
PLASTIC.
IT'S VERY MUCH THE JANE LYNCH
OF MATERIALS, IN THAT
IT'S INCREDIBLY VERSATILE,
APPEARS IN ALMOST EVERYTHING,
AND ISN'T GOING ANYWHERE
FOR THE NEXT 400 YEARS.
PLASTIC REALLY IS UBIQUITOUS.
IT'S IN FOOD PACKAGING,
IT'S IN BUILDING MATERIALS
ON PLANES AND CARS,
IT'S IN BICYCLE HELMETS,
AND IT'S IN THIS STRAP-ON
THIGH DILDO.
IMAGINE A WORLD BEFORE PLASTICS,
WHEN YOUR FEMUR PENIS WOULD HAVE
TO MADE FROM WOOD, OR IF YOU
WERE WEALTHY ENOUGH, IVORY.
IT DOESN'T BEAR THINKING ABOUT.
BUT FOR ALMOST AS LONG AS
PLASTICS HAVE BEEN AROUND,
THERE'S BEEN THE QUESTION OF
WHAT TO DO WITH THEM AFTER
THEY'RE USED... A QUESTION ANY
NUMBER OF CREEPY RECYCLING
MASCOTS HAVE TRIED TO ANSWER.
FROM THE RECYCLING WIZARD IN
SOUTH CAROLINA, TO RECYCLING BEN
FROM GEORGIA, TO MUNCIE,
INDIANA'S MR. BLUE... WHO
APPEARS TO BE A BAG OF RECYCLING
OR AN ASPHYXIATED SAUSAGE...
TO MY ABSOLUTE FAVORITE,
TOTES McGOATS.
THE POPULAR SOCIAL MEDIA
NEWS-SITE MASHABLE WRITES OF
"NIAGARA FALL'S TERRIFYING NEW
RECYCLING MASCOT " AND " HORRIFIC
GOAT-MAN HYBRID."
SURE, YEAH, AND YOU KNOW
WHAT?
I'VE SEEN CHILDREN CRY AT THE
EASTER BUNNY AND SANTA CLAUS AS
WELL.
UM, BUT OUR TARGET MARKET ISN'T
THREE AND 4-YEAR-OLDS OF COURSE.
IT'S SOMEONE WHO'S LEARNING
ABOUT THE ENVIRONMENT,
SO MIDDLE SCHOOL, TEENAGERS,
PEOPLE WHO MAYBE AREN'T SO
AFRAID OF GOATS AND CLOWNS.
WELL, HANG ON.
WHO SAID ANYTHING ABOUT CLOWNS?
NO ONE WOULD EVER MISTAKE THAT
THING FOR A CLOWN.
I KNOW WE'VE BEEN TOUGH ON
CLOWNS IN THE PAST.
THEY'RE WEIRD, SCARY, NOT FUNNY,
AND THEY EAT CHILDREN, BUT
CREDIT WHERE IT'S DUE... THEY DO
PUT IN THE WORK.
YOU THINK A LOOK THIS FRESH
JUST COMES TOGETHER?
OF COURSE NOT!
THIS GUY CLEARLY MADE AN EFFORT.
HE DIDN'T JUST GOOGLE
"RUBBER GOAT MASK CHEAP," AND
BUY THE FIRST RESULT, WHICH,
INCIDENTALLY, SEEMS TO BE
THE EXACT MASK THAT FUCKED-UP
GOAT IS WEARING.
AND WE'VE PRODUCED A LOT OF
PLASTIC FOR ALL THOSE MASCOTS
TO RECYCLE.
SINCE PLASTIC'S INTRODUCTION,
PRODUCTION HAS SKYROCKETED
TO 380 MILLION TONS IN 2015.
IN FACT, HALF OF ALL PLASTICS
EVER MADE HAVE BEEN PRODUCED
SINCE 2005.
AND FOR ALL THE HYPE ABOUT
RECYCLING, A LOT LESS PLASTIC
WINDS UP GETTING RECYCLED THAN
YOU MIGHT THINK.
LESS THAN 9% OF THE PLASTICS
GENERATED ARE RECYCLED
IN THE UNITED STATES,
WITH THE VAST MAJORITY
ENDING UP IN LANDFILLS OR
IN THE ENVIRONMENT.
BUT BEFORE YOU START BLAMING
YOURSELF, OR YOUR NEIGHBORS,
FOR NOT SORTING THEIR TRASH AND
SEPARATING ITEMS, IT'S ACTUALLY
NOT THAT SIMPLE, AS THIS
REPORTER FOUND OUT WHILE WALKING
THROUGH A PORTLAND SUPERMARKET.
IT SEEMS LIKE EVERYBODY IS
BUYING LETTUCE IN A BOX NOW.
IS THIS RECYCLABLE?
IN THIS STATE, NONE OF THIS
IS... NONE OF THIS IS
RECYCLABLE.
OKAY.
WHAT ABOUT ALL OF THESE?
THIS IS EVERYWHERE IN EVERY
SUPERMARKET.
IN OREGON, AGAIN, THERE ARE
NO CURBSIDE PROGRAMS THAT WOULD
ACCEPT ANY OF THESE TUBS.
YEAH, THAT IS SHOCKING!
BECAUSE THINK OF WHAT THAT
THE STUFF WE ALL
ROUTINELY BUY AT THE SUPERMARKET
...ASSUMING, UNDERSTANDABLY, IT
WILL GET RECYCLED... IS, IN MANY
CASES, NOT.
AND THAT IS DESPITE THE
IMPRESSION WE MIGHT HAVE TAKEN
FROM MASCOTS LIKE TOTES McGOATS,
WHOSE NAME I'M HONESTLY
UNCOMFORTABLE EVEN UTTERING OUT
LOUD, JUST ON THE OFF-CHANCE
THAT HE'S LIKE BEETLEJUICE AND
SAYING "TOTES McGOATS"
THREE TIMES SOMEHOW SUMMONS HIM
INTO...
OH, SHIT!
HOW THE HELL DID YOU GET
IN HERE?
THIS IS A COVID-COMPLIANT SET!
YOU CAN'T BE HERE!
WAIT... YOU GOT THE VACCINE?
HOW THE FUCK ARE YOU ELIGIBLE
FOR THE VACCINE?
HYPERTENSION, JOHN.
OH, BULLSHIT!
YOU KNOW WHAT?
I DON'T CARE!
YOU NEED TO GET OUT OF HERE!
GET OUT OF HERE!
YOU'RE SO MUCH WORSE IN PERSON,
TOTES!
YOU LOOK LIKE A FURRY
WHO CAN'T COMMIT.
GET OUT OF HERE!
THE FACT IS, A HUGE AMOUNT OF
THE PLASTIC SURROUNDING US
ISN'T RECYCLED BECAUSE IT'S
NOT REALLY RECYCLABLE.
AND THAT MEANS IT ENDS UP IN
LANDFILLS, OR BURNT, OR IN THE
OCEAN, WHERE IT BREAKS DOWN INTO
"MICRO-PLASTICS," GET EATEN BY
FISH, AND CAN END UP INSIDE US.
PLASTIC IN THE OCEAN HAS A
TENDENCY TO BREAK DOWN INTO EVER
SMALLER PIECES.
AND THESE TINY PIECES THEN GET
TAKEN UP EVEN LOWER DOWN
IN THE FOOD CHAIN.
SO WE KNOW THAT IT ENDS UP ON
OUR DINNER PLATES.
THERE IS PLASTIC IN YOUR FOOD,
PLASTIC IN YOUR SEA SALT,
AND PLASTIC COMING OUT OF YOUR
TAP.
IT'S TRUE.
A RECENT STUDY EVEN ESTIMATED
THAT AN AVERAGE PERSON GLOBALLY
COULD BE INGESTING ABOUT A
CREDIT CARD'S WORTH OF PLASTIC
INTO THEIR SYSTEM EVERY WEEK.
WHICH KIND OF EXPLAINS
CAPITAL ONE'S NEW SLOGAN,
"WHAT'S IN YOUR STOMACH?"
GOOD QUESTION, MR. JACKSON.
BECAUSE APPARENTLY, IT'S
1.5% CASH BACK, A FEW THOUSAND
FREE AIRLINE MILES, AND A
FUCKING SHITLOAD OF PLASTIC.
SO HOW IS IT THAT TONS OF
PLASTIC THAT WE ASSUME IS
GETTING RECYCLED CAN INSTEAD
SOMETIMES END UP INSIDE OF US?
WELL, THAT IS WHAT THIS STORY IS
ABOUT.
IT'S ABOUT WHY SO LITTLE PLASTIC
GETS RECYCLED, THE HARM THAT
CAN DO, AND HOW THE PLASTICS
INDUSTRY HAS MANAGED TO CONVINCE
US ALL THAT IT'S OUR FAULT.
AND LET'S START WITH SOME
HISTORY.
AS PLASTIC PRODUCTION
BEGAN TO GROW IN THE 1950s,
SO DID PLASTIC WASTE, AND
THEREFORE, PUBLIC BACKLASH.
BY THE '60s AND '70s,
ORGANIZATIONS BEGAN DRAWING
ATTENTION TO ALL THE PACKAGING
WASTE LITTERING THE LANDSCAPE,
THROUGH ADS LIKE THIS ONE.
SOME PEOPLE HAVE A DEEP,
ABIDING RESPECT FOR THE NATURAL
BEAUTY THAT WAS ONCE THIS
COUNTRY.
AND SOME PEOPLE DON'T.
PEOPLE START POLLUTION.
PEOPLE CAN STOP IT.
NOW YOU MIGHT HAVE SEEN
THAT AD BEFORE.
IT REALLY TOUCHED PEOPLE'S
HEARTSTRINGS, BECAUSE APPARENTLY
THE WORST THING WHITE PEOPLE
EVER DID TO AMERICA'S INDIGENOUS
POPULATIONS WAS LITTER ON THE
FREEWAY.
BUT THERE ARE A FEW MISLEADING
THINGS ABOUT IT.
FIRST, THAT MAN WASN'T ACTUALLY
NATIVE AMERICAN... HE WAS AN
ITALIAN-AMERICAN ACTOR WHO
PLAYED THEM FOR A LIVING.
AND WHILE IT'S BY NO MEANS
THE FIRST TIME SOMEONE OF
ITALIAN DESCENT INSERTED
THEMSELVES INTO A
NATIVE AMERICAN NARRATIVE
WITHOUT ASKING, I GUESS AT LEAST
THIS TIME NO ONE NAMED A HOLIDAY
AFTER HIM.
BUT MORE TO THE POINT,
THE ORGANIZATION THAT PRODUCED
THAT AD, KEEP AMERICA BEAUTIFUL,
WAS FUNDED IN PART BY A PLASTICS
INDUSTRY TRADE GROUP, AND
COMPOSED OF LEADING BEVERAGE AND
PACKAGING CORPORATIONS.
WHICH MIGHT SEEM ODD, UNTIL YOU
REALIZE THAT THE UNDERLYING
MESSAGE THERE IS,
"IT'S UP TO YOU, THE CONSUMER,
TO STOP POLLUTION."
AND THAT HAS BEEN A MAJOR
THROUGHLINE IN THE RECYCLING
MOVEMENT... A MOVEMENT OFTEN
BANKROLLED BY COMPANIES WHO
WANTED TO DRILL HOME THE MESSAGE
THAT IT IS YOUR RESPONSIBILITY
TO DEAL WITH THE ENVIRONMENTAL
IMPACT OF THEIR PRODUCTS.
AND NOWHERE IS THIS CO-OPTING OF
ENVIRONMENTALISM CLEARER THAN
WITH THAT RECYCLING SYMBOL THAT
YOU FIND ON PLASTIC PRODUCTS YOU
BUY... THE FAMOUS "CHASING
ARROWS."
THEY ARE ON EVERYTHING,
AND THE NUMBERS INSIDE THEM ARE
PRETTY IMPORTANT, BECAUSE THEY
REPRESENT WHAT TYPE OF PLASTIC
IT IS.
NUMBER 1 STANDS FOR P.E.T.
THINK WATER AND SODA BOTTLES.
NUMBER 2 IS HDPE, OFTEN USED AS
PACKAGING FOR DETERGENT AND
SHAMPOO.
THEN, THERE'S 3, 4, 5, 6, AND
WILD CARD NUMBER 7, WHICH STANDS
FOR OTHER... MEANING EVERYTHING
ELSE.
RIGHT, NUMBER 7 IS
BASICALLY THE CATCH-ALL FOR
"EVERYTHING ELSE," IN THE SAME
WAY THAT THAT ONE DRAWER
IN YOUR KITCHEN IS A CATCH-ALL
FOR EVERYTHING.
YEAH, THERE'S KETCHUP PACKETS,
BUT ALSO, RUBBER BANDS,
THE INSTRUCTIONS TO AN IMMERSION
BLENDER YOU LOST A YEAR AGO,
AND A POST-IT NOTE WITH JUST
A PHONE NUMBER ON IT AND
NO INDICATION WHO IT BELONGS TO.
CALL THAT NUMBER!
I DARE YOU!
BUT CRUCIALLY, VERY FEW OF THOSE
SEVEN TYPES OF PLASTIC ARE
COMMONLY RECYCLABLE.
CERTAIN TYPES OF NUMBER 1 AND 2
PLASTICS... THINGS LIKE SODA AND
LAUNDRY DETERGENT BOTTLES... DO
GET RECYCLED.
ALTHOUGH, DEPENDING ON WHERE YOU
LIVE, CERTAIN OTHER TYPES...
LIKE THOSE LETTUCE TUBS YOU SAW
EARLIER... MAY NOT.
AND WHEN IT COMES TO PLASTICS
NUMBERS 3 THROUGH 7... WHICH CAN
BE THINGS LIKE PLASTIC BAGS,
CUPS, OR POUCHES... WE HAVE THE
CAPACITY TO RECYCLE LESS THAN
5% OF IT.
SO OUT OF THE SEVEN NUMBERS,
ONLY TWO ARE REALLY MUCH GOOD.
AND THAT IS A PRETTY BAD RATIO
FOR A GROUP OF SEVEN.
IDEALLY, YOU'D WANT A BALANCE
A LITTLE MORE LIKE BTS.
THERE'S NOT A WEAK LINK IN THAT
UNBREAKABLE CHAIN OF
HEARTTHROBS.
WITH SO MANY PEOPLE ONSTAGE,
YOU'D UNDERSTAND IF SOMETIMES
JIMIN ONLY GAVE 50%,
BUT HE DOESN'T, HE BEATS UP
THE DANCE FLOOR EVERY NIGHT
LIKE HE JUST CAUGHT IT
ROBBING HIS HOUSE.
AND THERE ARE A NUMBER OF
REASONS WHY CERTAIN PLASTICS
DON'T GET RECYCLED.
SOME ARE COMPLEX MIXES OF
DIFFERENT RESINS, MAKING
RECYCLING THEM DIFFICULT.
OTHER TIMES, THERE ARE PRACTICAL
OBSTACLES... THAT THE PLASTIC IS
CONTAMINATED, OR DIFFICULT TO
SORT.
AND THEN THERE ARE ECONOMIC
REASONS... SOMETIMES, THERE'S
NO MARKET FOR CERTAIN TYPES OF
PLASTIC.
AND RIGHT NOW, IT'S CHEAPER FOR
COMPANIES TO MAKE VIRGIN PLASTIC
THAN FOR THEM TO RECYCLE IT.
BUT THE THING IS, DESPITE
KNOWING THAT MOST PLASTICS
CAN'T BE RECYCLED, THE INDUSTRY
LOBBIED STATE LEGISLATURES TO
PASS LAWS REQUIRING THAT CHASING
ARROWS SYMBOL TO BE PLACED ON
ALL OF THEIR CONTAINERS,
REGARDLESS OF WHETHER THEY COULD
ACTUALLY BE RECYCLED OR NOT.
MANUFACTURERS AND COMPANIES
LIKE COCA-COLA ALSO LOBBIED
LOCAL GOVERNMENTS TO INVEST
IN CURBSIDE RECYCLING PROGRAMS,
EVEN THOUGH, BEHIND DOORS,
ONE INDUSTRY INSIDER
ACKNOWLEDGED AS FAR BACK AS 1974
THAT, "THERE IS SERIOUS DOUBT
THAT RECYCLING PLASTIC CAN EVER
BE MADE VIABLE ON AN ECONOMIC
BASIS."
AND HONESTLY, IT WASN'T ALL THAT
DIFFICULT FOR THEM TO CONVINCE
US THAT ALL THEIR WASTE IS
RECYCLABLE, BECAUSE WE SO BADLY
WANT TO BELIEVE IT.
LIES GO DOWN EASIER WHEN YOU
WANT THEM TO BE TRUE.
IN FACT, OUR DESIRE FOR THINGS
TO BE RECYCLED IS SO STRONG THAT
PEOPLE WHO WORK IN THE INDUSTRY
EVEN HAVE A SPECIAL TERM FOR IT.
A LOT OF THINGS REALLY AREN'T
RECYCLABLE, NO MATTER HOW MUCH
WE WANT THEM TO BE.
PEOPLE JUST WANT TO THROW,
YOU KNOW, EVERYTHING IN AND,
YOU KNOW, THEY WISH IT WAS
RECYCLING.
SO WE CALL IT "WISHCYCLING."
HERE'S SOME "WISHCYCLING"
FOR YOU.
HERE'S AN UMBRELLA.
I WISH IT WAS RECYCLABLE.
IT'S NOT.
NOW, FIRST OFF,
HE'S RIGHT THAT UMBRELLAS ARE
NOT RECYCLABLE, WHICH IS A PITY,
AS THE AVERAGE AMERICAN GOES
THROUGH ROUGHLY 4,000 OF THEM
A YEAR.
I'VE ALREADY SOMEHOW LOST 12
SO FAR THIS YEAR, AND IT DOESN'T
EVEN RAIN IN THIS VOID.
AND SECONDLY, THE TERM
"WISHCYCLING" IS JUST TOO GOOD
TO BE WASTED ON GARBAGE.
"WISHCYCLING" SOUNDS LIKE
A SPIN CLASS TAUGHT BY A
UNICORN, OR THE SEWAGE TREATMENT
SYSTEM AT HOGWARTS.
"AND THIS, CHILDREN, IS WHERE
WE WISHCYCLE ALL YOUR COLLECTED
URINE INTO THIS DELICIOUS
BUTTERBEER!
OH, IT'S FINE, CALM DOWN, IT'S
MAGIC, STOP CRYING, IT'S FINE."
BUT WISHCYCLING CAN END UP DOING
REAL HARM.
BECAUSE AT BEST, NON-RECYCLABLE
ITEMS CAN BE A HASSLE TO REMOVE.
PLANTS OFTEN HAVE TO STOP
MACHINES TO CUT OUT ALL OF
THE PLASTIC BAGS THAT PEOPLE
DESPERATELY WANT TO THINK THEY
CAN HANDLE.
AND AT WORST, THEY CAN END UP
CONTAMINATING LOADS OF PLASTICS
THAT COULD OTHERWISE BE
RECYCLED.
SO THE FALSE IMPRESSION WE'VE
ALL BEEN GIVEN THAT ALL
THE PLASTICS WE'RE PUTTING INTO
THE RECYCLING ARE BEING
RECYCLED IS VERY MUCH
NOT THE CASE.
AND FOR A FEW BLISSFUL DECADES,
AMERICA AND MOST OF THE WORLD
DIDN'T REALLY WORRY ABOUT THIS,
BECAUSE WE SIMPLY SHIPPED MUCH
OF THE LOWER-QUALITY PLASTIC
WASTE WE COULDN'T USE, IN BULK,
TO CHINA.
AT ONE POINT, ROUGHLY 70% OF
THE WORLD'S PLASTIC WASTE WENT
THERE.
BUT THAT STOPPED IN 2018, WHEN
CHINA FLAT-OUT BANNED THE IMPORT
OF MOST PLASTICS.
AND SINCE THEN, MUCH OF OUR
WASTE HAS BEEN LEFT TO EITHER
PILE UP IN DOMESTIC RECYCLING
PLANTS WITH NO ONE TO BUY IT OR
SHIPPED OUT TO OTHER COUNTRIES
IN ASIA, WHERE IT CAN GET
DROPPED INTO LANDFILLS, LIKE
THIS ONE IN MALAYSIA.
LOOK AT HOW BIG THIS IS.
JUST TAKE A LOOK.
LOOK HOW FAR IT GOES.
THIS IS JUST ONE DUMP.
ONE DUMP.
A VAST FIELD OF PLASTIC.
TWO STORIES HIGH.
SEE IF WE CAN LOOK ON THE
BACK HERE, "MARYSVILLE, OHIO."
THIS IS FROM ITALY,
PENNSYLVANIA, NEW YORK.
LOOK, WALMART BAG.
YEAH, A LOT OF OUR
PLASTIC JUST ENDS UP SITTING
IN GIANT LANDFILLS ON THE OTHER
SIDE OF THE WORLD.
SO I GUESS KATY PERRY'S
QUESTION, "DO YOU EVER FEEL
LIKE A PLASTIC BAG DRIFTING
THROUGH THE WIND, WANTING TO
START AGAIN?"
SHOULD REALLY BE, "DO YOU EVER
FEEL LIKE A PLASTIC WALMART BAG
DROWNING IN TWO STORIES OF
SOCIETY'S UNMITIGATED FILTH?"
AND SINCE YOU'RE ASKING... YEAH,
KATY, I DO.
ALL THE TIME.
AND THE PROBLEM IS, THOSE
COUNTRIES DON'T NECESSARILY HAVE
THE CAPABILITIES TO DEAL WITH
THEIR OWN PLASTIC WASTE, LET
ALONE MILLIONS OF TONS OF OURS.
WHICH CAN HAVE SERIOUS
CONSEQUENCES FOR THE HEALTH AND
SAFETY OF PEOPLE WHO LIVE THERE.
IN MALAYSIA, SOME OPERATIONS ARE
ILLEGALLY INCINERATING LOTS OF
PLASTIC WASTE.
AND JUST LISTEN TO THIS
COMMUNITY ACTIVIST DESCRIBING
WHAT IT'S LIKE TO LIVE NEARBY.
THE AIR POLLUTION BECOMES
VERY SERIOUS IN MY VILLAGE.
THE BURNING CAUSED A LOT OF
RESPIRATORY DISEASE PROBLEMS
TO OUR PEOPLE, ESPECIALLY OUR
CHILDREN AND OUR ELDERLY, WHO
HAS THIS PROBLEM OF REPEATING
ASTHMA, REPEATING COUGHING
ALSO.
THAT'S TERRIBLE.
AND I HAVE TO SAY, THERE'S JUST
NO WAY THAT THE PEOPLE
RESPONSIBLE FOR BURNING THAT
WASTE DON'T KNOW THE FUMES ARE
TOXIC.
WHEN YOU SMELL BURNING PLASTIC,
YOU DON'T THINK, "OOH, THAT
SMELLS GREAT.
IS SOMEONE BAKING COOKIES?"
YOU THINK, "MY NOSE SEEMS TO BE
DYING AND IT'S TAKING MY BRAIN
DOWN WITH IT."
NOW, THE GOOD NEWS IS, MORE THAN
180 COUNTRIES AGREED LAST YEAR
TO PLACE STRICT LIMITS ON
EXPORTS OF PLASTIC WASTE FROM
RICHER COUNTRIES TO POORER ONES.
THE BAD NEWS IS THAT,
THE UNITED STATES IS ONE OF THE
FEW COUNTRIES IN THE WORLD THAT
DIDN'T RATIFY THAT GLOBAL BAND.
AND THE THING IS,
WHEN PLASTIC ISN'T
BURNED, IT CAN END UP IN
LANDFILLS OR IN THE ENVIRONMENT.
ACROSS THE WORLD, MORE THAN
EIGHT MILLION TONS END UP
IN OUR OCEANS EVERY YEAR.
THERE'S FAMOUSLY EVEN A SWIRLING
GARBAGE PATCH OF MICROPLASTIC
WASTE IN THE PACIFIC OCEAN,
SPREAD OUT OVER AN AREA THAT IS
"BIGGER THAN FRANCE, GERMANY,
AND SPAIN COMBINED."
AND BY 2050, THE OCEAN IS
EXPECTED TO CONTAIN, BY WEIGHT,
MORE PLASTICS THAN FISH.
THAT IS ALL FISH.
THAT INCLUDES THE RED SNAPPER,
SALMON, AND, OF COURSE
THE BLOB FISH, THE ONLY FISH
WITH A FACE THAT SCREAMS
"I WOULD BE VOICED BY
RICHARD KIND IN A PIXAR MOVIE
AND HE WOULD ABSOLUTELY
NAIL IT."
ISN'T THAT RIGHT, BLOB FISH?
OH, ABSOLUTELY, JOHN, 100%!
I MEAN, LOOK AT ME!
I'M A BLOB FISH!
I'M SLURP THE BLOB FISH!
OF COURSE YOU'RE CALLED
SLURP!
THAT IS SOME SPOT ON CASTING
RIGHT THERE.
WELL, I'D ONLY BE A
SUPPORTING CHARACTER, BUT, LOOK,
WITH THIS FACE?
YOU KNOW DAMN WELL I'M GONNA
STEAL THE SHOW.
I KNOW YOU WILL, SLURP!
I WOULD PROVIDE COMIC RELIEF
THROUGHOUT A VERY FUN, YET
INTERMITTENTLY TOUCHING FILM.
AND WORD HAS IT THERE'S GONNA
BE AT LEAST TWO SEQUELS.
AND JOHN?
ENTRE NOUS?
YES?
I DIE AT THE END OF
THE THIRD ONE!
BUT DON'T WORRY, I'VE GOT PROFIT
PARTICIPATION!
GOOD FOR YOU, SLURP!
GET THAT MONEY.
AND FRUSTRATINGLY, THE PLASTICS
INDUSTRY'S RESPONSE TO ALL THE
DAMAGE YOU'VE SEEN HAS BEEN
TO MAKE A BIG SHOW OF TINY
IMPROVEMENTS, AND THEN REVERT
TO WHAT THEY'VE ALWAYS DONE,
WHICH IS HEAVILY PUSH THE IDEA
THAT IF WE AS CONSUMERS SIMPLY
TRIED HARD ENOUGH, WE COULD MAKE
OUR PLASTIC PROBLEM GO AWAY.
KEEP AMERICA BEAUTIFUL...
THE PEOPLE BEHIND THAT FAKE
NATIVE AMERICAN AD... IS STILL
AROUND, MAKING DUMB COMMERCIALS
LIKE THIS ONE, WHERE A BOTTLE
GOES ON A LONG, INSPIRING
JOURNEY TO A RECYCLING BIN AND
ENDS UP FULFILLING ITS DREAM OF
BECOMING A BENCH.
AND IF BOTTLES WERE SENTIENT,
I'D GENUINELY BE SURPRISED IF
THEIR BIGGEST DREAM WAS
"I WISH OLD PEOPLE WOULD PLAY
CHESS WHILE SITTING ON MY FACE."
BUT I WILL SAY, AT LEAST
THEY'RE BEING HONEST THERE THAT
THE BOTTLE BECAME A BENCH AND
THEN NOTHING ELSE.
BECAUSE THE TRUTH IS, ONLY ABOUT
2% OF ALL RECYCLED PLASTIC WINDS
UP IN A SO-CALLED CLOSED-LOOP
SYSTEM, WHERE IT BECOMES THE
THING IT ORIGINALLY WAS,
IN OTHER WORDS, A BOTTLE GETTING
RECYCLED AND BECOMING A BOTTLE
AGAIN.
INSTEAD, MOST RECYCLED PLASTIC
GETS "DOWNCYCLED" TO
BECOME A CARPET,
OR A FLEECE SWEATSHIRT, OR
INDEED, A BENCH, AND IT THEN
CAN'T BE RECYCLED AGAIN.
AND YET DESPITE THIS FACT,
COMPANIES LIKE NESTLE WATER HAVE
GONE OUT OF THEIR WAY TO MAKE
ADS INDICATING THAT IF WE JUST
DID OUR PART, PLASTICS COULD BE
PUT INTO CONTINUOUS REUSE, LIKE
THIS AD FROM 2012.
NATURE HAS A BIOLOGICAL
METABOLISM WHERE ONE THING'S
WASTE BECOMES ANOTHER THING'S
FOOD.
SO IF I LOOK AT SOMETHING LIKE
A PLASTIC BOTTLE, I DON'T SEE
WASTE, I SEE A NUTRIENT.
THIS IS RAW MATERIAL?
SO IF THIS IS RAW MATERIAL,
PEOPLE NEED TO START THINKING
ABOUT IT THAT WAY.
IT COULD COME BACK AS A
BOTTLE, OF COURSE.
WE ONLY HAVE TO MAKE THIS
VIRGIN MATERIAL ONE TIME.
AND THE REST OF IT'S UP TO YOU.
WE GET THE BOTTLE BACK, WE'LL
MAKE THIS BOTTLE OUT OF RECYCLED
CONTENT AGAIN.
WELL, THAT SOUNDS
AMAZING!
UNFORTUNATELY, WHAT THAT
EXECUTIVE BOARD KEN DOLL IS
SUGGESTING THERE IS COMPLETE
BULLSHIT.
BECAUSE NESTLE WATER DOESN'T,
IN FACT, HAVE TO MAKE VIRGIN
PLASTIC JUST "ONE TIME" IF YOU
SIMPLY GIVE YOUR BOTTLE BACK.
AND THE REASON WE KNOW THAT IS,
EVEN EIGHT YEARS AFTER THAT AD
AIRED, ONLY 20% OF THE PLASTIC
THEY USE WAS RECYCLED, MEANING
80% WAS FROM VIRGIN MATERIAL.
SO THAT'S THE MOST OBVIOUS
OVERSTATEMENT IN AN AD SINCE
THIS ONE FOR GAMEBOY IN THE '90s
THAT CLAIMED IT WAS
"MORE FUN THAN A FERRET DOWN
YOUR TROUSERS."
THAT AD IS REAL.
AND I'M SORRY, MARIO, BUT NO,
YOU'RE NOT MORE FUN.
NOT IF THE FERRET KNOWS WHAT
IT'S DOING.
AND THE CRAZY THING IS,
THAT COMPANY ACTUALLY HAS
A BETTER TRACK RECORD THAN MANY
OTHER BRANDS WHEN IT COMES TO
THIS.
THAT IS HOW BAD THINGS ARE.
TAKE COCA-COLA.
BRAND AUDITS OF OF PLASTIC WASTE
COLLECTED AT CLEANUPS HAVE
CONSISTENTLY FOUND COKE PRODUCTS
AS THE NUMBER ONE TOP GLOBAL
POLLUTER.
WHICH IS DAMNING.
AND PROBABLY WHY COKE HAS BEEN
SO ANXIOUS TO MAKE SPLASHY
PROMISES WE ALL SO BADLY
WANT TO HEAR,
LIKE PLEDGING TO USE AT LEAST
50% RECYCLED MATERIAL IN THEIR
PACKAGING BY 2030.
WHICH DOES SOUNDS REALLY GOOD.
THE PROBLEM IS, COKE HAS BEEN
MAKING AND BREAKING PROMISES
LIKE THAT FOR DECADES.
OVER THE YEARS, THEY'VE
REPEATEDLY, LOUDLY LAUNCHED BIG
RECYCLED-PLASTIC INITIATIVES
THAT THEY THEN QUIETLY
ABANDONED WITH NO ONE REALLY
NOTICING.
IN 2009, THEY ANNOUNCED PLANS
TO SOURCE 25% OF THEIR PLASTIC
FROM RECYCLED MATERIAL BY 2015.
EXCEPT YOU'LL NOTICE THAT
IT'S SIX YEARS PAST THAT
DEADLINE, AND THEIR CURRENT
PROPORTION IS JUST 10%.
SO I WOULDN'T BE SURPRISED IF,
BY 2030, THE MAIN THING COKE IS
RECYCLING IS THE SAME BULLSHIT
PROMISES IT'S BEEN MAKING FOR
YEARS.
AND LOOK, ON A PERSONAL LEVEL,
I KNOW THIS CAN FEEL
DEMORALIZING,
BECAUSE IT CAN SEEM THAT
RECYCLING IS POINTLESS.
BUT IT'S IMPORTANT TO KNOW THAT
IT'S NOT.
WE SHOULD ABSOLUTELY KEEP
RECYCLING PAPER, CARDBOARD, AND
ALUMINUM.
AND EVEN RECYCLING PLASTIC...
WHILE IT MIGHT BE 90% MORE
POINTLESS THAN YOU ASSUMED...
CAN STILL HAVE MODEST
ENVIRONMENTAL BENEFITS.
ALTHOUGH, WE SHOULD DO IT MORE
MINDFULLY... YOU SHOULD CHECK
WITH YOUR LOCAL MUNICIPALITY TO
SEE WHAT TYPES OF PLASTIC THEY
ACCEPT, AND THEN ONLY RECYCLE
THOSE.
OTHERWISE, REMEMBER, YOU COULD
END UP CONTAMINATING USABLE
MATERIALS.
AND AS A GOOD RULE, DEFINITELY
DON'T "WISHCYCLE" THINGS LIKE
UMBRELLAS, BECAUSE THERE'S A
NONZERO CHANCE THAT YOU'RE GOING
TO END UP ANGERING
TOTES McGOATS.
OH, SHIT.
NO.
ABSOLUTELY NOT.
LEAVE THIS PLACE.
NO!
BUT MORE IMPORTANTLY,
OUR PERSONAL BEHAVIOR IS
NOT THE MAIN CULPRIT HERE,
DESPITE WHAT THE PLASTICS
INDUSTRY HAS SPENT DECADES,
AND MILLIONS OF
DOLLARS TRYING TO CONVINCE US.
SO YES, WE SHOULDN'T BE USING
SINGLE-USE PLASTICS LIKE
GROCERY BAGS OR TAKE-OUT
CONTAINERS... REDUCING THAT
WOULD MAKE A HUGE DIFFERENCE, AS
NEARLY HALF OF THE PLASTIC WASTE
GENERATED GLOBALLY IN 2015 WAS
PLASTIC PACKAGING, MOST OF IT
SINGLE USE.
BUT IT CAN BE HARD, ON AN
INDIVIDUAL LEVEL, TO END THEIR
USE.
A BETTER MOVE WOULD BE TO
IMPLEMENT SMART, THOUGHTFUL,
TARGETED BANS THAT FORCE THE
INTRODUCTION OF ALTERNATIVES.
AND TO THEIR CREDIT, MANY CITIES
HAVE BANNED SINGLE-USE PLASTIC
BAGS.
UNFORTUNATELY, THE INDUSTRY HAS
FOUGHT THOSE BANS HARD,
EVEN LOBBYING SOME STATE
LEGISLATURES, TO THE
POINT THAT EIGHTEEN STATES NOW
HAVE PREEMPTIVE LAWS STOPPING
LOCAL REGULATION.
WHICH IS A BIT WEIRD.
I GUESS THOSE STATES JUST HAVE
A HARD-ON FOR PLASTIC BAGS NOT
SEEN SINCE THAT CREEPY KID FROM
"AMERICAN BEAUTY."
THE KID LOVED.
SO WHAT CAN WE REALLY DO HERE?
WELL, THE REAL BEHAVIOR CHANGE
HAS TO COME FROM PLASTICS
MANUFACTURERS THEMSELVES.
WITHOUT THAT, NOTHING
SIGNIFICANT IS GOING TO HAPPEN.
WE HAVE TO MAKE THEM INTERNALIZE
THE COSTS OF THE POLLUTION THAT
THEY ARE CREATING.
AND THERE IS A WAY TO DO THIS,
THROUGH A CONCEPT CALLED
"EXTENDED PRODUCER
RESPONSIBILITY" OR
"THE POLLUTER PAYS PRINCIPLE."
THE IDEA IS TO CREATE LAWS
THAT ESSENTIALLY SHIFT
RESPONSIBILITY, AND THE COSTS OF
COLLECTION, FROM THE PUBLIC
SECTOR AND ALL OF US TO THE
ACTUAL PRODUCERS OF THE PLASTIC
WASTE.
EPR LAWS COULD, AMONG OTHER
THINGS, FORCE COMPANIES TO
EITHER CREATE THE INFRASTRUCTURE
AND MARKETS TO RECYCLE THE
PRODUCTS THEY MAKE, OR FORCE
THEM TO STOP MAKING THEM
ALTOGETHER.
THE U.S. IS ONE OF THE ONLY
DEVELOPED COUNTRIES ON EARTH
WITHOUT A NATIONAL EPR LAW
ADDRESSING PACKAGING.
BECAUSE OF COURSE IT IS.
BUT ON THE POSITIVE SIDE,
SEVERAL STATES ARE CURRENTLY
CONSIDERING EPR LAWS, AND THERE
WAS EVEN A NATIONAL LAW
INTRODUCED IN THE LAST CONGRESS.
IT WENT NOWHERE, BUT IT'LL SOON
BE INTRODUCED AGAIN, AND WE'RE
GOING TO NEED SOME VERSION OF AN
EPR LAW TO PASS, AND SOON.
BECAUSE THIS PROBLEM'S GETTING
WORSE.
PLASTIC PRODUCTION IS EXPECTED
TO TRIPLE BY 2050.
AND IT'S OBVIOUS THAT MEANINGFUL
CHANGE IS ONLY GOING TO COME
THROUGH BEING ABLE TO FORCE
THIS VERY POWERFUL INDUSTRY TO
DO THINGS THAT IT'S SHOWN FOR
HALF A CENTURY IT HAS ABSOLUTELY
NO INTEREST IN DOING.
WE HAVE TO MAKE THEM CHANGE...
AND IF NOT FOR OUR SAKE, OR THE
SAKE OF FUTURE GENERATIONS,
LET'S AT LEAST DO IT FOR ALL
THE FISH WHO ARE ABOUT TO BE
OUTNUMBERED BY PLASTIC
IN THE OCEAN.
JUST LIKE ME!
AIN'T THAT RIGHT, JOHN?
EXACTLY, SLURP,
JUST LIKE YOU!
THAT'S OUR SHOW, THANK YOU SO
MUCH FOR WATCHING.
WE'RE OFF NEXT WEEK, SO WE'LL
SEE YOU IN TWO WEEKS' TIME.
A HIATUS?
ARE YOU FUCKING KIDDING ME?
ALREADY?
JESUS.
GOD ALMIGHTY, JOHN.
C'MON, JOHN, BUCKLE DOWN.
YOU'VE GOT MORE WRITERS THAN
THE JONESTOWN MASSACRE.
MY GOD!
SLURP, IT'S A VERY
INTENSIVE PRODUCTION.
OUR STAFF IS ENTITLED
TO A BREAK.
SEE YOU ALL APRIL 4th.
GOOD NIGHT!
HEY!
LOOK AT ME, EVERYBODY!
I KNOW WHAT YOU'RE THINKING.
YOU'RE THINKING I LOOK LIKE
SOMETHING ANOTHER FISH COUGHED
UP.
HUH?
THAT MY HEAD LOOKS LIKE A BASKET
INGREDIENT FROM "CHOPPED."
YEAH, OKAY.
TO EVERYBODY OUT THERE
ON THE INTERNET WHO SAID I LOOK
LIKE TED CRUZ, REMEMBER:
I GOT FEELINGS.
AND YOU'VE HURT THEM.
GOOD NIGHT.
I LOVE YOU ALL.
MIAMI BEACH IS THE GREATEST
AUDIENCE IN THE WORLD!
MWAH!
GOOD NIGHT!
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org