Hi ! Welcome to the show,
still taking place in this blank void,
which I've nicknamed "Henry Kissinger"
because it's white, unpleasant
and I'm just mad it's still around.
Another busy week. Netanyahu looks
like he may have lost power,
Fauci's emails were released
and the White House partnered
with Anheuser-Busch
to offer free beer
to incentivize vaccines.
"Rewarding you with beer"
really cements Joe Biden's status
as America's uncle who probably
shouldn't be left in charge.
As the vaccination rollout
continues in the US
and life slowly returns to normal,
it is worth remembering
many other countries are still very
much in the grips of this pandemic.
Take the United Kingdom,
which is currently planning
to fully reopen later this month,
even as experts warn a potential
third wave of Covid may be underway.
Demand is also growing there
for a public inquiry
into Boris Johnson's
mismanagement of the pandemic,
following testimony
in a committee hearing last week
from former top advisor
and "smug Moby", Dominic Cummings.
He revealed a chilling moment
from last March,
when top government officials
realized just how badly
the pandemic planning
had been botched.
At this point, the second most
powerful official in the country,
Helen MacNamara,
is the deputy cabinet secretary.
She walked into the office,
she says:
"I've just been talking
to the official, Mark Sweeney,"
"who is in charge of coordinating
with the Department for Health."
He said: "I've been told for years
that there is a whole plan for this."
"There is no plan.
We're in huge trouble."
Helen MacNamara said:
"I've come through here to the Prime
Minister's office to tell you all,"
quote:
"I think we are absolutely fucked."
No plan. We're in huge trouble.
I think we're absolutely fucked.
You do not expect to hear
an assessment that grim
unless it's from the team behind
the Fyre Festival
or Warner Brothers Discovery.
Hi there, new business daddy !
Just checking in to say
I absolutely love the corporate logo
you dropped this week !
It looks like the opening title
of "The Simpsons"
if the font were not found.
And quick note: "the stuff
that dreams are made of"
is a quote
from "The Maltese Falcon"
about how the thing that seemed
like a priceless treasure
was actually worthless garbage that
brought chaos and despair to everyone.
Anyway, good luck with the merger,
I'm sure everything's gonna go great !
The truth is, as bad as the details
of Cummings' testimony were,
the U.K.'s Covid response pales
next to that of Brazil's.
Because the handling of the pandemic
by its president, Jair Bolsonaro,
has been a spectacular failure,
with the country recording
over 1.9 million new cases
in the past month alone.
Brazilians are understandably fed up,
staging protests across the country.
Demonstrators want this government
to account for the negligence
in purchasing vaccines after trying
to lead Brazil towards herd immunity.
Brazilian people always got vaccinated.
It could have been the first country
with the whole population vaccinated.
Instead, we see such irresponsibility.
That woman makes a great point,
despite wearing
what I assume biologists use
to disguise themselves
while watching crocodiles fuck.
The Brazilian government
is in the midst of an inquiry
into its own negligence,
and it has uncovered some bombshells,
including that last August, Pfizer
offered Brazil's health ministry
70 million doses
of the vaccine it was developing,
but the company "got no answer".
And come on, Brazil.
You can't ghost Pfizer.
They're a company who was offering
you a potentially life-saving vaccine,
not a fruitarian entrepreneur
slash poet you met on OkCupid.
In that case,
absolutely hit "ignore".
And that shouldn't even be surprising
given how publicly dismissive
Bolsonaro's been of the vaccines.
That woman's crocodile hat
wasn't just showcasing her ability
to serve looks that are exuberant
without being obnoxious.
She was making an explicit reference
to a shitty joke Bolsonaro told,
about how companies wouldn't take
responsibility for side effects.
If you turn into a crocodile,
it's your problem.
If you turn into Superman,
if a woman grows a beard
or a man starts speaking in a high
voice, they want nothing to do with it.
That's obviously complete bullshit, but
if I may just address his insinuation
that "if the vaccine turns you into
a crocodile, that's your problem."
Honey, no. If you turn into
a crocodile, it's your solution.
Crocodiles are incredible swimmers,
they can see at night
and, instead of sweating, they do
something called "mouth gaping"
that looks a little like this.
And think how much embarrassment
that would save you on a hot day !
No pit stains on you, buddy.
Just mouth open, dick out,
swimming through life
without a care.
Because, thank fucking God,
you're a crocodile.
When you combine this new inquiry's
findings with Brazil's death rate,
it's frankly no wonder polls
now show 57 percent of Brazilians
backing Bolsonaro's impeachment.
But not only is he not backing down,
just this week, he approved this.
The country with the world's second
largest Covid-19 death toll
will host the Copa America,
welcoming South American teams
for a four week football tournament.
Yeah ! Brazil is suddenly
hosting a massive soccer tournament
on just 13 days' notice.
It was originally supposed
to be hosted by Argentina,
but it was canceled
due to Covid rates.
Despite that, Bolsonaro, whose
country's rates are higher,
is now choosing to host a tournament
one senator has dubbed
"the championship of death"
and which has inspired memes
like this to make the rounds in Brazil.
I will say, that is a pretty
cheerful little coffin.
It looks like Clippy the paperclip
popping up to ask you:
"It looks like you're about to host
a soccer tournament"
"while your country's death toll
is sky high."
"Would you like
to not fucking do that ?"
What's happening in Brazil
should be a warning for everyone,
because if vaccine misinformation
continues to spread
and variants continue to emerge,
the whole world could remain
in trouble for a very long time.
Despite how well things seem
to be going right now in the U.S.,
if we don't actively help get
this virus under control globally,
then, to quote a former
top U.K. official...
I think we are absolutely fucked.
Exactly. And now, this.
People On TV Lose Their Shit Over
The Phrase "Hot Vax Summer".
The hot vax summer. That's what they're
calling it. I can't make this up.
'Cause last summer
was hot girl summer.
- They just substituted that word.
- All right.
All vax-ed up, no place to go,
it's a hot vax summer !
I'm dressed for hot vax summer.
The hot vax summer.
- Hot vax, summer in the city.
- No !
So, a play on the "Hot Girl Summer"
from Megan Thee Stallion.
Three words: hot vax summer.
Consumers are ready to spend...
Hot vax summer. I'm telling you.
I don't know if you can tell,
I'm blushing.
Okay, Jan ? Jan ?
What are you saying ?
I'm gonna borrow that, Charles.
I love that philosophy.
It's going to be a hot vax summer.
Moving on. Our main story
tonight concerns Asian Americans.
A group that currently makes up
around 7 percent of the U.S. population
and is actually
the fastest-growing racial group,
and yet despite that, Asian Americans
can sometimes be oddly overlooked.
A survey asked respondents to simply
name a well-known Asian American
and the results were not good.
42 percent of people
said they don't know one.
The next most popular answers
were Jackie Chan,
who's from Hong Kong,
and Bruce Lee, who died in 1973.
Come on. No disrespect
to Jackie Chan and Bruce Lee there,
but that is embarrassing
even before you consider
the poll was conducted
while Kamala Harris,
who's Asian American,
was vice president.
How do you fuck up
a question that easy ?
It'd be like asking Americans
to name a well-known Joe
and getting back: "What's Joe ?"
"John Krasinski"
and "Joe Millionaire".
It is pretty clear many in this country
don't seem to know much
about the histories
or experiences of Asian Americans.
And to the extent that experience
has been discussed in recent years,
it's often been in a tragic context,
such as killings or mass shootings
or racism around the coronavirus
triggering verbal and physical attacks,
as well as the kind of idiocy
that forced local news
to have to produce pieces like:
"No, you can't get coronavirus
by eating Chinese food."
Of course you fucking can't.
You're about as likely to get
coronavirus from eating Chinese food
as you are to get chicken pox
from eating KFC.
That's not going to happen and
it's alarming anyone thought it might.
All of this has highlighted the need
to have a better-informed conversation
about the way this country
regards Asian Americans.
And before we start: I fully recognize
the history of white people on TV
generalizing confidently
about this subject isn't great,
sometimes making statements
that are offensive,
even when they think
they're being complimentary,
like this idea
that has come up constantly.
They've worked their way past
Column As and Column Bs,
past "no starch please",
to become our nation's model minority.
Listen to the numbers.
Median family income,
higher for Asians than for whites.
Super-achieving Asian American
students are becoming a phenomenon.
They are overachievers driven
to excel by tradition.
The academic achievement
of Asian American students
are so notable that in some colleges,
students warn each other
that if they end up in a class with
a lot of Oriental faces, get out.
The grading curve, they say,
will go out of sight.
It is jarring to hear, especially when
delivered with such a weird combination
of amused self-satisfaction and
totally inappropriate sourcing.
I was eavesdropping
on some teens last week
and I heard one of them say: "Never
share a cab with a Black person."
Just thought I'd pass that along.
This has been, for some reason,
the news.
But that idea, that Asian Americans
are a model minority,
has been as persistent
as it is problematic.
We thought we'd try and unpack
both parts of this sentence.
Let's start with the first half:
Asian Americans.
We're going to spend
most of our time on this term,
because it's having to do
a lot of work.
It encompasses a vast group
who can trace their heritage
back to more than 20 countries,
covering a huge amount
of the world's land mass,
from Mongolia, to Indonesia,
to Pakistan, to Japan.
Even some who fall under
the term "Asian American",
or the broader "AAPI",
which includes Pacific Islanders,
feel that it may not fit them
or that the broadness of the category
means their experiences
get erased.
People associate Asian
with East Asian.
Filipinos aren't so much dismissed,
they're just overlooked,
just because they're not as popular
within at least the American culture.
Sometimes I will identify as Asian,
but then other Indian people
don't identify as Asian.
Why are you considered Asian,
you're in the Pacific Islander,
wouldn't you be considered
more Hawaiian ? I'm like, not really !
The term "Asian American" applies
to a ridiculously large
and diverse group of people.
And there is clearly not going to be
enough time to discuss everyone
who supposedly fits
under that umbrella in this piece,
even though I do intend
to talk very fast.
Apologies in advance
to all 127 Maldivian Americans.
I promise I will make it up to my one
Maldivian American fan in the future.
I'm serious, Kareem,
stay with me, trust me on this,
you will be seen.
But the fact the term "Asian American"
is so incredibly broad
isn't an accident, it was kind
of the point from the start.
It was first coined in the late 1960s
by Asian American
student activists in California,
who went on strike alongside Black,
Hispanic, and Native American students
to demand
an ethnic studies curriculum.
In those days, the term
Asian American didn't exist.
We were all Orientals.
1968, that was the first time
that I heard the term Asian Americans.
Asian American encompasses
everybody. I thought, that's something.
People are finally starting to realize
that we wear our race on our face.
It's true. Under a system
of white supremacy,
we do tend to
"wear our race on our face".
My face is currently wearing
down market vintage colonial casual.
I'd change it into something
a little less imperial if I could,
but I can't,
so instead I wear these glasses.
For those activists, the term
"Asian American" was an attempt
to unite a massively diffuse
community in solidarity,
thus increasing their power, and,
crucially, forcing their universities
to devote resources to making sure
the histories of all their communities
were actually taught.
It was a political term,
a radical redefinition at the time.
But, it's since become a common
shorthand that can, unfortunately,
end up being used in a way that is
far too reductive and superficial,
to the point where an old
government PSA felt the need
to make a pretty obvious statement.
People always ask me
how I like America.
My great-grandfather was born here.
Like most Americans,
we've been American for a long time.
Some of us follow Asian tradition.
My family is apple pie American.
Minibikes, football, rock guitar.
All Asian Americans are no more alike
than any other kind of American.
We don't all look alike, do we ?
Well, do we ?
The fuck ?
Government money paid for that ?
Even this kid has a smirk that says:
"fucking white people".
Although, I will admit, the writer of
that PSA defining "apple pie American"
as "minibikes, football, rock guitar"
is magnificent.
It should be the oath of citizenship.
You put your hand over your heart,
say: "minibikes, football, rock guitar"
and then you never ride
a regular-sized bike again.
Why ?
Because you are an American now.
Recognizing the diversity
of Asian Americans is about much more
than simply recognizing those three
children have three different faces.
One of the main dangers of treating
Asian Americans as a single entity
is that it obscures the reality
of what is happening for
the different subgroups inside it.
For example, about 10 percent
of Asian Americans live in poverty,
which is actually "lower than
the overall U.S. poverty rate".
When you disaggregate the data,
when you break it down by subgroup,
you start to see
a much more complicated situation,
with Mongolian and Burmese Americans
having a poverty rate of 25 percent,
"more than twice
the national average."
When it comes to education, while
around 75 percent of Indian Americans
have a bachelor's degree,
well above the national average,
for Bhutanese Americans, that figure
is just 15 percent, well below it.
The point is, disaggregating the data
can reveal big disparities
that you couldn't see previously.
Looking at averages
for Asian Americans as a whole
is like looking at the average income
of the Hemsworth brothers.
It's very misleading when we all know
some hems are worth a lot more
than other hems are worth.
Using the term "Asian Americans"
to represent a political coalition
made sense, and still does,
to some extent.
But a coalition is not a monolith.
And to start to understand
some of the present day differences,
it really helps to understand
the differences in when and how
people came to this country.
You can break down those experiences
into a few broad categories,
starting with those who arrived
earlier in the 19th century
and the first half of the 20th.
Asian immigration in that time
was essentially a cycle
of economic exploitation, followed
by a violent and restrictive backlash.
This began with Chinese immigrants,
who were recruited to work
on the railroads in the 1860s.
They faced virulent racism
from the beginning,
both from their bosses,
who saw their lives as disposable,
and from whites, many of whom saw
them as unfair competition for jobs.
At the time,
this senator from California
described Chinese immigrants as
"automatic engines of flesh and blood",
making them sound like some kind
of railroad-laying terminators,
and demanded
the federal government secure
the "American Anglo-Saxon civilization
without contamination or adulteration."
And in 1882, with the Chinese
Exclusion Act, he got his wish.
The Chinese Exclusion Law
is one of the first really
comprehensively restrictive laws.
It's also the first and only time
in the history of the United States
that a group is singled out by name,
Chinese, by name,
as being undesirable.
So, this
is truly a remarkable moment.
The poster said: "Hip ! Hurrah !"
to the Chinese Exclusion Act,
and if you look at the whole thing,
it says in the middle:
"Hip ! Hurrah !
The White Man is on Top."
Which is a bit redundant.
If you've said: "Hip ! Hurrah !" twice,
you really don't need to say:
"The White Man is on Top."
It's like saying
"blue lives matter"
or "welcome
to Carrie Bradshaw's bedroom."
"The white man on top" part
is very much implied.
And America committed
to that exclusion policy.
Here is something
you might not know:
There were six Chinese men who
survived the sinking of the Titanic,
but, upon reaching U.S. shores,
were "not permitted to enter
the United States" to recover.
They were forced onto another boat
and sent away the very next day.
Which isn't just racist,
it's insensitive.
Did it really have
to be another boat ?
They had just been on the best boat
and it fucking sucked.
Could you not put them
on a zeppelin or something ?
At the very least, let's try and mix up
the doomed turn of the century
transportation methods here.
The experience of Chinese immigrants
unfortunately set the template
for the different groups
that followed.
Because waves of Japanese, Korean,
South Asian and Filipino immigrants
later came over
as agricultural workers,
with those in charge often pitting
the groups against each other
with unequal wages and treatment.
Each group faced the comon
eperience of racial hostility,
violence, and laws
denying them the possibility
of becoming citizens
or owning land.
Here is a poster
targeting Chinese people,
here is a sign targeting Japanese,
and here is one targeting Filipinos.
It's just like
the Statue of Liberty says:
"Give me your tired, your poor,
your huddled masses..."
"But not over there. Not there
either. Definitely not in Maine."
"You guys just figure it out.
The signs will make it really obvious."
No matter how long Asian Americans
or families had been in this country,
they were, as now,
treated as perpetual foreigners
whose loyalties were in question,
with the most famous example of this
being the World War II
internment camps,
where 120 000 Japanese Americans,
who'd been rounded up en masse,
were imprisoned.
And to add insult to injury, when
they were finally allowed to leave,
the U.S. government had the gall
to try and give it a positive spin.
If you don't have money enough
to get to your new location,
the government through W.R.A.
will make a grant of enough money
to get you there, and a little extra
until the paychecks start coming in.
This money
does not have to be repaid,
it's a helping hand from Uncle Sam.
It's a big moment when you start
to pack for your trip outside.
It's an even bigger moment
when you walk through the gates,
for the last time.
And present your pass to the guard
And take a look at the barbed wire
fence for the last time.
As you look at that barbed wire,
you can think "fuck you, America"
for the last time.
Go ahead. We're cool with it.
You can even say it out loud.
We'll pretend we didn't hear you
and then we'll be even.
In fact, you know what,
let's shake on that.
You can say: "fuck you, America"
one time, and then we'll be cool.
Around the middle of the last century,
attitudes began to shift
as the U.S., locked in a Cold War,
came to see exclusion laws
and racial quotas
as bad for its global image.
Laws like the Chinese Exclusion Act
went away,
to eventually be replaced
by the 1965 Immigration Act.
And this is the next broad category
of Asian American immigrants:
those who came post-1965
as a result of that act.
Because in contrast
to the previous migrants,
who were generally relegated
to low wage manual labor,
a key thing that this law did
was prioritize educated
and highly skilled workers,
like doctors and engineers.
And it also tried to address
specific labor needs,
like when a nursing shortage resulted
in overseas ads like these.
Labor recruiters and travel agencies
started targeting Filipino nurses
with ads that promised them
bright futures in America.
One particular ad featured
a basket that was decorated
with the Philippines flag.
It's addressing
the Filipino nurse saying:
"Dear nurse, if you're not happy
where you are right now", contact us
and
"we can't promise you happiness,"
"but we can help you
chase it all over the place."
I've gotta say,
that is a refreshingly honest slogan.
"You might not catch happiness,
but you can chase it !"
And it did seem to work,
as nurses are one of this country's
top imports from the Philippines,
followed closely by,
of course, Jollibee,
the world's greatest fast-food mascot.
Because believe me: unlike
American labor recruiters in the '60s,
Jollibee can promise you happiness
and deliver it to you,
in videos like this.
Yes, please. I don't know
what I love more there:
Jollibee tastefully shaking
that stinger
like it's a bottle of his signature
banana ketchup,
or the coy flutter of those naughty,
humanoid eyes. Jollibee can get it.
So, very broadly,
Asian Americans before 1965
were largely exploited for their labor
and legally discriminated against,
while after 1965, there were many
more who came as skilled workers
and who faced fewer
formal legal barriers.
Then there's the final group here,
that has less to do
with America's labor needs
and more to do
with its geopolitical interests:
those who arrived as refugees.
Between 1975 and 2010,
we took in over a million refugees
from Vietnam,
Laos and Cambodia.
Which wasn't so much generous
as it was a direct result
of people seeking refuge from wars
that America waged in the region.
We bombed their countries
to thwart the spread of communism,
sometimes in secret wars to
fulfill Henry Kissinger's napalm kink,
and then,
once we took those refugees in,
we didn't really do much
to set them up for success.
When it comes to refugees,
we hold a lot of trauma, PTSD,
a lot of mental illness
from the war and the genocide.
We have in the U.S.
with respect to our refugee policy,
this doctrine of "work first
or work immediately".
Doesn't matter
if you just came from a war zone
and haven't healed from
the mental and physical traumas of war,
we want you to get a low wage
job immediately.
And that is really the full spectrum
of the American experience, isn't it ?
To go from the U.S. not giving
a shit about your life abroad,
to not giving a shit
about your life here.
Good luck ! And by the way,
if you think you hear bombs again,
try not to freak out, it's either
a holiday half the country kinda hates
or some couple telling their friends
what gender their baby is.
Welcome to America !
Different groups of Asian Americans
had divergent migration experiences.
When you understand them more,
the variation that you see,
in everything from income
to education to health outcomes,
begins to make sense.
And yet, groups that have,
in some ways, so little in common,
often have been unified through
the common experience of bigotry,
as was the case in the early 1980s,
when America's fear
of an economically ascendant Japan
led to a racist fervor at home.
Pretty soon, the finger
of blame ended up on Japan.
All of this hatred,
you could feel it, it was palpable.
Detroiters were invited
for 50 cents a smash
to take out
their anger on Japanese cars.
That's stupid. I honestly can't think
of a good reason to beat up a car,
except maybe if Lightning McQueen
owes you money.
And to be honest, even then,
if you really want to hurt him,
you don't beat him
with a sledgehammer.
You light Mater on fire
and you make him watch.
That's what you do.
Everybody knows that.
Where is my fucking money, McQueen ?
But tragically, and unsurprisingly,
that type of resentment and blame
turned to violence,
and eventually culminated
in the murder of Vincent Chin,
a Chinese American man who was
beaten to death by two white men
who blamed him for what Japan
was doing to the U.S. auto industry.
Chin's killers
were arrested and convicted,
but the judge sentenced them
to exactly no prison time,
instead giving each of them
three years' probation
and less than 4 000 dollars in fines.
And he insisted at the time
he'd made the right decision.
Judge Charles Kaufman
says justice was done.
He would not talk to CBS News,
but he did tell a Detroit newspaper
that the two defendants were longtime,
hardworking members of the community,
adding: "These men are not going
to go out and harm somebody else."
"I just didn't think
that putting them in prison"
"would do any good
for them or for society."
It gets worse !
That judge also said:
"these weren't the kind of men
you send to jail."
And it's hard to tell what criteria
that judge used to decide
what kind of men
these two murderers were.
Was it the color of the skin
on their faces ?
The color of the skin on their hands ?
Or just judicial instinct,
a gut feeling that these two men
were, in fact, white ?
That's the thing
about the criminal justice system:
at the end of the day,
it's more race art than race science.
But the enduring legacy
of the Vincent Chin case
was that it managed to bring Asian
Americans of all ethnicities together
to call for justice.
And out of that sprang a new chapter
of Asian American activism
and political identity.
And that is just
the most famous example
of a rich history
of Asian American activism,
which has often worked
across racial lines,
from the student strike we mentioned
earlier, to Filipino labor leaders
working with Cesar Chavez
to organize a grape boycott,
to Yuri Kochiyama's friendship
with Malcolm X,
and her advocacy for marginalized
people of all backgrounds.
A prevailing narrative most people
hear regarding Asian Americans
is one of conflict between them
and other communities of color,
like during the 1992 L.A. uprising.
It's not that
those tensions aren't very real,
but it's not
the whole picture either.
It's also a narrative that fits
into a much larger pattern,
in which white America
has actively pitted Asian Americans
against other communities.
And that brings us
to the second half of this sentence,
and the "model minority" myth.
The idea of the model minority
emerged over half a century ago,
in part, because some Asian Americans
were type-casting themselves
in a bid to enhance
their demands for racial equality.
They did so by promoting
their communities
as upstanding and hardworking.
And as immigration law began selecting
for skilled and educated immigrants,
the credentials of those new arrivals
seemed to conform to the stereotype,
which then took on a life of its own,
especially in the civil rights era,
as whites unnerved by Black Americans'
radical challenges to the system,
held up Japanese and Chinese
Americans and their success
as evidence that they claimed
disproved systemic racism.
Basically, America prioritized wealthy,
more educated Asian immigrants,
then turned to Black people,
who'd been subjugated for centuries,
and said: "See ? They're educated and
successful, why aren't you ?"
Using Asian American success
to downplay American racism
is a trend that very much
continues to this day.
If America was
such a hate-filled, discriminatory,
racist society filled
with animus against Asian Americans,
how do you explain the remarkable
success of Asian Americans ?
Their mindset
is to just work really hard.
It's not to protest things
and not to shut things down.
The Asians,
the whole reason why they kick ass
is because they don't spend
any time on petty bullshit.
Asians are concerned
about hate crimes
but they're very upwardly mobile,
very success-oriented,
very business-oriented.
They're model citizens
in many cases in my view.
Probably the most admirable
ethnic group we have.
Congratulations,
Asian Americans !
Dick Morris thinks you're the most
admirable ethnic group we have.
That's so sweet of him to say.
If you want to write a thank you note,
just address the envelope
to "Shove This Right Up Dick Morris's
Ass, New York, NY,"
"Whatever ZIP Code
Dick Morris' Asshole Is In."
A central premise
of the model minority myth
is that the key
to overcoming American racism
is simply strong values
and hard work,
with the implication being
that groups that haven't succeeded,
simply haven't tried hard enough.
And putting aside
how offensive that is,
the truth is,
whether or not you're successful,
living a life defined by a racist
fantasy just isn't good for you.
Striving to maintain
the idea of a model minority
has severed my self-esteem.
It really makes me feel
that I'm nothing more
than someone
who could get good grades,
someone who was supposed to be
perfect and be mum about everything.
Trying to be perfect your whole life
is going to be too much to bear.
That is why I made a promise
when I started this show
that I'd always get one fact
in every story completely wrong.
Is that responsible ?
Absolutely not.
But it is what keeps me
looking young.
And the model minority myth
is especially galling
for some members of groups, like
those whose families came as refugees,
whose lived experience doesn't
remotely match the stereotype.
The truth is, that kind of pressure
can do real damage.
Suicide is the leading cause of death
for Asian Americans between
the ages of 15 and 24.
Only 8 percent of Asian Americans
sought help for their mental health,
which is less than half the rate
of the general population.
That is not just a result of cultural
stigmas around mental health.
It's also what happens
when you're consistently told
to quietly and happily
accept discrimination
because your version
is the "nice racism".
But there is no nice racism.
There is no silver lining to it
and there is no working
your way out of it.
You are still perpetually
treated as a foreigner,
still asked
where you're "really from"
and Asian Americans always seem
to be just one geopolitical crisis away
from becoming
the targets of violence yet again,
whether it's those internment
camps for Japanese Americans,
or the spate of attacks
on South Asians after 9/11
or all of the recent racial violence
during the pandemic.
So the model minority myth
is both a tool of white supremacy
and a trap.
As with so many things in this story,
with a community this diverse,
there are going to be different
perspectives on how to handle it.
Andrew Yang has annoyed
some by leaning into it,
with selfdeprecating jokes
and his fucking "math" hat.
He also angered many
when he responded
to the Trump administration's
"China virus" rhetoric
by writing
an op-ed in which he claimed:
"We Asian Americans need to embrace
and show our American-ness"
"in ways we never have before,"
by, among other things,
"wearing red white and blue".
That argument prompted a backlash,
with Eddie Huang tweeting:
"Fuck out of here with this America
drag... you bumbling pineapple bun".
And I do get that.
'Cause it's pretty insulting to suggest
centuries of racism could be defeated
by serving Uncle Sam realness.
So all of that is, very simplistically,
too broadly and probably too quickly,
an abridged version of how we
all got to where we are right now.
Where do we go from here ?
Well, what is clear is,
we have to find a way to have smarter,
more nuanced conversations
about the reality
of the Asian American experience.
We cannot do that without access
to high quality, disaggregated data
that can help better fit public policy
to the actual needs
of individual communities.
But that is not all.
Asian Americans have been warning
for decades about all of this.
Watch a man tell a reporter,
five years before I was even born,
what I've been trying to tell you
tonight, during yet another one
of those old
"model minority" profiles.
I suggested that compared
to the Black and the Chicano,
the Japanese American has it made.
He can get a job, a place to live.
It's a situation where I think
the question is not material,
making it in terms of economics,
but a question of human dignity.
You know what I mean
in terms of human dignity ?
We've been set in a certain
category and many people argue:
"You got a good stereotype !"
You got a stereotype that gets you
apartments where you don't have to pay
a cleaning deposit because
you're so goddamn clean !
That's our stereotype,
but it's an infringement,
it's a violation of our human dignity
'cause they don't view us
as individuals, as human beings.
We fit into a certain category,
a certain box, that's how they view us.
He's right. It's a category,
it's a box, but the thing is,
you don't learn anything from it
unless you bother to look inside.
Because obviously, no group,
community, or indeed individual,
is just one thing.
When you reduce the Asian American
experience to that of a model minority
you are omitting a history that
includes exploitation and exclusion,
but also includes activism,
some infighting,
challenges with issues
like immigration, education,
and access to social services
that continue to this day,
and interests and achievements
that go far beyond these two guys,
to be as vast and diverse
as America itself.
By the way: can you see
who's in there ? I told you, Kareem !
I told you I got your back !
I see you, Kareem !
I know this story has barely
skimmed the surface of this subject,
but I hope that it's at least
introduced some of you
to a bit
of the history involved here,
as well as what I think we can all
agree is the world's most fuckable bee.
That's our show. Thanks for watching.
We'll see you next week, good night !