♪ ♪
John: HI THERE!
WELCOME TO THE SHOW, STILL
TAKING PLACE IN THIS BLANK VOID.
AND IF YOU'RE STARTING TO ENJOY
THIS VOID AT ALL, YOU'LL LOVE
ITS SPINOFF SERIES,
"YOUNG VOID," COMING EXCLUSIVELY
TO HBO MAX.
YES, HBO MAX: THERE'S A NEW
MOVIE EVERY MONTH!
THIS MONTH, IT'S... OH, FUCK ME.
LOOK, IT'S BEEN A BUSY WEEK,
FROM THE HORROR SHOW OF CPAC TO
JOE BIDEN GIVING M.B.S. A PASS
OVER THE MURDER OF
JAMAL KHASHOGGI, TO THE POST
OFFICE UNVEILING ITS NEW
DELIVERY TRUCK, WHICH LOOKS LIKE
THE STAR OF A CHILDREN'S BOOK
WHO THINKS IT CAN, BUT CAN'T.
BUT WE'RE ACTUALLY GOING TO
START RIGHT HERE AT HOME, WITH
NEW YORK'S GOVERNOR,
ANDREW CUOMO.
A MAN WHOSE FACE, BUILD, AND
GENERAL DEMEANOR ALWAYS SEEMS TO
SCREAM "BUSINESS FRANKENSTEIN."
CUOMO HAS BEEN IN SOME HOT WATER
LATELY.
THIS MORNING, NEW YORK
GOVERNOR ANDREW CUOMO'S
ADMINISTRATION IS UNDER FEDERAL
SCRUTINY FOR ITS HANDLING OF
COVID-RELATED FATALITY DATA AT
NURSING HOMES.
THE FALLOUT COMES AFTER A
76-PAGE REPORT FROM NEW YORK'S
ATTORNEY GENERAL LAST MONTH
REVEALED THE STATE HAD BEEN
UNDERREPORTING DEATHS IN NURSING
HOMES AND LONG-TERM CARE
FACILITIES BY AS MUCH AS 50%.
John: UNDERREPORTING NURSING
HOME DEATHS... YOU'D EXPECT THAT
LESS FROM A TRANSPARENT
DEMOCRACY, AND MORE FROM AN
AUTHORITARIAN REGIME LIKE NORTH
NORTH KOREA, WHICH
TO THIS DAY HAS YET TO REPORT
A SINGLE CASE OF CORONAVIRUS.
I ASSUME THEIR STATE MEDIA IS
CLAIMING THAT THE VIRUS WAS
REPELLED FROM THE COUNTRY AFTER
KIM JONG-UN BREATHED FIRE ON IT.
THIS SCANDAL STEMS FROM A
DIRECTIVE CUOMO MADE LAST MARCH,
TELLING NURSING HOMES TO ACCEPT
COVID-POSITIVE PATIENTS
TO FREE UP HOSPITAL BEDS.
THAT WOULD BE BAD ENOUGH, BUT
SINCE THEN, HIS ADMINISTRATION
HAS TRIED TO DOWNPLAY ANY
CONSEQUENCES OF THAT ACTION...
RELEASING A REPORT LAST JULY
THAT LAID THE BLAME ON
NURSING HOME STAFFERS FOR
INFECTING RESIDENTS, AND,
AS A CUOMO AIDE RECENTLY TOLD
LAWMAKERS, ACTIVELY CONCEALING
DATA ON COVID DEATHS OUT OF FEAR
IT'D BE USED AGAINST THEM BY
FEDERAL PROSECUTORS.
THAT REVELATION, UNDERSTANDABLY,
SET OFF A FIRESTORM.
AND AFTER A DEMOCRATIC
LEGISLATOR, RON KIM, MADE A
STATEMENT ABOUT IT TO THE PRESS,
HE SAYS HE GOT A CALL FROM CUOMO
THAT WENT ABOUT AS WELL AS YOU
MIGHT EXPECT.
THE GOVERNOR ASKED ME TO
ISSUE A STATEMENT THAT COUNTERED
WHAT I HEARD IN THE MEETING AND
ESSENTIALLY COVER UP THE
COVER-UP.
HE SPENT 10 MINUTES BERATING ME,
THREATENING ME TO END MY CAREER
IN FRONT OF MY FAMILY, IN FRONT
OF MY KIDS.
John: YEAH, NOT GREAT.
NOW, I HAVE TO SAY,
CUOMO HAS DENIED KIM'S ACCOUNT
OF THAT CALL.
BUT YOU SHOULD KNOW, MANY, MANY
PEOPLE WHO'VE DEALT WITH CUOMO
IN THE PAST HAVE SAID IT SOUNDS
EXACTLY LIKE HIM.
AND THAT REPUTATION ALONE
GOES A LONG WAY.
BE HONEST, IF YOU SAW A HEADLINE
TOMORROW THAT SAID, "LEAKED MEMO
SHOWS JOHN OLIVER ASKED STAFF
IF BIRD HE SAW IN CENTRAL PARK
HAD AN ONLYFANS PAGE,"
YOU'D BELIEVE IT.
EVEN IF I DENIED THE ACCOUNT OF
THAT CONVERSATION, DEEP DOWN,
YOU'D KNOW IT HAPPENED, BECAUSE
IT JUST SOUNDS LIKE SOMETHING
I'D DO.
AND CUOMO IS FAMOUSLY
UNPLEASANT.
HE REPORTEDLY HAS A
"DO-NOT-YELL-AT" LIST,
WHICH A FORMER AIDE APPARENTLY
ADMITTED IS VERY SMALL.
AND JUST THIS WEEK,
A DIFFERENT FORMER AIDE ACCUSED
HIM OF SEXUAL HARASSMENT,
A CLAIM HE DENIES.
ALTHOUGH, ON THE SAME DAY THAT
STORY BROKE, CUOMO WAS AT A
VACCINATION SITE, AND COULDN'T
HELP HIMSELF FROM JOKING ABOUT
VACCINATING THIS STATE SENATOR.
I'M GOING TO BE DOING
THE VACCINATION.
I GET TO SELECT THE PART OF THE
ANATOMY WHERE I DO THE VACCINE.
AND YOU'LL BE SURPRISED, OR
MAYBE NOT, WHEN YOU SEE THE PART
OF THE ANATOMY THAT I PICK.
John: IS IT HIS PENIS,
ANDREW?
ARE YOU GOING TO VACCINATE HIM
IN THE PENIS?
BECAUSE I'LL BE HONEST, I WOULD
ACTUALLY BE SURPRISED IF YOU
WANTED TO VACCINATE HIM IN THE
PENIS.
THE VEIN IS HARD TO FIND.
PRACTITIONERS GENERALLY
RECOMMEND THE NON-DOMINANT ARM
AND ALSO, WHAT THE FUCK IS WRONG
WITH YOU?
EVEN BEFORE THE CURRENT
SCANDALS, THERE WAS SOMETHING
GROSS ABOUT CUOMO'S GLEE IN HIS
PUBLIC ADULATION LAST YEAR,
FROM HIS CONSTANT APPEARANCES
WITH HIS BROTHER ON CNN,
TO HIM CO-SIGNING ON THE TERM
"CUOMOSEXUALS"... THE ONLY
SEXUAL ORIENTATION, BY THE WAY,
IT'S COMPLETELY ACCEPTABLE TO
DISCRIMINATE AGAINST.
TO THE BOOK HE PUBLISHED LAST
OCTOBER ABOUT THE LESSONS
HE'D LEARNED FROM HANDLING THE
STILL-ONGOING PANDEMIC,
WHICH WERE PRESUMABLY:
"1: DO PRESS CONFERENCES."
"2: THE END."
AND THOSE PRESS CONFERENCES
WHERE CUOMO LOVED TO INSIST ON
THE IMPORTANCE OF FACTS NOW PLAY
A LITTLE DIFFERENTLY, AFTER
EVERYTHING WE'VE LEARNED.
ESPECIALLY MOMENTS LIKE THIS.
"FOLLOW THE FACTS, THEY WILL
SHOW YOU THE WAY,"
A.J. PARKINSON.
THAT'S WHAT WE'VE BEEN DOING IN
NEW YORK, FOLLOWING THE FACTS.
John: OKAY, THE THING IS,
IT'S HARD TO FOLLOW THE FACTS
IF THE PEOPLE IN CHARGE OF THOSE
FACTS ARE ACTIVELY WITHHOLDING
THEM FROM YOU.
AS FAR AS ADVICE GOES, THAT'S
BASICALLY AS USEFUL AS A BULLY
SAYING "STOP HITTING YOURSELF,"
IN THAT IN BOTH CASES, YEAH,
I'D ACTUALLY REALLY LIKE TO.
THE THING IS, SOME ASSHOLE WON'T
LET ME.
AND YOU MAY'VE NOTICED THAT HE
WAS QUOTING SOMEONE NAMED
A.J. PARKINSON THERE.
THAT IS SOMETHING HE DOES A LOT.
REMEMBER, "TEXTBOOKS SAY
POLITICIANS LEAD AND THE PEOPLE
FOLLOW.
NO, IT IS OFTEN THE PEOPLE WHO
LEAD AND THE POLITICIANS WHO
FOLLOW," A.J. PARKINSON.
A.J. PARKINSON, GREAT QUOTE,
"I RESPECT ELECTED OFFICIALS WHO
AREN'T TYPICAL POLITICIANS."
"DON'T PASS THE BUCK WITHOUT
PASSING THE BUCKS,"
A.J PARKINSON.
A.J. PARKINSON.
A.J. PARKINSON SAID THAT.
John: NOW, IF YOU'RE
CURRENTLY THINKING, "OH, NO,
AM I SUPPOSED TO KNOW WHO
A.J. PARKINSON IS?"
DON'T WORRY, HE'S NOT A FAMOUS
HISTORICAL FIGURE THAT YOU
LEARNED ABOUT IN SCHOOL, LIKE
PLATO, OR JANE AUSTEN,
OR JAMES JOYCE.
ALTHOUGH, IN FAIRNESS, YOU
DIDN'T LEARN MUCH ABOUT THEM
EITHER, CONSIDERING YOU DIDN'T
REALIZE THAT THAT'S ACTUALLY
SOCRATES, THAT'S EMILY
DICKINSON, AND THAT'S
T.S. ELIOT.
BUT THE POINT IS, IT'S ACTUALLY
COMPLETELY FINE NOT TO BE
FAMILIAR WITH A.J. PARKINSON,
BECAUSE HE DOESN'T EXIST.
HE'S A COMPLETELY MADE UP
PERSON.
APPARENTLY, BY CUOMO'S DAD,
FORMER GOVERNOR AND KEVIN SPACEY
COSPLAYER MARIO CUOMO.
HE USED TO INVOKE THE NAME OF
A.J. PARKINSON AS AN INSIDE JOKE
WITH THE PRESS.
AND WHILE THAT MAY HAVE BEEN
CHARMING AT THE TIME,
THE CURRENT CUOMO DOING IT
DURING A PANDEMIC WHEN VIRTUALLY
NO ONE GETS THAT IT'S A JOKE IS
A PRETTY WEIRD MOVE.
IF YOU'RE TRYING TO LIGHTEN THE
MOOD, THERE ARE SO MANY OTHER
REAL QUOTES YOU COULD HAVE GONE
WITH.
FOR EXAMPLE, NICKI MINAJ'S
TWEET, "OKAY, BOYS, WHAT'S YOUR
BALL SIZE?"
SURE, NOT APPROPRIATE FOR THE
OCCASION, BUT AT LEAST SHE'S
A REAL PERSON.
OH, AND FOR THE RECORD, NIKKI,
THE ANSWER IS: SURPRISINGLY
DECENT-SIZED.
I CALL THEM THE HEMSWORTH
BROTHERS, BECAUSE THEY LOOK
GREAT AND EVERYONE'S SURPRISED
THERE'S A THIRD ONE.
AND LOOK, CIRCULATING
FAKE QUOTES IS OBVIOULY NOT
THE WORST THING CUOMO'S DONE.
THAT IS BECOMING INCREASINGLY
CLEAR.
BUT IT DOES FEEL LIKE
A PRETTY APT METAPHOR FOR
AN ADMINISTRATION THAT HAS
AGGRESSIVELY MANAGED FACTS
TO FIT ITS CHOSEN REALITY.
AND IT ACTUALLY BRINGS TO MIND
ANOTHER INSIGHTFUL SAYING:
"ANDREW CUOMO IS A COLOSSAL
ASSHOLE."
IT'S FROM AN EXCELLENT WRITER
NAMED T.J. PIMPERNICKLE.
AND I'LL TELL YOU EXACTLY TWO
THINGS ABOUT T.J. PIMPERNICKLE:
ONE, HE IS A PERSON I TOTALLY
MADE UP, AND TWO, HE'S ALSO
COMPLETELY RIGHT ABOUT
ANDREW CUOMO.
AND NOW, THIS.
♪ ♪
Announcer: AND NOW...
DID FOX BUSINESS' LIZ CLAMAN
MENTIONED THAT SHE LIKES
PELETON?
IF YOU JUST LOOK AT PELETON,
FOR EXAMPLE, I HAVE ONE, I LOVE
IT.
I HAVE A PELETON.
I LOVE IT AND I USE IT A LOT.
I WANT TO GIVE YOU AN ANECDOTE
HERE.
I DO HAVE A PELETON.
I HAVE A PELETON.
LUCKY ENOUGH TO HAVE A
PELETON.
OF COURSE SHE HAS A PELETON.
LET'S LOOK AT PELETON STOCK.
IT IS POPPING RIGHT NOW.
I AM PART OF THAT COMMUNITY.
I GOT IT FOR MY BIRTHDAY COUPLE
OF YEARS AGO.
THAT WAS MY BIRTHDAY PRESENT.
A SPEAKER MY HUSBAND GAVE ME A
PELETON FOR MY BIRTHDAY TWO
YEARS AGO.
DIDN'T YOU GET A PELETON
BIKE?
TWO YEARS AGO FOR MY
BIRTHDAY.
THE STOCK IS UP.
I PERSONALLY ATTRIBUTED TO MY
FAVORITE INSTRUCTOR, CODY.
TAKING MY FAVORITE CLASS.
MAYBE ONE DAY I CAN SIT NEXT TO
CODY AND DO A LITTLE CLASS ONCE
THIS WHOLE THING IS OVER.
YOU GOT TO UNDERSTAND, I LOVE ME
SOME JENNA SHERMAN AND CODY AND
HANNAH.
AND FIVE TO TEN YEARS, THOSE
PELOTON MACHINES ARE GOING TO BE
SITTING IN THE GARAGE AND WON'T
SELL VERY WELL AT THE GARAGE
SALE.
YEAH, I DON'T KNOW.
I AM A BIG PELETON FAN.
♪ ♪
John: MOVING ON.
OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT CONCERNS
POLICING.
IT'S ONE OF TV'S FAVORITE
SUBJECTS, FROM
"HILL STREET BLUES" THROUGH
"LAW & ORDER" THROUGH THIS:
DO YOU THINK THE COPS HAVE
TOO MUCH POWER?
DO YOU THINK THEY USED EXCESSIVE
FORCE?
TELL US, WAS YOUR LIFE IN
DANGER?
DOES THIS MAKE YOU FEEL ANY
REMORSE?
ARE YOU PART OF ORGANIZED
OUTCRY?
ARE YOU ACTING ON YOUR OWN?
WOULD YOU AGREE THIS CASE HAS
RACIAL OVERTONES?
John: NOW, YOU'RE PROBABLY
JUST CURRENTLY SHOUTING, "WHAT?"
INCREASINGLY LOUDLY.
SO LET ME EXPLAIN: THAT'S A
SCENE FROM "COP ROCK," A VERY
REAL MUSICAL COP SHOW THAT
PREMIERED ON ABC IN 1990 AND
LASTED EXACTLY 11 EPISODES.
THINK OF IT LIKE IF
"PITCH PERFECT" CRASHED INTO
"THE WIRE" AND THERE WERE
ABSOLUTELY NO SURVIVORS.
I'D SAY THAT WAS THE BEST WORST
THING I'VE EVER SEEN ON TV, BUT
THE THING IS, I HAVE SEEN MORE
"COP ROCK."
THERE'S A SUBPLOT ABOUT
CHILD-SELLING!
AND IF YOU ARE WONDERING, DOES
THE CHILD SELLER SING?
YEP!
I'M THE BABY MERCHANT!
TOTS 'R' US.
I'LL GIVE YOU ALL THE SERVICE
AND NO DAMN FUSS.
GIVE THE BABY MERCHANT
JUST A WEEK OR TWO.
I'LL HAVE A BABY FOR YOU.
John: THAT SONG IS THREE
MINUTES LONG AND THEY NEVER DO
ANYTHING ELSE.
THAT COUPLE JUST STANDS THERE
WHILE A MAN INFORMS THEM THAT
HE'S THE BABY MERCHANT FOR
THREE HUMAN MINUTES.
THAT SHOW WAS ON TELEVISION
IN AMERICA.
BUT AS LONG AS WE'VE BEEN
QUESTIONING ON TV WHETHER
POLICING HAS... AND I APOLOGIZE
FOR EVEN ATTEMPTING THIS...
"RACIAL OVERTONES," WE'VE MADE
VERY LITTLE PROGRESS TOWARDS
ACTUALLY ADDRESSING THAT ISSUE.
AS WE'VE DISCUSSED BEFORE,
THE PAST AND PRESENT OF POLICING
IN AMERICA IS VERY MUCH TIED UP
WITH RACISM.
AND WE WANT TO FOCUS ON ONE AREA
OF POLICING IN PARTICULAR
TONIGHT: POLICE RAIDS.
IT'S A PRACTICE THAT ATTRACTED
A LOT OF ATTENTION LAST YEAR IN
THE WAKE OF THE BREONNA TAYLOR
CASE.
SHE WAS KILLED AFTER OFFICERS
BROKE DOWN HER DOOR IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE NIGHT AND
FIRED 32 SHOTS INTO HER HOME.
A YEAR LATER, NONE OF THESE
OFFICERS HAVE BEEN INDICTED FOR
CHARGES RELATING TO HER DEATH.
AND IF IT IS SOMEHOW NOBODY'S
FAULT THAT AN INNOCENT WOMAN
WAS KILLED IN THE MIDDLE OF
THE NIGHT IN HER OWN HOME,
THERE MIGHT BE AN ISSUE WITH
POLICE RAIDS.
DATA ON THEM IS SCARCE, SO IT'S
HARD TO SAY HOW MANY TAKE PLACE
IN AMERICA, BUT ESTIMATES PUT
IT IN THE TENS OF THOUSANDS
PER YEAR.
AND THEY CAN BE CARRIED OUT BY
ALMOST ANYONE IN LAW ENFORCEMENT
...FROM FEDERAL AGENTS, TO
S.W.A.T. TEAMS WITHIN POLICE
DEPARTMENTS, TO DETECTIVES,
AND PATROL OFFICERS.
AND WHILE THESE TACTICS WERE
INITIALLY INTENDED FOR
LIFE-OR-DEATH SCENARIOS, LIKE
ACTIVE SHOOTERS OR HOSTAGE
SITUATIONS, ONE ANALYSIS FOUND
THAT ONLY 7% OF SWAT DEPLOYMENTS
MET THAT CRITERIA, WHILE MORE
THAN 60% OF THE CASES INVOLVED
SEARCHES FOR DRUGS.
AND THAT SHIFT WAS THE RESULT OF
INTENTIONAL POLICY CHOICES.
POLICE RAIDS WERE SUPERCHARGED
BY THE WAR ON DRUGS, AND THE
TACTIC BECAME SO POPULAR THAT
GERALDO RIVERA EVEN PRODUCED
A SPECIAL WHERE HE SHOWED YOU
RAIDS HAPPEN IN REAL TIME.
THIS IS REAL LIFE, THE FIRST
IN A SERIES OF RAIDS WE'LL BE
SHOWING YOU THIS EVENING.
IN THIS ONE, MEMBERS OF THE
SAN DIEGO POLICE DEPARTMENT ARE
RAIDING A SO-CALLED CRACK HOUSE,
WHERE PUSHERS SELL COCAINE TO
PEOPLE IN THIS NEIGHBORHOOD.
FOR THE PAST SIX MONTHS, WE HAVE
COVERED THE STREET COPS WHOSE
JOB IS TO RIP AND TEAR AND POUND
THEIR WAY INTO THE NATION'S
CRACK-HOUSES AND SHOOTING
GALLERIES.
AND WE HAVE GONE UNDERCOVER TO
EXPOSE THE PUSHERS WHO PROFIT
FROM THIS DIRTY BUSINESS.
John: WOW.
THEY ALL SEEM TO BE HAVING FUN
THERE, FROM THE OFFICERS'
MAD DASH LIKE IT'S BLACK FRIDAY
AND WALMART HAS A SALE ON
MARIJUANA, TO GERALDO'S
RIDICULOUS DISGUISE, WHICH LOOKS
LIKE THE PRINGLES GUY
AUDITIONING FOR "MIAMI VICE."
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, THAT'S
STILL BETTER THAN HIS CURRENT
LOOK, WHICH ANSWERS THE
QUESTION, WHAT IF EVERY SINGLE
"BATMAN" JOKER WERE ROLLED INTO
ONE?
AND RAIDS CAN OBVIOUSLY HAVE
DIRE CONSEQUENCES.
A "TIMES" INVESTIGATION FOUND
THAT, FROM 2010 TO 2016,
AT LEAST 81 CIVILIANS WERE
KILLED IN THEM.
AND THESE TACTICS ARE RARELY
PROPORTIONAL TO THE ALLEGED
CRIMES BEING TARGETED.
IN LOUISVILLE, BREONNA TAYLOR'S
HOME, A YEAR AND A HALF BEFORE
THE RAID THAT KILLED HER, THIS
HAPPENED.
THIS POLICE BODY CAMERA VIDEO
SHOWS LMPD SWAT OFFICERS
BREAKING INTO DAUGHERTY AND
BURR'S HOUSE ON WEST CHESTNUT
STREET.
HURRY UP, COME ON, PUT YOUR
HANDS UP!
THE COUPLE AND THEIR THREE
CHILDREN, WHO WERE UNDER THE AGE
OF 16 AT THE TIME, CLAIM THEY
WERE HELD AT GUNPOINT THE
MORNING OF OCTOBER 26TH, 2018.
17 SWAT OFFICERS BURST IN
BECAUSE A DETECTIVE SMELLED
MARIJUANA COMING FROM THE
FAMILY'S HOME.
John: HE "SMELLED MARIJUANA."
COME ON!
IF YOU JUST "SMELL MARIJUANA,"
YOU DON'T SHOW UP WITH LOADED
ASSAULT RIFLES LIKE YOU'RE IN
"CALL OF DUTY."
YOU SHOW UP WITH
"SETTLERS OF CATAN" AND $50
WORTH OF COOKIES FROM SUBWAY.
DON'T BE SUCH FUCKING SQUARES.
AND THE THING IS, ABSURDLY
DISPROPORTIONATE AND DANGEROUS
RESPONSES ARE BASICALLY PAR FOR
THE COURSE WHEN IT COMES TO
POLICE RAIDS.
SO TONIGHT, LET'S TALK ABOUT
THEM... WHY THEY'RE SUCH
A FAVORED TOOL OF POLICE,
WHY THEY REALLY SHOULDN'T BE,
AND WHAT WE SHOULD DO ABOUT
THAT.
AND LET'S START WITH WHAT YOU
PROBABLY KNOW ALREADY, WHICH IS
THAT NOT ALL OF US ARE AT EQUAL
DANGER OF BEING RAIDED.
WHEN CBS 2 IN CHICAGO DID AN
INVESTIGATION OF SEVERAL YEARS'
WORTH OF SEARCH WARRANTS,
THEY FOUND THAT CERTAIN
NEIGHBORHOODS TENDED TO BE HIT
A LOT MORE OFTEN THAN OTHERS.
ENGLEWOOD HAD 872
SEARCH WARRANTS.
ALSO IN THE TOP FIVE
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE AUSTIN
WITH 668, NORTH LAWNDALE, 455,
GARFIELD PARK, 442, AND
HUMBOLDT PARK WITH 376.
CENSUS DATA SHOWS THESE
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE ALL NEARLY
90% OR MORE BLACK AND LATINO.
WE FOUND ONLY A SMALL PERCENTAGE
HAPPEN IN WHITE NEIGHBORHOODS
AND NONE LISTED FOR EDISON PARK,
PRINTERS ROW, WRIGLEYVILLE,
MUSEUM CAMPUS,
AND MAGNIFICENT MILE.
John: YEAH, THAT'S ABOUT
AS FUCKED AS YOU'D EXPECT.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, YOU DIDN'T
HAVE TO TELL ME THOSE
NEIGHBORHOODS ARE
PREDOMINANTLY WHITE.
BECAUSE EDISON PARK,
MUSEUM CAMPUS, AND
MAGNIFICENT MILE ARE SOME OF
THE WHITEST SOUNDING PLACE NAMES
I'VE EVER HEARD.
RIGHT UP THERE WITH ALABASTER
PRIM, SPF-50-VILLE, AND VERMONT.
AND THAT RACIAL DISPARITY
HAS BEEN FOUND AGAIN AND AGAIN.
IN LOUISVILLE, AN EXAMINATION
FOUND SEARCH WARRANTS
DISPROPORTIONATELY TARGETED
BLACK RESIDENTS, AND A STUDY
OF ONE YEAR OF WARRANTS IN
WASHINGTON, D.C. FOUND THEY WERE
ALMOST EXCLUSIVELY EXECUTED IN
BLACK COMMUNITIES.
AND POLICE HAVE BEEN GIVEN TOOLS
TO CARRY OUT THOSE WARRANTS WITH
INCREASING FORCE.
POLICE DEPARTMENTS HAVE BECOME
HEAVILY MILITARIZED AFTER EITHER
PURCHASING OR JUST BEING HANDED
MILITARY EQUIPMENT.
AND SOME DON'T EVEN TRY TO HIDE
HOW MUCH THEY ENJOY USING IT.
JUST LISTEN TO THIS OFFICER
INTRODUCE ONE OF HIS TOYS IN A
CAREER DAY LIVESTREAM FOR KIDS.
WE CALL THIS THE BIG BAD
WOLF.
BECAUSE WITH ENOUGH FORCE,
I CAN TAKE THIS RAM ON THE FRONT
OF THIS VEHICLE AND I CAN PUT IT
AGAINST A BRICK HOUSE AND I CAN
GO RIGHT THROUGH THAT BRICK.
AND I CAN COME RIGHT IN
YOUR HOUSE IF I NEED TO.
NOT YOUR HOUSE, BECAUSE ALL
OF YOU ARE GOOD KIDS.
WE ONLY DO IT FOR THE BAD KIDS.
John: OH, YOU DO, DO YOU?
WELL, THAT'S REASSURING.
WE'VE CERTAINLY GOT NO REASON
NOT TO TRUST YOU TO DETERMINE
WHO'S A GOOD KID AND A BAD KID.
YOU'RE JUST A NICE, TALKATIVE
GUY WHO, APPARENTLY, ROOTS FOR
THE WOLF IN THE STORY OF THE
THREE LITTLE PIGS.
"IF ONLY THE WOLF HAD POSSESSED
MILITARY GRADE EQUIPMENT,"
YOU SAY AS YOU TUCK YOUR
CHILDREN IN AT NIGHT.
"FORTUNATELY, YOUR GOD-LIKE
FATHER HAS NO SUCH LIMITATIONS
ON HIS POWERS.
SLEEP TIGHT, GOOD KIDS!"
NOW, THERE ARE IMPORTANT
QUESTIONS OVER WHETHER OR NOT
POLICE OFFICERS REALLY NEED
ACCESS TO THAT KIND OF
EQUIPMENT, JUST AS THERE ARE
QUESTIONS OVER WHAT MESSAGES
THEY TAKE AWAY FROM SOME OF
THE TRAINING THEY RECEIVE.
TAKE A LOOK AT ONE PARTICULARLY
EXTREME EXERCISE FOR
S.W.A.T. TEAM MEMBERS.
THE CULT LEADER REALIZES
THAT THEY GOT AN ARMORED VEHICLE
GOING TO START.
HE GOES, OKAY, LET'S PULL
THE TRIGGER, SENDS OUT THE RPG,
AND THEN THEY START EXECUTING
PEOPLE.
OH, MY GOD.
IT'S REALLY A MASS SUICIDE.
BUT IN FACT, IT'S REALLY A
MURDER SUICIDE.
NONE OF THE SCENARIOS WE SAW
LEFT MUCH ROOM FOR NONVIOLENT
SOLUTIONS.
AND THEN BACK IN HERE,
THE CULT LEADERS BASICALLY
SYSTEMATICALLY EXECUTING BABIES.
SHOW ME YOUR HANDS,
SHOW ME YOUR HANDS!
WHEN THE AMOUNT OF HOURS
YOU SPEND AT THE SHOOTING RANGE
OUTNUMBER THE NUMBER OF HOURS
YOU SPEND LEARNING CONFLICT
RESOLUTION BY, YOU KNOW,
10 OR 15 TO ONE, YOU'RE GOING TO
BE MORE LIKELY TO USE THE TOOL
THAT YOU'VE TRAINED MORE WITH.
John: YEAH, NO SHIT!
BECAUSE LOOK, I'M NOT SAYING
THEY SHOULDN'T BE PREPARED FOR
CULT LEADER BABY MURDER.
BUT HOW MANY CULT LEADER
BABY MURDERS DO THEY THINK
THEY'RE GOING TO BE CALLED TO
EVERY YEAR?
AND I KNOW WHAT YOU'RE THINKING,
"BUT JOHN, IF THERE IS A BABY
MURDER CULT, HOW ARE WE GOING
TO REPLACE ALL THOSE BABIES?"
DON'T WORRY.
I'M PRETTY SURE I KNOW A GUY
WHO CAN HELP.
I'M THE BABY MERCHANT!
TOTS 'R' US.
John: SERIOUSLY.
IT'S THREE MINUTES LONG.
IT'S SO WEIRD.
I'M NOT SAYING YOU SHOULD SEEK
IT OUT, I'M JUST SAYING,
YOU DO NEED TO KNOW IT EXISTS.
THE OBVIOUS DANGER OF FOSTERING
A MILITARIZED POLICE CULTURE
THAT TRAINS AND EQUIPS OFFICERS
LIKE THEY'RE THE LEAD IN AN
ACTION MOVIE IS THAT IT CAN
ENCOURAGE THEM TO THEN ACT
THAT WAY.
TAKE A LOOK AT A RAID THAT
TOOK PLACE IN LITTLE ROCK.
HERE, THE POLICE BLOW OPEN THE
DOOR OF THE APARTMENT BELONGING
TO A MAN NAMED RODERICK TALLEY,
BECAUSE THEY FALSELY BELIEVED
HE WAS SELLING COCAINE.
BUT DESPITE NOT FINDING ANY,
WHEN THEY REALIZED HE HAD
A HOME SECURITY CAMERA, THEY
ASKED HIM... WHILE HE WAS STILL
CUFFED TO A CHAIR... IF THEY
COULD REWATCH THE FOOTAGE OF
THEIR RAID, SO THEY COULD SEE
HOW IT LOOKED.
THAT'S AWESOME, I'M GONNA
RECORD THAT REAL QUICK.
CAN YOU PLAY IT BACK AGAIN?
THAT WAS WORTH COMING TO WORK
FOR.
ONE MORE TIME.
WE AIN'T LAUGHING AT YOU,
THOUGH.
John: YEAH, DON'T WORRY,
WE'RE NOT
LAUGHING AT YOU, WE'RE JUST
HIGH-FIVING OURSELVES FOR
HOW COOL IT LOOKED WHEN WE BLEW
YOUR DOOR IN.
BUT YOU GET IT!
YOU WERE THERE!
BY THE WAY, THANKS FOR BEING
SUCH A GOOD SPORT ABOUT THIS,
EVEN THOUGH WE DO ALL HAVE GUNS
SO YOU KIND OF HAVE TO BE!
THIS JOB IS FUN!
AND POLICE MIGHT TELL YOU THAT,
THEY DON'T JUST USE GUNS, THEY
ALSO HAVE SUPPOSEDLY NONLETHAL
TOOLS OUT THERE TO EXPOSURE.
BUT EVEN THEN, THERE CAN BE
ISSUES.
TAKE FLASHBANG GRENADES.
IN THEORY, THEY JUST STUN AND
DISORIENT PEOPLE.
BUT THEY CAN GENERATE HEAT
IN EXCESS OF 2,000 DEGREES.
SO YOU'D HOPE OFFICERS WOULD
BE REALLY CAREFUL WITH THEM,
CERTAINLY A LOT MORE CAREFUL
THAN THIS.
WE HEARD A LOUD... A LOUD
NOISE, WHICH WAS BUSTING THROUGH
THE DOOR.
THEN CAME A FLASH GRENADE
RIGHT INTO THE TWO-YEAR-OLD'S
BED.
YOU CAN SEE BY THIS PICTURE
HOW BADLY IT WAS DAMAGED.
AND I KEPT BEGGING THE
OFFICER, YOU KNOW,
"GIVE ME MY SON.
JUST LET ME HOLD HIM.
HE'S SCARED.
HE NEEDS ME."
THE OFFICER TOLD ME TO SHUT UP
AND GO SIT DOWN.
POLICE WERE LOOKING FOR
DRUGS, BUT FOUND NOTHING.
John: YEAH, THE POLICE THREW
A FLASHBANG GRENADE INTO A CRIB.
AND LOOK, I'M NO POLICEMAN.
I HAVEN'T STUDIED ALL THE
BYLAWS, I DON'T HAVE A PhD IN
FLASH GRENADE-OLOGY.
BUT PURELY AS A LAYPERSON,
THE POLICE SHOULD NOT HAVE
THROWN THAT FUCKING GRENADE
INTO A FUCKING CRIB.
AND IF THE POLICE ARE TRULY
INCAPABLE OF KNOWING WHETHER
THEY'RE THROWING A GRENADE
INTO A CRIB, MAYBE THEY
SHOULDN'T HAVE FUCKING GRENADES.
HERE'S ANOTHER QUICK RULE THAT
APPLIES TO BOTH HORSESHOES AND
HAND GRENADES: IF YOU THROW
EITHER OF THEM INTO A CRIB
EVEN ONE TIME, GUESS WHAT?
YOU DON'T GET TO PLAY WITH THEM
ANYMORE.
NOW, THANKFULLY, THAT BABY
SURVIVED.
BUT IT'S HARD TO BELIEVE THAT
POLICE DIDN'T REALIZE THERE WERE
CHILDREN IN THE HOUSE, GIVEN
THE FAMILY HAD LIVED AT THAT
ADDRESS FOR TWO MONTHS, AND
THERE WAS A MINIVAN WITH
FOUR CAR SEATS IN THE DRIVEWAY.
AND WHEN THEY DID FIND THE MAN
THEY WERE ACTUALLY LOOKING FOR
AT A DIFFERENT HOUSE, HE
SURRENDERED PEACEFULLY WHEN
OFFICERS KNOCKED ON HIS DOOR.
SO IN HINDSIGHT, GRENADING
A BABY MIGHT NOT HAVE BEEN
NECESSARY.
AND, AGAIN, THEY WERE LOOKING
FOR DRUGS.
AND, AGAIN, THEY DIDN'T FIND
WHAT THEY WERE LOOKING FOR.
THIS HAPPENS ALL THE TIME.
AND TROUBLINGLY, POLICE DON'T
HAVE TO WORK VERY HARD TO GET
A WARRANT TO BLOW SOMEONE'S DOOR
OPEN.
JUDGES HAVE TO SIGN OFF ON
WARRANTS, AND IDEALLY, THEY
WOULD FUNCTION AS A CHECK HERE.
BUT IN PRACTICE, THEY OFTEN
DON'T SPEND MUCH TIME
SCRUTINIZING POLICE
JUSTIFICATION.
AN INVESTIGATION IN UTAH OF MORE
THAN 10,000
ELECTRONICALLY-SUBMITTED
WARRANTS FOUND THAT HALF
THE TIME, JUDGES APPROVED
WARRANTS IN LESS THAN THREE
MINUTES, WITH HUNDREDS SIGNED
OFF IN LESS THAN 30 SECONDS.
THAT'S ABSURD!
EVEN THE CASES ON
"CHRISSY'S COURT" WERE LONGER
THAN 30 SECONDS, AND IT WAS A
SHOW ON QUIBI, A PLATFORM THAT
WE ALL COLLECTIVELY FEVER
DREAMED.
AND THE BAR FOR GETTING A JUDGE
TO SIGN OFF ON A SEARCH WARRANT
IS PRETTY LOW.
ALL YOU NEED IS PROBABLE CAUSE,
OR A REASONABLE BELIEF THAT
EVIDENCE OF A CRIME WILL BE
FOUND IN THE PLACE YOU WANT TO
SEARCH.
AND THAT BELIEF CAN COME FROM
ANYWHERE.
WHETHER IT'S THE SMELL OF
MARIJUANA OR, VERY OFTEN,
THE WORD OF A CONFIDENTIAL
INFORMANT, WHO MIGHT BE TRADING
TIPS FOR MONEY OR LENIENCY.
AND A LOT OF THOSE TIPS TURN OUT
TO BE COMPLETE BULLSHIT.
TO GET THE SEARCH WARRANT THAT
LED TO THE RAID ON
RODERICK TALLEY'S HOME,
POLICE TOLD A JUDGE THAT
A CONFIDENTIAL INFORMANT HAD
BOUGHT COCAINE FROM HIM, AND
THAT THEY'D OBSERVED THE
INTERACTION.
BUT LUCKILY, TALLEY HAD A
DOORBELL CAM THAT SHOWED
THE INFORMANT WALKING UP TO
THE DOOR, ALONE, STANDING THERE,
AND THEN WALKING AWAY.
AND LOOK, NORMALLY, I'M NOT
A BIG FAN OF DOORBELL CAMS.
ALL THEY DO IS RECORD ME GIVING
MYSELF A FIVE MINUTE PEP-TALK
BEFORE I ENTER ANY PARTY.
BUT IN THIS INSTANCE, I'M REALLY
GLAD HE HAD ONE.
AND POLICE HAVE SOMETIMES BEEN
CAUGHT MAKING INFORMANTS UP,
GIVING MISLEADING INFORMATION
IN THEIR WARRANT APPLICATION,
OR FAILING TO DO EVEN THE MOST
BASIC CHECKING TO SEE IF THEIR
SUSPECT IS ACTUALLY IN THE HOME
THEY'RE RAIDING, OR SOMEWHERE
ELSE THAT THEY PROBABLY SHOULD
HAVE KNOWN ABOUT.
JOLANDA BLASSINGAME SAYS IT
WAS UTTERLY TERRIFYING, CHICAGO
POLICE ALLEGEDLY BREAKING HER
DOOR DOWN IN NORTH LAWNDALE,
POINTING RIFLES AT HER CHILDREN
IN WHAT'S BEING CALLED A
COLOSSAL POLICE BLUNDER.
THEY DID NOT BOTHER TO
PERFORM THE SIMPLEST,
MOST ROUTINE VERIFICATION.
THE TARGET OF THE WARRANT,
MR. BELL, WAS AT THAT TIME
SERVING A 20-YEAR PRISON
SENTENCE FOR A MURDER CONVICTION
200 MILES AWAY IN HILL
CORRECTIONAL CENTER IN
GALESBURG, ILLINOIS.
John: WELL, THAT'S
PRETTY EMBARRASSING.
BUT I GUESS IT'S LIKE WHEN
YOU TURN YOUR HOME UPSIDE-DOWN
LOOKING FOR YOUR KEYS, ONLY TO
DISCOVER THEY WERE IN YOUR
POCKET THE WHOLE TIME.
ONLY IN THIS CASE, THE KEYS ARE
A MAN, THE HOME ISN'T YOURS, AND
YOUR POCKET IS A MEDIUM-SECURITY
PRISON IN ANOTHER ZIP CODE.
SO WHEN YOU HAVE BAD POLICE WORK
ON THE FRONT END, AND MINIMAL
JUDICIAL OVERSIGHT ON THE BACK
END, IT BECOMES FAR TOO EASY TO
GET A SEARCH WARRANT.
AND ONCE POLICE HAVE ONE, THERE
REALLY AREN'T A LOT OF LIMITS ON
WHAT THEY CAN DO.
JUST ABOUT EVERY SEARCH WARRANT
GIVES OFFICERS PERMISSION TO
BREAK DOWN A DOOR TO CONDUCT
THE SEARCH.
AND I KNOW THERE'S A LOT OF TALK
RIGHT NOW SPECIFICALLY ABOUT
"NO-KNOCK" RAIDS, BUT IT'S WORTH
NOTING, THE LINE BETWEEN "KNOCK"
AND "NO-KNOCK" IS VERY VERY
THIN, THANKS TO A SERIES OF
COURT RULINGS LIKE THIS:
THE U.S. SUPREME COURT RULED
TODAY POLICE DO NOT HAVE TO
WAIT MORE THAN 20 SECONDS BEFORE
BREAKING INTO A DRUG SUSPECTS'
HOME, THE UNANIMOUS RULING SAID
WAITING ANY LONGER WOULD LET
SUSPECTS FLUSH EVIDENCE
DOWN THE TOILET.
John: YEAH, THE RULING WAS,
GIVING YOU 20 SECONDS TO ANSWER
YOUR DOOR IS REASONABLE, BECAUSE
YOU MIGHT FLUSH EVIDENCE DOWN
THE TOILET.
WHICH RAISES THE OBVIOUS
QUESTION HERE,
WHY THE FUCK ARE WE
RAIDING PEOPLE'S HOMES FOR AN
AMOUNT OF EVIDENCE THAT CAN BE
FLUSHED AWAY IN 20 SECONDS?
UNLESS SOMEONE IS ACCUSED OF
TRAFFICKING SMURFS OR STEALING
THE WORLD'S MOST VALUABLE
GOLDFISH, MAYBE WE SHOULD BE
FINDING A DIFFERENT WAY TO DO
THIS.
AND POLICE REALLY AREN'T
INCENTIVIZED TO GIVE YOU ANY
SECONDS TO ANSWER YOUR DOOR.
BECAUSE IN 2006, THE SUPREME
COURT RULED THAT, EVEN WHEN THEY
VIOLATE THE RULES REQUIRING THEM
TO KNOCK, ANNOUNCE, AND WAIT,
THE PROSECUTION CAN STILL USE
THE EVIDENCE OBTAINED DURING
THAT SEARCH.
SO THERE'S OFTEN NO MEANINGFUL
CONSEQUENCES TO BUSTING RIGHT
THROUGH YOUR DOOR.
AND DECISIONS LIKE THAT MEAN THE
DISTINCTION BETWEEN A NO-KNOCK
RAID AND A "KNOCK AND ANNOUNCE"
RAID IS BARELY THERE.
AS A JUDGE IN GEORGIA PUT IT,
"EITHER THE DOOR COMES IN AND
PEOPLE ARE YELLING,
"SHERIFF'S OFFICE" OR
PEOPLE YELL, "SHERIFF'S OFFICE"
AND THE DOOR COMES IN."
AND THAT IS FUNDAMENTALLY
THE SAME!
IT'S LIKE COMPARING
BRYCE DALLAS HOWARD AND
JESSICA CHASTAIN.
ARE THEY DIFFERENT?
NOMINALLY, SURE, ALTHOUGH NOT
IN ANY WAY THAT MEANS ANYTHING.
IF YOU DO NEED TO TELL THEM
APART, BRYCE DALLAS HOWARD IS
THE ONE WHO LOOKS SLIGHTLY MORE
LIKE JESSICA CHASTAIN.
AND ON TOP OF ALL OF THIS, THERE
IS JUST CASE AFTER CASE OF THE
POLICE MESSING UP THE EXECUTION
OF A RAID, THAT RANGE FROM THE
HORRIFIC TO THE ALMOST
CARTOONISHLY IDIOTIC... LIKE
THIS VIDEO OF THEM LOOKING FOR
A SUSPECTED DRUG DEALER,
BUT INSTEAD
RAIDING THE HOME OF HIS
NEIGHBOR, ONREE NORRIS,
A 78-YEAR-OLD WITH HEART
PROBLEMS WHO THANKFULLY
SURVIVED, DESPITE THE POLICE
MAKING ONE MISTAKE AFTER
ANOTHER.
HOW DID DEPUTIES END UP
HITTING A HOUSE WITH A DIFFERENT
COLOR, A SEPARATE DRIVEWAY,
ITS OWN MAILBOX, AND ANOTHER
ADDRESS?
WHAT'S WRONG?
MISSED IT.
OH!
[BLEEP].
[BLEEP]!
MISSED IT.
FIRST, THE TACTICAL TEAM GOT
LOST FOLLOWING INSTRUCTIONS FROM
A GPS APP ON A PHONE.
TURN RIGHT ON...
THEN, AS SOON AS THEY GOT
TO THE CORRECT ADDRESS,
DEPUTIES WERE IMMEDIATELY
CONFUSED.
WHERE'S THE HOUSE?
THEY WALKED RIGHT PAST THE
TARGET HOUSE WITHOUT CLEARING IT
AND HEADED THROUGH THE TREE LINE
TO THE NEXT HOUSE ON THE STREET.
EVEN THEN, DEPUTIES WERE UNSURE.
THIS HOUSE?
LOOKING BACK AND FORTH
AT THE TWO HOUSES,
IT WAS TOO LATE.
THE ENTRY TEAM WAS ALREADY
FORCING ITS WAY INTO ONREE'S
HOME.
John: OH, FOR FUCK'S SAKE.
IT IS HUMILIATING TO WATCH A
TRAINED TACTICAL UNIT OUTFITTED
WITH MILITARY HARDWARE GET SO
COMPLETELY STUMPED BY
"THE MYSTERY OF THE
MORE THAN ONE HOUSE."
AND YOU MIGHT THINK, "OH, THAT'S
JUST A ONE-OFF"... MISTAKES LIKE
THAT HAPPEN ALL THE TIME.
IT WAS A TOTAL NIGHTMARE FOR
THIS FAMILY WHEN COPS BURST INTO
THEIR HOME, WHICH TURNED OUT TO
BE THE WRONG ADDRESS.
THAT IS THE WRONG APARTMENT.
AND THAT IS THE ONE THAT
THE S.W.A.T. TEAM WENT INSIDE.
SHAWN AND HIS WIFE, WHO BOTH
WORK FULL TIME, LIVE HERE.
THE PEOPLE THE POLICE WERE
LOOKING FOR LIVE HERE.
THE DEA IS APOLOGIZING FOR
BURSTING INTO THE RENCK FAMILY
HOME WITH THE BRADLEY COUNTY
S.W.A.T. TEAM, ONLY LATER
FINDING OUT THAT IT WAS
THE WRONG HOME.
THAT'S NOT A MISTAKE TO MAKE.
HELL, YOU COULD HAVE LOOKED
AT THE MAILBOX.
John: YEAH, EXACTLY.
AND THE POLICE HITTING
THE WRONG ADDRESS IS JUST
COMPLETELY UNACCEPTABLE WHEN
THE STAKES ARE SO HIGH.
EVEN EDIBLE ARRANGEMENTS MANAGES
TO DELIVER TO THE CORRECT
ADDRESS, AND THAT BUSINESS IS
JUST PURE CHAOTIC EVIL.
"HAPPY ANNIVERSARY!
PLEASE ENJOY THIS FLAVORLESS
CRUCIFIED MELON."
AMAZINGLY, THERE OFTEN AREN'T
CONSEQUENCES FOR CASES LIKE
THOSE.
OFFICERS ARE RARELY CRIMINALLY
CHARGED, AND EVEN MORE RARELY
CONVICTED.
BOTCHED RAIDS USUALLY AREN'T
EVEN INVESTIGATED, UNLESS
SOMEONE IS KILLED, THE MEDIA
GETS INVOLVED, OR THERE'S
A LAWSUIT.
AND EVEN WHEN THEY HAPPEN,
POLICE OFFICERS ARE PROTECTED
FROM CIVIL LIABILITY BY THE
DOCTRINE OF QUALIFIED IMMUNITY.
AS FOR THEIR DEPARTMENTS,
THEY AREN'T EVEN RESPONSIBLE FOR
PAYING TO REPAIR A BROKEN FRONT
DOOR, OR COMPENSATING RESIDENTS
FOR ANY OTHER LOSSES OR DAMAGES,
EVEN WHEN THEY RAID THE WRONG
RESIDENCE.
WHICH IS JUST ABSURD.
LOOK, THIS IS OBVIOUSLY
INCREDIBLY DANGEROUS, AND NOT
JUST FOR THE PEOPLE WHOSE HOMES
ARE RAIDED.
FOR THE POLICE, TOO.
THAT SAME INVESTIGATION THAT
FOUND 81 CIVILIANS HAD BEEN
KILLED IN RAIDS FOUND THAT
13 POLICE OFFICERS HAD DIED,
AS WELL.
WHICH SHOULDN'T BE THAT
SURPRISING.
THESE RAIDS ARE, BY DESIGN,
HIGHLY DISORIENTING, AND FOR THE
PEOPLE WOKEN UP IN THE MIDDLE OF
THE NIGHT TO THE SOUNDS OF AN
ARMED INVASION, THEY HAVE TO
MAKE A SPLIT-SECOND DECISION
WHETHER OR NOT TO DEFEND
THEMSELVES.
THAT IS SOMETHING EVERYONE CAN
UNDERSTAND.
IN GEORGIA, A REPUBLICAN STATE
SENATOR GOT IN TROUBLE FOR
SAYING, IF POLICE RAIDED HIS
HOME IN A NO-KNOCK RAID,
HE WOULD SHOOT THEM DEAD,
AND WHEN HE WAS PUSHED ON THAT,
HE DID NOT BACK DOWN.
IF SOMEBODY KICKS DOWN
MY DOOR UNANNOUNCED,
THEY WILL MEET WITH RESISTANCE,
I GUARANTEE YOU.
BUT IF IT'S LAW ENFORCEMENT?
THEY WOULD BE THERE...
HOW AM I SUPPOSED TO KNOW AT
3:00 IN THE MORNING?
SOMEBODY SHOWS UP IN
BLACK OUTFITS, THEY CAN SAY
THEY'RE LAW ENFORCEMENT.
MAYBE THEY'RE NOT.
THEY'VE GOT A GUN POINTED AT ME.
WHAT ARE YOU GONNA DO, DALE?
John: YEAH, DALE!
WHAT'RE YOU GONNA DO?
I KNOW THAT GUY LOOKS LIKE A BIT
OF A BELLIGERENT ASSHOLE,
BUT THE THING IS, THE COUNTRY
IS FULL OF BELLIGERENT ASSHOLES,
AND LOTS OF THEM HAVE GUNS.
AND WHILE IT IS EASY FOR
A WHITE STATE SENATOR TO
FANTASIZE ABOUT HIMSELF,
OR INDEED, DALE, MOUNTING A
HYPOTHETICAL ARMED RESISTANCE
TO A POLICE RAID, FOR THOSE WHO
ACTUALLY DO GET RAIDED, THERE
ARE REAL CONSEQUENCES TO THOSE
ACTIONS... IF NOT DEATH, THEN
SERIOUS CRIMINAL CHARGES.
JUST A FEW HOURS AFTER
BREONNA TAYLOR WAS KILLED,
HER BOYRIEND, KENNETH WALKER,
WHO BELIEVED THE POLICE WERE
INTRUDERS, WAS CHARGED WITH
ATTEMPTED MURDER FOR FIRING
HIS GUN DURING THE RAID AND
ALLEGEDLY INJURING AN OFFICER
IN THE LEG.
THOSE CHARGES WERE DROPPED,
BUT ONLY BECAUSE HE HAD NATIONAL
ATTENTION AND A GOOD LAWYER.
MEANWHILE, 18-YEAR-OLD
TYLER HARRELL WAS SENTENCED TO
13 AND A HALF YEARS IN PRISON
AFTER HE INJURED A POLICE
OFFICER DURING A SURPRISE
DRUG RAID AT HIS HOME, EVEN
THOUGH A JURY FOUND "NO PROOF
THAT HE KNEW HE WAS SHOOTING
AT POLICE."
LIVES ARE GETTING DESTROYED
THROUGH POLICE RAIDS.
AND EVEN IF NOBODY GETS
PHYSICALLY HURT, THAT DOESN'T
MEAN NO DAMAGE IS DONE.
HAVING YOUR HOME VIOLATED IS
A TRAUMATIZING EXPERIENCE,
OFTEN EXACERBATED BY HOW TARGETS
OF RAIDS ARE TREATED.
TAKE ANJANETTE YOUNG,
A SOCIAL WORKER IN CHICAGO WHOSE
HOME WAS RAIDED, AND WHO FOUGHT
HARD TO GET THE BODY CAMERA
FOOTAGE RELEASED TO THE PUBLIC,
EVEN THOUGH IT IS INCREDIBLY
DIFFICULT TO WATCH.
YOU SEE THEM RUNNING UP TO
THE APARTMENT COMPLEX WITH THE
BATTERING RAM IN THEIR HAND.
IT WAS SO TRAUMATIC TO HEAR
THE WAY THE THING WAS HITTING
THE DOOR.
GO, GO, GO, GO!
SEARCH WARRANT!
POLICE SEARCH WARRANT!
AND IT HAPPENED SO FAST,
I DIDN'T HAVE TIME TO PUT ON
CLOTHES.
YOU'VE GOT THE WRONG HOUSE!
AND SHE WAS RIGHT.
THEY WERE IN THE WRONG HOUSE.
WE FOUND THEY SIMPLY TOOK THE
WORD OF AN INFORMANT WHO GAVE
THEM ANJANETTE YOUNG'S ADDRESS.
THE INFORMANT CLAIMED A
23-YEAR-OLD MAN WHO WAS A KNOWN
FELON HAD A GUN AND AMMO INSIDE.
I DON'T KNOW WHO THAT PERSON
IS.
I'VE BEEN LIVING HERE FOR FOUR
YEARS AND NOBODY LIVES HERE
BUT ME!
OKAY.
YOU DON'T HAVE TO SHOUT.
I DON'T HAVE TO SHOUT!
THIS IS RIDICULOUS!
John: YEAH, IT IS.
THEY BROKE INTO HER HOME, HAVING
DONE NEXT TO NO DUE DILIGENCE,
AND HANDCUFFED HER COMPLETELY
NAKED, BEFORE EVENTUALLY
THROWING A BLANKET OVER HER,
WHILE SHE WAS STILL
HANDCUFFED.
AND THEN THEY SAID, "YOU DON'T
HAVE TO SHOUT."
SHOUTING IS NOT THE DRASTIC
MEASURE BEING TAKEN HERE.
PEOPLE SHOUT FOR MANY REASONS.
BECAUSE THEY WANT PEANUTS.
BECAUSE THEY DON'T WANT TO
GET UP OR JUST BECAUSE THE SONG
TOLD THEM TO.
WHEN YOU ARE HANDCUFFED NAKED
IN YOUR OWN HOME BECAUSE
THE POLICE SCREWED UP
A SEARCH WARRANT, SHOUTING
SHOULD BE IN YOUR FUCKING
MIRANDA RIGHTS.
AND WHEN YOU TREAT PEOPLE
LIKE THAT, IT'S CLEAR YOU HAVE
NO INTEREST IN FORGING A HEALTHY
RELATIONSHIP WITH THE COMMUNITY
YOU'RE SUPPOSED TO BE SERVING.
INSTEAD, THE COMMUNITY HAS TO
LIVE WITH THE KNOWLEDGE THAT
NO SPACE IS TRULY SECURE FROM
THE THREAT OF POLICE VIOLENCE.
THAT IS A MESSAGE THAT IS
RECEIVED LOUD AND CLEAR
FROM A VERY YOUNG AGE.
SO WHAT DO WE DO ABOUT IT?
WELL, I WOULD ARGUE SMALL
CHANGES JUST AREN'T GOING TO CUT
IT HERE.
BECAUSE, YEAH, IT WOULD BE
BETTER IF SEARCH WARRANTS WERE
HARDER TO GET AND OFFICERS WERE
REQUIRED TO VERIFY INFORMATION
FROM CONFIDENTIAL INFORMANTS AND
WE DIDN'T GIVE MILITARY GRADE
EQUIPMENT TO PEOPLE WHO CAN'T BE
TRUSTED NOT TO THROW IT
INTO A FUCKING CRIB.
BUT THAT IS JUST NOT NEARLY
ENOUGH.
AND EVEN REFORMS THAT APPEAR
SWEEPING CAN BE PRETTY LIMITED.
AFTER BREONNA TAYLOR'S DEATH,
NO-KNOCK WARRANTS WERE BANNED
IN, AMONG OTHER PLACES,
LOUISVILLE AND VIRGINIA,
WHICH INITIALLY SOUNDS GOOD.
THE THING IS, AS YOU'VE SEEN
TONIGHT, THE DIFFERENCE BETWEEN
"NO KNOCK" AND "KNOCK" IS
BASICALLY NO DIFFERENCE AT ALL.
AND I'D ARGUE THAT THERE IS
A BIG SOLUTION HERE THAT IS
STARING US RIGHT IN THE FACE.
AND THAT IS, STOP DOING DRUG
RAIDS.
JUST STOP IT.
AND IF THAT SOUNDS EXTREME,
YOU MIGHT WANT TO KNOW, THE
FORMER CHAIRMAN OF THE NATIONAL
TACTICAL OFFICERS ASSOCIATION
RECOMMENDS THAT RAIDS NEVER
BE USED TO SERVE NARCOTICS
WARRANTS, SAYING, "WHY WOULD YOU
RUN INTO A GUNFIGHT?
YOU DEFINITELY DON'T GO IN AND
RISK YOUR LIFE FOR DRUGS."
AND HE'S RIGHT.
DRUG RAIDS JUST HAVE TO STOP.
AND RAIDS IN GENERAL SHOULD ONLY
BE USED A LAST RESORT TO SAVE
LIVES THAT ARE IN IMMEDIATE
DANGER.
BECAUSE BURSTING INTO SOMEONE'S
HOME IS NEVER GOING TO BE SAFE
FOR ANYONE INVOLVED.
AND RIGHT NOW, RAIDS ARE BEING
USED FAR TOO WIDELY, AND ARE
DESTROYING LIVES, BOTH FOR
THE INDIVIDUALS WHO ARE KILLED,
INJURED, OR TRAUMATIZED,
AND ALL THE BLACK AND BROWN
PEOPLE WHO HAVE NO CHOICE BUT TO
INTERNALIZE THE LESSONS
OF THAT TRAUMA.
THEY DESERVE THE RESPECT AND
CONSIDERATION OF A POLICE FORCE
THAT'S SUPPOSED TO PROTECT THEM,
NOT ONE THAT MERELY SEES THEIR
LIVES AS AN OPPORTUNITY FOR
ACTION MOVIE COSPLAY,
A THRILLING TV SPECIAL,
OR THE REENACTMENT OF
A MISREMEMBERED NURSERY RHYME
WITH A SOUPED-UP FUCKING
BATTERING RAM.
AND MAYBE, JUST MAYBE, IF WE CAN
DO THE RIGHT THING HERE, AND
CLIMB DOWN FROM OUR CURRENT WILD
OVERUSE OF RAIDS, THEN, AND ONLY
THEN, WE'D HAVE A POLICE STORY
LEGITIMATELY WORTH SINGING
ABOUT.
THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
GOOD NIGHT.
♪ I'M THE BABY MERCHANT ♪
♪ TOTS 'R' US ♪
♪ I GIVE YOU ALL THE SERVICE ♪
♪ AND NO DAMN FOSSE ♪
♪ JUST A WEEK OR TWO ♪
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org