♪ ♪
>> John: HI, THERE, WELCOME TO
THE SHOW, STILL FOR JUST THREE
MORE WEEKS TAKING PLACE IN THIS
BLANK VOID, WHICH I RECENTLY
LEARNED IS SENTIENT.
IT'S BEEN LISTENING A LOT TO ME,
SO I THOUGHT
I WOULD GIVE IT THE FLOOR FOR A
MOMENT.
VOID, IS THERE ANYTHING YOU
WOULD LIKE TO SAY?
>> REALLY?
I CAN SAY ANYTHING I WANT?
>> John: GO AHEAD, SPEAK YOUR
MIND.
>> OKAY.
WOW.
I WISH CHRIS PRATT WASN'T TRYING
TO MAKE THE ACTION HERO THING
STICK.
YOU KNOW?
>> John: UH-HUH.
>> IT'S HIS CAREER, HE CAN DO
WHATEVER HE WANTS WITH IT.
I JUST FEEL LIKE THE BUFF THING,
IT'S NOT WORKING FOR ME.
>> John: OKAY, I'VE GOT TO BE
HONEST.
I THOUGHT YOU WOULD BE MORE
INTERESTING THAN THIS.
>> EXCUSE ME?
YOU ASK SOMEONE ON THEIR SHOW
AND TELL THEM TO SAY WHATEVER
THEY WANT. THEY CAN SAY WHATEVER THEY WANT,
AND THEN YOU TELL THEM THEY ARE
NOT INTERESTING?
WHO DOES THAT?
WHAT KIND OF MONSTER DOES THAT?
>> John: THAT IS FAIR.
>> YOU KNOW WHAT?
I SEE WHY YOU STOPPED HAVING
GUESTS ON ON SEASON ONE.
>> John: MOVING ON --
>> YOU ARE NOT A NICE PERSON.
>> John: MOVING ON.
TUCKER CARLSON CELEBRATED
INTERNATIONAL
AUTHORITARIAN APPRECIATION WEEK
BY DOING A ROAD-SHOW IN HUNGARY,
O.J. SIMPSON URGED PEOPLE TO GET
VACCINATED, PUTTING ME IN THE
STRANGE POSITION OF SAYING "I'M
WITH O.J.," AND NEW YORK'S AG
RELEASED A DEVASTATING REPORT
OF HIS INVESTIGATION INTO
ALLEGATIONS
DEVASTATING SEXUAL HARASSMENT BY
ANDREW CUOMO WHICH, INCREDIBLY,
HE IS TRYING TO RIDE OUT, TRYING
TO DOWNPLAY THE ACCUSATIONS.
>> I DO KISS PEOPLE ON THE
FOREHEAD.
I DO KISS PEOPLE ON THE CHEEK.
I DO KISS PEOPLE ON THE HAND.
I DO EMBRACE PEOPLE.
I DO HUG PEOPLE, MEN AND WOMEN.
>> John: OKAY!
BUT THAT'S NOT WHAT THIS IS
ABOUT.
AND IT'S FRANKLY INCREDIBLE THAT
CUOMO THOUGHT RELEASING AN
IRRELEVANT MONTAGE OF PHOTOS
WOULD SOMEHOW EXONERATE HIM.
APPARENTLY HIS STRATEGY FOR
LITERALLY ANY CRISIS IS
"PUT TOGETHER A POWERPOINT AND
THAT'S IT."
BUT THE REST OF THE WORLD'S
ATTENTION WAS DOMINATED THIS
WEEK BY THE OLYMPICS.
THEY ENDED TONIGHT AND THEY
PROVIDED SOME INCREDIBLE MOMENTS
FROM THE ATHLETES, BUT ALSO SOME
CONTROVERSY FROM THE FACT
THE GAMES WERE EVEN HAPPENING IN
THE FIRST PLACE, IN THE MIDDLE
OF A PANDEMIC, TO A DECISION
TAKEN BEFORE THEY BEGAN
REGARDING ONE OF THE TEAMS
INVOLVED.
>> IN OTHER OLYMPIC NEWS THIS
MORNING, RUSSIA IS COMPETING
UNDER A NEW NAME AT THESE
OLYMPICS FOLLOWING THEIR DOPING
SCANDAL.
THEY'LL BE COMPETING AS THE
"RUSSIAN OLYMPIC COMMITTEE."
THE RUSSIAN NAME, FLAG, AND
ANTHEM HAVE ALL BEEN BANNED IF
ATHLETES DO WIN ANY MEDALS.
>> John: YEAH, THOUGH THE
RUSSIAN NAME ISN'T REALLY BANNED
IF THEY'RE COMPETING AS THE
"RUSSIAN" OLYMPIC COMMITTEE, IS
IT?
IT'S LIKE SAYING, "A MONSTER
LIKE HARVEY WEINSTEIN HAS
ABSOLUTELY NO AFFILIATION WITH
THE WEINSTEIN COMPANY."
I DUNNO ABOUT THAT.
THE NAME THERE REALLY IMPLIES
OTHERWISE.
THE NEW DESIGNATION IS DUE TO
THE FACT THAT RUSSIA WAS
TECHNICALLY BANNED FOR OPERATING
A YEARS-LONG, STATE-SPONSORED
DOPING SCHEME, AND THIS ISN'T
THE FIRST TIME THEY'VE BEEN
SANCTIONED.
IN PYEONGCHANG IN 2018, RUSSIAN
ATHLETES HAD TO COMPETE UNDER
THIS NEUTRAL BANNER INSTEAD OF
THEIR FLAG.
BUT BEFORE TOKYO, THE PUNISHMENT
WAS DOWNGRADED, AND THEY WERE
ALLOWED TO COMPETE AS THE
"RUSSIAN OLYMPIC COMMITTEE" WITH
UNIFORMS THAT CLEARLY BEAR MORE
THAN A PASSING RESEMBLANCE TO
THE RUSSIAN FLAG.
WE ALL KNOW WHAT IS GOING ON
THERE, IN THE SAME WAY THAT
CALLING THIS A RED PLUMBER
HALLOWEEN COSTUME ISN'T FOOLING
ANYONE.
AND WHILE WINNING RUSSIAN
ATHLETES DIDN'T GET TO HEAR
THEIR NATIONAL ANTHEM ON THE
MEDAL STAND, THEY DID GET THIS:
[TCHAIKOVSKY'S PIANO CONCERTO
NO. 1]
♪ ♪
YEAH, THEY GOT TCHAIKOVSKY.
THAT IS MORE RUSSIAN THAN THE
RUSSIAN NATIONAL ANTHEM.
IN FACT, THERE IS NO SOUND MORE
QUINTESSENTIALLY RUSSIAN, ASIDE
FROM MAYBE AN OLD MAN WEEPING
UNCONTROLLABLY WHILE EATING A
POTATO.
IF ANYTHING, IT SEEMS RUSSIA
EMBRACED THE R.O.C. DESIGNATION
DURING THESE GAMES, WITH THE
OFFICIAL @Russia ACCOUNT EVEN
RUNNING A CAMPAIGN USING THE
HASHTAG #WeWillRocYou.
AND YOU DON'T GET TO USE
"R.O.C." AS A FUN, SASSY NAME!
THAT WAS SUPPOSED TO BE YOUR
PUNISHMENT.
IT'S LIKE IF HANNIBAL LECTER
STARTED TWEETING #MuzzleMeDaddy.
NO!
YOU EAT PEOPLE.
YOU DON'T GET TO RECLAIM THE
MUZZLE.
THE THING IS, THESE
DESIGNATIONS WERE PUT IN PLACE
FOR A REASON -- BUT THAT REASON
IS NOT SOMETHING THE R.O.C.'S
BEEN EAGER TO ACKNOWLEDGE.
AFTER A U.S. SWIMMER INITIALLY
SUGGESTED HIS RACE "WAS PROBABLY
NOT CLEAN," THE R.O.C. -- WHOSE
ATHLETE HAD WON THAT RACE --
RESPONDED AGGRESSIVELY:
>> THE RUSSIAN OLYMPIC COMMITTEE
HAVE RESPONDED VIA A STRONGLY
WORDED STATEMENT ON TWITTER
WHICH SAYS, IN PART, "HOW
UNNERVING OUR VICTORIES ARE FOR
SOME.
YES, WE ARE HERE AT THE
OLYMPICS.
ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
WHETHER PEOPLE LIKE IT OR NOT."
>> John: WOW.
THAT IS A HARD PUSHBACK.
AND THE R.O.C. WAS VERY MUCH NOT
DONE, CALLING THE COMPLAINTS
"ENGLISH-LANGUAGE PROPAGANDA,
OOZING VERBAL SWEAT IN
THE TOKYO HEAT."
WHICH IS UNDENIABLY POETIC.
"OOZING VERBAL SWEAT IN THE
TOKYO HEAT" SOUNDS LESS LIKE
RUSSIAN TOUGH TALK AND MORE LIKE
A LINE FROM "A STREETCAR NAMED
DESIRE 2: BLANCHE GOES EAST."
IT'S PRETTY CLEAR THAT MAKING
RUSSIA COMPETE UNDER A
SUPPOSEDLY "NEUTRAL" FLAG AND
UNIFORMS, WHEN NEITHER THE FLAG
NOR THE UNIFORMS WERE NEUTRAL,
MEANS THAT THIS PUNISHMENT
WASN'T REALLY A PUNISHMENT AT
ALL.
SO LET'S TRY AND LEARN FROM
THIS, AND NEXT TIME THIS PROBLEM
ARISES, LET'S MAKE SURE BANNED
COUNTRIES HAVE A MUCH CLEARER
ASTERISK ON THEIR PARTICIPATION.
SO INSTEAD OF A OBVIOUSLY
FLAG-THEMED TRACKSUIT, LET'S
PUT THEM IN A SHREK-THEMED
SWEATSHIRT PAIRED WITH
SHIT EMOJI SLIPPERS AND A
LOBSTER HAT.
SOMETHING LIKE THIS:
SEE?
NOW THAT IS A NEUTRAL LOOK.
GOOD LUCK GUESSING WHAT NATION
THAT ATHLETE IS COMPETING FOR
FROM THAT OUTFIT.
AND WHEN THEIR ATHLETES WIN
GOLD, DON'T GIVE THEM SOMETHING
THAT INSPIRES NATIONAL PRIDE
LIKE TCHAIKOVSKY.
INSTEAD, PLAY SOMETHING AWFUL
THAT'S GUARANTEED TO STICK IN
YOUR HEAD AND REMIND YOU THAT
SOMETHING OBJECTIONABLE HAS
HAPPENED.
MAY I SUGGEST THIS:
>> ♪ 1 877 KARS 4 KIDS ♪
♪ K-A-R-S, KARS FOR KIDS ♪
♪ 1-877 KARS 4 KIDS ♪
♪ DONATE YOUR CAR TODAY! ♪
>> John: NOW I KNOW IT'S HARSH,
OF BUT LET'S AGREE,
IT IS THE ULTIMATE
DETERRENT.
AND NOW THIS.
>> Announcer: AND NOW, THE
ELECTRIFYING SMALL TALK OF
CALIFORNIA'S "DAYTIME WITH
KIMBERLY AND ESTEBAN.">> "DAYTID
ESTEBAN" STARTS NOW.
>> WELCOME TO "DAYTIME."
IT'S MONDAY.
>> IT IS MONDAY.
>> HOLLA!
HELLO.
HOW WAS YOUR WEEKEND?
>> BUSY BUT GOOD.
>> HOW ARE YOU?
>> I AM GOOD.
YOURSELF?
>> DOING GOOD.
HOW ARE YOU?
>> GOOD.
CHILLING.
ANOTHER DAY.
>> WHAT IS UP?
HAVE YOU EVER WONDERED HOW SMART
YOUR DOG IS?
>> YEAH.
>> AIRING MOVIES YOU CAN'T
NECESSARILY SEE AT THE THEATERS.
WE ARE READY, WE ARE IN THIS
SPIRIT.
>> YEP.
WE ARE.
>> THIS IS ONE OF MY FAVORITE
SHOWS WE DO EVERY SINGLE YEAR.
>> I THINK IT'S...
FUN.
>> DOING GOOD.
DOING REAL GOOD.
>> ALL RIGHTS.
>> HOW ARE YOU DOING.
>> GOOD.
>> NOT A LOT OF CHANGE FROM
YESTERDAY.
IT'S GOOD MORNING.
>> HOW WAS THE DAY?
GOOD?
>> AGAIN, GOOD.
>> John: MOVING ON.
OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT CONCERNS
A PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS THAT'S
EXPOSED THE FAILURE OF AMERICAN
INSTITUTIONS.
NO, NOT THAT ONE.
NOT THAT ONE EITHER.
THAT'S A GOOD POINT, BUT NOT
ACTUALLY THIS TIME.
YEP, THERE IT IS.
THE OPIOID EPIDEMIC.
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING, "HOLD
ON, DIDN'T YOU ALREADY DO A SHOW
ABOUT THIS?"
YOU'RE WRONG.
WE'VE ACTUALLY DONE TWO OF THEM,
BUT WE THOUGHT IT WOULD BE WORTH
DOING A THIRD INSTALLMENT
TONIGHT FOR A COUPLE OF REASONS.
FIRST, IT'S AN EPIDEMIC THAT'S
STILL VERY MUCH RAGING,
EXACERBATED BY BOTH THE PANDEMIC
AND ILLICIT FENTANYL, TO THE
POINT THAT LAST YEAR, NEARLY
70,000 PEOPLE DIED FROM OPIOID
OVERDOSES.
THAT IS THE HIGHEST ANNUAL DEATH
TOLL EVER.
AND SECOND, YOU MAY HAVE SEEN A
BUNCH OF HEADLINES RECENTLY
ABOUT TRIALS AND SETTLEMENTS
TAKING PLACE AROUND THE COUNTRY.
THERE'VE BEEN SO MANY, IT CAN BE
GENUINELY BE HARD TO KEEP TRACK.
BUT WE WANT TO FOCUS ON JUST ONE
COMPANY TONIGHT: PURDUE PHARMA,
WHOSE ROLLOUT OF OXYCONTIN
ARGUABLY FUELED THE OPIOID
CRISIS.
WE'VE TALKED ABOUT THEIR
RELENTLESS PUSH TO SELL
OXYCONTIN BEFORE, BUT MORE
MATERIAL HAS COME OUT IN THE
LAST COUPLE OF YEARS --
INCLUDING THIS SPECTACULAR
GLIMPSE INTO A 1997 MOTIVATIONAL
SALES MEETING FOR THE COMPANY'S
DRUG REPS:
>> ♪ YOU KNOW, YOU MAKE ME WANT
TO SELL! ♪
♪ OXYCONTIN! ♪
♪ MS CONTIN! ♪
♪ SETTLE DOWN NOW! ♪
♪ WE'RE PURDUE NOW! ♪
>> ♪ SELL! ♪
>> ♪ ME AND YOU NOW! ♪
>> ♪ COME ON NOW! ♪
>> ♪ SELL! ♪
>> John: WOW.
THAT WAS PURDUE'S VP OF SALES
PERFORMING AN OXY-THEMED COVER
OF "SHOUT!"
AND THAT HAS GOT TO BE THE ONE
OF THE MOST UPSETTING DECISIONS
FROM THE LATE '90s, RIGHT UP
THERE WITH, "GIVE EVERY LONELY
CHILD AN ELECTRONIC IMAGINARY
FRIEND THAT WILL IMMEDIATELY
DIE," AND "LET'S SET EVERY
SITCOM IN NEW YORK CITY.
AND MAKE SURE THE TWIN TOWERS
ARE PROMINENTLY FEATURED IN THE
TRANSITION SHOTS, REALLY REMIND
PEOPLE THEY'RE THERE."
PURDUE PHARMA IS OWNED BY THE
SACKLER FAMILY, AND IN RECENT
YEARS, PURDUE AND THE SACKLERS
HAVE FOUND THEMSELVES BEING
INVESTIGATED BY THE DOJ AND
FACING THOUSANDS OF LAWSUITS
FILED BY STATE AND LOCAL
GOVERNMENTS, NATIVE AMERICAN
TRIBES, HOSPITALS, AND
INDIVIDUALS.
AND THEY'VE SPENT YEARS WORKING
WITH AN ARMY OF LAWYERS,
ATTEMPTING TO NEGOTIATE THEIR
WAY OUT OF ALL OF IT, WHICH HAS
RESULTED IN TWO MAJOR
RESOLUTIONS, INCLUDING THIS BIG
NEWS FROM LAST OCTOBER.
>> IT'S BEING HAILED BY THE
FEDERAL GOVERNMENT AS A MAJOR
VICTORY AGAINST A COMPANY WHOSE
DRUG OXYCONTIN IS PART OF THE
PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS OF OPIOID
ADDICTION THAT HAS LED TO THE
DEATHS OF HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS
OF AMERICANS.
>> THE MAKER OF OXYCONTIN
ADMITTED TO DEFRAUDING
REGULATORS AND PAYING ILLEGAL
KICKBACKS TO DOCTORS.
>> John: IT'S TRUE!
PURDUE HAS PLED GUILTY TO
MULTIPLE FELONIES.
AND IT'S WEIRD TO HEAR NEWS THAT
SOUNDS SO GENUINELY GOOD.
IT'D BE REALLY NICE TO GET MORE
OF THAT ONCE IN A WHILE, LIKE
"NO ONCE-IN-A-CENTURY WEATHER
EVENTS FOR THE NEXT FEW HOURS,"
OR "BILLIONAIRE GOES TO SPACE
AND DIES THERE."
YOU KNOW, SOMETHING
HEARTWARMING.
THAT GUILTY PLEA WAS ACTUALLY
PART OF A MUCH LARGER PLAN WE'LL
GET INTO LATER, INVOLVING THE
COMPANY ALSO FILING FOR
BANKRUPTCY, AND JUST THIS PAST
MARCH, SUBMITTING A
REORGANIZATION PLAN THAT WOULD
END SACKLER OWNERSHIP.
AND THE THING IS, THIS MIGHT ALL
SOUND LIKE A MAJOR VICTORY --
THAT THE SACKLERS ARE FINALLY
EXPERIENCING SIGNIFICANT
CONSEQUENCES -- BUT
UNFORTUNATELY, THAT COULDN'T BE
FARTHER FROM THE TRUTH.
SO TONIGHT, WITH THE
BANKRUPTCY'S CONFIRMATION
HEARING SCHEDULED TO BEGIN LATER
THIS WEEK, LET'S TALK ABOUT THE
SACKLER FAMILY -- HOW HARD
THEY'VE BEEN FIGHTING TO DEFEND
THEIR NAME, THE DETAILS OF THE
DEAL THEY'RE ATTEMPTING TO
STRIKE, AND WHY THE WHOLE THING
IS A BUNCH OF BULLSHIT.
AND LET'S START WITH A BASIC
QUESTION: WHO ARE THE SACKLERS?
WELL, THE SACKLERS ARE THE
DESCENDANTS OF THREE BROTHERS --
ARTHUR, RAYMOND, AND MORTIMER --
WHO IN 1952 BOUGHT THE COMPANY
THAT WOULD EVENTUALLY BECOME
PURDUE PHARMA.
AND WHILE ARTHUR'S BRANCH OF THE
FAMILY SOLD THEIR STAKE DECADES
AGO, BEFORE OXYCONTIN WAS
DEVELOPED, THE HEIRS OF RAYMOND
AND MORTIMER BOTH BENEFITED
FROM, AND IN SOME CASES ACTIVELY
MANAGED, PURDUE'S BOOM YEARS OF
SELLING OPIOIDS.
MANY SACKLERS EITHER WORKED AT
THE COMPANY OR SERVED ON ITS
BOARD, AND AS THE MASSACHUSETTS
A.G. POINTS OUT, SOME OF THEM
WERE PRETTY HANDS-ON.
>> THEY WERE IN THE BOARDROOM.
THEY OWNED THE COMPANY.
WE HAVE EMAILS AND MEMOS THAT
SHOW THE DIRECT CONTROL THAT
THEY EXERCISED OVER SALES AND
MARKETING.
ONE OF THE SACKLER FAMILY
MEMBERS WENT SO FAR AS TO WANT
TO GET IN THE CAR WITH PURDUE'S
SALES REPS AND DRIVE AROUND TO
VISIT DOCTORS' OFFICES.
>> John: IT'S TRUE, AND DOING A
DRUG REP RIDE-ALONG IS ABOUT AS
HANDS-ON AS YOU CAN GET.
AND QUICK SIDE NOTE, SPARE A
THOUGHT FOR THE SALES REP IN
QUESTION THERE.
SURE, THEY TOO CONTRIBUTED TO
THE OVER-PRESCRIPTION OF AMERICA
AND PROBABLY LED TO THEIR OWN
LOCAL MINI-EPIDEMIC, BUT
NOBODY -- NOT EVEN HITLER --
SHOULD HAVE TO SIT IN A CAR WITH
THEIR BOSS.
AND TALK ABOUT WHAT?
THE WEATHER?
AND THEN, WHEN YOU RUN OUT OF
THINGS TO SAY ABOUT IT, DO WHAT?
SIT IN SILENCE?
AND THEN SAY, "ACTUALLY, I COULD
GO FOR A BATHROOM BREAK RIGHT
NOW," AND HAVE HIM SAY, "I'M
FINE, BUT FEEL FREE TO STOP?"
AND THEN, WHAT -- YOU STOP?
AND HE WAITS IN THE CAR?
AND THEN WHEN YOU GET BACK HE
LOOKS INCONVENIENCED?
I WOULD SOONER THROW MYSELF OUT
OF THE CAR IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
FREEWAY.
NOW, THE MAN RESPONSIBLE FOR
THAT RIDE-ALONG WAS RICHARD
SACKLER, WHO WAS ACTUALLY
PRESIDENT OF THE COMPANY FOR
YEARS.
AND YET, INTERESTINGLY, IT'S
HARD TO FIND IMAGES OF HIM OTHER
THAN THAT ONE.
IN FACT, WHILE THE SACKLERS HAVE
RELISHED SLAPPING THEIR FAMILY
NAME ON INSTITUTIONS, AS
INDIVIDUALS, THEY'VE TRIED TO
STAY OUT OF THE SPOTLIGHT.
WHEN RICHARD SACKLER GAVE A
DEPOSITION IN 2015, PURDUE
FOUGHT HARD TO KEEP IT PRIVATE.
THAT'S WHY, IN OUR LAST PIECE,
WE HAD A BUNCH OF ACTORS PLAY
HIM TO CONVEY IMPORTANT THINGS
LIKE THE FACT HE'D SAID "I DON'T
KNOW" MORE THAN 100 TIMES.
THANKFULLY, THAT DEPOSITION HAS
SINCE BEEN RELEASED, SO YOU CAN
FINALLY WATCH THE MAN IN ACTION.
>> HOW MUCH MONEY HAS PURDUE
FREDERICK OR PURDUE PHARMA MADE
OFF THE SALE OF OXYCONTIN?
>> I DON'T KNOW.
I DON'T KNOW.
I DON'T KNOW THE ANSWER.
I DON'T KNOW BUT -- I JUST DON'T
KNOW.
>> John: ADMIT IT --
THE GUY JUST OOZES CHARISMA.
ALTHOUGH HONESTLY?
HAVING ACTUALLY SEEN IT, I THINK
I PREFER THE VERSION WE MADE:
>> HOW MUCH MONEY HAS PURDUE
FREDERICK OR PURDUE PHARMA MADE
OFF THE SALE OF OXYCONTIN?
>> I DUNNO.
I DUNNO.
I DON'T KNOW.
>> HOW MANY PURDUE ENTITIES ARE
THERE?
>> I DUNNO!
>> John: YEAH, THAT'S JUST
OBJECTIVELY BETTER.
NOW, WHILE RICHARD WAS THE MOST
INVOLVED, HE WASN'T ALONE.
HIS COUSIN KATHE SACKLER WAS AN
OFFICER OF THE COMPANY FOR YEARS
AND EVEN CLAIMED IN EMAILS THAT
DEVELOPING OXYCONTIN WAS HER
IDEA.
ALTHOUGH, DESPITE THAT, WHEN
KATHE WAS CALLED BEFORE CONGRESS
LAST YEAR AND ASKED TO APOLOGIZE
FOR HER ROLE IN THE OPIOID
CRISIS, SHE DIDN'T EXACTLY DO
THAT.
>> I HAVE TRIED TO FIGURE OUT,
WAS -- IS THERE ANYTHING THAT I
COULD HAVE DONE DIFFERENTLY
KNOWING WHAT I KNEW THEN, NOT
WHAT I KNOW NOW.
I HAVE TO SAY, I CAN'T -- THERE
IS NOTHING THAT I CAN FIND THAT
I WOULD HAVE DONE DIFFERENTLY.
>> John: OKAY, FIRST, THAT'S NOT
AN APOLOGY, KATHE.
AND SECOND, COME ON -- NEARLY A
YEAR INTO A PANDEMIC, THAT'S AN
UNACCEPTABLE AT-HOME SETUP.
PUT YOUR LAPTOP ON A COUPLE
BOOKS.
UPGRADE YOUR ROUTER.
AND WHILE YOU'RE AT IT,
ONE-CLICK A RING LIGHT.
SO, KATHE, THAT'S BOOKS, ROUTER,
RING LIGHT.
IT'S THE LITTLE ZOOM TRICKS
WE'VE ALL LEARNED THAT'LL HELP
YOU LOOK YOUR BEST AS YOU
ABSOLVE YOURSELF OF
RESPONSIBILITY FOR A MASSIVE
PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS.
BUT THE SACKLERS HAVEN'T JUST
BEEN APPEARING AT CONGRESSIONAL
HEARINGS.
SOME HAVE BEEN WORKING HARD TO
REHABILITATE THEIR IMAGE AND
EVEN PAINT THEMSELVES AS
VICTIMS.
TAKE DAVID SACKLER.
HE'S RICHARD'S SON AND A FORMER
BOARD MEMBER HIMSELF.
HE GAVE AN INTERVIEW TO
"VANITY FAIR" FEATURING THIS
PORTRAIT, WHICH LOOKS LIKE IT
SHOULD BE A POSTER FOR
NATURAL FAMILY PLANNING IN A
CHRISTIAN HEALTH CLINIC.
AND IN IT, HE COMPLAINED,
"MY FOUR-YEAR-OLD CAME HOME FROM
NURSERY SCHOOL AND ASKED,
'WHY ARE MY FRIENDS TELLING ME
THAT OUR FAMILY'S WORK IS
KILLING PEOPLE?'" WHICH DOESN'T
SEEM REMOTELY CREDIBLE.
FOR A START, EVERYONE KNOWS
THAT'S NOT HOW FOUR-YEAR-OLDS
TALK.
YOU'RE MISSING 8 "UMS,"
15 "AND, AND, ANDS," 3 TIMES
THEY'RE COMPLETELY OUT OF BREATH
FOR NO REASON, AND 5 COMPLETE
TRAIL-OFFS.
I CALL BULLSHIT ON THAT FAKE
ANECDOTE.
BUT THAT'S JUST THE BEGINNING.
DAVID'S BRANCH OF THE FAMILY WAS
ALSO INVOLVED IN THE LAUNCH OF A
PRO-SACKLER WEBSITE THAT AIMS TO
"CORRECT THE RECORD," CALLED
JudgeForYourselves.info,
WHICH IS SHOCKING FOR A NUMBER
OF REASONS.
FIRST, BECAUSE BILLIONAIRES, FOR
SOME REASON, CHOSE NOT TO
SPLURGE FOR THE DOT-COM, BUT
ALSO BECAUSE OF JUST HOW PETTY
THE WEBSITE IS.
IT FEATURES A LIST OF OUTLETS
THAT MISTAKENLY USED THE BRAND
NAME "OXYCONTIN" WHEN THEY MEANT
THE GENERIC "OXYCODONE,"
INCLUDING A COLLEGE NEWSPAPER,
AND OVER SEVEN HOURS OF VIDEO
PRESENTATIONS IN WHICH A
CATASTROPHICALLY UNCHARISMATIC
LAWYER ATTEMPTS TO DISPROVE
EVERY LEGAL ARGUMENT EVER MADE
AGAINST THE SACKLERS AND PURDUE.
THIS TERRIBLE WEBSITE OF
SELF-SERVING NONSENSE HAS BEEN
PROMOTED BY, AMONG OTHERS,
JOSS SACKLER, DAVID'S WIFE, WHO
YOU MAY REMEMBER FROM HER
FAILURE TO FACE THE CAMERA IN
"VANITY FAIR."
NOW, EVEN THOUGH JOSS ISN'T
DIRECTLY INVOLVED IN THE FAMILY
BUSINESS, SHE ACTUALLY TALKS
PUBLICLY MORE THAN MOST
SACKLERS.
SHE HAS A CLOTHING LINE CALLED
"LBV," OR "LES BOULEDOGUES
VIGNERONNES," WHICH TRANSLATES
TO "THE WINEMAKING BULLDOGS" AND
IS AN OFFSHOOT OF HER
"MEMBERS-ONLY WINE AND SOCIAL
CLUB."
JOSS WAS ALSO ONCE INTERVIEWED
FOR "TOWN & COUNTRY," IN WHICH
SHE COMPLAINED ABOUT HOW
UNFAIRLY THE PRESS TREATS BOTH
HER AND HER FAMILY, NOTING
THAT A PREVIOUS ARTICLE
WOULDN'T REFER TO HER AS
DR. JOSS SACKLER, DESPITE HER
TELLING THEM SHE HAD A Ph.D. IN
LINGUISTICS, GOING ON TO SAY,
"THEY'RE GOING TO REGRET FUCKING
WITH A LINGUIST."
AND THAT'S ONE HELL OF A CLAIM,
JOSS.
BECAUSE NOBODY IS INTIMIDATED BY
LINGUISTS.
YOU'RE BASICALLY AN ENGLISH
MAJOR WHO WASTED MORE TIME.
I'LL FUCK WITH A LINGUIST ALL
DAY LONG.
I'LL SHOW YOU: HOW DO YOU MAKE
TWO PROPER NOUNS INTO A DOUBLE
NEGATIVE?
JOSS AND DAVID.
BOOM!
LINGUIST, FUCKED WITH.
SO TO RECAP, IT'S PRETTY CLEAR:
SOME SACKLERS HAVE BEEN WORKING
EXTREMELY HARD TO TRY AND
ENGENDER PUBLIC SYMPATHY.
BUT THE REAL BATTLE THE FAMILY'S
BEEN FIGHTING HAS BEEN A LEGAL
ONE.
AND THAT IS WHAT I WANT TO SPEND
THE REST OF THIS PIECE TALKING
ABOUT, BECAUSE WHILE THE DETAILS
OF WHAT THE SACKLERS ARE DOING
ARE INCREDIBLY COMPLICATED, THE
END RESULT IS BOTH SIMPLE AND
ABSOLUTELY INFURIATING.
AND LET'S START WITH THAT DEAL
YOU HEARD ABOUT EARLIER, WHERE
PURDUE PLED GUILTY TO THREE
FELONIES.
IT SOUNDED LIKE SOME GOOD NEWS.
BUT THERE ARE SOME MAJOR
ASTERISKS THERE, BECAUSE WHILE
THE COMPANY PLED GUILTY TO THOSE
CHARGES, NO INDIVIDUALS DID --
AND CERTAINLY NO SACKLERS.
AND THAT ALONE IS A BIG DEAL TO
THEM.
IN FACT, JUST WATCH AS KATHE
JUMPED TO REMIND EVERYONE OF
THAT FACT DURING HER
CONGRESSIONAL HEARING.
>> THE SACKLER FAMILY, THROUGH
PURDUE, HAS THREE FELONY
CONVICTIONS, BUT NO ONE'S IN
JAIL AND IT HAS ITS BILLIONS
STILL.
>> EXCUSE ME, THE SACKLER FAMILY
DOESN'T HAVE A FELONY
CONVICTION.
PURDUE PHARMA HAS A FELONY
I'M AN INDIVIDUAL PERSON.
>> John: OKAY, HOLD ON.
I DO GET THE POINT SHE'S MAKING,
BUT THE FACT IS, PURDUE IS MADE
UP OF INDIVIDUAL PEOPLE WHO
CONTROL IT.
THINK OF PURDUE LIKE LAMBCHOP.
IF LAMBCHOP THREATENED TO KILL
THE PRESIDENT ON LIVE TV,
LAMBCHOP WOULDN'T GET IN TROUBLE
OR GO TO PRISON.
SHARI LEWIS WOULD.
WHY?
BECAUSE LAMBCHOP IS A PUPPET
WHO DOES WHATEVER THE FUCK
SHARI LEWIS TELLS LAMBCHOP
TO DO.
NOW, THE SACKLERS MIGHT ARGUE
THAT PURDUE WAS CONTROLLED BY
MANY PEOPLE -- INCLUDING
NON-FAMILY MEMBERS -- AND THAT
WHILE THEY'RE NOT FACING
CRIMINAL CHARGES, THEY'RE STILL
FACING CONSEQUENCES.
BUT HERE'S THE THING: ARE THEY?
REALLY?
AND THAT BRINGS US BACK TO THE
BANKRUPTCY I MENTIONED EARLIER.
BECAUSE THE BANKRUPTCY DEAL
PURDUE HAS PROPOSED IS THE
VEHICLE THROUGH WHICH THE
SACKLERS ARE LIKELY TO ESCAPE
ANY TRUE ACCOUNTABILITY.
VERY BASICALLY, PURDUE WAS
BURIED IN THOUSANDS OF LAWSUITS,
AND RATHER THAN FIGHTING THEM
ALL SEPARATELY, THE COMPANY
FILED FOR BANKRUPTCY,
NEGOTIATING TO RESOLVE ALL ITS
DEBTS IN ONE PLACE.
THIS PROPOSED DEAL REQUIRES,
AMONG OTHER THINGS, THE SACKLERS
RELINQUISH OWNERSHIP OF PURDUE,
WHICH WILL BE TURNED INTO A
"PUBLIC BENEFIT COMPANY," WHOSE
PROFITS WILL GO TOWARD FIGHTING
THE OPIOID EPIDEMIC.
NOW, THE COMPANY CLAIMS THE
BANKRUPTCY WILL DELIVER MORE
THAN $10 BILLION IN VALUE.
BUT A FEW THINGS ABOUT THAT.
FIRST, THE SACKLERS THEMSELVES
ARE ONLY CONTRIBUTING AROUND
$4.3 BILLION TO THAT SETTLEMENT.
WHICH DOES SOUND LIKE A LOT
UNTIL YOU LEARN THE FAMILY HAS
ASSETS OF AROUND $11 BILLION,
WHICH IS A MASSIVE AMOUNT OF
MONEY, BUT I GUESS THAT'S WHAT
HAPPENS WHEN YOUR COMPANY MAKES
A HIGHLY ADDICTIVE PRODUCT AND
PUSHES ITS EMPLOYEES TO --
>> ♪ SELL OXYCONTIN! ♪
♪ MS CONTIN! ♪
♪ SELL! ♪
>> John: I JUST SAW THAT TEN
MINUTES AGO AND SOMEHOW IT'S
GOTTEN EVEN WORSE.
ALSO, YOU MIGHT WANT TO KNOW, A
LOT OF THE SACKLER FAMILY'S NET
WORTH WAS BUILT UP IN A
PARTICULAR PERIOD.
BECAUSE FROM 2008 TO 2017, EVEN
AS THE OPIOID EPIDEMIC WAS
KICKING INTO HIGH GEAR, MORE
THAN $10 BILLION WAS TRANSFERRED
OUT OF THE COMPANY FOR THE
BENEFIT OF THE FAMILY.
NOW, THE SACKLERS FIERCELY
MAINTAIN THOSE TRANSFERS WERE
PROPER.
BUT THE DOJ ALLEGED THAT THEY
WERE MADE TO HINDER FUTURE
CREDITORS -- IN OTHER WORDS, TO
GET THE MONEY OUT OF THE
COMPANY SO THE SACKLERS COULD
PROTECT IT -- AND THEY FOUND
SOME PRETTY DAMNING EVIDENCE,
PARTICULARLY FROM DAVID SACKLER,
WHO SEEMED TO DIRECTLY EXPRESS
FEARS OVER LAWSUITS TAKING THE
FAMILY MONEY BACK IN 2007,
WRITING IN AN EMAIL,
"WE'RE RICH?
FOR HOW LONG?
UNTIL WHICH SUITS GET THROUGH TO
THE FAMILY?"
AND DAVID, BUDDY, DON'T SEND
THAT KIND OF THING OVER EMAIL.
I MEAN, DON'T SEND IT IN THE
MAIL-MAIL, DON'T SPEAK IT, DON'T
THINK IT, DON'T RECEIVE AN
UPBRINGING THAT WOULD PLANT THE
THOUGHT IN YOUR MIND, AND, IF
YOU COULD, JUST TRY AND AVOID
CONCEPTION ALTOGETHER.
BUT BARE MINIMUM, KEEP IT OUT OF
THE PERMANENT LEGAL RECORD.
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING, "OKAY,
SO, THEY TRANSFERRED MONEY TO
THE FAMILY.
BUT PEOPLE CAN STILL PURSUE
CLAIMS AGAINST THE SACKLERS
DIRECTLY, RIGHT?"
WELL, NO.
BECAUSE HERE'S THE REALLY
INSIDIOUS PART: WHILE THERE ARE
APPROXIMATELY 400 CIVIL SUITS
THAT DO NAME THE SACKLERS
THEMSELVES, THE FAMILY IS
INSISTING THAT THEY WILL ONLY
AGREE TO THIS SETTLEMENT IF THEY
GET WHAT'S CALLED A
NON-CONSENSUAL THIRD-PARTY
RELEASE.
AND THIS THING IS BULLSHIT.
BECAUSE IF THEY GET IT, ALL
CURRENT LAWSUITS AGAINST THE
SACKLERS EVAPORATE AND NO FUTURE
LAWSUITS CAN BE FILED.
MEANING THE SACKLERS --
WHO DIDN'T FILE FOR PERSONAL
BANKRUPTCY THEMSELVES,
REMEMBER -- ARE BASICALLY OFF
THE HOOK.
AND IF IT SOUNDS WEIRD TO YOU
THAT A COMPANY CAN DECLARE
BANKRUPTCY AND THEN A BUNCH OF
INDIVIDUALS GET SHIELDED FROM
LIABILITY, THAT'S BECAUSE IT IS!
IT'S REALLY FUCKING WEIRD!
IN FACT, SOME BANKRUPTCY COURTS
DON'T ALLOW THESE THIRD-PARTY
RELEASES AT ALL.
BUT PURDUE VERY CAREFULLY CHOSE
ONE THAT THEY KNEW PROBABLY
WOULD.
A FEW MONTHS BEFORE FILING FOR
BANKRUPTCY, PURDUE CHANGED ONE
OF ITS OFFICIAL CORPORATE
ADDRESSES TO ONE IN WHITE
PLAINS, NEW YORK, AT WHICH IT'S
NEVER CONDUCTED BUSINESS, AND
WHERE THERE IS ONLY ONE
BANKRUPTCY JUDGE, WHO --
COMPLETELY COINCIDENTALLY -- HAS
SUPPORTED THIRD-PARTY RELEASES
IN THE PAST.
WHICH IS ALL A PRETTY OBVIOUS
TACTIC.
IT'S NOT LIKE THEY MOVED TO
WHITE PLAINS FOR ANY OTHER
REASON.
IF YOU LOOK UP "THINGS TO DO IN
WHITE PLAINS" -- AND THIS IS
TRUE -- THE FIRST RESULT YOU GET
IS A TRIPADVISOR PAGE
RECOMMENDING A HELICOPTER TOUR
OF NEW YORK CITY.
WHICH IS JUST INCREDIBLE.
"COME VISIT WHITE PLAINS, WHERE
YOU CAN IMMEDIATELY LEAVE AND GO
LOOK AT SOMEWHERE MORE
INTERESTING TO LIVE."
AND THE SACKLERS' THIRD-PARTY
RELEASE IS COMPREHENSIVE,
STATING THAT THE RELEASED
PARTIES SHALL BE CONCLUSIVELY,
ABSOLUTELY, UNCONDITIONALLY,
IRREVOCABLY, FULLY, FINALLY,
FOREVER, AND PERMANENTLY
RELEASED FROM ANY AND ALL
CLAIMS, OF ANY KIND, FROM THE
BEGINNING OF TIME.
AND THIS IS THE LIST OF EVERY
PERSON AND ENTITY THEY WANT
COVERED.
IT CONTAINS OVER 200 COMPANIES
AND 200 MORE TRUSTS WHERE THE
SACKLERS HAVE TUCKED THEIR MONEY
AWAY.
THIS RELEASE IS LUDICROUSLY
BROAD, WHICH IS PROBABLY WHY
NINE STATE A.G.s ARE STILL
OBJECTING TO IT, AND TWO
BRANCHES OF THE DOJ HAVE SAID IT
VIOLATES THE U.S. CONSTITUTION
AND SPECIFICALLY VIOLATES DUE
PROCESS, BECAUSE IT DENIES
INDIVIDUALS OF AN OPPORTUNITY TO
BE HEARD, AND YET, INCREDIBLY,
DESPITE ALL THIS, IT'S WIDELY
ASSUMED THAT THIS WHOLE DEAL IS
GOING TO GO AHEAD.
AND WHILE IT SOUNDS TERRIBLE TO
ME, I WILL SAY, AT LEAST ONE
PERSON THINKS THAT'S A VERY GOOD
THING.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, THAT ONE
PERSON IS PURDUE'S CURRENT
CHAIRMAN.
>> THIS IS A MILESTONE IN PUBLIC
HEALTH HISTORY.
NEVER BEFORE HAVE YOU SEEN THIS
AMOUNT OF MONEY, $10 BILLION
BEING DEVOTED TO OPIOID
ABATEMENT, AND IT'S ONLY
AVAILABLE THROUGH THIS PLAN,
ASSUMING WE CAN GET IT APPROVED.
AND I THINK WHEN PEOPLE THINK
ABOUT IT, THEY WILL COME AROUND
TO THE NOTION, "WELL, I MIGHT
HAVE LIKED SOMETHING SLIGHTLY
DIFFERENT, BUT THIS IS CERTAINLY
A LOT BETTER THAN GOING INTO
ENDLESS, COSTLY LITIGATION THAT
MAY END UP WITH NO PROCEEDS
GOING TO ANYBODY."
>> John: OKAY, NO.
"I MIGHT HAVE LIKED SOMETHING
DIFFERENT, BUT THIS IS BETTER
THAN NOTHING" IS WHAT YOU SAY
WHEN YOUR DAD INSISTS ON HAVING
DINNER AT CHILI'S, NOT WHEN
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT THE FATE OF
A COMPANY THAT POISONED A
GENERATION.
WHICH, INCIDENTALLY, IS, I
BELIEVE, CHILI'S CURRENT SLOGAN.
AND HERE'S THE THING: THAT MAN'S
NOT EVEN ENTIRELY WRONG.
THE LONGER THESE LAWSUITS DRAG
ON, THE MORE MONEY WILL GET
WASTED IN COURT, AND AN
INCREASINGLY LARGE PERCENTAGE OF
IT WILL GO TO LAWYERS RATHER
THAN VICTIMS.
BECAUSE RIGHT NOW, UNDER THIS
SETTLEMENT, CLAIMANTS COULD
RECEIVE PAYMENTS FROM $3,500 TO
$48,000.
WHICH, YES, FEELS WILDLY
INSUFFICIENT.
BUT SOME FAMILIES ARE
RELUCTANTLY WILLING TO TAKE WHAT
THEY CAN GET.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY OTHERS, LIKE
THIS WOMAN -- WHOSE SON BECAME
ADDICTED TO OPIOIDS AFTER BEING
PRESCRIBED OXYCONTIN AS A HIGH
SCHOOL STUDENT -- ARE FURIOUS
THAT THIS IS WHAT IT'S COME TO.
>> WE WANT OUR VOICES HEARD, NOT
INTERPRETED BY THE COURT LIKE
THEY HAVE BEEN.
I DON'T WANT SOMEBODY SAYING
THAT I LOVE -- I'M SO HAPPY WITH
THE SETTLEMENT AS I HEAR AT
PRACTICALLY EVERY HEARING.
I'M A MOM, I'M NOT HAPPY WITH
ANY OF THIS, AND I KNOW HUNDREDS
OF MOMS THAT AREN'T EITHER AND
FAMILIES.
>> John: EXACTLY.
FOR SOME FAMILIES OF VICTIMS,
THE OPPORTUNITY TO HAVE THEIR
VOICES HEARD IS PRICELESS, WHICH
IS TO SAY, A FUCK OF A LOT MORE
THAN $48,000.
SOME HAVE EVEN CALLED IN TO
COURT ONLY TO BE TOLD IT WASN'T
THE RIGHT FORUM.
ONE WOMAN CALLED IN TO THE
BANKRUPTCY HEARING AND SAID, "I
LOST MY BROTHER TRAGICALLY AT
THE TIP OF THE EPIDEMIC IN 2012.
I WOULD LIKE TO SPEAK IN MEMORY
OF MY BROTHER."
TO WHICH THE JUDGE REPLIED, "I
HOLD HEARINGS ON WHAT IS
SCHEDULED BEFORE ME.
I DON'T THINK THAT THIS IS THE
PROPER FORUM TO DO THIS."
AND THE THING IS, HE'S RIGHT.
BUT THIS ALSO MAY BE THE LAST
FORUM THESE FAMILIES HAVE TO BE
HEARD.
LOOK, IT MIGHT BE TRUE THAT THIS
IS THE BEST DEAL WE CAN GET
UNDER OUR CURRENT SYSTEM.
BUT THE FACT THAT'S THE CASE
DOESN'T SPEAK TO WELL TO THIS
DEAL, OR, INDEED, THE SYSTEM
ITSELF.
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING, "WELL,
THE SACKLERS ARE PAYING SO MUCH
ALREADY, WHAT MORE DO YOU WANT?"
I'M NOT SURE THAT'S THE RIGHT
WAY TO THINK ABOUT THIS.
BECAUSE I'D ARGUE THAT WHEN YOUR
FAMILY'S COMPANY RECKLESSLY SOLD
A PRODUCT AS DAMAGING AS
OXYCONTIN, THE QUESTION MIGHT
NOT BE, "HOW MANY BILLIONS IS IT
RIGHT FOR YOU TO PAY?"
IT'S "HOW MANY BILLIONS IS IT
RIGHT FOR YOU TO KEEP?"
AND I WOULD ARGUE "NO BILLIONS."
AND I'M AFRAID IT GETS ONE STEP
WORSE, BECAUSE THE WAY THIS
SETTLEMENT IS STRUCTURED, IT'S
ACTUALLY HURTING THE SACKLERS
EVEN LESS THAN YOU MIGHT THINK.
THAT $4.3 BILLION THEY'VE AGREED
TO PAY IS SPREAD OUT OVER NINE
YEARS, WITH THE LARGEST PAYMENTS
COMING TOWARD THE END OF THAT
PERIOD, WHICH MEANS THEY COULD
MAKE THAT MONEY UP IN INTEREST
AND INVESTMENTS AND NEVER HAVE
TO TOUCH THE PRINCIPAL.
IN FACT, WHEN THE SACKLERS ARE
DONE PAYING IN 2030, THEY WILL
PROBABLY BE RICHER THAN THEY ARE
TODAY.
SO I GUESS THE ANSWER TO
"WE'RE RICH?
FOR HOW LONG?" IS "DON'T WORRY,
FOREVER, DAVID, BECAUSE IT SEEMS
THAT'S HOW THE FUCKING SYSTEM
WORKS."
UNFORTUNATELY, WHEN IT COMES TO
ACCOUNTABILITY FOR THE SACKLERS,
THIS IS PROBABLY IT.
BECAUSE WHILE, TECHNICALLY, THE
COULD STILL BE CRIMINALLY
CHARGED, NOBODY EXPECTS
THAT TO HAPPEN.
AND IT'S JUST INFURIATING THAT
THINGS ARE SET TO END SO
COMFORTABLY FOR A FAMILY THAT'S
MADE SO MUCH AT THE EXPENSE OF
SO MANY.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, THERE IS
ONE TINY POSITIVE HERE.
AND THAT'S THAT PURDUE AND THE
SACKLERS HAVE ALWAYS HEAVILY
VALUED SECRECY.
BUT THIS DEAL REQUIRES THE
CREATION OF AN ONLINE PUBLIC
REPOSITORY THAT WILL EVENTUALLY
CONTAIN 30 MILLION DOCUMENTS
INCLUDING DEPOSITION VIDEOS AND
THE SACKLERS' COMPANY EMAILS.
WHICH IS UNDENIABLY GOOD.
BUT EVEN WITH THAT, LET'S ADMIT,
WE'RE NOT GETTING ANYTHING
APPROACHING JUSTICE HERE.
AND THE SACKLERS, IN SPARING NO
EXPENSE, HAVE SUCCESSFULLY
BOUGHT THEIR WAY OUT OF THIS
PROBLEM.
WELL, NOT NO EXPENSE.
BECAUSE AGAIN, DESPITE SPENDING
MILLIONS ON LAWYERS, AND EVEN
CREATING A WEBSITE FILLED WITH
LEGAL PROPAGANDA, THEY STILL
SOMEHOW COULDN'T SCRAPE UP THE
$2,500 REQUIRED TO BUY THE
DOT-COM FOR IT.
AND THE REASON I HAPPEN TO KNOW
EXACTLY HOW MUCH IT COSTS IS
BECAUSE THAT'S HOW MUCH WE SPENT
TO BUY IT.
IT'S TRUE: WE BOUGHT
JudgeForYourselves.com,
AND I KNOW THAT IT DOES
ABSOLUTELY NOTHING TO EVEN THE
SCALES HERE.
BUT IT DOES GIVES ME THE TINIEST
BIT OF COMFORT TO IMAGINE IT
MIGHT IRRITATE THE SACKLERS JUST
A BIT TO KNOW THAT WHEN PEOPLE
GO TO THAT SITE IN THE FUTURE,
THIS IS WHAT THEY'LL SEE.
>> HI, IT'S ME.
THE REAL RICHARD SACKLER.
WELCOME TO THE PREMIERE SOURCE
OF INFORMATION ON THE SACKLER
FAMILY THAT YOU CAN FIND ON THE
INTERNET.
IT'S CALLED
JudgeForYourselves.com!
BUT YOU GOTTA GET THE DOT-COM!
[LAUGHS]
WHAT KIND OF FUCKING IDIOT WOULD
SET UP AN IMPORTANT WEBSITE AND
NOT BUY THE DOT-COM?
I DUNNO!
ANYWAY, IF YOU WANT THE TRUTH,
YOU'VE COME TO THE RIGHT PLACE.
SO CLICK AROUND, OKAY?
GET A SENSE OF WHAT MY TERRIBLE
FAMILY HAS DONE.
YOU KNOW, MAYBE WE'LL THROW IN
SOME MAKE-UP TIDBITS.
I DON'T KNOW.
MAYBE HOW TO MAKE A GREAT PESTO
CHICKEN.
ANYWAY, THERE'S SOME GREAT
BUTTONS THAT YOU PRESS AROUND
AND YOU'LL GET THERE SOMEHOW.
ANYWAY, BEST OF LUCK TO YOU.
ALL RIGHT.
BYE-BYE.
>> John: THANK YOU,
RICHARD SACKLER.
THIS NEW WEBSITE LETS
YOU "JUDGE FOR YOURSELVES"
WHETHER THE SACKLERS GOT OFF TOO
EASY -- WHICH THEY DID.
ON IT, YOU CAN SEE RICHARD
SACKLER'S FULL DEPOSITION, ALL
OF OUR EPISODES ABOUT THE
OPIOIDS CRISIS, AND THERE'S EVEN
A LINK THAT WILL EVENTUALLY
DIRECT YOU TO THE DOCUMENT
REPOSITORY THE MOMENT IT'S
LAUNCHED.
ALSO, BECAUSE THE FAMILIES OF
THOSE IMPACTED BY THE SACKLERS
HAVEN'T ALWAYS BEEN HEARD, THERE
ARE SOME EXCERPTS ON THE WEBSITE
OF WHAT SOME OF THEM WANTED TO
SAY.
ALL OF THIS WILL BE UP AS LONG
AS WE OWN THE DOMAIN.
AND THIS IS AT LEAST SOMETHING
THE SACKLERS CAN'T THROW THEIR
DIRTY MONEY AT AND MAKE GO AWAY.
WHICH IS NOT TO SAY THAT IT
ISN'T FOR SALE AT ALL,
SACKLER FAMILY.
IT'S AVAILABLE FOR A PRICE.
LET'S SAY $10 BILLION.
THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANKS SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
GOOD NIGHT!
♪ ♪
>> HEY!
ME AGAIN!
RICHARD SACKLER!
LISTEN, THE DOCUMENTS AREN'T OUT
YET.
I WISH THEY WERE, BUT THEY'RE
NOT.
WHAT ARE YOU GOING TO DO?
KEEP CHECKING BACK, ALL RIGHT?