LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
Welcome to "Last Week Tonight"!
I'm John Oliver.
Thank you so much for joining us.
It has been another busy week.
The Senate confirmed Ketanji
Brown Jackson to the Supreme Court,
Elon Musk
joined the board of Twitter,
presumably to innovate new ways
to make it even worse,
and the Russian invasion of Ukraine
continued to escalate,
with reports of unfathomable horrors,
strongly suggesting war crimes,
if not genocide.
I know this is allegedly
a comedy show,
and I have said the most upsetting
collection of words
since "Louis C.K. wins Grammy
for best comedy album."
But we do need to at least briefly deal
with what is going on in Ukraine,
and particularly Bucha, site of some of
the worst images to emerge this week.
Because Russian state TV
is going out of its way not to.
Here is how one broadcaster there
spun those terrible images
of bodies in the streets.
There are people on the screen
that are lying dead in the street
with white armbands.
What does that mean? It means
that after Russian forces left Bucha,
the so-called liberators came in and
they simply killed peaceful civilians.
On the screen, people are moving. That
means that actors were also involved.
A conclusion out of all of this is
that to achieve their media goals,
the Ukrainian Kyiv regime
killed its own people.
So that man's official argument is
Ukrainians killed their own civilians,
who aren't civilians, they're actors
who were just pretending to be dead,
and the Ukrainian government itself
is responsible for the real slaughter
of its own fake civilians.
That is obviously ridiculous, and
also ignores the first rule of lying:
don't over-complicate.
There is a reason the line is,
"I definitely have a girlfriend,
she just goes to another school",
and not, "I definitely have
a girlfriend, she's actually twins,
sometimes they merge
and become one really big girl,
I'd invite you to come over
and meet them,
but that might be confusing,
because I am you from the future."
Russian state TV has been grasping
at straws all week,
with a presenter
at one point arguing,
as evidence that Bucha
was the site of a false flag attack,
that "Biden said that Putin
is a butcher.
Bucha sounds like 'butcher.'
How could they not take advantage
of such a town?"
Which is just insane.
If bad things only happened in
places with names that sounded scary,
all of America's worst shit would
be happening in Tombstone, Arizona,
Cape Fear, North Carolina,
or Hell, Michigan,
and not where it actually happens,
Tallahassee, Florida.
But this flagrant lying is consistent
with how Russia's state media
has been dealing
with this war from the beginning.
At first, they refused to even
acknowledge that there was a war,
let alone address casualties.
Just watch what happened
last month
when a military officer
merely mentioned Russian deaths.
Our guys are really out there,
both Donetsk and Luhansk (forces),
and our special operation forces,
they're dying now.
And our country...
No! I don't want to hear this!
Wait!
- They're dying anyway!
- Stop!
- Can't you stop, or what?
I just want us to stand up now
and honor their memories
at least with a minute of silence.
What are you doing?
Our boys that are still fighting over
there for Russia and for the Donbas.
Can you stop now?
Close call there! Russian viewers
almost learned that their troops
were being killed until that host
jumped up and screamed,
"Whoa, ix-nay
on the asualties-cay".
Some truly grade-A
propaganda work there
from the network
that brought you
"Shut Up About
Vladimir Putin's Election Fraud"
and "Poisoning Opponents?
I Can't Hear You."
It seems Russia
is determined to deny the obvious
and to justify
the indefensible here.
But that is getting increasingly hard
to do.
And if you think
"those bodies are actually actors"
is as pathetic as it got this week,
just listen to Rossiya 24's
ridiculous explanation.
This is how the preparation
for performance, literally,
of military actions in Ukraine
is taking place.
As you can see,
it's quite uncomplicated.
Two people in military uniforms
carefully wrap the mannequin with tape,
obviously, they are going
to pass it off as a corpse.
That is clearly absurd, not only are
the Ukrainian casualties obviously real
that footage turned out to be
part of a TV drama
being filmed
near St. Petersburg last month.
If you're wondering which TV show,
it's "Zoey's Extraordinary Playlist."
What can I say?
Russian audiences really connect
with the story of a woman forced
to hallucinate a more joyful existence.
And there will be more to say about
the Ukrainian situation as it develops.
But for now, let's move to a much less
consequential story concerning OAN,
the network with a logo that looks
like it belongs on the side of a truck
transporting refrigerator parts.
We've talked about OAN
a few times over the years,
primarily because they were
Trump's favorite news outlet,
as well as a perpetual source
of misinformation about Covid
and platform for pillow prince Mike
Lindell's election-fraud documentary
"Absolute Proof".
And yes,
I am using the word "documentary" there
with Christlike generosity.
This was a big week for OAN,
although not in a good way,
as one of their anchors explained.
Come Monday,
you will no longer see One America
News on a certain satellite provider,
which I will not mention
because I don't even like uttering
their name out of my mouth.
Ah, yes, the hallmark
of a great news network,
bringing you hard-hitting
news stories
without specifics
because they make the anchor sad.
The provider that he's referring
to there is DirecTV,
which is a subsidiary
of a parent company I will not mention
because I don't even like uttering
their name out of my mouth.
Interestingly, as of Friday,
AT&T officially no longer owns us,
so it is goodbye from me,
business daddy.
And let me say this, which is frankly
two more bars than you have ever had.
Now, as we've mentioned before,
AT&T was instrumental in OAN's rise,
with about 90% of its revenue
reportedly generated
from its AT&T
and DirecTV deals.
But this past week, OAN
was finally dropped by the provider,
and not a moment too soon.
Its coverage of Ukraine, in particular,
has been appalling,
with this fucking guy suggesting that
this bombing of a maternity hospital
might have been a hoax.
So, what's the most recent story
cooked up by the American Pravda?
It turns out that the Russians,
Democrats' favorite adversary,
blew up a hospital, killing
several people, including a child.
Perhaps war crimes
are being committed,
perhaps civilians
are being murdered,
but perhaps they aren't.
It is pretty maddening
to watch neo-fascist Vin Diesel there
question civilian casualties
with the tone of a stoned teenager
talking about penguins.
"Perhaps they're wearing
little bird tuxedos,
but perhaps... they aren't?"
Losing distribution on DirecTV
is clearly a big blow to OAN,
and they are not going out
without a fight,
as their owners are currently suing
AT&T and DirecTV for $1 billion,
claiming at one point in the suit
that AT&T
breached a "non-disparagement
provision" in their contract,
because shows the company
owned had been critical of them.
And here is where things
get a bit fun.
Because it turns out,
we're actually in that lawsuit.
It cites a number of things
that I said about OAN in the past,
like the fact they are "Fox News with
less shame and even fewer scruples,"
and a "ragtag band of fascists"
who are "happy to give a platform
to batshit election fraud theories
from America's most out-of-breath
pillow fetishist."
And while I am truly happy
to have said all of those things,
I cannot believe
that they left out the fact
that I also called this guy
"decaf Pitbull" just last year,
and frankly, I want that entered
into the legal record.
And look,
I do get that they are upset here.
Just as I get that they are an
intellectually bankrupt organization
full of grifters who've done nothing
but make this country a worse place.
But perhaps
this isn't the time for that.
And perhaps I am sorry
for taking joy in their misfortune
and kicking them
when they are so clearly down.
But on the other hand,
perhaps I am not.
And now, this!
And Now: Things Get Uncomfortable
on Local News
Thanks to a Terrible Holiday.
Allegedly,
it's National Hug a Newsperson Day.
My goodness.
I'm good, fam. I'm good.
I am also good.
I don't want anything.
Today is National
Hug a Newsperson Day.
Or don't. I guess. Apparently.
Jackie, is there anyone you really
want to give a hug to?
First of all, I hate hugs.
You know that. I hate hugs.
I was like, I'm going to give you,
and then I remembered. Yeah.
So much! I hate hugs.
So much, like, even with my family.
- Am I ever going to hug you?
- No, do not...
Today is National Hug
a Newsperson Day.
Just don't come up and hug
somebody you don't know.
- Just don't hug you?
- I don't know you.
- Hug a Newsperson Day.
- You made that up.
- I did not make that up!
- Did you find it on a bogus website?
- What are you doing?
- I'm warming up my hugging muscles.
Who are you hugging?
Maybe Patrick will get a hug today
from Krista, we'll see.
I don't think he'd want one.
Who knows? Justin got one last hour,
but that was an interesting one.
Moving on. Our main story tonight
concerns computers.
There's one in my house,
one in my pocket, and one on my wrist,
and, fun fact, if they all broke
at the same time, I'd die!
More specifically,
we're going to talk about the fact
that we've all had unsettling moments
when it became clear
that our computer
was monitoring our activities
a little more closely
than we might like.
After financial planner Rod Laurenz
opened a new office,
he used a credit card to buy baby wipes
to clean the place.
He says after picking up
just one canister,
he was shocked to be bombarded
with targeted online ads
for other baby wipes
and more children's products,
something this single guy
around town
says he's definitely not interested in,
at least not now.
Yeah, it's true. Poor Rod got roped
into the modern update
of Hemingway's classic story,
"For sale. Baby shoes. Click here."
Of course Rod didn't want that shit.
He was a man about town!
He was only interested in three things:
getting laids, getting paids,
and rocking the hell
out of some wrap-around shades.
But we have all found ourselves
being targeted by ads
for something
oddly specific and thought,
"How on earth did
they know to show me that?"
And tonight, we're going to talk
about who makes that possible:
data brokers.
It's a multibillion-dollar industry,
encompassing everyone
from credit-reporting companies,
to these weird people-finding websites
that pop up
whenever you Google the name
of your friend's sketchy new boyfriend,
to these names
that you may never have heard of.
But what all these companies
have in common is,
they collect your personal information
and resell or share it with others.
As one expert puts it, they're the
"middlemen of surveillance capitalism."
Which sounds
like both a horrific profession
and also,
a B-plus Jake Gyllenhaal thriller.
He's not a spy, and he's not a civilian.
He's the middleman.
And ladies?
In this one, he shows trunk.
I know it is not news
that you get tracked online.
In fact,
roughly six in 10 U.S. adults
say that they don't think
it is possible to go through daily life
"without having data collected about
them by companies or the government,"
making four out of 10
U.S. adults embarrassingly wrong.
But this isn't about the convenience
and/or irritation of targeted ads.
Data brokers operate in a sprawling,
unregulated ecosystem,
which can get very creepy,
very fast.
The major U.S. retailer
OfficeMax
new not only that Mike Seay's
daughter was dead,
but how she died.
It says, "Mike Seay, Daughter Killed
in Car Crash or Current Business",
and this is my home.
Why would they have
that kind of information?
Why would they need that?
Right, and obviously
that is completely appalling.
But I will say,
it is not that surprising to me
that OfficeMax was behind that,
as they're clearly not entirely
on top of their shit.
If you Google "OfficeMax"
right now,
the "people also ask" questions
include, and this is true,
"Is OfficeMax
the same as Office Depot?"
"Is OfficeMax and Staples the same?"
and "Does OfficeMax exist?"
The truth is,
when it comes to data brokers,
they know significantly more
about you than you might like,
and do significantly more with it
than you might think.
So tonight,
let's talk about the whole industry.
And let's start with how
your information is collected.
Basically, every time
you interact with society,
you are leaving little breadcrumbs
that can be gathered together and sold.
And much of this happens online,
thanks in large part to cookies.
Cookies were developed
in the early days of the internet,
and they're actually one of the things
that make it slightly better,
a distinction that they share
with Henry Winkler's Twitter feed
and literally nothing else.
What they essentially do is enable
websites to remember you.
They are why Amazon remembers
that you put a $106 complete box set
of "The Mentalist" in your cart
after eating an unexpectedly strong
weed gummy, even if you don't.
And if that's all cookies did,
it'd honestly be fine.
But the practice gradually evolved
to include third-party cookies,
basically, companies other than
the site that you are on,
planting a piece of code
in your browser
that allows them to track where else
you are going on the internet.
Just watch as a tech writer
explains what they found
when they tried to learn just how
many companies were tracking them.
So, I started the day on Google
and did a search.
And nine trackers were downloaded
onto my computer.
Trackers do what it sounds
like they do. They track you.
They can get my IP address or the
device I'm using, or the screen size.
They were able to determine
my location very precisely.
Next, I went to HuffPo,
and I was swarmed.
The trackers kind of multiplied.
There were dozens and dozens.
And the trackers are just kind of,
you know, on my heels
as I go around the web.
And I don't know about you, but I
don't want a whole crowd of strangers
watching what I search for
on the internet.
Not because it's gross. It's private.
Private doesn't have to mean gross.
There's nothing gross
about looking up, let's say,
"Are there any showerheads
with a 'contains pulp' option?"
I wouldn't want it all the time,
I wouldn't need it all the time.
That's why it's an option.
The option to have some pulp.
In the shower.
It's, can I finish?
It's a normal shower most
of the time, but occasionally
I'll have the option to get pelted with
something that's got some heft to it.
Just some weighted chunks
of whatever.
Something to wake me up
and keep me on my toes.
Sometimes I need it,
don't claim that you don't.
We'd all love to pretend
that the sun only rises in peacetime,
but things being what they are,
we find ourselves again at war.
So, yeah, start my day and rock me
with some juicy bits.
That's what I want.
And I don't want anyone watching me
when I search to see how close we are
to that particular technology existing,
because it is private.
But data brokers
often take all the breadcrumbs
that they have gathered about you,
pair them with other data they obtain,
and then share all of it with
businesses who want to market to you.
And they will frame this
as a win-win.
Here is how Epsilon, one of the biggest
data-broker firms, positions itself.
This is a person.
So is this. Here's another.
And another.
They all look and act different,
but people are fundamentally the same.
They all want respect, protection,
and an easier time getting the things
they need from brands.
Right! The big three!
It's all in Maslow's
famous hierarchy of needs,
people want their physiological
needs met, their safety accounted for,
and their search history handed over
directly to the Aflac Duck.
Epsilon's ad even goes on to show
how that service of theirs works,
demonstrating how they can create
a client ID
for someone that contains
everything they know about them,
like the fact they're a vegan and
that they make 45 to $50,000 a year,
or that they are a 41-year-old male
who is married with kids at home
and is Googling "snow globe stuck
in butt, what to do, question mark."
Once companies like Epsilon collect
enough information about you,
they can sort you into groups.
Data broker firms sell access
to lists with names like
"couples with clout," "ambitious
singles," "boomers and boomerangs,"
"potlucks and the great outdoors,"
"golf carts and gourmets,"
and "kids and cabernet."
Those are all both real names
of groups compiled by a data broker
and, as of now, immediately
greenlit shows on TLC.
And, look, you might not care if
a company wants to toss your data
in a group
called "kids and cabernet"
so marketers can more
effectively sell you things
that make you seem
like a bad mom in a fun way,
but there is also a dark side here.
Because some companies can,
and do,
draw up even more narrowly
targeted lists,
like people with certain ailments,
or sexual preferences,
and then sell those lists
to anyone who wants to buy them.
And what they can buy
is pretty troubling.
WRAL bought thousands
of names and addresses
of local people
with serious illnesses.
This group living
in the 27607 ZIP code have diabetes.
These people in 27608
have cancer.
These residents of 27609
have high blood pressure.
And all of these locals
battle depression.
This list is moms-to-be.
So, we bought this data,
and it tells us you're pregnant.
- Yes.
- And you are?
Yeah, I am 18 weeks.
That's pretty creepy, isn't it?
I honestly did not think
there could be a worse thing
to ask a woman you don't know
than "are you pregnant?"
But "you are pregnant,
wanna know who I paid to find out?"
has certainly entered the chat.
And if you're thinking, "But
that's illegal under HIPAA, right?"
No. As one researcher pointed out,
the medical information
that you relay to your physician
is highly protected,
but if you go to a medical website
and search for terms
like "HIV" or "abortion," that
information is not protected at all.
It's a system
that seems ripe for abuse
before you learn that some
data brokers have offered lists
such as, "Suffering Seniors",
"Pay Day Loan Central Hispanic",
or even "Help Needed,
I Am 90 Days Behind on Bills".
And some in this industry
will insist that they would never put
people at risk by selling their data.
Remember Epsilon,
the company that collects
clouds of information about you?
In 2014, their then-CEO
even went on "60 Minutes"
to reassure people that his business,
in particular,
operated in a completely
above-board manner.
If there are abuses out there,
we don't believe those happen
within our company,
and we would be
the first to raise our hand.
Really? You would be the first
to raise your hand, would you?
That is interesting.
Especially because last year,
Epsilon settled with the DOJ
for $150 million
for facilitating elder fraud schemes,
after admitting that it sold
more than 30 million consumers' data
to clients who employees
knew were carrying out scams.
And they were doing it
for nearly a decade.
So, I guess that that guy should've
been doing that entire interview
with his fucking hand in the air.
At this point, you may be thinking,
"Okay. I think I get it.
I am sufficiently creeped out, there is
nothing more that you need to tell me."
Well, hold on. What about
the fact that apps on your phone
can give away your exact location
to third parties,
sometimes without you
even knowing it?
This free flashlight app settled
with the FTC for doing just that.
And they are not alone.
Take Life360, an app giving families
the opportunity to keep track
of one another.
You may have seen their ads
featuring parents looking relieved
because they can see
where their kids are going
and know when they have
safely reached their destination.
Guess what?
A new report from the website
The Markup says that Life360
sells its location data
to about a dozen different brokers,
who then sell it to marketers.
It turns out they were selling location
data to around 12 different brokers.
It's like those old commercials:
"It's 10 o'clock,
do you know where your children are?
'Cause if so, same!"
And I have to tell you, Life360 insists
that they are no longer doing that,
and that anyway, they had de-identified
their users' data before selling it.
That last claim
is actually very common
among both data brokers
and the companies that they work with,
and it is worth taking a look at.
'Cause while it sounds reassuring,
the truth is, it can be incredibly easy
to find out
who is behind a number or a code.
One team of researchers even found
that 99.98 percent of Americans
would be correctly re-identified
in any data set
using just 15 demographic attributes,
among them age, gender, marital status.
And the ease of de-anonymizing data
is something that we have
actually known about for years.
In 2006,
AOL turned over a bunch
of these anonymized search records
of their users to the public,
and it only took a few short hours
for a reporter to decode
who user number 4417749 was.
Between searches for things like
"numb fingers," "60s single men",
and "dog that urinates
on everything",
the reporter uncovered
a woman named Thelma Arnold.
She was age 62.
Okay, I am not saying that it is at all
pleasant that that happened,
but for the record, I am glad that it
introduced me to Thelma Arnold
because I love that woman.
She hasn't given up,
despite her numb fingers,
lackluster love life,
and utterly broken dog.
None of that is stopping her
from shooting her shot
and looking for single men
in her area.
We stan a middle-aged queen
with stamina.
As we looked into this story,
we constantly got reminders
that none of us
are really anonymous online.
At one point, a researcher
clicked on this company's website,
didn't do anything else,
just went there on his browser,
and later that day, got this email,
saying that they knew he visited,
and "We offer a pretty cool service
called Website Visitor Identification
which helps brands identify
who's browsing their website.
In fact, it's how we knew
how to send you this quick email!"
Which is just objectively unsettling.
I don't want anyone tracking
what my staff members are doing online,
mainly because I don't want to know
how many of them have looked up
"What is John Oliver like?"
And it is not like data brokers
are super careful
about who gets
your sensitive information.
You have already seen a local news
station ambush a pregnant woman.
And a few years ago, CBS bought
some location data from brokers
and it did not take much for them
to find out whose it was,
where they lived,
and what they were doing.
No names or phone numbers
were tied to the data,
but it was easy to figure out
who each phone belongs to
based on where they spend
their nights here in Greenwich.
One phone pinged in the morning
inside a $7 million mansion.
The person
then visited a country club
before heading downtown
and returning home.
That doesn't feel great, does it?
Although I will say, that particular
example is not that surprising to me.
If you told me
an individual woke up
in a $7 million mansion
in Greenwich, Connecticut,
and made me guess where they
went next, I'd have gone with,
"I don't know, a country club,
downtown to hunt humans for sport,
and then home again."
And I'd have been pretty sure
that I was right.
And the thing is,
that kind of identifying information
can cause huge problems.
Just last year,
a priest was forced to resign
after a Catholic newsletter said
it used app data signals from Grindr
to monitor his activity, and matching
his phone to his residence,
essentially outing him.
Which is a massive,
harmful invasion of privacy,
and definitely the worst scandal
ever to hit the Catholic Church.
Also, just quick side note here.
Catholic Church, are you absolutely
sure that Jesus was homophobic?
Think about it, he had mutually
respectful friendships with women,
a distant relationship
with his father,
and when he found out
he was going to be betrayed,
he invited everyone
to a confrontational dinner.
I'm just saying it might be worth
re-examining your thesis there.
And look, you might still think,
"I don't care about this.
My life is an open book,
I have no secrets,
so data brokers
can just have at it."
Even if that is true for you, though,
consider there are others out there
who might have very good reasons
to not want to be found.
Donna is a domestic violence victim.
We're protecting her identity.
One of her addresses
came up on a data broker site.
She says that's frightening.
If you have
someone that's tried to kill you,
for them to be able
to just type in your name
and any known address
that you've ever stayed in can pop up,
it's scary because now they know
ways to start trying to find you.
Right, and that's not just theoretical,
it has happened.
In New Hampshire,
a stalker killed a former classmate
after finding her with information
that he bought from a data broker
for $45.
And if you have a stalker, or you
are a victim of domestic violence,
it is understandable
to want your information
removed from these
people-search sites.
But each has its own specific,
and sometimes very complex
process of requesting
the removal of information.
And there is no federal law requiring
that they honor an opt-out request.
And the lack of regulation here
doesn't just benefit individuals
who might mean you harm,
it benefits the government, too.
Because it gives them
a very attractive loophole
to the Fourth Amendment protection
against unreasonable
search and seizures.
Because under that, the government
typically needs a warrant
to collect information
about you without your consent.
But if it is not forcing someone
to turn over your data,
if it's simply buying it
from a data broker,
that is apparently fine,
no warrant necessary.
And you can see how valuable
that would be to them.
It happens all the time.
In fact, federal agencies from the
FBI to ICE have purchased data,
"without warrants, public disclosures,
or robust oversight,
to carry out everything from criminal
investigations to deportations."
And you might not know
if your information has been supplied
to the government by an app.
Even the company
behind the app might not know.
Because it might sell
your info to a broker,
which then resells it to someone else,
which supplies it to the government.
I'll give you an example:
a couple years back,
Vice found that the app Muslim Pro,
which let Muslims know when to pray,
had been selling user location data
to a broker that supplied information
to the U.S. government.
And while,
because the chain is so opaque,
it is hard to know what was sold,
or what the government did with it,
the app's users
were understandably pretty alarmed.
Feeling disturbed,
appalled, but not surprised.
Sara Mostafavi used Muslim Pro,
that app has since reportedly
severed ties with its data partners.
So intrusive!
My conversation with God
is not information
the government needs.
Yeah, of course it's not information
There's a reason the book wasn't called
"Are You There God? It's Me Margaret
and Homeland Security's On the Line
as Well, Hope That's Cool."
So, to recap here,
we've got shady data brokers
with virtually
no oversight collecting your data
and building profiles that can track
who you are, where you are,
and what you are most
likely to do or buy.
You cannot edit this dossier,
and others,
from cops to reporters
to your own abusers,
can find and use this information.
It's not a great situation.
So, what do we do?
Well, it is a bit tricky,
especially given the fact
that the entire economy
of the internet right now
is basically built on this practice.
All the free stuff
that you take for granted online
is only free
because you are the product.
They make money
by selling your data.
But experts say
that there are actually some small
steps that you can personally take.
You can use
web browsers like these
to help better protect you
against third-party tracking.
And if you have an iPhone,
you can go to the privacy menu,
hit the tracking button,
and turn off "allow apps
to request to track."
But this should
not be your responsibility,
your privacy should be
the default setting here.
And there should be legal fixes to this.
Other countries have actually tried.
The EU passed a law
to force sites to disclose cookies
and allow you to opt-out.
But, I will say, companies now
often cleverly present those options
in the most annoying way possible,
with "accept all cookies"
an easy default,
but if you want to reject them,
forcing you to go through multiple
confusing steps for no clear reason.
Which is very smart,
to be honest.
No one is going to put in the work
to reject cookies
just to sneak a peek at an article
titled "Five Times
Andrew Garfield Just Was."
You'd much rather just hit "accept"
and enjoy your remaining time on Earth
gazing at the most emotionally
connected Spiderman
to ever splooge the ooze.
Now, as for here in the U.S.,
individual states have tried
to limit data brokers,
but advocates
say that what is really needed
is a comprehensive federal
privacy law governing them.
This has been proposed
for years now,
but nothing has happened,
for a couple of key reasons.
First, data broker spending
on lobbying in 2020
rivaled that of Facebook and Google.
But also,
politicians now famously
build their campaigns
on data obtained from brokers.
Both parties regularly boast
about how much they use data.
And in fact, just listen to former
RNC Chair Reince Preibus
openly bragging about it.
Everything about almost every
potential voter in Georgia is known.
And it's not even a joke,
they know what beer they drink,
what car they drive,
how many kids they have,
and all that data is used to target
every single voter in Georgia.
It's true.
Politicians rely on data
to be able to target our interests
with pinpoint precision.
Although I do wonder
why no presidential candidate
has then yet targeted me personally
with ads promising to fight
for the shower of morning chunks
I so richly deserve.
I Google it all the time,
you would have my vote instantly.
It is frustrating that the people who
could do something about data brokers
are so actively incentivized not to.
But here is where
we may be able to help.
Because, interestingly,
the one time that Congress
has acted quickly
to safeguard people's privacy
was back in the 1980s,
when Robert Bork
was nominated to the Supreme Court,
and a reporter
walked into a local video store
and asked the manager
whether he could have a peek
at Bork's video rental history,
and he got it.
And as soon as Congress realized
there was nothing stopping anyone
from retrieving
their video rental records, too,
they freaked the fuck out,
and lo and behold,
The Video Privacy Protection Act
was passed with quite deliberate speed.
So, it does seem when Congress'
own privacy is at risk,
they somehow find a way to act.
And it also seems
like they are not entirely aware
just how easy it is for anyone,
and I do mean anyone,
to get their personal information.
Which brings me to me.
Because in researching this story,
we realized there is any number
of perfectly legal bits of fuckery
that we could engage in.
We could, for example,
use data brokers to go fishing
for members of Congress,
by creating a demographic group
consisting of men aged 45 and up,
in a five-mile radius
of the U.S. Capitol,
who had previously
visited sites regarding,
or searched for terms including,
"divorce," "massage,"
"hair loss," and "midlife crisis."
We could call that group
"Congress and Cabernet,"
and then target that list with ads
that might attract those men to click,
like, "Marriage shouldn't be a prison,"
or "Can you vote twice?"
We could also throw in,
"Do you want to read Ted Cruz
erotic fan fiction?"
just to see what would happen.
And if anyone clicked,
we would then be able to harvest
even more data from them,
which we could then theoretically
take steps to de-anonymize.
Now, am I saying that
we're actually going to do that?
Collect all that raw information
and store it in,
let's say,
a manila envelope somewhere?
I'm sorry to disappoint you:
we are not going to do that.
Why would we,
when we've already done it?
Because...
All that raw data
is currently right in here.
And honestly, this whole
exercise was fucking creepy.
We ran those three targeted ads
this week in the Capitol Hill area,
and to give you just a sense
of how many clicks we got,
it was very much not zero.
Do you want to see more?
Because I do! Please, come with me.
'Cause...
Let's start
with the very first hit that we got.
It came at 3:35 PM
on Tuesday afternoon
from around
the Embassy Row area,
when a man fitting our demographic
description clicked on the Ted Cruz ad,
meaning that we now have
his IP address and device ID,
and also know that he did it
on an Android phone.
So, we could now take steps
to identify him.
Just like we could
with all these others
who clicked on one of our ads
in the Capitol Hill area this week,
including at least three
who may have been inside
the Capitol Building itself.
One of whom clicked on
the "Can you vote twice?" ad,
one of whom clicked
on the divorce one
and another who clicked
on the Ted Cruz erotic fanfiction,
which was distressingly popular.
And if you're thinking,
"How on earth is any of this legal?"
I totally agree with you,
it shouldn't be.
And if you happen to be
a legislator who is feeling
a little nervous right now
about whether your information
is in this envelope,
and you are terrified
about what I might do with it,
you might want
to channel that worry
into making sure
that I can't do anything.
Anyway, sleep well!
That's our show.
Thank you so much for watching.
We'll see you next week. Good night!