LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
Season 2
Episode 16
Welcome, welcome, welcome
to Last Week Tonight.
I'm John Oliver,
thank you so much
for being with us
this evening.
Just time for a quick recap
of the week,
and obviously we begin
with FIFA,
the sports organization
that is much easier to pronounce
than "Niffle", "Mulb",
or "Unba".
Last week, we covered
FIFA's recent scandals,
and how shocking it was that their
Swiss lizard of a president,
Sepp Blatter,
was still in office.
Well, on Tuesday there
was some amazing news.
Top of the hour as Sepp Blatter
shocks the globe.
You don't often say that with accuracy,
but that happened today,
resigning as the president
of FIFA.
Oh, my God !
He's leaving !
He's actually leaving !
I feel like a
Greenpeace volunteer
who successfully got
someone's attention.
I didn't think
this would happen,
and now I don't know
what to do.
Now, if you watched us
last week, you'll know
that I may have some personal Bud Light
Lime related consequences due to this.
We will deal with that
later in the show.
But for now,
let's just focus on the story,
because the timing of
Blatter's announcement
was notable for two reasons.
First, it was only four days
after being reelected president.
That's like being elected pope
and immediately announcing,
"Judaism makes some
good points.
I think I may have
got this wrong."
And secondly, Blatter stepped down
just days before the U.S. release
of United Passions, a suspiciously
glowing movie history of FIFA.
This is the movie version
of Sepp Blatter,
played by Tim Roth
and largely bankrolled
by the football
organization itself.
This movie theater is the only one
in New York showing United Passions.
We're just a few minutes
from the very first showing,
and, well, they're not exactly
fighting off the crowds.
Am I the only person
going to see this film ?
So far.
Okay.
So I say this.
To the one person
in New York who has been looking
for a large private room in which
to masturbate to images of Tim Roth,
it would appear you
are finally in luck.
Thank you for your patience.
The reviews so far
have been phenomenal.
The Guardian said that
"as cinema, it is excrement."
And The New York Times called it
"one of the most unwatchable films
in recent memory."
And remember,
this is the same week
the Entourage movie came out.
Hashtag, the boys are back.
But perhaps most worrying
of all for FIFA
was that their former
vice president Jack Warner,
who stands accused of facilitating
at least $10 million in bribes,
has indicated he might
take everyone else down with him.
In a rambling seven-minute
video he released Wednesday
entitled "Jack Warner:
The Gloves Are Off,"
he vowed to reveal
rampant wrongdoing
at the highest levels
of world soccer.
I have, as promised, comparative,
comprehensive series of documents
including checks and statements
and I placed them
in different and respected hands.
I don't know what
I love more about that,
that he released a video
that was basically a veiled threat,
or that it played
on Trinidadian television.
Because apparently,
you can just buy time on TV there
to say whatever you like.
So here's the thing,
that's what we've done.
We have...
We have more to say to Jack Warner
than we have room for here.
So we bought five minutes of airtime
on Trinidad's TV 6
at 9:01 p.m. on Tuesday.
We will be preempting the first
five minutes of, and this is true,
Mike & Molly,
and we'll be doing it
with "John Oliver:
The Mittens
Of Disapproval Are On."
So fly to Trinidad on Tuesday
if you want to see that.
But for now, the rest of us,
let's move on
to cyber security,
the only reason most of us
know our mother's maiden name.
It's an increasingly
important part of America's defense,
and on Thursday
we saw why.
This morning the U.S.
government is struggling
to assess the damage,
officials revealing possibly
the biggest cyber attack
on the U.S. government ever breached
their critical computer networks.
Okay, CNN, a hack into government
computers is perfectly scary enough
without adding leftover
graphics from The Matrix.
The problem is already huge
without the specter
of a merciless kung fu quasi-Jesus
in a duster jacket.
The hackers broke into systems
containing information
for more than four million
current and former federal employees,
potentially hitting
every federal agency
from the Department
of Justice all the way
to even the National
Marine Fisheries Service.
Which means there could be an
undercover Fisheries officer right now
whose information
is in the hands of hackers.
Sergeant Gillis,
swim away !
Your cover's blown !
Get out of there !
So I have to know,
who is responsible for this ?
According to officials,
evidence points to hackers
working for
the Chinese military.
The motive here may be
to obtain personal information
that can be used
for blackmail purposes
to turn some of those
U.S. employees
into spies, perhaps even,
for the Chinese, at least informants.
That's crazy.
Listen, China.
If you want to blackmail Americans,
you're going about this wrong.
Don't bother hacking into government
computers to grab our personnel files.
Just get our browser histories
and we'll turn traitor instantly.
Because you can have
our Social Security numbers,
but there is no one on Earth
who would not betray their country
to keep people from finding out that
their last five Google searches were
"What country are dragons in ?",
"Ray Romano nip slip,"
"Sexiest cats,"
"Tinder one year
no matches troubleshoot,"
and "Uncontrollable
farting cancer ?"
You want leverage, China,
that's where you'll find it.
And finally,
finally this week, Turkey.
Turkey, the country that's always
much bigger than you think it is.
Much like Tim Robbins. Did you know
he's six-five ? He's very big.
Turkey's election was today,
and the ruling party
lost their majority.
The election turned on too many issues
to get into now,
but there was one
which I have to mention,
because last week
opposition leader Kemal Kilicdaroglu
accused Turkey's president
Recep Erdogan
of wasting taxpayer money
on something truly ridiculous.
Opposition leader
Kemal Kilicdaroglu
accused the president
of using taxpayers' money
to decorate his bathroom,
most notably
with a golden lavatory.
Yes. He claimed Erdogan
has a golden toilet.
And that hurts, 'cause on the list of
offensive symbols of wealth,
that is somewhere between
having a servant carry you
everywhere piggyback style
and owning poor people
touching gloves.
It's a heavy accusation,
which is why Erdogan
hit back hard.
The president issued a challenge
to the opposition leader.
I invite him
to please come
and take a tour.
I wonder if he'll be able to find
such a golden toilet seat
in any of these washrooms.
If he finds it,
I will resign from the presidency.
If he can't find them,
he will resign from his party.
Yes, you heard that right.
He was offering a good,
old-fashioned,
loser leaves town
Turkish toilet hunt.
And those
are some high stakes.
Because normally, the worst thing that
happens when you can't find a toilet
is you tie a sweatshirt
around your waist
and you quietly leave
the house party.
Now, sadly, the challenge was refused,
which is a tragedy.
Because what Erdogan was proposing
was a literal game of thrones.
"All this power will be yours, if you
can find the fabled golden toilet.
However, if you cannot, you shall
be banished from the kingdom.
For in the game of thrones,
you poop or you die."
And now, this.
And now,
Last Week Tonight salutes
all the horses
who didn't win the triple crown
this week !
Here's to you...
Wickets and Biscuits
Nimble Tim,
Bumblebee's Climax,
Oedipal Steve,
White Guilt,
Why Did Daddy Leave ?,
Tomorrow's Glue,
Recliners ! Recliners ! Recliners !,
DR. JUDDY LEVINSON, D.D.S.
Shakira's Tapeworm,
and Hank Bonesack,
Private Investigator.
Congratulations on being horses !
To us, you're all winners !
AND
NOW
Our main story tonight
is bail.
We're so used to it, it has become
a fixture of American life.
Down here at the shore,
one minute you got three girls
in a Jacuzzi, next minute
somebody's in jail
and you have to
bail them out.
That's what happens
down at the shore.
The other thing that happens
down at the shore ? Chlamydia.
Just a medically astounding
rate of chlamydia.
At its heart, America's bail system
sounds pretty simple.
If you're charged with a crime,
the court might ask for an amount
of money as bond and then return it
to you once you show up for trial.
And if you have that money,
it's no big deal.
But if you don't,
you can be in big trouble.
Just look at one example,
a man called Miguel.
He was arrested for driving
with a suspended license,
the court set bail at a thousand
dollars, and he had a choice,
pay it or await a trial
in Rikers Island.
And I'll let Miguel and his wife take
the story from there.
I wouldn't wish Rikers
on my worst enemy, 'cause it's rough.
It was hard because I had to borrow,
I had to try to borrow money
from this person,
and this person,
and this person
to try to get him out.
He told the judge, "I can't afford
a thousand dollar bail."
So he really didn't
have a choice but to plead guilty.
Now whether he was guilty or not,
the fact is a nonviolent offender
spent time in Rikers because
he didn't have a thousand dollars.
And this is
a systemic problem.
Increasingly,
bail has become a way
to lock up the poor
regardless of guilt.
Because Miguel
was a family man
who posed no danger to society
whatsoever and he was stuck in Rikers,
whereas millionaire
Robert Durst,
who'd been accused
of murder in Texas,
had a completely different
experience of the bail system.
I'd been told
by the detective that,
"You've been charged with murder,
bail has been set at $250,000."
But was your intention when you put up
the $250,000 to run away ?
Oh, good-bye $250,000.
Good-bye jail. I'm out !
"I'm out !"
That, of course, is an excerpt from
Robert Durst's children's book
"Goodbye Jail."
"Good-bye, money.
Good-bye, bail.
I killed them all,
but good-bye jail.
Of course. Of course."
The problem is the frequency and cost
of bail have risen dramatically,
and it is disproportionately
hurting the poor.
In fact, in 2013, an analysis
of New Jersey's jail population
found that nearly 40 percent
were being held solely because
they couldn't meet the terms
of their bail, which is crazy.
Jail is supposed to be
for dangerous criminals.
If 40 percent of a group don't meet
the basic criteria to be there,
that should change your perception
of what that group is.
If 40 percent of the Girl Scouts
were grown men,
you'd feel weird about
buying cookies from them.
So what happens
if you can't make bail ?
Much like a game of "Fuck, Marry, Kill"
with Crosby, Stills, and Nash,
there are a few
terrible scenarios.
Option one,
you sit in jail.
And again, if you're poor,
as this defense attorney explains,
that has immediate
consequences.
Our clients work at jobs where if
you're absent, you're fired.
Our clients live in shelters
or in transitional housing,
places where if you're not there
for the night, your place is gone.
So there are a lot of different ways
in which incarceration,
even for a short period of time,
can really destroy someone's life.
Exactly. Jail can do
for your actual life
what being in a marching band
can do for your social life.
Even if you're just in
for a little while, it can destroy you.
Destroy you.
But that means,
it's no wonder
that many defendants who can't afford
bail favor option number two,
simply pleading guilty
even if you're not,
as a former public defender
explains.
You sit in jail because
you can't afford
to pay your way to freedom.
And you're often confronted with a deal
that goes like this,
plead guilty, get out,
maintain your innocence
and go to trial, stay in.
And poor people are regularly choosing
to admit guilt
just to get out of there,
which isn't good.
The only time that's appropriate is in
a Catholic confessional.
"What do you mean
is there anything else ?
I don't know, I masturbated
into a kiwi fruit.
Is that what you want to hear ?
Just let me leave !
I have stuff to do."
And the problem is, if you do plead
guilty to a crime you didn't commit,
that has its own downsides,
because, unfortunately,
on a job application
next to the question
"Have you ever been convicted
of a crime ? Check yes or no..."
most don't then leave
four pages of blank space to explain
the social and economic inequalities
inherent in the legal system.
That brings us to your final option,
commercial bail bondsmen.
You know, the people who make
amazing ads like these.
Grumpy's Bail Bonds
has busted out
all over middle Tennessee.
I ain't going out like that
I'm a call for bail bonds
'cause they got my back
They got me out in no time,
now I'm back on track
Jesus Christ Bail Bonds !
May God release you on
a payment plan by calling me.
I'm Bishop Barry
of Jesus Christ Bail Bonds.
410-292-3029.
- If you're locked up and afraid...
- Bail out !
Bail out !
Jesus Christ Bail Bonds !
Yes. Jesus Christ
Bail Bonds !
Amazing.
But I will say,
it is a little weird
given that Jesus,
pretty memorably, I think,
was not bailed out.
I mean,
he did eventually escape custody,
but it was a real
workaround of the system.
Now here is how
that system works, though.
Bail bondsmen promise
the court to pay your bail
if you fail to show up
for a trial.
In exchange, you pay them
10 to 15 percent of the bail amount,
which they then keep
regardless of how your trial goes.
So if your bail
is $5,000 and you're found innocent,
then you've basically
just paid a $750 fee to a bondsman
for doing absolutely
nothing wrong.
And paying $750
for absolutely nothing
should be reserved
for one thing and one thing only
six-month gym memberships.
That's it.
You're not gonna use it, Gerald.
You're gonna use the treadmill twice,
and that's it.
This is learning to speak Korean
all over again, Gerald.
And if you don't show up
for your trial,
bail bondsmen routinely
hire bounty hunters to track you down,
and they have a frightening
amount of power.
In all but four states,
the companies are legally
allowed to take almost any measure
necessary to capture a client,
including crossing state lines
and breaking into homes.
It's a dangerous business
for everyone involved,
with few rules
and little oversight.
Oh, they're not kidding.
In 18 states,
anyone can become
a bounty hunter
regardless of education,
training,
or prior criminal history.
Becoming a bounty hunter
is basically a lot
like becoming
a social media expert.
All it takes is
wanting it bad enough
and not caring about whether strangers
hate you or not.
But then the news
that any idiot can be a bounty hunter
shouldn't really be
that surprising to you
if you've ever turned on A&E
and stumbled across this.
I am a lawman
on a mission from God.
When I say "freeze !",
they know what I'm saying.
- How's it going, man ?
- Freeze !
Get down !
The only way this guy
will get away from us
is if he kills himself
right now
and jumps into
a pool of sharks.
Okay. Okay.
I have to be a stickler
over chronology, Dog,
but how do you kill yourself and then
jump into a pool of sharks ?
That's the kind
of attention to detail, Dog,
that makes me worry about you
operating as an unregulated vigilante.
Now that show
was so popular,
it inspired pretty much
every other bail business
to pitch themselves
as a reality show.
Just click around online
and you will find sizzle reels
for a veritable
smorgasbord of similar shows.
Walk and you talk
and you're acting like a criminal
Running through the woods
like a four-legged animal
The bottom line is, while
you're on bond, we're on your ass.
Dear idiot,
we're coming to get you.
Bounty hunting
is a natural high.
You gotta think like them,
be like them,
and react quicker than them.
Put your hands up !
You want tough ?
You want action ?
Meet Big Benny.
They call him Teddy Bear.
Denise
The Huntress
It doesn't stop there.
There's also Richard,
the Screwdriver.
Richard L.,
the Other Richard.
Allison,
the Greco Roman Wrestler.
Caroline, the one who took up archery
after watching The Hunger Games.
And don't forget Jennifer,
the arthritic alpaca in a bowler hat.
Actually, you know what ?
I now regret
making fun of that.
Now that
I'm seeing the cast, I get the appeal.
I want to see
those characters grow.
Clearly, these shows
are in a competitive marketplace.
And the problem is,
when people try to stick out,
ideas like this happen.
So what do we
do differently ?
We don't just bounty hunt,
we bounty race.
Each week,
two new teams
of bounty hunters...
go head to head.
Welcome to the most dangerous
competition on television.
Bail Chasers.
Okay. First of all,
first of all, the most dangerous
competition on television
is The Bachelorette.
Those women have loved
and they've lost.
Love is a reward, but it's also a risk,
goddamn it ! It's a risk !
She's putting herself
on the line !
She's there
for the right reasons !
She sees her husband
in that room !
And second, it says something
about how comfortable we all are
with how our bail system
works that a TV show
where people with guns
hunt humans for sport
seems legitimate
because we just think,
"Well, they're just
doing their actual job."
And when you give
bounty hunters this kind of power,
bad things happen.
Veteran Gene Travis says
he was sitting with his wife
on his Bethpage front porch.
Next thing he knows,
his barn is being searched, and Travis
has a stun gun pointed at his back.
The intruders, Mark Brummett
and his wife Angela,
bounty hunters who police
say had the wrong home.
Clay was shot
by one of the bondsman.
He was then transported
to EIRMC, where he died.
Was a bounty hunter
justified in tasing
a Midwest City homeowner
last Saturday ?
Was another justified
in shooting his dog ?
Police say the video tape
they took says no.
Yeah, the video says no,
basic human decency says no,
even a Magic 8 Ball
having seen that would say,
"Holy shit ! I can't believe
you're even asking me. No !"
Look, our current
bail system makes no sense
and it does a lot of harm.
And the frustrating thing
is we've known this for a long time.
Just watch this TV
news special from 1964.
Yes, the jails
are bursting at the seams,
a problem of great concern
to New York City Commissioner
of Correction Anna Cross.
Remaining in jail
because you can't get bail
is really being punished
before you're even found guilty.
As far as I was concerned,
that was not just.
That was destroying
our concept of justice.
That's right.
This problem has been obvious
since it was considered okay
to wear a wastebasket on your head.
But look,
here's the good news.
There is a better way,
and it's already in use
in our federal courts
and in Washington, D.C.
Judges in Washington
are allowed to set money bail
only if the defendant
can afford it.
The results have been far fewer people
spending time behind bars.
We are the only city
in America
where tonight
at our jail
there is not a single man
or woman
who is sitting
because they don't have the money
to meet their money bond.
And it's a testament
to the state
of our justice system
that that qualifies
as bragging,
because that should
be the norm.
He's like a bus driver
showing up at school saying,
"23 kids picked up,
23 kids dropped off.
I pitched a perfect game."
Pretrial services
works like this.
After you're arrested,
specialists assess
if you're dangerous
or a flight risk.
If a judge decides that you're not,
you can go home,
and they may monitor you with things
like drug tests or ankle monitors.
They even call you
to remind you of your court date.
It's a system built
on interviews,
pre-arranged appearances,
and trust.
Much like Scientology
marriages, only in this case,
much more effective.
And pretrial service programs
have succeeded around the country
in places ranging
from Oregon to Florida.
And it is a truly
frightening state of affairs
when Florida is a model
for progressive change.
It shouldn't be a judicial example
for anything.
Did you know,
by the way, that under Florida law
if you possess over five grams of meth,
you can marry it.
That's a fact.
That's a legal fact.
That's an actual photo
that ran in a newspaper's
wedding section in Florida.
And yet,
even counties in Florida recognize
our money bail system is broken.
And not only is pretrial services
better, it's cheaper.
A recent assessment of one system
showed it costing only a tenth
as much as keeping
someone locked up.
Which makes sense, because
calling someone to check in
costs virtually nothing.
This message brought
to you by your mother.
Your mother, she brought you
into this world,
and would like to hear
your fucking voice once in a while !
So...
So if pretrial services
are fairer, better, and cheaper,
why aren't we all
using it ?
Well, maybe because
thanks to reality shows,
we think that this
is what justice looks like.
We're gonna hunt
this scum down.
Down ! Now !
Bad dog.
So maybe we just need
a new kind of reality show
to get us used
to the alternative.
You want tough ?
You want action ?
Move !
Meet Steve Carp.
He's one of the most respected pretrial
services caseworkers
in the United States.
So let's see. Okay, looks like
you were ticketed
with public urination.
No priors.
Seems like
a one-off sort of thing.
Can we count on you to be back here
in six weeks for your trial ?
Of course.
Great.
We're done here.
Nothing else to talk about ?
No.
This is a routine thing.
Statistically,
he's virtually guaranteed to turn up.
We're done here.
They call him, Steve
"The Hand Grenade,"
and he works with a crack team
of legal enforcers.
Meet Deborah.
PRETRIAL SERVICES - "THE PIT"
Hello. This is Deborah
from Pretrial Services.
I'm just calling
to remind you about
your upcoming court date
this Thursday.
Well, you're welcome.
They call her "The Viper."
I feel like a cat.
You know...
All right, back to work.
PRETRIAL SERVICES - "THE VAULT"
And then there's Brett.
So all these
are risk assessments.
This is all computerized,
but, you know,
I keep a hard copy
just in case.
That's why they call him
"The Annihilator."
And finally, Gerald,
the guy in charge
of urine tests.
Clear. If there's something
in there that's illegal,
I'm gonna sniff it out.
'Cause that's what I do.
I'm a piss sniffer.
We got one.
They call him "The Nose."
You really gonna make
a TV show out of this ?
Who's gonna watch it ?
You will, because this fall,
we'll be bringing you
all the thrills and excitement
of pretrial supervision as this
elite team brings people to justice.
Well, we don't bring them to justice.
It's more like we make arrangements
for them to bring
themselves to justice.
Ignore that. This show is full
of high-stakes drama...
You better pray I don't get you
for secret Santa this year !
You don't wanna
fuck with Deborah.
And inter-office romance.
Gerald is a bloodhound.
Oh, yeah ! She wants me.
And if wasn't for all them
cats, I would hit that.
I would knock the bottom
out of her.
But most importantly...
We take you
closer to the action !
Filling out forms
and filing them in triplicate
We won't lock you up
if your crime's not significant
If you get a ticket
for public urination
We won't lock you up
so you lose your occupation
We kick it indoors,
screaming dead or alive
This is an office job,
we all go home at five
The system works well,
so there's no need for nervousness
It's all in the game
at Pretrial Services
Pretrial Services.
Coming this fall to A&E.
It's cost-effective,
motherfucker.
And finally tonight,
FIFA again.
Listen, I cannot
avoid this any longer.
We have some
unfinished business.
On Sunday night,
while reporting on
the FIFA scandal,
John Oliver
made this promise.
Budweiser,
if you pull your support,
and help get rid of Blatter,
I will put my mouth
where my mouth is
and I will personally
drink one of your disgusting items.
I'm serious.
It can be a Bud Light.
I will even drink
a Bud Light Lime.
I did promise that.
And, you know what ?
It didn't end there.
I also promised to wear
these ridiculous Adidas shoes
and take a bite from everything
on the McDonald's Dollar Menu.
I didn't think
this would happen.
Now, to be fair,
to be fair,
it is not clear that the sponsors had
anything to do with Blatter leaving,
and Blatter's departure
still leaves FIFA with a huge amount
of restructuring to do.
But, that said,
a promise is a promise,
and I'm a man of my word.
So first,
check these puppies out.
Who needs arch support
when you look
like Louis XIV
going to a rap battle ?
And as for McDonald's,
well... I'm doin' it.
So let's see.
A bite of all of this disgusting mess.
It's like there's
a party in my mouth,
and my stomach
has called the cops to shut it down.
Look, I can't
delay it any longer.
We all know
what the main event is.
I promised I'd drink a Bud Light Lime
and say it was delicious.
However, for the record,
I didn't promise anything
about what I would say
before I drank it.
Which is...
that Bud Light Lime tastes
like Jolly Green Giant's
ejaculate.
It tastes like the Great Gazoo
urinating in a public pool...
or a lime Jolly Rancher fished out
of Mickey Rourke's mouth.
But, look,
if I'm gonna do this,
I'm not gonna do it small.
I'm gonna do it properly.
So please come with me.
It's a cool party !
Where cool people are having
a good time. Thank you very much.
So here we go.
Bud Light Lime may taste
like your tongue
is angry with you,
but after seeing Sepp Blatter
leaving, to me it tastes...
Delicious !
That's our show.
A reminder,
we're on Trinidad
at 9:01 p.m. Tuesday.
See you next week.
Good night !
LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
Season 2
End of episode 16