LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
SEASON III
EPISODE 24
Welcome to Last Week Tonight !
I'm John Oliver.
Thank you for joining us.
We begin with the 2016 election,
as it's more commonly known,
"What did I do to deserve this,
I tried to be a good person is this"
"because I stole candy in 4th grade
please stop punishing us" 2016.
This week
saw the first presidential debate.
Donald Trump's performance
consisted mainly of an incoherent
jumble of sniffles and nonsense,
like a racist toddler
coming out of dental surgery.
And it all culminated
in this amazing assertion.
I think my strongest asset,
maybe by far, is my temperament.
I have a winning temperament.
I know how to win.
That is an incredible statement.
If he had said:
"I am a small Korean woman"
it would have been
more believable.
And you can't incoherently rant
about having the best temperament.
That is a claim that disproves itself.
It's like getting a forehead tattoo:
"I have excelent judgement".
But we then saw what
a "winning temperament" means.
It's a temperament that allows you
to insist that you won something
that you demonstrably lost.
Trump spent the last 7 days
citing his victories
in what he called
"final debate polls",
peppering his rallies
with boasts like this.
And so we won
every single online poll.
Hundreds and hundreds
of thousands of voters.
Almost every single poll
had us winning the debate
against crooked Hillary Clinton.
Every single online poll
said we won, which is great.
First of all, he did not win
every single online poll.
He didn't win this BuzzFeed poll
about whether candy corn is good.
If you are wondering who did win that,
it was BuzzFeed, you idiots.
BuzzFeed wins every BuzzFeed poll.
The clear problem with online polls
is that you can vote anonymously
as many times as you want.
That is how, when a British government
agency held a name our ship poll,
the people's overwhelming choice
was "Boaty McBoatface".
It's how, when there was an internet
vote on where Pitbull should perform,
he ended up, and this is true,
in an Alaska Wal-Mart.
And yet, Trump kept citing
these nonsense polls,
as did his media boosters,
like Sean Hannity.
If you look at all the online polls,
the Hill, time.com, Slate,
the list was really long,
Trump won the debate
in these online polls.
And everyone's gonna say
they're not scientific. I hear it.
Do you, though ?
I'm not sure you do.
I'm not sure you even hear
what your own company is saying,
because Fox News sent out an internal
memo saying that such polls, quote:
"Do not meet our editorial standards".
Shocking, since I was pretty sure
Fox News's only "editorial standards"
were "All ladies must be 8's or above"
and "Try not to say the N-word".
The Trump campaign's insistence that
online polls were just as good as real
ones was beginning
to drive people nuts.
The polls that happened that night,
night of the debate,
the ones that happen online,
those all showed Mr. Trump winning.
What scientific poll
had Donald Trump winning ?
Everything else was...
Those are fan polls, man.
Those are polls that computer
programmers can mess with.
Hillary's got support from the insiders
and from the media,
Mr. Trump's got support
from the people.
Jason, you've been doing this a while.
You know those are bogus !
Look how frustrated he is !
Chuck Todd's head is about to explode.
And this pains him, because
he's talking to a fellow goateewearer.
They stick together against a world
that makes fun of their facial hair.
But there was an even more
inexplicable narrative developing.
Because Trump did score a few points
early on against Hillary Clinton.
He could've spent the whole week
talking about those.
But he fixated on one particular thing
she said towards the end of the night.
One of the worst things he said
was about a woman in a beauty contest.
He called this woman "Miss Piggy",
then "Miss Housekeeping",
because she was Latina.
Donald, she has a name.
Her name is Alicia Machado.
Where did you find it ?
Why does he care
where she found it ?
Is he flummoxed because it doesn't
come from any of his 3 news sources,
Breitbart,
dudes hanging out at golf club bars,
the minotaur who talks to him in the
one hour that he sleeps every night ?
That Miss Universe moment was
a small part of a 90-minute debate.
So all Trump had to do
was not take the bait.
And yet, the next morning,
he went on Fox & Friends
and, without even being asked,
brought the subject up.
Watch the anchors' faces as it sinks
in that he is actually doing this.
She was a Miss Universe person
and she was the worst we ever had.
The worst, the absolute worst.
She was impossible,
and she was a Miss Universe
contestant and ultimately a winner
who they had a tremendously
difficult time with as Miss Universe.
- Did not know that story.
- I didn't know either.
She was the winner,
she gained a massive amount of weight,
and it was a real problem.
You can see them thinking:
"What are you doing ?"
"Don't you know it's wrong to degrade
former beauty pageant winners ?"
"We at Fox learned that,
due to the circumstances"
"of Roger Ailes' departure
from this very company."
But Trump still wasn't done.
He pressed the issue all week long
culminating in an online meltdown
in the early hours of Friday morning.
His tweet storm began at 3am
and didn't stop until about ten.
He unloaded on former Miss Universe,
Alicia Machado.
"Did crooked Hillary help disgusting
(check out sex tape and past)"
"Alicia M become a citizen so she
could use her in the debate ?"
That is a candidate
for president of the United States
urging America
to check out a sex tape.
Do me a favor up,
look up into the sky right now.
Higher. No, higher still.
Do you see that, way up there,
way up above the clouds ?
That's rock bottom.
And we are currently way down here.
Not that it makes it any better,
but Trump behaved
equally appallingly to her face,
during a 1997 CBS interview.
Alicia has done an incredible job.
She has turned out to be one
of the great Miss Universes.
And she had a little problem,
she gained a little weight...
- I don't think so.
- She's probably right.
- Okay.
Donald Trump really should've been
prepared for Monday night.
It seems he's been losing televised
debates to women for 20 years now.
Amazingly, in that same interview,
it emerged that CBS
would be running an unscientific viewer
poll during the Miss Universe pageant.
Something tells me that Donald Trump
had something to do with the question.
The viewers can call in and vote.
Let's bring up the question.
It says:
"Should a pageant title holder"
"be required to maintain her physical
appearance during her reign ?"
Why do you think
this is an important question ?
That has come up
over the last year.
It came up over that past year because
you made a media circus out of it.
Trump treats his statements
like they're Pokemon:
they're imaginary things
that he nurtures and evolves
and eventually uses
to fight with strangers.
And thus, the two threads
of this week come together:
completely unscientific polling,
which Donald Trump trusts implicitly,
and his deeply held belief
that female weight gain is a betrayal.
So here is the moment of truth:
what were the results of that poll ?
Do you think that Miss Universe,
or the pageant holder,
should be required to maintain her
physical appearance during her reign ?
Most of the people said no.
How about that, Donald ?
It seems you have a choice,
either admit
that unscientific polling is bullshit,
or that your views
on women's bodies are horrifying.
I await whatever decision you make
at 3am tonight on Twitter.
And in the meantime,
I would like to leave you all
with the wise words of Alicia Machado.
Advice for the new Miss Universe ?
Good luck. She need it.
Who knew that the advice,
'good luck, you'll need it',
would be equally applicable
to Miss Universe 1997,
and everyone in the most powerful
nation on earth ?
And now this !
And now,
newscasters quoting movies !
It's Bond, James Bond.
You can't handle the truth !
After all,
tomorrow is another day.
To infinity and beyond.
Johnny's here or whatever,
here's Johnny.
Say hello to my little friend.
- Say hello to my little friend.
- Right, just a little bit.
Say hello to my little friend.
Scarface.
Get down, get to the chopper !
I gotta get to the chopper.
I'll be back.
I know it was you Fredo,
you broke my heart. Godfather 2.
Alright, alright, alright.
Show me the money.
Show me the money,
as Cuba Gooding used to say !
Moving on.
Our main story concerns the police.
As these cops show frequently have
to deal with humanity at its worst.
What's the first amendment ?
You don't even know !
Constitutiooooon !
Yeah. Constitution ! Read it !
And live by it.
Let's have a seat
in the back of the car.
Ron Paul 2012 !
That's perfect. It's not like
he needed to say "Ron Paul 2012".
That was implicit in everything
he said up to that point.
But it's certainly nice
to have it confirmed.
The police have been at the center
of a great deal of controversy.
From the Black Lives Matter movement,
to Colin Kaepernick's protest,
to Mary J. Blige awkwardly singing
a Springsteen song at Hillary Clinton.
Is it a gun,
is it a knife, is it a wallet,
this is your life ?
You can get killed
just for living in
your American skin.
Hillary, thank you !
God !
Hillary would have won
my undying respect
if she'd looked Mary J. Blige
straight in the face and said:
"I support your message,
but that was awkward as fuck".
"And I wish you hadn't done it".
That would've been honest.
The trust between police
and the communities they serve
is clearly a cornerstone
of civilized society.
That trust has been rocked following
controversial police shootings
from Alton Sterling,
to Philando Castile, to Tamir Rice,
to so many others,
I literally cannot mention them all.
These deaths, taken with countless
smaller incidents of police misconduct,
have led to a common refrain.
I just want the police
to be held accountable.
We want the system of policing
Those police
need to be held accountable.
Whenever they commit a crime,
whenever something goes wrong,
and I'm talking about serious stuff
like murder and whatnot,
these guys never get prosecuted.
Now those are valid frustrations.
Although, as a side note:
"Murder and Whatnot"
would be an amazing CSI spinoff.
That's a watchable show right there.
Police accountability is what we're
going to be talking about.
I should say,
as the police will tell you,
they have a difficult,
dangerous, challenging job.
No reasonable person
would disagree with that.
That's all the more reason
for ensuring that it's done perfectly.
The worst thing that happens
if a cake decorator fucks up
is you end up wishing someone
a Happy Analversary.
While that's obviously not ideal,
who knows ?
Maybe it's their analversary, too !
The police will argue that what they
have is less an institutional problem,
than it is an individual one.
There's been
some bad apples out there.
I don't think that that is indicative
of the entire police department.
But you got bad apples
in every occupation.
You're gonna have some bad apples.
They're out to protect you
and that's what policing's about.
That is a weirdly blasé attitude.
Bad apples can erode trust fast.
Snow White wasn't afraid of apples
before she took a bite
out of that one really bad one,
but the next time an old lady
comes at her with a piece of fruit,
Snow is gonna
get the fuck out of there.
That argument "it's a few bad apples"
has some real problems.
For a start, it doesn't address
bad laws and policies
that good officers
are made to enforce
which we've touched
on multiple times before.
Criminal justice is kind
of our show's signature bit.
It is to us what assessing
the shape of your poop is to Dr. Oz.
Also, you can't claim
there's just a few bad apples,
when no one knows exactly
how many there are.
There are nearly 18 000
police departments in America,
and they are not great
about reporting or sharing data.
Even some surprisingly
basic questions are hard to answer,
as the head of the FBI admits.
We can't have an informed discussion,
we don't have data.
People have data about who went to
a movie, how many books were sold,
how many cases of the flu
walked into an emergency room.
I cannot tell you how many people
were shot by police in the US
last month, last year,
or anything about the demographics.
How is that possible ? We have
numbers for almost everything !
We have ratings for how many people
watched Jeremy Piven in "Mr. Selfridge"
The government tracks how many
people are killed by falling TVs
a number inflated by people
who were watching "Mr. Selfridge"
and said "I choose death", and then
pulled the TV down on top of them.
The best numbers on police misconduct
come from a researcher, Philip Stinson,
who accumulated
over a decade's worth of data
by setting up 48 Google alerts
in 2005.
Google Alerts.
And his stats are truly chilling.
Out of thousands of fatal
police shootings since 2005,
only 77 officers have been charged
with murder or manslaughter.
And to date,
only 26 have been convicted.
And while the truth is,
many police shootings are justified,
26 seems suspiciously low.
So: how can that be the number ?
Well, broadly speaking,
most investigations of police
misconduct face a few obstacles.
And the first one is big: misconduct
is often investigated internally,
by an officer's colleagues,
which does not inspire confidence.
But if you listen to the police chief
in Bakersfield, the system is fine.
You're confident that that structure
of review is entirely impartial ?
I am.
These guys are expert in their field.
They're part of the departments.
They have hundreds of years of law
enforcement experience combined.
Here's the thing there.
Combined experience is not a thing
that automatically
makes you do a better job.
Our staff has a combined
347 years in television
and that doesn't mean we won't
throw a fuckload of raisins on a desk
and call it entertainment.
The DOJ has consistently found
flaws with internal investigations.
In Cleveland, investigators admitted
they intentionally cast an officer
in the best light possible when
investigating a use of deadly force.
In Miami, investigations took so long
that "at least two officers"
"killed a suspect while still under
investigation for a previous shooting".
And there should never be
a second one of anything
before you figure out
whether the first was justified.
Call it the "Dolphin Tale 2" rule.
How is there a second one of these ?
I thought Harry Connick Jr. ate the
dolphin at the end of the first one.
I don't know for sure,
I haven't seen it.
But no one has
and that's the point.
In Baltimore, the DOJ report included
the story of Joe Crystal,
a detective who reported two fellow
officers for alleged excessive force,
and was labeled a "rat",
with one colleague leaving pictures
of cheese on his desk,
which is almost charming,
until you learn
how far some others went.
He found himself cut off. He didn't
get backup in dangerous situations.
Someone left a dead rat
on his windshield.
It was like their way of telling me:
you don't belong here...
Leaving a dead rat on an officer's
windshield is hostile.
Unless of course,
that officer is a police cat,
in which case it means:
"Welcome to the force, Whiskers !"
"We're lucky to have you !
Enjoy the rat."
Accountability doesn't just suffer
from an unwritten code of silence.
That code can be enshrined
within state laws or union contracts.
It's hard to spot problem officers
because, in many jurisdictions,
policies allow disciplinary
records to be destroyed.
In Baton Rouge,
a sustained complaint
can be stricken from
your record after just 18 months.
And in Mesa, Arizona, when
a journalist demanded records,
a police chief made an internal video
reminding his officers
that there was a way
for them to clean up their past.
I don't want anybody to relive
a problem they've been disciplined for,
that has already seen the scrutiny
in the public eye.
Purge your files according to policy,
make sure the things you don't
want in there aren't in there.
That seems wrong.
You should not be able to erase parts
of your past that are damning.
This is an official police file,
not a Volkswagen corporate history
that somehow starts
after World War II.
Nazi cars. The choice of the Nazis.
Deleting records is not an officer's
only option to escape their past.
After an incident, they'll resign,
and move to another department.
It happens so much, people in law
enforcement call them "gypsy cops".
In South Carolina, a TV station
looked into one officer
who spent a total of nine years
working for nine departments,
three of them in one year, and in one
case, he left in spectacular fashion.
Deputies believed Yarbrough's
driving was "compromised"
and they discovered a half-empty
"bottle of rye whiskey"
and a baggie of "assorted pills"
in his patrol cruiser.
Yarbrough said: "I'm not taking
no drug test, I guess I'll resign."
Holy shit. "I'm not taking no
drug test, I guess I'll resign"
is a sentence you do not want
to hear from a police officer.
It's barely appropriate from
a roadie leaving Aerosmith.
"Gypsy cops" have been involved
in tragic incidents.
In the Tamir Rice case, the officer
who shot the 12-year-old
had been in the process
of being fired, before resigning.
But, the Cleveland police missed
that red flag when hiring him,
they didn't read
his personnel file,
an incident
during weapons training
where he had a loss of composure,
leading his supervisor to conclude:
"I do not believe time, nor training,
will change or correct deficiencies."
That performance review should keep
you from getting hired at Staples,
let alone a job
where you're given a gun.
That cop was never even charged.
Like many such cases,
his never made it past
the grand jury.
Which seems inherently surprising,
until you realize:
local prosecutors and cops have to work
together, which can get complicated.
As a former prosecutor,
you rely upon the police.
You trust the police. The police
are in your office examining evidence,
preparing for trial.
And then have to turn around and
prosecute them to prosecute you.
Exactly. For a prosecutor to go
after a cop they work with is awkward.
I can't think of anything more
awkward, other than this:
Hillary, thank you.
God, it's not getting any better.
Nothing in Hillary's life
has ever been
more awkward than that.
Think about
what a high bar that is.
Even when cases go to trial,
officers have a major advantage,
juries tend to have a natural
predisposition to trust them.
Police officers get a presumption
of innocence
whereas most criminal defendants don't
come in with presumption of innocence.
A judge will toss the case
at a preliminary hearing
or a grand jury will refuse to indict,
so you never even get to trial.
Jurors do not come in
with any belief
that officers can commit a crime.
Many people see a police uniform
and think "trustworthy".
Unless it includes a sleeveless shirt
and a boom-box,
in which case
they think "stripper".
And sometimes: "Wait... Jim ?
From middle school ?!"
The police have a certain amount of
leeway regarding lethal force,
meaning that "fatal shootings
can be considered legal"
"even if they are
unnecessary or disproportional."
There is even a shorthand
for such cases, lawful but awful.
Which is also the legal
definition of Woody Allen's marriage.
I think that's it.
Who are you angry with here ?
Put the boos
back in your pocket.
Officers can bring in expert witnesses
who can present nearly any situation
as a potential threat.
Dr. Bill Lewinski runs
the Force Science Institute.
For years, he has testified
on behalf of police officers.
Here is why it may be okay
to shoot someone that has a knife.
Knives can be more dangerous.
They don't have to be reloaded.
Can be used at close distance.
A stab or a cut
can be extremely quick.
That is not the motion you make
when you are stabbing someone.
It's the motion you make when you are
a teenage magician finishing a trick.
Is this your card ?
There is no doubt, a knife
is a dangerous weapon.
What if someone
doesn't have a knife ?
Could force still be necessary
when someone is unarmed ?
It's significant to know
that unarmed does not mean
they're not dangerous.
The fist may have been first weapon
human beings used against each other.
I've measured strikes on human,
and the strikes can occur
at a speed of 4, 5, or 6 strikes
in a second, some really hard.
What is he talking about ?
The only time a fist
is a match for a weapon is during
a game of rock paper scissors.
It can be defeated by paper,
for reasons which make no sense.
But that's not the point.
Defendants are allowed
to call expert witnesses.
Weird is, Lewinski has appeared
before grand juries,
where prosecutors are supposed
to present their best case
for an officer's indictment.
Why would they let
Lewinski in there ?
They're shooting
their own case in the foot.
Presumably justified, because feet
were the second weapon ever invented.
We've focused heavily on trials,
but in a perfect world,
there would be enough
police accountability
that the blunt instrument of a trial
would very rarely be necessary.
How can we fix all this ?
Body cameras have increased
transparency and trust.
In Rialto, Calfornia,
after one year of using them,
the number of complaints filed
against officers fell by 88 percent,
and the use of force dropped
by around 60 percent.
When Baltimore's trial run of a body
camera program ended,
their commissioner
begged for their return.
Officers want cameras. This is
a moment everybody wants cameras.
I was speaking to some folks
and we had a couple police officers
who were turning in their body cameras
and were asking
"when can we get these back ?"
Right, and these cops
aren't M. Night Shyamalan.
If they plead to let them have
a camera, you should give it to them.
Give it to them !
Body cameras are one solution.
Other cities tried requiring officers
to file separate reports every time
there's a use of force,
or they've used early intervention
systems to spot problem officers,
or they brought in outside prosecutors
to handle controversial cases.
Police unions fiercely fight
any attempted reforms.
Just listen to James Stewart, head
of the biggest police union in Newark,
where the DOJ found three-quarters
of stops had no legal justification.
To listen to him,
the police are being too scrutinized.
I don't know
where the problem started,
but there is an animosity
or a lack of trust.
As soon as there's physical force
exerted by a police officer,
everybody's got cellphones out
to catch us doing wrong.
When you got the cop in the street
facing this negative opposition,
does there come a point when
the police officer's going to say:
"Maybe he doesn't have to go to jail.
I'll take a path of least resistance."
"I'll put the blinders on at the corner
where the 10 guys are hanging out."
There is a lot to unpack there:
first, threatening not to do your job
because you've faced
public criticism is childish.
You think Steven Seagal
gave up on his movie career
because people said mean things ?
Of course not ! Just this year,
he starred in End of a Gun,
The Perfect Weapon,
The Asian Connection,
Code of Honor
and Sniper: Special Ops. Why ?
Because he's a fucking professional !
And he commits to his job.
More importantly:
when you say you might ignore
ten people hanging out on a corner,
yeah, maybe do that !
That's not typically a crime.
In some cases, ten people on a corner
is just a fucking yard sale.
For many people, Stewart's argument
that for police to be effective,
they need to be given broad leeway
to use force, is very appealing.
It's especially appealing for those
of us who, for whatever reason,
are confident that that force
won't be applied to them.
But it is worth looking at
the actual cost of that tradeoff.
Lack of trust in police accountability
leads to a lack of trust in police.
We have reached the point
where there are schools
who teach kids how to safely
interact with law enforcement.
I want you to repeat after me.
I want you to say: "Officer !"
"Am I free to go ?"
One more time ! "Officer."
Am I free to go ?"
The hope is, with this advice,
teens can protect their rights
and maybe their lives.
That is so depressing.
Especially when you realize
that's the only class where
nobody will raise their hand
and say: "When are we
ever going to use this ?"
When you see something
like that, it makes it hard to buy in
when someone dismisses police
misconduct issues.
They're out to protect you.
Are there bad apples ? Yeah !
Yeah but here's the thing
about that:
the phrase isn't, "it's just a few bad
apples, don't worry about it."
The phrase is: "a few bad
apples spoil the barrel."
We currently have a system,
which is set up to ignore bad apples,
destroy bad apples' records,
persecute good apples for speaking up
and shuffle dangerous,
emotionally unstable apples around
to the point that children have
to attend apple classes.
You cannot look at our situation
and claim anybody likes them apples.
And now this.
And now, newscasters quoting movies,
all Chris Matthews edition.
We have here
a failure to communicate.
I'm mad and I'm not
gonna take it anymore.
Of all the gin joints in all the towns,
she walks into mine.
Houston, we have a problem.
I wish I knew how to quit you.
Make my day. Lieutenant Dan.
My name is Inigo Montoya, you killed
my father, prepare to die.
Robert DeNiro played him
when... You talking to me ?
Robert DeNiro, you talking to me ?
You talking to me ?
They can't handle the truth.
Remember ?
We don't need no badges,
like in the movie.
William Wallace in the movie,
some think we've never
had a country of our own.
That whole idea,
if we have our own country.
Don't know if the accent
was right...
And finally tonight, a quick
update about Wells Fargo.
The bank that, until recently,
was laughing all the way to itself.
Now, last week, we covered
the revelation their employees
had created millions of fake
accounts in customers' names.
We got more details on why it
may've gone on for quite so long.
Allegations
that Wells Fargo retaliated
against employees
who called an ethics hotline.
Many workers called that line
because they felt pressured
to open phony accounts
to meet unreasonable quotas.
It's true. Wells Fargo is accused
of retaliating against whistleblowers
who called their ethics line.
Although it was probably a dead
giveaway that the number
was 1-800-snitches-get-stitches.
And their bad week
didn't stop there.
Wells Fargo's CEO, John Stumpf,
had to appear in front of lawmakers,
still with a brace on his hand,
which I legally cannot say
was from a wrist sprain suffered
while jamming stolen money up his ass.
That's why I wouldn't say that.
Stumpf forfeited $41 million
of his pay this week,
but he is still somehow holding
onto his job.
Which is especially galling,
considering it also emerged this week
that Wells Fargo paid $24 million
to settle an entirely different case.
The department of justice
has charged Wells Fargo,
illegally repossessing 413 vehicles
owned by members of the military.
That is no way
to treat members of the military.
Thank you for your service.
While we're at it,
your Honda Civic,
thank you very much.
And this pattern of behavior
is hard to take,
coming from a bank who,
just ten years ago,
were producing actual ethics videos
for their employees to watch.
This is an uncomfortable subject.
But let's face it:
we're in the business
of trust and money.
While we pride
on our high level of honesty,
even we are not immune
from the occasional bad apple.
I'm talking about internal fraud.
Consequences are swift and severe.
Jobs are lost,
family and friends embarrassed.
There's the possibility
of going to jail
and the obligation to repay
every penny back.
Ethics rules aren't
meant to be stretched. If they are...
They inevitably
come back to bite you.
Cool.
Wells Fargo is almost begging
employees not to take him seriously,
nothing says a commitment
to ethics like a mixed metaphor
being delivered through
bad prop comedy
by a man in a shirt
the color of mustard.
We tracked that guy down.
Which wasn't difficult to do.
Because, and you are
not going to believe this,
he's one of the writers
on our show now.
It's true.
Ten years ago, he used to do
internal company videos.
While he's left all that behind,
guess what, Wells Fargo ?
He's agreed to do one more video,
this time, just for you.
This is an uncomfortable subject,
but remember me, Wells Fargo ?
I'm your fraud guy ! From the video
that, judging by your behavior,
none of you assholes watched.
I'm sure you've noticed,
I did steal this suit from wardrobe.
Criticize me for taking
what didn't belong to me.
I dare you.
I fucking dare you.
There were things
I didn't mention in that video,
I thought
they went without saying.
Don't set crazy goals that encourage
your staff to open fake accounts.
Don't punish whistleblowers.
Don't illegally repossess soldiers'
cars when on active duty.
Come on Wells Fargo. These are basic
lessons for being a human being.
Get your shit together.
I'll tell you why.
It turns out, ethics violations
aren't actually like a rubber band.
They're more like a dildo
attached to a boomerang.
Because they will come back
and they will fuck you.
That's our show !
See you next week ! Good night !
LAST WEEK TONIGHT
WITH JOHN OLIVER
END OF EPISODE 24,
SEASON III