♪ ♪
John: HI THERE.
WELCOME TO THE SHOW.
STILL TAKING PLACE IN THIS
BLANK VOID WHICH, FUN FACT, IS
ACTUALLY THE INTERIOR OF THE
STAY PUFT MARSHMALLOW MAN'S
BLEACHED ASSHOLE.
IT'S TRUE!
AND YOU KNOW WHAT?
IT'S ACTUALLY WARMER IN HERE
THAN YOU MIGHT THINK.
THIS IS OUR FIRST SHOW IN A
MONTH, AND THERE'S CLEARLY A LOT
TO CATCH UP ON, INCLUDING THE
FACT THAT VIN DIESEL CHOSE TO
PREMIERE HIS NEW SONG TO
KELLY CLARKSON'S VIRTUAL
AUDIENCE LIKE THIS:
♪ ALL OF THE TIMES YOU TRIED
TO FIND SOMEONE ♪
♪ THAT HIT ME LIKE YOU ♪
♪ AND I'M NOT THE TYPE WHO LIKES
TO RUSH IN ♪
♪ BUT I WANT TO ♪
♪ I DON'T KNOW YOU ♪
♪ BUT IT FEELS LIKE I DO ♪
♪ AND I WAS FROZEN ♪
♪ WHEN YOU WALKED IN THE ROOM ♪
John: YES.
I KNOW YOU MIGHT BE EXPECTING ME
TO SHIT ON PROFESSIONAL GRUNTER
VIN DIESEL RELEASING A POP SONG
TO WHAT LOOKS LIKE A DIGITAL PTA
MEETING, BUT YOU HAVE READ ME
WRONG ON THIS ONE.
BECAUSE THAT SONG IS PURE,
TENDER ART.
IT'S HONESTLY THE ONLY THING
THAT'S BROUGHT ME JOY IN THE
LAST SIX MONTHS, AND I HAD AN
EMMY EXPLOSIVELY PUNCHED AT ME
JUST LAST WEEKEND.
LET ME ASK THIS: IS VIN DIESEL A
BRITISH SAUSAGE PRODUCER?
BECAUSE THE MAN MAKES
BANGERS.
BUT SADLY, IT HASN'T ALL BEEN
FUN SINCE WE'VE BEEN AWAY.
IN FACT, BASICALLY NOTHING'S
BEEN FUN.
U.S. COVID DEATHS HIT 200,000,
PARTS OF THE WEST COAST ARE
STILL ON FIRE.
AND IN LOUISVILLE, A GRAND JURY
DECLINED TO INDICT ANYONE OVER
THE DEATH OF BREONNA TAYLOR,
MERELY CHARGING ONE OFFICER WITH
WANTON ENDANGERMENT FOR SHOOTING
AT HER APARTMENT BUILDING.
IT WAS AN INFURIATINGLY
PREDICTABLE DECISION, LEADING TO
WIDESPREAD PROTESTS, WHICH
FOX NEWS SOUGHT TO DOWNPLAY WITH
THE HELP OF THIS FORMER COP.
YOU HAVE THE ATTORNEY GENERAL
FOR... DANIEL CAMERON FOR THE
STATE OF KENTUCKY WHO ANNOUNCED
THE CHARGE AND ALSO THE CITY
PAID $12 MILLION TO THE FAMILY,
AND YOU HAVE TO ASK, WHY ARE THE
DEMONSTRATIONS CONTINUING?
ARE... IT'S ONLY CONTINUING, IN
MY MIND, BECAUSE THERE ARE
PEOPLE WHO HAVE THEIR OWN
AGENDA.
John: NOW, I KNOW THAT SOUNDS
AWFUL, AND THAT'S BECAUSE IT IS.
BUT TRY AND LOOK AT IT FROM HIS
PERSPECTIVE: THE COPS IN
QUESTION WERE INVESTIGATED, LET
OFF, AND THE VICTIM'S FAMILY WAS
PAID OFF WITH TAXPAYER MONEY.
FROM A FORMER POLICE OFFICER'S
POINT OF VIEW, THAT'S THE SYSTEM
WORKING AS DESIGNED...
AND THAT IS KIND OF THE WHOLE
FUCKING PROBLEM HERE.
BUT OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT
CONCERNS THE FACT THAT, LAST
WEEKEND, RUTH BADER GINSBURG
DIED, WHICH WAS DISTRESSING
ENOUGH.
BUT IT'S BEEN COMPOUNDED BY THE
FACT THAT JUST YESTERDAY, THIS
HAPPENED:
GOOD EVENING, WE BEGIN WITH
THE NUMERIC BREAKING NEWS.
THE PRESIDENT NOMINATING ANY CO.
BARRETT IS FAVORITE OF
RELIGIOUS CONSERVATIVES FOR HER
STRONG ANTI-ABORTION RIGHTS
VIEWS AND, IF CONFIRMED, WOULD
MOVE THE COURT TO THE RIGHT FOR
A GENERATION.
John: RIGHT, TRUMP IS ABOUT
TO REPLACE A LIBERAL ICON WITH
AN EXTREMELY CONSERVATIVE
JUSTICE WHO'S BEEN CALLED THE
FEMALE ANTONIN SCALIA, AND SHE
COULD SERVE FOR A LONG, LONG
TIME.
AMY CONEY BARRETT IS ONLY 48,
AND I KNOW THAT I MAKE 43 LOOK
LIKE 76, BUT TRUST ME, THAT'S
YOUNG FOR A SUPREME COURT
JUSTICE.
AND LOOK, IF... AND ALMOST
CERTAINLY WHEN... BARRETT IS
CONFIRMED TO THE SUPREME COURT,
THE IMPACT COULD BE DIRE.
IN RECENT YEARS, KEY CASES HAVE
BEEN DECIDED BY JUST ONE VOTE,
FROM UPHOLDING THE AFFORDABLE
CARE ACT TO PRESERVING DACA TO
STRIKING DOWN AN INCREDIBLY
RESTRICTIVE ABORTION LAW.
SHOULD THOSE ISSUES COME BEFORE
THE COURT AGAIN, THEY COULD NOW
EASILY GO THE OTHER WAY.
AND THERE IS CLEARLY NO POINT
HOLDING ONTO HOPE THAT
CONSERVATIVES MIGHT CHOOSE TO
RESPECT THE PRECEDENT THEY SET
BY REFUSING TO EVEN CONSIDER
MERRICK GARLAND IN AN ELECTION
YEAR, BECAUSE THAT WAS ALWAYS IN
BAD FAITH, AS WAS OBVIOUS AT THE
TIME.
IN FACT, AHEAD OF THE 2016
ELECTION, SENATOR RICHARD BURR
EVEN PRIVATELY SAID THIS TO A
GROUP OF CAMPAIGN VOLUNTEERS:
IF HILLARY CLINTON BECOMES
PRESIDENT, I AM GOING TO DO
EVERYTHING I CAN DO TO MAKE
SURE THAT, FOUR YEARS FROM NOW,
WE STILL GOT AN OPENING ON THE
SUPREME COURT.
John: YEAH, THAT'S A
REPUBLICAN SENATOR COMMITTING TO
BLOCKING A JUSTICE CONFIRMATION,
NOT JUST IN AN ELECTION YEAR,
BUT FOR AN ENTIRE PRESIDENTIAL
TERM.
AND JUST THINK ABOUT HOW LONG
FOUR YEARS IS.
FOUR YEARS AGO, HARVEY WEINSTEIN
WAS STILL PRODUCING MOVIES.
IN THE PAST FOUR YEARS,
HARRY AND MEGHAN BEGAN DATING,
GOT ENGAGED, GOT MARRIED, LEFT
THE ROYAL FAMILY, AND I THINK
OWN NETFLIX NOW?
AND IN THE PAST FOUR YEARS,
LEONARDO DiCAPRIO'S GIRLFRIEND
GAINED THE RIGHT TO LEGALLY
DRINK ALCOHOL.
TWO MORE YEARS, AND SHE'LL
HAVE NO PROBLEM GETTING
A RENTAL CAR...
TO MOVE HER BELONGINGS OUT OF
HIS HOUSE.
TIME IS AMAZING.
AND SOME REPUBLICANS SEEM TO
RATIONALIZE THEIR PARTY'S
BLATANT HYPOCRISY BY SAYING
THAT, SHOULD THEY CONFIRM
TRUMP'S NOMINEE, THEY'LL SIMPLY
BE BRINGING THE COURT CLOSER TO
THE WILL OF THE COUNTRY.
I RECOGNIZE THAT WE MAY HAVE
A COURT WHICH HAS MORE OF A
CONSERVATIVE BENT THAN IT'S HAD
OVER THE LAST FEW DECADES, BUT
MY LIBERAL FRIENDS HAVE, OVER
MANY DECADES, GOTTEN VERY USED
TO THE IDEA OF HAVING A LIBERAL
COURT, AND THAT'S NOT WRITTEN IN
THE STARS.
IT'S ALSO APPROPRIATE FOR A
NATION WHICH IS, IF YOU WILL,
CENTER RIGHT, TO HAVE A COURT
WHICH REFLECTS CENTER RIGHT
POINTS OF VIEW.
John: WHAT THE HELL ARE YOU
TALKING ABOUT, MITT?
SET ASIDE THE NOTION THAT A
COURT THAT GUTTED THE VOTING
RIGHTS ACT IS A "LIBERAL COURT,"
SINCE WHEN IS THIS NATION
NATURALLY CENTER RIGHT?
DID WE ALL TAKE A BUZZFEED QUIZ
THAT I'M NOT REMEMBERING, LIKE
"CHOOSE YOUR FAVORITE
FALL LASAGNA INGREDIENTS AND
WE'LL TELL YOU WHICH DIRECTION
THE NATION'S ELECTORATE LEANS?"
BECAUSE, FOR THE RECORD, MORE
AMERICANS SAY THEY ALIGN WITH
THE DEMOCRATIC PARTY THAN THE
REPUBLICANS.
PLUS, POLL AFTER POLL HAS SHOWN
AMERICANS FAVOR ABORTION RIGHTS,
WITH SUPPORT OF ROE V. WADE
REACHING RECORD HIGHS, WHILE A
STRONG MAJORITY OF THE PUBLIC
ALSO SUPPORTS MEDICARE FOR ALL.
OH, AND INCIDENTALLY, A SOLID
MAJORITY SAY THE WINNER OF THIS
PRESIDENTIAL ELECTION SHOULD BE
THE ONE TO CHOOSE GINSBURG'S
SUCCESSOR.
SO OUR COUNTRY ISN'T SO MUCH
CENTER RIGHT AS MITT ROMNEY IS
CENTER WRONG.
LOOK, THIS HAS BEEN A VERY DARK
WEEK FOR A LOT OF PEOPLE.
THE SUPREME COURT IS ABOUT TO
LURCH TO THE RIGHT FOR THE
FORESEEABLE FUTURE.
AND IF THINGS SEEM HOPELESS
RIGHT NOW, IT'S BECAUSE, TO BE
COMPLETELY HONEST, THEY
BASICALLY ARE.
THIS IS A PIVOTAL MOMENT, AND
WHILE WE GOT HERE A LITTLE BIT
BY BAD LUCK AND BAD TIMING, WE
ALSO GOT HERE THROUGH DILIGENT
EFFORT BY REPUBLICAN LEADERSHIP
AND, CRUCIALLY, SOME VERY BIG
SYSTEMIC PROBLEMS WHICH JUST
HAVE TO BE ADDRESSED.
SO TONIGHT, LET'S TALK ABOUT
THAT: SPECIFICALLY, HOW THE FUCK
WE GOT HERE AND WHAT THE FUCK WE
CAN POSSIBLY DO NEXT.
AND THERE ARE BASICALLY TWO
MAJOR FACTORS THAT BROUGHT US TO
THIS POINT.
THE FIRST IS THIS MAN,
MITCH McCONNELL, THE ONLY THING
TO COME OUT OF KENTUCKY MORE
SHAMELESS THAN THE KFC MENU.
HOW DO YOU WANT YOUR CHICKEN?
REGULAR?
CRISPY?
CHEETO-FLAVORED?
IN A WARM SLURRY?
AS BREAD?
'CAUSE IT'S ALL ON THE TABLE.
AT KFC, WE PROMISE:
MAXIMUM FLAVOR FOR YOU,
MAXIMUM DISRESPECT FOR A
CHICKEN'S MEMORY.
RECONFIGURING AMERICA'S COURTS
HAS BEEN A SINGLE-MINDED FOCUS
FOR McCONNELL.
TRUMP ONCE MARVELED TO
BOB WOODWARD THAT "YOU KNOW WHAT
MITCH'S BIGGEST THING IS IN THE
WHOLE WORLD?
HIS JUDGES."
AND HIS OBSESSION ISN'T JUST
WITH THE SUPREME COURT.
McCONNELL'S BLOCKADE OF
MERRICK GARLAND JUSTIFIABLY GOT
A LOT OF ATTENTION, BUT HE ALSO
MADE SURE TRUMP COULD STACK THE
LOWER COURTS WITH CONSERVATIVE
JUDGES, SOMETHING TRUMP ALSO
EXPLAINED TO WOODWARD.
I'M GOING TO BE UP TO
280 JUDGES VERY SOON.
NOBODY'S EVER HAD THAT.
280.
OBAMA GAVE US 142 JUDGES WHEN I
CAME HERE.
THIS NEVER HAPPENED.
YOU NEVER HAD ONE.
IF YOU WERE A PRESIDENT, YOU
WOULD NEVER HAVE ANY FEDERAL...
THEY WERE LIKE GOLDEN NUGGETS,
RIGHT?
John: OKAY, FIRST, IT'S WEIRD
TO REFER TO ANYTHING AS
"GOLDEN NUGGETS" UNLESS
YOU'RE TALKING ABOUT ACTUAL
GOLDEN NUGGETS OR YOU'RE
DESCRIBING YOUR HUSBAND'S BALLS
IN THE MIDDLE OF HIS
TIGER-THEMED FUNERAL WHILE
IMPERSONATING A PRIEST.
THOSE ARE THE ONLY TWO PERFECTLY
APPROPRIATE TIMES.
BUT NEEDLESS TO SAY, OBAMA VERY
MUCH DIDN'T DELIBERATELY LEAVE
THOSE VACANCIES OPEN FOR TRUMP.
WHEN REPUBLICANS TOOK THE SENATE
IN 2014, MITCH McCONNELL BEGAN
SYSTEMATICALLY BLOCKING
LOWER COURT APPOINTEES SO A
FUTURE REPUBLICAN PRESIDENT
COULD FILL THE SEATS LATER.
SO OBAMA DIDN'T GIVE TRUMP THOSE
JUDGES ANY MORE THAN THE
NATIONAL ARCHIVES GAVE
NICOLAS CAGE THE DECLARATION OF
INDEPENDENCE.
IN FACT, OBAMA'S ONLY EVER GIVEN
TRUMP TWO THINGS: A BRIEF TOUR
OF THE WHITE HOUSE AND A
COLOSSAL INFERIORITY COMPLEX
THAT FUELED TRUMP'S RISE TO
POWER AND MADE HIM SO FURIOUS HE
DECIDED TO TURN AMERICA INTO AN
APOCALYPTIC HELLSCAPE AND
DESTROY DEMOCRACY AS WE KNOW IT.
REALLY JUST THOSE TWO THINGS.
AND McCONNELL'S WILLINGNESS TO
GO TO THE MAT FOR JUDICIAL
APPOINTMENTS WAS PERHAPS NEVER
MORE OBVIOUS THAN DURING THE
KAVANAUGH HEARINGS, BECAUSE
IMMEDIATELY AFTER
CHRISTINE BLASEY FORD'S
GUT-WRENCHING TESTIMONY,
McCONNELL APPARENTLY HAD THIS
CONVERSATION WITH THE PRESIDENT.
BOTH OF THEM ARE KIND OF
TESTING EACH OTHER A BIT.
"WHERE ARE YOU AT ON THIS?"
YOU KNOW, "HOW STRONG ARE YOU?"
AND McCONNELL BASICALLY SAYS TO
THE PRESIDENT, "YOU DON'T WORRY
ABOUT ME.
I'M STRONG AS MULE PISS."
THAT'S HIS QUOTE.
"I'M STRONG AS MULE PISS."
IN OTHER WORDS, HE'S NOT GOING
TO LET UP, HE'S NOT GOING TO
GIVE UP, HE'S NOT GOING TO
SURRENDER.
John: WOW.
THAT IS EXTRAORDINARY.
BECAUSE IT'S EASY TO FORGET THAT
AFTER BLASEY FORD'S TESTIMONY,
KAVANAUGH'S CONFIRMATION FELT A
LOT LESS CERTAIN.
AND TO REACT TO WHAT SHE SAID
WITH, "DON'T WORRY, I'M STRONG
AS MULE PISS" IS BOTH HORRENDOUS
AND DEEPLY WEIRD.
QUICK SIDE NOTE: I WASN'T SURE
HOW STRONG MULE PISS ACTUALLY
IS, AND THE INTERNET IS
SURPRISINGLY SHORT OF VIDEOS OF
MULES URINATING.
ALTHOUGH WE DID FIND MANAGE TO
FIND THIS STOCK FOOTAGE TITLED
"DONKEY WHO URINE AT SUNSET,"
AND I HAVE TO SAY, THAT IS AN
IMPRESSIVELY STRONG STREAM.
SO I DO TOTALLY GET IT NOW.
AND GOING FORWARD, EVERY TIME I
THINK OF MITCH McCONNELL, I WILL
THINK OF THAT DONKEY
WHO URINE AT SUNSET.
BUT AS EASY AND FUN AS IT IS TO
BLAME MITCH McCONNELL AND HIS
MULE PISS FOR EVERYTHING, IT'S A
MISTAKE TO FOCUS JUST ON THE
PEOPLE INVOLVED HERE, BECAUSE
THERE IS A WHOLE SYSTEM
UNDERNEATH THEM THAT HAS ENABLED
WHAT THEY HAVE DONE.
AND THAT BRINGS US TO THE SECOND
MAJOR FACTOR THAT GOT US TO
WHERE WE ARE NOW: THE DEEPLY
UNDEMOCRATIC NATURE OF
AMERICA'S INSTITUTIONS.
BECAUSE THERE IS NO DOUBT, THE
REPUBLICAN PARTY CURRENTLY
CONTROLS BOTH THE SENATE AND THE
WHITE HOUSE.
IT'S TRUE.
AND THEY WILL ARGUE
THIS GIVES THEM A MANDATE TO DO
EXACTLY WHAT THEY'RE DOING.
CHRIS, THE SENATE MAJORITY IS
PERFORMING OUR CONSTITUTIONAL
DUTY AND FULFILLING THE MANDATE
THAT THE VOTERS GAVE US.
VOTERS HAVE ELECTED A
REPUBLICAN PRESIDENT.
THEY ELECTED A REPUBLICAN
SENATE.
AND I THINK REPUBLICANS NEED TO
KEEP THEIR PROMISES HERE, AND
THAT'S WHAT I INTEND TO DO.
THE AMERICAN PEOPLE ELECTED
PRESIDENT TRUMP AND A REPUBLICAN
MAJORITY BECAUSE WE WANT THE
CONSTITUTION AND BILL OF RIGHTS
PROTECTED, AND THAT IS OUR JOB.
IT'S WHAT WE NEED TO DO.
John: I DO NOT LIKE THAT MAN
TED CRUZ.
I DO NOT LIKE
HIS BACKWARD VIEWS.
I DO NOT LIKE HIS STUPID SUITS.
I DO NOT LIKE HIS COWBOY BOOTS.
I DO NOT LIKE HIM WHEN
HE SNEEZES.
I DO NOT LIKE HIM
EATING CHEESES.
I HATE TO SEE
HIS DUMB FACE SMIRKIN',
BECAUSE HIS BEARD LOOKS LIKE
A MERKIN.
BUT, LOOK, LET'S TALK ABOUT THAT
MANDATE, BECAUSE NEITHER THE
PRESIDENCY NOR THE SENATE ARE AS
REFLECTIVE OF THE WILL OF THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE AS THEY'RE
SUGGESTING THERE.
FIRST, TAKE THE WHITE HOUSE.
A DEMOCRAT HAS WON THE NATIONAL
POPULAR VOTE IN FOUR OUT OF THE
LAST FIVE ELECTIONS, BUT WE HAVE
SPENT 12 OF THE LAST 20 YEARS
WITH A REPUBLICAN IN OFFICE, AND
THAT IS BECAUSE THE ELECTORAL
COLLEGE, WITH ITS
WINNER-TAKE-ALL APPROACH IN MOST
STATES, CAN DISTORT THE WILL OF
THE MAJORITY, ON TOP OF WHICH IT
GRANTS DISPROPORTIONATE POWER TO
LESS POPULOUS STATES, WHICH TEND
TO BE RURAL AND MORE
CONSERVATIVE, SOMETHING WHICH IS
EVEN MORE PRONOUNCED IN THE
SENATE, WHERE THERE ARE
15 STATES REPRESENTING
38 MILLION PEOPLE THAT HAVE
30 REPUBLICAN SENATORS, EVEN
THOUGH THAT IS LESS THAN THE
TOTAL POPULATION OF CALIFORNIA,
WHICH HAS JUST TWO DEMOCRATIC
ONES.
AND THAT'S BEFORE YOU EVEN
GET INTO THE FACT THAT
PLACES LIKE PUERTO RICO AND
WASHINGTON D.C.... WHERE THE
POPULATIONS ARE LARGELY BLACK
OR HISPANIC... DON'T HAVE
REPRESENTATION IN THE SENATE AT
ALL.
IN FACT, IF YOU TAKE ALL THIS
TOGETHER, THE SENATE GIVES THE
AVERAGE BLACK AMERICAN ONLY 75%
AS MUCH REPRESENTATION AS THE
AVERAGE WHITE AMERICAN AND THE
AVERAGE HISPANIC AMERICAN ONLY
55% AS MUCH.
AND IT'S CLEARLY NOT GREAT WHEN
THE BEST THING YOU CAN SAY ABOUT
YOUR REPRESENTATIVE DEMOCRACY
IS, "HEY, AT LEAST BLACK PEOPLE
GOT ABOVE THREE FIFTHS THIS
TIME.
AT THIS RATE, THEY COULD COUNT
AS 100% OF A WHITE PERSON AS
EARLY AS 2408.
ONWARDS AND UPWARDS,
BLACK PEOPLE!
YOU TRULY ARE AN INSPIRATION TO
HISPANIC HALF-PEOPLE
EVERYWHERE."
SO THE FACT IS, WHEN BARRETT IS
CONFIRMED, A PRESIDENT WHO LOST
THE POPULAR VOTE WILL HAVE
PICKED A QUARTER OF THE FEDERAL
JUDICIARY AND A THIRD OF THE
SUPREME COURT, AND HIS CHOICES
WILL HAVE BEEN RUBBER-STAMPED BY
A SENATE REPUBLICAN MAJORITY
REPRESENTING 15 MILLION FEWER
PEOPLE THAN THE DEMOCRATIC
"MINORITY," AND THOSE COURTS
HAVE ALLOWED REPUBLICANS TO SET
WILDLY UNPOPULAR POLICY THAT
WOULDN'T ACTUALLY PASS MUSTER
WITH VOTERS.
AND THAT BRINGS US TO OUR FINAL
QUESTION OF, WHAT CAN NOW BE
DONE?
WELL, FOR DEMOCRATS, THE FIRST
PRIORITY IS TO TRY AND TAKE
CONTROL OF THE WHITE HOUSE AND
BOTH CHAMBERS OF CONGRESS THIS
NOVEMBER, WHICH, GIVEN
EVERYTHING WE'VE JUST DISCUSSED,
IS BY NO MEANS A CERTAINTY.
NOT ONLY COULD TRUMP WIN THE
ELECTION OUTRIGHT, EVEN IF HE
DOESN'T, HE COULD, AS HE'S
REPEATEDLY INDICATED, REFUSE TO
CONCEDE AND FORCE THE RESULT
INTO THE COURTS.
AND THAT POSSIBILITY IS CLEARLY
PART OF HIS HASTE TO GET A
JUSTICE CONFIRMED BEFORE THE
ELECTION.
BECAUSE HE'S NOT EVEN TRYING TO
HIDE IT NOW.
WE NEED NINE JUSTICES.
YOU NEED THAT.
WITH THE UNSOLICITED MILLIONS OF
BALLOTS THAT THEY'RE SENDING,
IT'S A SCAM, IT'S A HOAX,
EVERYBODY KNOWS THAT.
AND THE DEMOCRATS KNOW IT BETTER
THAN ANYBODY ELSE.
SO YOU'RE GONNA NEED NINE
JUSTICES UP THERE.
I THINK IT'S GOING TO BE VERY
IMPORTANT.
John: OKAY.
THERE IS A NUMBER OF
DARK INSINUATIONS THERE,
INCLUDING, "IT'S IMPORTANT FOR
US TO CHOOSE THE NEXT JUSTICE SO
THEY CAN DECIDE WHAT THE
AMERICAN PEOPLE CHOSE."
AND THAT MAKES IT PRETTY CLEAR
THAT, FOR TRUMP, HAVING AN
ADDITIONAL SUPREME COURT
APPOINTMENT IS ABSOLUTELY
CRUCIAL TO HIS RE-ELECTION...
AS CRUCIAL, SAY, AS ANGRY WHITE
PEOPLE WEARING RED HATS,
FACEBOOK POSTS FROM UNDERCOVER
RUSSIAN OPERATIVES, AND, BASED
ON HIS CAMPAIGN'S ONLINE STORE,
SELLING TRUMP COLORING BOOKS
THAT EVEN THE KIDS IN THE AD
LOOK BORED BY.
WHAT IS GOING ON THERE?
THE YOUNGER KID ISN'T EVEN
PAYING ATTENTION, AND THE OLDER
ONE LOOKS LIKE HE'S TRYING TO
WILL THE COLORING BOOK INTO
BECOMING A NINTENDO SWITCH WITH
HIS EYES.
ALSO, WHY AREN'T THEY
COLORING IN THE COLORING BOOK?
THE FATHER SEEMS TO BE READING
IT TO HIS CHILDREN, WHICH IS
OBJECTIVELY THE ONE WRONG WAY TO
ENJOY A COLORING BOOK.
BUT LOO, LET'S SAY, FOR THE SAKE
OF ARGUMENT, DEMOCRATS DO MANAGE
TO SWEEP THE UPCOMING ELECTION.
THE BIGGEST MISTAKE WOULD BE TO
THINK THAT THAT HAS, IN ITSELF,
FIXED EVERYTHING... OR, INDEED,
ANYTHING... BECAUSE THERE'S NO
POINT GETTING POWER UNLESS YOU
ARE THEN WILLING TO BE BOLD
ENOUGH TO USE IT TO MAKE
SIGNIFICANT STRUCTURAL CHANGE.
WE'VE ARGUED BEFORE THAT THE
FILIBUSTER SHOULD BE ABOLISHED.
THAT WOULD ALLOW LEGISLATION TO
GET PASSED WITH A SIMPLE
MAJORITY.
IT IS ADMITTEDLY RISKY,
ESPECIALLY FOR A PARTY THAT,
AGAIN, FOR STRUCTURAL REASONS,
CAN EXPECT TO BE IN THE MINORITY
MORE OFTEN THAN IT SHOULD.
BUT THOSE VERY FACTORS MAKE IT
EXTREMELY HARD FOR DEMOCRATS TO
WIN A FILIBUSTER-PROOF
SUPERMAJORITY AND DO ANYTHING
MEANINGFUL.
WHAT IS FRUSTRATING IS THAT SOME
CENTRIST DEMOCRATS, LIKE
JOE MANCHIN, HONESTLY SEEM TO
THINK THAT, EVEN IF THEY GET
SIGNIFICANTLY MORE POWER, THE
BEST WAY FORWARD IS TO TRY AND
RETURN TO A MORE CIVILIZED,
MODERATE ERA IN AMERICAN
POLITICS.
I WILL MAKE EVERY DECISION
I CAN THAT KEEPS THE SENATE
BIPARTISAN.
SIMPLE AS THAT.
WE HAVE GOT TO FIGHT FOR
BASICALLY WHO WE ARE AS A
SENATE.
CAN WE REPRESENT THE PEOPLE IN A
BIPARTISAN WAY?
DEMOCRATS AND REPUBLICANS.
John: OH, I'VE GOT AN ANSWER
TO THAT QUESTION FOR YOU, JOE:
NO.
YOU CAN'T.
IT SEEMS THE MESSAGE MANCHIN
WOULD TAKE FROM AMERICA SURGING
TO THE LEFT, AGAINST THE ODDS,
WOULD BE "I THINK THEY WANT US
TO WORK WITH REPUBLICANS."
AND THAT IS NOT JUST DUMB,
THAT'S DUMB ON THE LEVEL OF
JAMES CAMERON GOING, "YOU KNOW
WHAT PEOPLE WANT?
FOUR MORE 'AVATAR' MOVIES."
AND TO BOTH OF THOSE MEN, I SAY
THIS: NO ONE WANTS THAT, STOP
TALKING ABOUT IT, AND JUST GIVE
US WHAT WE WANT:
ONE MORE GOOD "TERMINATOR" MOVIE
AND A GREEN NEW DEAL.
I DON'T CARE WHICH OF YOU DOES
WHICH, JUST GET IT THE FUCK
DONE.
ALTHOUGH I WILL SAY, EVEN IF THE
DEMOCRATS SWEEP THE ELECTION,
AND EVEN IF THEY THEN GET RID OF
THE FILIBUSTER AND THEN HAVE THE
COURAGE TO PASS MAJOR
LEGISLATION, THOSE LAWS ARE NOW
INCREASINGLY VULNERABLE TO A
MORE CONSERVATIVE SUPREME COURT
STRIKING THEM DOWN.
AND THAT HAS LED SOME TO SUGGEST
TAKING THE MORE DRAMATIC STEP OF
EXPANDING THE SUPREME COURT BY
ADDING JUSTICES.
IT'S POSSIBLE.
THE CONSTITUTION DOESN'T SPECIFY
HOW MANY SEATS THERE SHOULD BE,
AND IT CAN AND HAS BEEN DONE IN
THE PAST THROUGH A SIMPLE ACT OF
CONGRESS, ALTHOUGH THERE ARE
REAL CONCERNS ABOUT WHAT THE
EVENTUAL BLOWBACK TO THAT WOULD
BE.
BECAUES IT DOESN'T TAKE A GENIUS
TO IMAGINE WHAT REPUBLICANS
WOULD DO NEXT TIME THEY TOOK
CONTROL OF THE GOVERNMENT.
SERIOUSLY, IT DOESN'T TAKE A
GENIUS.
THEY WANNA PACK THE COURT...
YOU KNOW WHAT THAT MEANS?
THEY WANNA PUT ON A LOT OF
JUSTICES.
THESE ARE THINGS THAT ARE JUST
HORRIBLE.
I GUESS WE COULD DO THAT TOO,
RIGHT?
WE COULD DO THAT TOO.
John: YEAH.
HE'S RIGHT.
HE COULD ABSOLUTELY DO THAT,
WHICH IS UNDENIABLY CHILLING.
EXPANDING THE COURT IS A BIT
LIKE DOING YOGA NAKED...
ONE WAY TO DAMPEN YOUR
ENTHUSIASM FOR THE IDEA IS TO
PICTURE DONALD TRUMP DOING IT
TOO.
COURT EXPANSION COULD OPEN THE
DOOR TO A NEVER-ENDING CYCLE OF
BOTH PARTIES DOING IT, WHICH
COULD PERMANENTLY DESTABILIZE
ONE OF THE BEDROCK INSTITUTIONS
OF AMERICAN GOVERNMENT.
NOW, DOES THAT OUTWEIGH THE
POTENTIAL FOR A COURT WITH
BARRETT ON IT UNDOING OR
BLOCKING YEARS OF PROTECTIONS
FOR OUR CLIMATE, HEALTH CARE,
AND CIVIL AND WOMEN'S RIGHTS?
THAT IS DEFINITELY WORTH
CONSIDERING.
NOTHING SHOULD BE TAKEN LIGHTLY
HERE... THOUGH I WILL SAY, THERE
ARE SOME OTHER STEPS WE COULD
TAKE THAT SHOULD BE IMPOSSIBLE
TO ARGUE WITH AT THIS POINT,
STEPS THAT WOULD MAKE BOTH THE
SENATE AND WHITE HOUSE MORE
REPRESENTATIVE OF THE
ELECTORATE.
ON THE SENATE SIDE, YOU
COULD GRANT STATEHOOD TO
WASHINGTON D.C. AND, IF VOTERS
THERE WANT IT, PUERTO RICO.
THAT WOULD NOT ONLY HELP BALANCE
OUT THE SENATE'S PRO-WHITE,
...BIAS TOWARD WHITE, RURAL
VOTERS,
IT'S ALSO THE
RIGHT FUCKING THING TO DO FOR
THE ALMOST 4 MILLION AMERICANS
WHO CURRENTLY HAVE NO SENATORIAL
REPRESENTATION WHATSOEVER, WHICH
IS JUST ASTONISHING.
IT'S ROUGHLY THE POPULATION OF
RHODE ISLAND, MAINE, MONTANA,
AND WYOMING COMBINED.
NOW, AS FOR THE PRESIDENCY, WE
HAVE TO GET RID OF THE ELECTORAL
COLLEGE, WHICH MIGHT SOUND
RADICAL, BUT IT REALLY ISN'T.
IT'S NOT EVEN A NEW IDEA.
IN FACT, IN THE LATE '60s, IT
VERY NEARLY HAPPENED.
HERE'S BIRCH BAYH, THE SENATOR
WHO SPEARHEADED THOSE EFFORTS,
MAKING WHAT IS, IN RETROSPECT, A
PRETTY CONVINCING CASE:
THERE IS A GREAT DANGER WITH
THE PRESENT ELECTORAL COLLEGE
SYSTEM OF ELECTING A MINORITY,
OR A NON-PLURALITY, PRESIDENT,
OF ELECTING A PRESIDENT WHO HAS
FEWER VOTES THAN THE FELLA HE'S
RUNNING AGAINST.
WHEN WE HAVE AN ELECTORAL
COLLEGE SYSTEM WHICH THREATENS
TO ELECT A MAN WHO HAS FEWER
VOTES THAN HIS OPPONENT, WE TEND
TO ERODE THE CONFIDENCE IN THE
PEOPLE OF THIS COUNTRY IN THEIR
PRESIDENT AND IN THEIR FORM OF
GOVERNMENT.
John: RIGHT.
AND AS SOMEONE WHO'S LIVED
THROUGH THE EXACT HYPOTHETICAL
HE JUST DESCRIBED, AND TWICE, I
CAN REPORT THAT OUR CONFIDENCE
IN GOVERNMENT HASN'T SO MUCH
BEEN ERODED... EROSION IS A
SLOW, DIGNIFIED PROCESS... AS
MUCH AS IT'S BEEN HIT BY AN
ASTEROID FULL OF SENTIENT
NUCLEAR JACKHAMMERS UNTIL IT
COLLAPSED IN ON ITSELF LIKE A
STAR INSIDE A BLACK HOLE.
BACK THEN, THE IDEA OF
ABOLISHING THE ELECTORAL COLLEGE
HAD BIPARTISAN SUPPORT.
THEN-PRESIDENT NIXON EVEN URGED
CONGRESS TO GO THROUGH WITH IT,
WRITING "EVERY FOUR YEARS, THE
AMERICAN DEMOCRACY PLACES A
LARGE, UNACCEPTABLE, AND
UNNECESSARY WAGER THAT THE
ELECTORAL COLLEGE WILL WORK ONE
MORE TIME."
WHICH DOES MAKE SENSE, BECAUSE
IF THERE'S ONE THING WE KNOW
NIXON WAS NOT A FAN OF, IT'S
LEAVING ELECTIONS UP TO CHANCE.
AND IF THERE ARE SIX THINGS WE
KNOW HE WASN'T A FAN OF, IT'S
JEWS, BLACKS, HIPPIES, SNITCHES,
LIVING VIETNAMESE PEOPLE, AND
THEN LEAVING ELECTIONS UP TO
CHANCE.
MISS YOU, DICK.
BUT OBVIOUSLY, WE DIDN'T END UP
DOING AWAY WITH THE ELECTORAL
COLLEGE IN 1970, BECAUSE THE
LEGISLATION WAS ULTIMATELY
BLOCKED BY, YOU GUESSED IT, A
FUCKING FILIBUSTER.
AND EVEN TODAY, THE IDEA HAS
WIDESPREAD SUPPORT, WITH 61% OF
AMERICANS SAYING WE SHOULD
ABOLISH THE ELECTORAL COLLEGE.
BUT REPUBLICANS WILL FIERCELY
DEFEND IT.
IN FACT, WHEN A MOVEMENT TO
SWITCH TO A NATIONAL POPULAR
VOTE BEGAN PICKING UP STEAM A
DECADE AGO, MITCH McCONNELL SAID
REPUBLICANS NEED TO "KILL IT IN
THE CRADLE BEFORE IT GROWS UP."
BUT THE BEAUTY IS, THE MOVEMENT
McCONNELL WAS TALKING ABOUT
THERE DOESN'T NECESSARILY
REQUIRE HIS COOPERATION...
OR, INDEED, AN ACT OF CONGRESS
AT ALL... BECAUSE A GROUP OF
STATES HAVE QUIETLY SIGNED ONTO
AN INTERESTING WORKAROUND.
RECENTLY, 15 STATES AND THE
DISTRICT OF COLUMBIA JOINED THE
NATIONAL POPULAR VOTE INTERSTATE
COMPACT.
THEY'RE PLEDGING TO GIVE THEIR
ELECTORAL VOTES TO THE CANDIDATE
WHO WINS THE NATIONAL POPULAR
VOTE RATHER THAN THE PERSON WHO
WINS THE POPULAR VOTE IN THEIR
STATE.
BUT THIS WON'T TAKE EFFECT UNTIL
ENOUGH STATES ADOPT IT WHICH, SO
FAR, HASN'T HAPPENED.
John: YEAH, IT'S KIND OF
AMAZING.
VERY BASICALLY, IF ENOUGH STATES
JUST PRETEND THE ELECTORAL
COLLEGE DOESN'T EXIST, IT COULD
FUNCTIONALLY DISAPPEAR.
IT'S THE SAME APPROACH EVERY
"HARRY POTTER" FAN IS CURRENTLY
TRYING TO TAKE TOWARD
J.K. ROWLING.
OBLIVIATE.
YOU GO, THE BOOKS STAY.
NOW, FOR THIS IDEA TO TAKE
EFFECT... SETTING ASIDE THE
LEGAL HURDLES IT WOULD ALMOST
CERTAINLY FACE... IT WOULD
NEED STATES REPRESENTING
270 ELECTORAL VOTES TO SIGN ON.
IT CURRENTLY HAS 196, WHICH IS A
LOT, BUT NEEDS 74 MORE, WHICH
WOULD BE INCREASINGLY HARD TO
GET.
AND OBVIOUSLY, THE BETTER WAY TO
ABOLISH THE ELECTORAL COLLEGE
WOULD BE TO DO IT THROUGH A
CONSTITUTIONAL AMENDMENT, BUT
THAT IS EVEN HARDER.
AND I WILL SAY,
THERE ARE OTHER IDEAS FOR
SIGNIFICANT REFORM, SUCH AS
SETTING TERM LIMITS FOR
SUPREME COURT JUSTICES, WHICH
WE'VE ARGUED BEFORE WE SHOULD
ABSOLUTELY DO.
THE POINT HERE IS, IT'S PAST
TIME FOR BIG CHANGE.
AND PERHAPS THAT'S WHY
REPUBLICANS LIKE KEVIN McCARTHY
ALREADY SEEM TO BE FREAKING OUT.
THE DEMOCRATS BELIEVE IT HAS
TO BE THEIR WAY OR NO WAY, BUT
NOW IT'S A NEW EXTREME.
THEY WANT TO EXPAND THE
COURT.
THEY WANT TO BRING NEW STATES
INTO THE UNION.
ANYTHING THAT RIGS THE SYSTEM ON
THEIR BEHALF INSTEAD OF
BELIEVING IN THE RULE OF LAW.
John: OKAY, FIRST OF ALL,
FUCK YOU, KEVIN.
IF THERE IS ONE GROUP OF PEOPLE
WHO DON'T GET TO COMPLAIN ABOUT
THEIR OPPONENTS GOING TO
EXTREMES TO GET WHAT THEY WANT,
ITS CONGRESSIONAL FUCKING
REPUBLICANS, AND SECONDLY, WE'VE
EXPANDED THE COURT BEFORE AND
WE'VE ADDED STATES BEFORE.
WE ADDED TWO STATES IN 1959.
WE DIDN'T FIGHT WORLD WAR II
WITH 50 STARS ON THE FLAG.
AMERICA IS CONSTANTLY SHIFTING,
AND GRANTING D.C. AND
PUERTO RICO STATEHOOD OR ENDING
THE ELECTORAL COLLEGE WOULD
ACTUALLY MAKE OUR SYSTEM MORE
DEMOCRATIC RATHER THAN LESS,
BECAUSE THE UNAVOIDABLE TRUTH
HERE IS THAT THE SYSTEM IS
ALREADY RIGGED.
AND IT'S RIGGED IN A WAY THAT
HAS ALLOWED A PARTY WITHOUT
POPULAR SUPPORT TO DRASTICALLY
RESHAPE AN ENTIRE BRANCH OF
GOVERNMENT FOR THE FORESEEABLE
FUTURE BY APPEALING ALMOST
EXCLUSIVELY TO WHITE VOTERS IN
SOME OF THE LEAST POPULOUS
REGIONS OF THE COUNTRY.
THAT'S NOT A MANDATE, AND IT'S
NOT DEMOCRACY.
IT'S A FUCKING TRAVESTY.
WE ARE AT END OF A GENERATIONAL
BATTLE, AND THE HEARTBREAKING
THING IS, WE LOST.
AND THAT HURTS.
IT'S GOING TO HURT FOR A LONG
TIME FOR A LOT OF PEOPLE IN WAYS
THAT COULD TAKE A WHILE TO FULLY
COMPREHEND.
BUT THE NEXT BATTLE HAS TO START
RIGHT NOW.
AND IT WILL BE LONG.
WE DIDN'T GET HERE OVERNIGHT,
AND WE WON'T GET OUT OF HERE
OVERNIGHT, BUT WE MUST BE
WILLING TO FIGHT TIRELESSLY AND
WITH EVERY TOOL AND TACTIC AT
OUR DISPOSAL, BECAUSE SOMETIMES,
FIGHTING FIRE WITH FIRE ISN'T
ENOUGH.
YOU HAVE TO FIGHT MULE PISS WITH
MULE PISS.
AND NOW THIS.
Announcer: AND NOW, AN
UNEXPECTED UPDATE REGARDING
PEEPS.
A MAJOR CHANGE FOR ONE CANDY
COMPANY, JUST BONE QUALITY
CONFECTIONS HAS ANNOUNCED IT
WON'T BE PRODUCING ITS POPULAR
PEEPS FOR HALLOWEEN, CHRISTMAS,
OR VALENTINE'S DAY.
VALENTINE'S DAY.
VICTORY!
THE PEEPS HAS BEEN PURGED FROM A
HOLIDAY-THEMED GIFT BASKETS.
I DIDN'T KNOW THEY MADE THEM
FOR HALLOWEEN OR CHRISTMAS.
I DIDN'T KNOW THEY WERE
HALLOWEEN PEEPS EITHER, BUT YOU
NEVER STOP LEARNING.
PEEPS WILL NOT BE IN
HALLOWEEN CANDY BASKETS THIS
YEAR, THE COMPANY THAT PRODUCES
THEM SAID THEY WILL BE IN STARS
FOR CHRISTMAS EITHER.
DARN.
NO, NOT DON, WHATEVER THE
OPPOSITE OF "DARN" IS.
EVERY FOUR OR FIVE YEARS I
CONVINCE MYSELF TO TRY TO PEEP
BECAUSE I LOVE MARSHMALLOWS, AND
EVERY TIME I'M MAD.
I DON'T EVEN TRY THEM
ANYMORE.
DON'T EVEN TRY THEM!
THE END OF PEEPS SHALL BE THE
ONE TO DEVOUR YOU.
PRODUCTION STOPPED IN SPRING
WITH LIMITED PRODUCTION RESUMING
IN MID-MAY, HOWEVER, THE CANDY
IS SET TO RESUME NEXT YEAR JUST
IN TIME FOR EASTER.
NO!
NO, NO, NO, FUCK, NO!
John: MOVING ON.
FINALLY TONIGHT, A QUICK WORD ON
THE CENSUS.
YOU MAY REMEMBER WE COVERED IT
LAST YEAR WHEN WE LEARNED
DONALD TRUMP THOUGHT IT WAS WHEN
YOU COUNT HOW MANY TOILETS ARE
IN PEOPLE'S HOUSES.
WHICH, Y'KNOW...
IT ISN'T.
THE CENSUS IS HOW THE GOVERNMENT
DETERMINES THINGS LIKE THE
NUMBER OF SEATS EACH STATE HAS
IN THE HOUSE AND THE
DISTRIBUTION OF FEDERAL FUNDS,
AND GIVEN EVERYTHING THAT WE
JUST TALKED ABOUT EARLIER IN THE
SHOW ABOUT UNDERREPRESENTATION,
IT COULDN'T BE MORE IMPORTANT
FOR PEOPLE TO FILL IT IN.
UNFORTUNATELY, WITH THE
PANDEMIC, IT'S BECOME A BIT OF A
CLUSTERFUCK, WITH THE LATEST
NEWS COMING JUST THIS WEEK:
ALL RIGHT, BREAKING
OVERNIGHT: A FEDERAL COURT
ORDERING THE TRUMP
ADMINISTRATION TO DROP PLANS TO
RUSH THE CENSUS TO A CONCLUSION
AND EXTENDING COUNTING IN THE
CENSUS FOR AN ADDITIONAL MONTH.
NOW, THE CENSUS RESULTS
DETERMINE FUTURE CONGRESSIONAL
DISTRICTING AND HOW FEDERAL
FUNDING IS DIVVIED UP ACROSS THE
COUNTRY.
COMMERCE SECRETARY WILBUR ROSS
HAD ORDERED THE CENSUS BUREAU TO
FINISH COUNTING BY SEPTEMBER
30TH, ONE MONTH EARLIER THAN
ORIGINALLY PLANNED.
THE RULING IS EXPECTED TO BE
APPEALED.
John: YEAH.
THE DEADLINE FOR THE CENSUS WAS
INITIALLY JULY 31, THEN IT WAS
PUSHED BACK TO OCTOBER 31, THEN
POINTLESSLY MOVED FORWARD TO
SEPTEMBER 30, WHICH IS IN JUST
THREE DAYS, AND NOW THE COURTS
WILL DECIDE WHETHER THAT'S
ACTUALLY THE DEADLINE OR NOT.
BUT REGARDLESS OF WHEN THE
DEADLINE IS, IT'S SOON.
AND CURRENTLY, ESTIMATES ARE
THAT AROUND 14 MILLION
HOUSEHOLDS HAVEN'T PARTICIPATED.
BASICALLY, THE CENSUS IS
SOMETHING EVERYONE SHOULD DO,
BUT SOME OF US AREN'T, PUTTING
IT IN THE SAME CATEGORY AS
FLOSSING, EXCEPT INSTEAD OF
GETTING GINGIVITIS, YOU'RE
GETTING UNDERREPRESENTED IN
CONGRESS.
AND IF YOU ARE ONE OF THOSE
PEOPLE WHO HASN'T FILLED IT OUT
YET, I CANNOT OVERSTATE HOW
IMPORTANT IT IS THAT YOU DO SO.
AND IT'S SO EASY.
JUST GO TO THIS WEBSITE, OR IF
YOU LOVE PHONE CALLS FOR SOME
REASON, DIAL THIS NUMBER.
THE CENSUS BUREAU SAYS YOU'LL BE
DONE IN LESS THAN 10 MINUTES,
BUT HONESTLY, AND NOT TO BRAG, I
FOUND IT TOOK ME LESS THAN TWO.
SO WHY NOT DO IT RIGHT NOW?
BECAUSE YOU DEFINITELY HAVE TWO
MINUTES.
AND THE REASON I KNOW THAT IS,
WE'RE CURRENTLY 28 MINUTES INTO
A 30-MINUTE SHOW, AND I'M ABOUT
TO DRIVE YOU AWAY TO GO FILL IT
IN.
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING, "I DON'T
KNOW ABOUT THAT, I'M PRETTY
COMFORTABLE RIGHT NOW"...
NOT FOR LONG, YOU'RE NOT.
BECAUSE FOR THE REST OF THIS
SHOW, I'M GOING TO LEAVE YOU
WATCHING THIS SCREENSAVER OF A
DVD LOGO BOUNCING AROUND, LIKE A
SUBSTITUTE TEACHER WHO FELL
ASLEEP AFTER "GLORY" ENDED.
AND NOT ONLY THAT, UNDERNEATH
IT, WE'RE GOING TO BE PLAYING
THE AUDIOBOOK VERSION OF
SEAN PENN'S "BOB HONEY WHO JUST
DO STUFF," READ BY ITS AUTHOR, A
MAN WITH A FACE THAT'S SEEN
BETTER DAYS AND A VOICE THAT'S
SEEN BETTER CENTURIES.
THE BOOK HAS NO FORMAL PLOT, A
PRESIDENT CHARACTER REFERRED TO
ONLY AS "MR. LANDLORD," AND IT
CONTAINS LINES LIKE
"EFFERVESCENCE LIVED IN HER
EVERY CELLULAR EXPRESSION, AND
SHE HAD SPIZZERINCTUM TO SPARE."
IT IS DREADFUL.
SO PLEASE SAVE YOURSELF AND GO
TO My2020Census. gov RIGHT NOW.
AND IF YOU'VE ALREADY FILLED OUT
YOUR CENSUS, WHY NOT USE THE
TIME TO REGISTER TO VOTE?
YOU CAN FIND INFORMATION ON HOW
TO DO THAT RIGHT HERE.
AND IF YOU'VE ALREADY DONE BOTH
OF THOSE THINGS, RUN FROM THIS
SCREEN.
LIKE THE WIND.
THAT'S OUR SHOW, THANKS SO MUCH
FOR WATCHING, SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
TAKE IT AWAY, BOB.
THE AMERICA BOB DROVE FROM
WOOD BUTTE TO NEW ORLEANS WAS
NOT THAT ONE OF THE WAR, NOT THE
ONE HE HAD KNOWN IN HIS EARLIEST
CROSS CONTINENTAL AUTOMOTIVE
EXCURSIONS, NOT THE ONE OF PAY
LATER GAS STATIONS, VINTAGE
DINERS, AND 2-LANE ROADS.
ONLY THE TRAINS REMAINED IN
TRIBUTE TO THAT SPIRIT REFUGE IN
A VANQUISHED BY MODERNITY'S
GRAVE AND THERE WERE A FEW...
EXPENSE IN SOLITUDE.
THE RATHER INTERSTATE
STRIP MALLS, RETAIL EMPORIUMS,
TRAFFIC, ROADWORK, AND
BOTTLENECKS.
AMERICA, IT SEEMED TO BOB, WAS
NO LONGER THAT BEAUTIFUL GIRL
WHO'D BIRTHED HIM.
BUT INSTEAD, THE GHOST OF A GIRL
HE'D NEVER KNOWN.
DRIVING AT NIGHT THROUGH THE
INTERMITTENT EXPENSES CAN BOB
SOMETIMES SEE THE DISTANT AMBER
LIGHTS OF ISOLATED COMPOUNDS.
PERHAPS PRISONS.
PERHAPS CASINOS.
IN EITHER CASE, SOMEBODY WAS IN
THERE LOSING.
IT SEEMED MANY OF THE TOWNS WERE
BUILT EITHER ON THE BACK OF
VO-TECHS OR ON THE JOB SECURITY
OFFERED BY VARIOUS STATES'
CORRECTIONS DEPARTMENTS.
AT ONE DINERS STOP IN
SAN ANTONIO, BOB SAT AT A
COUNTER WHERE HE WAS DRAWN INTO
CONVERSATION BY A GRIM
SEPTUAGENARIAN TRAVELER.
BOB IMPULSIVELY ASKED.
"WHAT'S WITH ALL THE INCEST IN
YOUR AREA."
HE STEPPED UP AND ANSWERED BOB'S
QUESTION QUIETLY.
"JUST FOLKS GETTING BY."
Subtitles >>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org