HI THERE.
WELCOME TO THE SHOW.
STILL TAKING PLACE IN THIS BLANK
VOID, MADE POSSIBLE THANKS TO
MILK.
JUST USE THE CODE "SLURP SLURP
JOHN OLLY'S COW JUICE" AT YOUR
LOCAL CHECKOUT THE NEXT TIME
YOU PURCHASE MILK.
YOU WON'T RECEIVE A DISCOUNT,
BUT YOU WILL RECEIVE MILK.
AND LOOK, IT'S BEEN ANOTHER
BUSY WEEK, FROM COVID CASES
SPIKING IN THE U.S.,
TO BRAZILIAN POLICE ALLEGEDLY
CATCHING A SENATOR THERE WITH
CASH BETWEEN HIS BUTT CHEEKS,
TO CONFIRMATION HEARINGS FOR
AMY CONEY BARRETT.
THEY INCLUDED TWO FULL DAYS OF
QUESTIONS AND NON-ANSWERS, BEST
SUMMED UP BY THIS EXCHANGE.
YOU KNOW, MOST OF US HAVE
MULTIPLE NOTEBOOKS AND NOTES
AND BOOKS AND THINGS LIKE THAT
IN FRONT OF US.
CAN YOU HOLD UP WHAT YOU'VE BEEN
REFERRING TO IN ANSWERING OUR
QUESTIONS?
IS THERE ANYTHING ON IT?
THE LETTERHEAD THAT SAYS
"UNITED STATES SENATE."
THAT'S IMPRESSIVE.
EXCEPT, NO, IT ISN'T.
IT'S REALLY NOT IMPRESSIVE AT
ALL.
PARTLY BECAUSE IT'S EMBLEMATIC
OF THE FACT SHE DODGED ALMOST
EVERYTHING SHE WAS ASKED,
AND PARTLY BECAUSE THIS WHOLE
HEARING WAS PRE-ORDAINED
BY THE REPUBLICANS.
THAT PAD COULD'VE CONTAINED
A DRAWING OF A MUSCULAR,
ANATOMICALLY-CORRECT GARFIELD,
AND THEY'D STILL HAVE ALL SAID,
"THAT'S VERY IMPRESSIVE.
IT'S A YES FROM ME."
BUT ALTHOUGH BARRETT WAS
EVASIVE, THERE WERE STILL
TELLING MOMENTS, LIKE HER
REFUSING TO SAY SHE ACCEPTS
CLIMATE CHANGE AS A SCIENTIFIC
FACT, ARGUING THAT ROE V. WADE
IS NOT A "SUPER-PRECEDENT,"
AND REFERRING TO GAY PEOPLE AS
HAVING A "SEXUAL PREFERENCE,"
RATHER THAN ORIENTATION.
WHICH IS JUST RIDICULOUS,
BECAUSE IT'S CLEARLY NOT A
PREFERENCE.
NO ONE JUST CHOOSES TO BE
ATTRACTED TO THE SAME SEX,
OR A DIFFERENT SEX,
OR TO ADAM DRIVER.
WE ALL SIMPLY ARE.
DISLOCATE MY ANKLES,
YOU RUSTY CELLO.
TIE MY FINGERS IN A SQUARE KNOT,
YOU EMOTIONALLY-UNAVAILABLE
WATER TOWER.
AND THE SUPREME COURT HEARINGS
WEREN'T THE ONLY
QUESTION-AND-ANSWER SESSIONS
THIS WEEK.
TRUMP AND BIDEN HELD DUELING
TOWN HALLS ON THURSDAY.
ORIGINALLY, IT WAS SUPPOSED TO
BE A DEBATE BETWEEN THE TWO,
BUT AFTER TRUMP PULLED OUT,
NBC REWARDED HIM WITH AN HOUR
OF TV ALL TO HIMSELF, SOMETHING
WHICH IS, IF NOTHING ELSE,
VERY MUCH ON-BRAND FOR THEM.
AND TRUMP'S HIGH POINT OF
THE NIGHT WAS PROBABLY THIS.
I HAVE TO SAY, YOU HAVE
A GREAT SMILE.
THANK YOU.
HE DOES.
YOU'RE SO HANDSOME
WHEN YOU SMILE.
IS HE?
IS HE REALLY?
I'M NOT QUITE SO SURE ABOUT
THAT. UNLESS BY "HANDSOME,"
YOU MEAN "LOOKS LIKE SOMEONE
DROPPED THEIR DENTURES IN A
JACK-O-LANTERN ON
NOVEMBER 14TH," IN WHICH CASE,
YOU'RE ABSOLUTELY RIGHT.
THE MAN'S GOT A SMILE THAT CAN
LIGHT UP A CROSS.
ALTHOUGH AS HIGH POINTS WENT,
THAT WAS BASICALLY IT FOR
THE PRESIDENT.
EVEN THAT MOMENT TURNED FAST.
JUST WATCH WHAT HAPPENED
IMMEDIATELY AFTERWARDS.
YOU'RE SO HANDSOME WHEN YOU
SMILE.
AS THE DAUGHTER OF IMMIGRANTS TO
THE UNITED STATES WHO FLED
EASTERN EUROPE DUE TO RELIGIOUS
PERSECUTION, THE UNITED STATES
IMMIGRATION POLICIES ARE VERY
PERSONAL FOR ME.
IF YOU ARE ELECTED TO A SECOND
TERM, DO YOU EXPECT TO PURSUE
YOUR PREVIOUS EFFORTS TO CUT
THE DACA PROGRAM?
WOW.
THAT MIGHT ACTUALLY BE
THE PERFECT WAY TO ASK TRUMP
A QUESTION.
"YOU HAVE A LOVELY SMILE.
ANYWAY, YOU'D HAVE DOOMED
MY ANCESTORS TO DIE
IN THE HOLOCAUST.
WHY?"
TRUMP'S TOWN HALL, LIKE HIS
ENTIRE CAMPAIGN, WAS EXTREMELY
LIGHT ON POLICY DETAILS.
BECAUSE HE DOESN'T LIKE TO TALK
IN SPECIFICS ABOUT WHAT A SECOND
TRUMP TERM WOULD MEAN.
HE'S MADE VERY FEW CONCRETE
PROMISES, OTHER THAN, "I WILL
NOT LEAVE, I WILL NOT DIE,"
AND, "I WILL GIVE YOU COVID
PERSONALLY."
BUT TONIGHT, I'D LIKE TO TALK
ABOUT SOMETHING INCREDIBLY
IMPORTANT THAT HINGES
ON THIS ELECTION.
BECAUSE OUR MAIN STORY CONCERNS
THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION,
OR W.H.O.
YOU MAY ALREADY BE AWARE OF IT
IN ITS ROLE AS ONE OF THE
PRESIDENT'S FAVORITE PUNCHING
BAGS.
THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION
SHOULD BE ASHAMED OF
THEMSELVES.
I'M NOT HAPPY WITH
THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION.
THEY'RE A PUPPET OF CHINA.
THEY'RE CHINA-CENTRIC,
TO PUT IT NICER.
THEY'RE LITERALLY A PIPE
ORGAN FOR CHINA.
THAT'S THE WAY I VIEW IT.
OKAY, THE W.H.O. IS
NOT LITERALLY A PIPE ORGAN FOR
CHINA, BECAUSE THE ONLY THING
THAT IS LITERALLY A PIPE ORGAN
FOR CHINA IS A PIPE ORGAN.
BECAUSE THAT'S WHAT THE WORD
"LITERALLY" MEANS.
OVER THE LAST SIX MONTHS,
TRUMP HAS CONSISTENTLY TRIED TO
DEFLECT BLAME FOR HIS HANDLING
OF THE CORONAVIRUS ONTO THE
W.H.O., CHINA, AND THE CLOSE
RELATIONSHIP HE CLAIMS
THE TWO HAVE.
AND AT THE BEGINNING OF JULY,
HE TURNED THAT CRITICISM INTO
REAL ACTION.
IN THE MIDST OF A PANDEMIC,
DONALD TRUMP IS FORMALLY PULLING
OUT OF THE WORLD HEALTH
ORGANIZATION.
WE WILL BE TODAY TERMINATING
OUR RELATIONSHIP WITH THE WORLD
HEALTH ORGANIZATION AND
REDIRECTING THOSE FUNDS TO OTHER
WORLDWIDE AND DESERVING URGENT
GLOBAL PUBLIC HEALTH NEEDS.
NOW, THAT IS VERY BAD
NEWS, BUT DO SPARE A THOUGHT
FOR MELANIA, WHO MUST'VE HEARD
THE SENTENCE, "WE WILL BE TODAY
TERMINATING OUR RELATIONSHIP,"
AND, FOR THE BRIEFEST OF
MOMENTS, FELT HOPE.
EXCEPT, I'M TOTALLY KIDDING,
SPARE NO THOUGHTS FOR HER...
SHE'S NOT A BABY.
SHE'S TOTALLY COMPLICIT,
AND NEVER FORGET THAT SHE ONCE
SAID, "WHO GIVES A FUCK ABOUT
CHRISTMAS STUFF AND
DECORATIONS?," AN ATTITUDE
FULLY PRESENT IN HER HOLIDAY
THEME, BEST DESCRIBED AS,
"WHAT IF TREES GOT PERIODS
AND HATED YOU?"
THE POINT IS, IN THE MIDST OF
EVERYTHING WE'RE GOING THROUGH
RIGHT NOW, TRUMP HAS DECIDED TO
WITHDRAW THE UNITED STATES FROM
THE W.H.O.
AND IF YOU'RE THINKING, "SURELY,
HE CAN'T DO THAT, RIGHT?"
THE GOOD NEWS IS, THE W.H.O.'S
CONSTITUTION DOESN'T INCLUDE ANY
PROVISIONS FOR MEMBERS TO
WITHDRAW.
THE BAD NEWS IS, THERE IS
EXACTLY ONE EXCEPTION TO THAT
RULE AND IF THE UNITED STATES,
WHICH PASSED A RESOLUTION
DECADES AGO SPECIFYING WE
ACTUALLY CAN WITHDRAW AFTER
GIVING ONE YEAR'S NOTICE.
AND THAT'S A PRETTY WEIRD PERK
FOR AMERICA ALONE TO HAVE.
IT'S LIKE FINDING OUT WE
DEMANDED TO BE THE ONLY COUNTRY
ALLOWED TO WAX THE PUBES OF
EVERY SQUIRREL.
WHY WOULD WE WANT THE RIGHT TO
DO THAT IN THE FIRST PLACE?
AND MORE TO THE POINT,
WHY WOULD WE EVER CONSIDER
ACTUALLY DOING IT?
AND THE THING IS, TRUMP IS NOT
BLUFFING.
HE'S ALREADY SUBMITTED A NOTICE
OF WITHDRAWAL TO THE U.N.
TO TAKE EFFECT NEXT JULY,
SO THE CLOCK IS TICKING.
AND GIVEN THAT WE'RE NOW ON
TRACK TO LEAVE THE W.H.O. IN
LESS THAN A YEAR, TONIGHT, LET'S
TALK ABOUT WHAT THAT ACTUALLY
MEANS... HOW IMPORTANT THE
W.H.O.'S WORK IS, HOW VALID
CRITICISMS OF IT ARE, AND WHAT
WE MIGHT BE PUTTING AT STAKE.
AND LET'S START WITH WHAT
THE W.H.O. DOES.
IT WAS FOUNDED IN 1948 AND HAS
SINCE GROWN TO 194 MEMBER STATES
...THAT'S NEARLY EVERY COUNTRY
ON EARTH.
AND VERY BROADLY, IT COORDINATES
GLOBAL RESPONSES TO A WIDE RANGE
OF HEALTH ISSUES, INCLUDING
ALERTING THE WORLD TO THREATS,
FIGHTING DISEASES, DEVELOPING
POLICY, AND IMPROVING ACCESS TO
CARE.
ONE OF THE BIGGEST POWERS IT HAS
IS THE ABILITY TO DECLARE
A PUBLIC HEALTH EMERGENCY OF
INTERNATIONAL CONCERN AND ISSUE
RECOMMENDATIONS ON HOW COUNTRIES
SHOULD RESPOND.
BUT... AND THIS IS REALLY
IMPORTANT... IT HAS ABSOLUTELY
NO POWER ON ITS OWN TO ENFORCE
THOSE RECOMMENDATIONS.
IT CAN ONLY ACT WITHIN A COUNTRY
TO THE EXTENT THAT COUNTRY
ALLOWS IT TO.
AND YET, DESPITE THOSE
SIGNIFICANT LIMITATIONS,
IT'S MANAGED TO DO SOME
INCREDIBLE THINGS IN THE PAST,
WITH PERHAPS ITS MOST NOTABLE
SUCCESS BEING THIS.
TODAY, A SUBSTANTIAL
MILESTONE IN HUMAN HISTORY.
THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION
SAYS SMALLPOX HAS NOW BEEN WIPED
OFF THE FACE OF THE EARTH AND
WILL NEVER RETURN.
IT SAYS IT'LL NEVER RETURN
BECAUSE SMALLPOX CAN ONLY BE
CAUGHT FROM ANOTHER PERSON,
AND IF NO OTHER PERSON HAS IT,
THERE IS NO OTHER WAY TO CATCH
IT.
IT'S TRUE.
THE W.H.O. COMPLETELY ERADICATED
SMALLPOX, WHICH KILLED
300 MILLION PEOPLE
IN THE 20TH CENTURY ALONE.
IN THE SPACE OF A DECADE,
IT TOOK SMALLPOX FROM 10 MILLION
CASES AND 2 MILLION DEATHS A
YEAR ALL THE WAY DOWN TO ZERO.
AND IT'S AMAZING THAT SOMETHING
CAN GO FROM BEING THAT
WIDESPREAD TO COMPLETELY
DISAPPEARING WITHIN A FEW YEARS.
SMALLPOX IS BASICALLY THE
CIRCUIT CITY OF INFECTIOUS
DISEASES.
AND IT'S EQUALLY AS MISSED.
AND IT'S NOT LIKE THE W.H.O. DID
THIS WITH A MAGIC WAND; IT TOOK
A HUGE AMOUNT OF WORK.
NOT ONLY DID THEY HAVE TO
ARRANGE A COLLABORATION BETWEEN
AMERICA AND THE U.S.S.R., AT THE
HEIGHT OF THE COLD WAR, ONE OF
THE LAST BIG COUNTRIES WHERE
SMALLPOX HAD TO BE TACKLED WAS
INDIA, AND JUST LISTEN TO ONE OF
THE DOCTORS INVOLVED IN THE
EFFORT EXPLAIN WHAT IT TOOK.
TO ERADICATE SMALLPOX,
IT MEANT THAT WE WOULD HAVE
TO VISIT EVERY SINGLE HOUSE IN
INDIA.
AND ULTIMATELY, WE DID.
WE VISITED 120 MILLION HOUSES
IN INDIA EVERY MONTH FOR ABOUT
20 MONTHS.
WE DID MORE THAN A BILLION HOUSE
THINK ABOUT THAT!
THEY VISITED A BILLION HOUSES!
THAT'S REMARKABLE.
IT'S ONLY A FEW MORE HOUSES
THAN CHRISHELL VISITED ON
"SELLING SUNSET."
AND THAT'S WHY SHE'S THE BEST.
YOU POUND THE PAVEMENT.
YOU GET THE LISTINGS AND YOU GET
THE RESULTS.
I DON'T KNOW WHERE CHRISHELL
HUSTLES MORE,
ON THE STREETS OF L.A. OR ON
THE "DANCING WITH THE STARS"
DANCE FLOOR.
#TeamChrishell.
BUT THE W.H.O.'S WORK ISN'T
ALWAYS AS LOFTY AS DOOR-TO-DOOR
DISEASE DESTRUCTION.
SOME OF ITS MOST IMPORTANT WORK
INVOLVES THE DEVELOPMENT OF
THE SEASONAL FLU VACCINE.
TWICE A YEAR, IT CONVENES
REPRESENTATIVES FROM ALL OVER
THE WORLD TO DETERMINE WHAT
STRAINS OF THE FLU VIRUS SHOULD
GO INTO THE ANNUAL FLU SHOT.
WHICH MIGHT SOUND TEDIOUS...
BECAUSE IT IS... BUT IT'S ALSO
KIND OF IMPORTANT.
THAT, BY THE WAY, WAS THE
ORIGINAL TITLE FOR THIS SHOW.
THE W.H.O. IS ALSO CURRENTLY
TRACKING AND RESPONDING TO
DOZENS OF INFECTIOUS DISEASE
OUTBREAKS AROUND THE WORLD,
INCLUDING MONKEYPOX,
YELLOW FEVER, AND AN ONGOING
EBOLA OUTBREAK.
AND WHEN, LET'S SAY,
HYPOTHETICALLY, A PANDEMIC
BREAKS OUT, THE ORGANIZATION
CAN PROVIDE A CRITICAL ROLE
AS A CENTRAL CLEARINGHOUSE OF
INFORMATION, CONDUCTING
INVESTIGATIONS, AND RELEASING
INFORMATION TO THE PUBLIC.
AND IT DOES ALL OF THIS
ON A CURRENT BUDGET OF
$2.4 BILLION A YEAR.
WHICH MIGHT SOUND LIKE A LOT,
BUT IT'S AROUND THE SAME AMOUNT
IT COSTS TO RUN A SINGLE
U.S. HOSPITAL.
WHICH IS WILD.
IT'S LIKE FINDING OUT THAT THE
U.S. NAVY RUNS ON THE SAME
BUDGET AS TYPHOON LAGOON AT
DISNEY WORLD.
I'M NOT SURE IF TYPHOON LAGOON'S
BUDGET IS WAY TOO HIGH, OR THE
NAVY'S IS WAY TOO LOW, BUT
SOMETHING IS DEFINITELY OFF
THERE.
SO AT ITS BEST, THE W.H.O. DOES
VITALLY IMPORTANT WORK FOR
SHOCKINGLY LITTLE MONEY.
WHICH IS NOT TO SAY THAT IT'S
PERFECT.
THERE ARE LEGITIMATE CRITICISMS
OF HOW IT'S BEHAVED IN THE PAST,
AMONG THEM THAT DURING THE EBOLA
OUTBREAK IN 2014, THEY ACTED TOO
SLOWLY TO DECLARE A PUBLIC
HEALTH EMERGENCY, WHICH HAD
MAJOR CONSEQUENCES.
BUT THE TRUTH IS, FOR TRUMP,
PAST PERFORMANCE ISN'T REALLY
THE ISSUE HERE.
FOR HIM, THERE ARE TWO
INSURMOUNTABLE PROBLEMS
WITH THE W.H.O.
THE FIRST IS HOW MUCH OF ITS
BUDGET THE U.S. PAYS.
WE PAY $400 TO $500 MILLION
A YEAR.
CHINA'S PAYING $38, $39,
AND $40 MILLION A YEAR.
AND IT'S LIKE THEY CONTROL THIS
GROUP.
THERE'S SOMETHING VERY BAD
GOING ON. AND YOU KNOW WHAT?
I'VE GOTTEN VERY MUCH INVOLVED.
IT'S BEEN GOING ON FOR A LONG
PERIOD OF TIME, AND WE DON'T
WANT TO BE THE SUCKERS ANYMORE.
NOW, YOU'RE PROBABLY
ALREADY ASSUMING IT'S MORE
COMPLICATED THAN THAT.
AND IT IS.
THE PROBLEM IS, TRUMP IS
INCAPABLE OF ACKNOWLEDGING
NUANCE.
IN HIS WORLD, YOU'RE EITHER
FUCKING SOMEONE, OR YOU'RE
GETTING FUCKED.
AND THAT'S NOT A GREAT
PERSPECTIVE WHEN IT COMES TO
COOPERATING ON GLOBAL HEALTH.
IT'S NOT EVEN A GREAT
PERSPECTIVE AT AN ORGY.
SURE, THERE'S A LOT OF BOTH
GOING ON, BUT THOSE CAN'T BE
THE ONLY OPTIONS.
SOMEONE'S GOTTA MAKE SURE
EVERYONE'S STAYING HYDRATED,
SOMEONE'S GOTTA BE AVAILABLE
TO TIP THE PIZZA DELIVERY
PERSON, SOMEONE'S GOT TO
DISINFECT THE COFFEE TABLE
AFTERWARDS.
IT CAN'T ALL BE JUST FUCKING AND
GETTING FUCKED, OR THERE'S GOING
TO BE CHAOS.
THAT'S BASIC ORGY MANAGEMENT.
NOW WHAT IS TRUE IN TRUMP'S
ARGUMENT IS THAT THERE'S A BIG
DISCREPANCY BETWEEN WHAT
THE U.S. AND CHINA GIVE TO
THE W.H.O.
IN 2019, THE U.S. PAID JUST OVER
$446 MILLION.
AND CHINA, THE SECOND LARGEST
ECONOMY IN THE WORLD, PAID
JUST $43 MILLION.
THAT IS A STRIKING DISPARITY.
BUT IT'S ROOTED IN HOW
THE W.H.O. IS FUNDED.
BECAUSE THE FACT IS, ONLY AROUND
17% OF ITS FUNDING COMES THROUGH
ASSESSED CONTRIBUTIONS,
WHICH ARE BASICALLY MEMBERSHIP
DUES BASED ON THE SIZE OF EACH
COUNTRY'S ECONOMY AND
POPULATION.
ALMOST ALL OF THE REST COMES
THROUGH VOLUNTARY
CONTRIBUTIONS.
THAT'S WHERE A COUNTRY DONATES
MONEY, BUT IN DOING SO, CAN
EARMARK EXACTLY WHAT THEY WANT
IT USED FOR.
AND MOST OF WHAT THE U.S. PAYS
EACH YEAR IS VOLUNTARY
CONTRIBUTIONS, WHEREAS CHINA
CHOOSES TO PAY ALMOST NOTHING.
AND YOU COULD ARGUE THIS IS A
DUMB WAY TO FUND AN
ORGANIZATION; IT'S ESSENTIALLY
THE GLOBAL HEALTH EQUIVALENT OF
UNDERFUNDING A PUBLIC SCHOOL AND
EXPECTING IT TO HOLD A BAKE SALE
TO MAKE UP THE DIFFERENCE.
BUT THE THING IS, THIS WHOLE
MESS IS ALMOST ENTIRELY
AMERICA'S FAULT.
BACK IN THE 1980s,
THE REAGAN ADMINISTRATION PUSHED
A ZERO-GROWTH POLICY FOR
THE W.H.O.'S BUDGET, WHICH
EVENTUALLY FROZE STATES'
ASSESSED CONTRIBUTIONS AT
1990s LEVELS.
SO WITH THOSE CONTRIBUTIONS
UNABLE TO GO UP, THE W.H.O. HAS
NATURALLY NEEDED MORE AND MORE
VOLUNTARY DONATIONS
AS THE YEARS HAVE GONE BY.
AND I WOULD SAY THAT WAS THE
WORST DECISION OF THE REAGAN
WHITE HOUSE, WERE IT NOT FOR
IRAN-CONTRA, THE WAR ON DRUGS,
TRICKLE DOWN ECONOMICS, AND
FAILING TO PUBLICLY SAY
THE WORD "AIDS" FOR FOUR YEARS.
I'M NOT SAYING EVERYTHING IS
REAGAN'S FAULT, ALL I'M SAYING
IS, IF I FOUND OUT TOMORROW THAT
MURDER HORNETS ARE ONLY HERE
BECAUSE HE STARTED BREEDING THEM
IN 1988, I CAN'T SAY I'D BE
ENTIRELY SURPRISED.
THE POINT IS, THAT IS WHY WE PAY
SO MUCH RELATIVE TO CHINA.
IT'S MOSTLY BECAUSE WE CHOOSE
TO BECAUSE THE W.H.O. IS
UNDERFUNDED BECAUSE OF
SOMETHING WE DID.
SO WHAT ABOUT TRUMP'S SECOND BIG
COMPLAINT, THAT THE W.H.O. IS A
LITERAL PIPE ORGAN FOR CHINA?
WHICH, AGAIN, IT LITERALLY
ISN'T.
THAT IS AN IDEA THAT HE AND HIS
SUPPORTERS HAVE HAMMERED HARD.
THE WORLD HEALTH
ORGANIZATION'S SUBSERVIENCE TO
THEIR MASTERS IN BEIJING HAS
ONLY BECOME MORE OBVIOUSLY MORE
NAKED.
ALLOWING THE WORLD HEALTH
ORGANIZATION TO INVESTIGATE
CHINA IS LIKE HAVING EL CHAPO
INVESTIGATE THE MEXICAN DRUG
CARTELS.
I MEAN, CHINA LIED, THE WORLD
HEALTH ORGANIZATION COMPLIED,
AND AS A RESULT, MANY AMERICANS
DIED.
OKAY, NOW I KNOW THAT
RHYME SOUNDED COMPELLING,
BUT IT'S
IMPORTANT TO REMEMBER: NOT
EVERYTHING THAT RHYMES IS TRUE.
HERE, I'LL SHOW YOU.
"IN 1981 JAMES COMER WAS UP TO
NO GOOD, HE STOOD ON A BOAT AND
PUSHED AS HARD AS HE COULD, AND
THAT'S HOW JAMES COMER KILLED
NATALIE WOOD."
THAT'S A FANTASTIC RHYME,
NO QUESTIONS THERE.
BUT I DO HAVE TO ACCEPT THAT IT
MIGHT BE UNTRUE.
WHAT THEY'RE ARGUING THERE IS,
THE W.H.O. MISHANDLED THE
PANDEMIC BECAUSE THEY'RE
DEFERENTIAL TO CHINA.
AND WHILE THERE'S SOME TRUTH TO
EACH HALF OF THAT STATEMENT,
THEY'RE NOT TRUE TOGETHER.
AND LET'S START WITH THE
ALLEGATION THE W.H.O. IS
DEFERENTIAL TO CHINA.
THAT CAN BE TRUE.
FOR INSTANCE, ITS MEMBER STATES
HAVE CONSISTENTLY ACQUIESCED TO
CHINA'S INSISTENCE THAT TAIWAN
NOT BE ALLOWED TO JOIN THE
ORGANIZATION AS A SEPARATE
ENTITY.
AND W.H.O. LEADERSHIP PRAISED
CHINA EARLY IN THE PANDEMIC,
CITING ITS "BOLD APPROACH TO
CONTAIN THE RAPID SPREAD"
OF THE CORONAVIRUS, WHICH
DOES NOT DATE WELL.
ALTHOUGH, IT IS IMPORTANT TO
REMEMBER, THE W.H.O. NEEDS
TO BE EXCEEDINGLY DIPLOMATIC
WITH ITS MEMBER COUNTRIES TO
GAIN THE ACCESS IT NEEDS FOR
ON-THE-GROUND INVESTIGATIONS
AS AN OUTBREAK EMERGES.
ALSO, FOR WHAT IT'S WORTH,
IT'S NOT LIKE IT WAS ALONE IN
PRAISING CHINA'S CORONAVIRUS
RESPONSE.
BACK IN FEBRUARY, TRUMP WAS
WORKING OUT A TRADE DEAL WITH
CHINA, AND HE SAID THIS.
CHINA IS WORKING VERY, VERY
HARD.
I HAVE SPOKEN TO PRESIDENT XI,
AND THEY'RE WORKING VERY HARD.
IF YOU KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT HIM,
I THINK HE'LL BE IN PRETTY GOOD
SHAPE.
THEY'VE HAD A ROUGH PATCH, AND I
THINK RIGHT NOW THEY HAVE IT...
IT LOOKS LIKE THEY'RE GETTING IT
UNDER CONTROL MORE AND MORE.
OH OH, AND THAT WAS
BY NO MEANS A ONE OFF.
TRUMP PRAISED CHINA'S RESPONSE
SO MANY TIMES POLITICO MADE IT
INTO AN ACTUAL LISTICLE AND
THAT'S A SERIOUS UNIT OF
MEASUREMENT.
TRUMP'S JOINING THE RANKS OF
"15 HEDGEHOGS WITH THINGS THAT
LOOK LIKE HEDGEHOGS," OR
"TOP 10 ACTORS WHO DIED IN
FIRES, " OR " 16 PEOPLE WHO WERE
LITERAL CHILDREN IN 2010 BUT
FULL GROWN ADULTS NOW," WHICH I
ASSUME WAS WRITTEN BY SOMEONE
WHO JUST EMERGED FROM A COMA
AND FORGOT HOW TIME WORKS,
INCIDENTALLY MAKING THEM
ELIGIBLE FOR "TIME" MAGAZINE'S
VERY REAL LISTICLE,
"TOP 10 COMAS."
NOW, AS FOR THE QUESTION OF
WHETHER THE W.H.O. MADE MISTAKES
EARLY ON, IT DEFINITELY DID.
IT ARGUABLY TOOK TOO LONG TO
ADVISE UNIVERSAL MASK WEARING
AND TO CLEARLY ACKNOWLEDGE
THE THREAT OF INDOOR AIRBORNE
TRANSMISSION.
BUT THERE IS NO EVIDENCE AT ALL
THAT THIS WAS DONE TO APPEASE
CHINA, SO MUCH AS, IN THE EARLY
STAGES OF A PANDEMIC, EVEN
EXPERTS TEND TO... TO USE A
TECHNICAL TERM... NOT KNOW WHAT
THE FUCK IS GOING ON.
BUT LET'S SAY, FOR THE SAKE OF
ARGUMENT, THAT YOU AGREE WITH
THE PRESIDENT THAT WE SIMPLY PAY
TOO MUCH TO THE W.H.O., AND THAT
CHINA IS CALLING ALL THE SHOTS
THERE.
THE QUESTION THEN BECOMES, WHAT
THEN? AND IF YOU LISTEN TO
MIKE POMPEO, WHICH YOU
ABSOLUTELY NEVER SHOULD,
HE WOULD ARGUE THE U.S. CAN JUST
GO IT ALONE.
IF THERE IS A FUNCTION THAT
ONLY THE W.H.O. CAN DO, AND WE
THINK IT IS IMPORTANT FOR
AMERICAN NATIONAL SECURITY OR
BECAUSE WE ARE GOOD HUMANITARIAN
PARTNERS AROUND THE WORLD,
I'M CONFIDENT WE WILL FIND A WAY
TO DELIVER THAT OUTCOME.
OKAY, THAT IS JUST RIDICULOUS.
THE U.S. CANNOT DO WHAT THE
W.H.O. DOES, FOR MANY, MANY
REASONS.
FOR A START, IF WE TRY AND GO
INTO ANOTHER COUNTRY FOR A
PUBLIC HEALTH MISSION, CHANCES
ARE WE'RE GOING TO GET GREETED
FAR LESS WARMLY.
BECAUSE THE W.H.O. HAS NEVER,
Y'KNOW, INVADED A NATION OR
FUNDED A COUP.
AS ONE FORMER U.S.
REPRESENTATIVE TO THE
ORGANIZATION HAS SAID, "PEOPLE
COMING INTO COUNTRIES IN W.H.O.
SHIRTS TO WORK ON POLIO OR AIDS
ARE LESS THREATENING."
ADDING, "NO ONE IS LOOKING FOR
U.S.-BASED ALTERNATIVES TO
W.H.O."
WHICH, OF COURSE THEY'RE NOT...
ESPECIALLY HAVING SEEN THE WAY
THAT WE'VE HANDLED THE
CORONAVIRUS.
NOBODY WANTS A U.S.-BASED
ALTERNATIVE HERE FOR THE SAME
REASON NOBODY'S LOOKING FOR A
JOE EXOTIC-BASED ALTERNATIVE TO
"JEOPARDY."
I'M NOT SAYING HE DOESN'T THINK
HE CAN DO IT.
BUT EVERYONE LIKES THE WAY IT
WORKS NOW, AND HIS ALTERNATIVE
MIGHT BE ACTIVELY DANGEROUS.
ALSO, WHEN IT COMES TO GLOBAL
HEALTH, THE U.S. HAS A CHECKERED
PAST.
BEFORE THE KILLING OF BIN LADEN,
ONE OF THE WAYS THE U.S.
VERIFIED HE WAS IN ABBOTABAD WAS
BY STAGING A FAKE VACCINATION
CAMPAIGN IN THAT TOWN AS A RUSE
TO GATHER DNA SAMPLES FROM THE
PEOPLE LIVING AT HIS COMPOUND,
SOMETHING WHICH NOT ONLY PUT
HEALTH WORKERS IN THE REGION AT
RISK, BUT ALSO CONTRIBUTED TO A
MAJOR SETBACK IN THE EFFORT TO
VACCINATE PEOPLE IN PAKISTAN
AGAINST POLIO.
AND IT'S NOT LIKE WE'RE GOING TO
MAKE FRIENDS BY SUDDENLY WALKING
AWAY FROM THE W.H.O. AND CUTTING
OFF ITS FUNDING, ESPECIALLY IN
THE MIDDLE OF A GLOBAL PANDEMIC.
AS ONE OFFICIAL PUTS IT,
THE U.S. DECISION TO LEAVE IS
ALMOST IMPOSSIBLE TO GET YOUR
HEAD AROUND.
AND SOMETIMES IT FEELS
LIKE A BAD DREAM.
AND FOR STAFF INSIDE THE
ORGANIZATION, THEY FEEL
DUMBFOUNDED.
COULD SOMEBODY EXPLAIN TO ME
WHY?
REALLY, WHY?
WHY TAKE THE FIRE ENGINES AWAY
IN THE MIDDLE OF FIGHTING A
FIRE?
EXACTLY!
IT'S TAKING THE FIRE ENGINES
AWAY IN THE MIDDLE OF FIGHTING
THE FIRE, OR GETTING RID OF
THE LIFEBOATS WHILE THE BOAT IS
SINKING, OR CHOOSING TO EDIT
KEVIN SPACEY INTO A MOVIE JUST
WEEKS BEFORE ITS RELEASE DATE...
IT'S THE WORST POSSIBLE DECISION
AT THE WORST POSSIBLE TIME.
AND IT GETS EVEN WORSE HERE,
BECAUSE THE W.H.O. IS RIGHT
ON THE EDGE OF DOING TO POLIO
WHAT IT DID TO SMALLPOX AND
ELIMINATING IT.
JUST TWO MONTHS AGO, IT WAS
FINALLY WIPED OUT IN AFRICA,
AND WE ARE NOW 99% OF THE
WAY TO GLOBAL ERADICATION,
WITH A CURRENT GOAL FOR IT
TO HAPPEN IN 2023.
UNFORTUNATELY, THE U.S. IS
THE SECOND LARGEST FUNDER OF
THE GLOBAL POLIO ERADICATION
INITIATIVE, AND THAT MONEY
SUDDENLY DISAPPEARING IS LIKELY
TO SET EVERYTHING BACK.
AND WHILE IT ALMOST FEELS
INAPPROPRIATE FOR POLIO NOT TO
MAKE A COMEBACK DURING THIS
FUCKING NIGHTMARE OF A YEAR,
WE SHOULD STILL PROBABLY TRY TO
PREVENT THAT FROM HAPPENING.
AND LOOK, IT IS FINE IF THE U.S.
HAS PROBLEMS WITH THE W.H.O.
IT HAS PROBLEMS.
BUT THE SOLUTION CLEARLY ISN'T
TO WALK AWAY.
IT'S TO TRY AND FIX THEM.
BUT THE ONLY WAY FOR THE U.S. TO
HAVE A SAY IN HOW THAT HAPPENS
IS TO HAVE A SEAT AT THE TABLE,
AND WE'RE ABOUT TO JUST GIVE
THAT UP.
AND THE THING IS,
THIS IS YET ANOTHER
DEPRESSING EXAMPLE OF TRUMP
SEEING SOMETHING THAT INVOLVES
SHARED SACRIFICE, TRADE-OFFS,
AND COMPLEXITY, AND DECIDING TO
JUST BLOW IT UP, BECAUSE HE
EITHER DOESN'T UNDERSTAND IT,
DOESN'T CARE, OR BOTH.
WE'VE SEEN THIS WITH
THE PARIS CLIMATE AGREEMENT AND
THE IRAN NUCLEAR DEAL.
AND NOW HE'S DOING IT WITH
THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION.
AND THIS IS INCREDIBLY
DANGEROUS.
BECAUSE THE FACT IS, WE'RE
CURRENTLY ON TRACK TO LEAVE THE
W.H.O. ON JULY 6th OF NEXT YEAR
IF, THAT IS, TRUMP IS
RE-ELECTED.
AND THIS MEANS OUR MEMBERSHIP
IN THE W.H.O. IS YET ANOTHER
IMPORTANT THING ON THE BALLOT
THIS YEAR.
AND EVEN THOUGH TRUMP LIKES
TO PRETEND WE CAN INSULATE
OURSELVES FROM THE REST OF
THE WORLD, IF THE CORONAVIRUS
HAS SHOWN US ANYTHING,
IT'S THAT DISEASES DON'T
RECOGNIZE BORDERS, AND WE'RE
ONLY AS STRONG AS OUR
WORST-PREPARED COUNTRY.
AND PULLING OUT OF THE W.H.O. AT
ANY TIME, BUT ESPECIALLY IN THE
MIDST OF A PANDEMIC THAT'S
KILLED OVER 200,000 AMERICANS
AND A MILLION PEOPLE AROUND
THE WORLD IS ONE OF THE MOST
ILL-ADVISED, DUMBEST THINGS WE
COULD POSSIBLY DO.
AND I MEAN THAT FUCKING
LITERALLY. AND NOW THIS.
AND NOW...
THERE'S AN OLD SAYING IN
POLITICS.
POLITICS, WHICH IS, YOU'VE GOT
TO DANCE WITH THE GIRL THAT
BRUNG YOU.
THERE'S A SAYING IN POLITICS
THAT FISH ALWAYS FLOP AROUND
BEFORE THEY DIE.
OLIVIA, THERE'S A SAYING IN
PRESIDENTIAL POLITICS THAT
SUMMER IS FOR DATING, FALL IS
FOR MATING.
THERE IS AN OLD SAYING IN
POLITICS, WHEN YOU ARE WHINING,
YOU ARE NOT WINNING.
THERE'S AN OLD SAYING IN
TEXAS POLITICS THAT THE GUILTY
DOG BARKS THE LOUDEST.
WE HAVE A SAYING ON OUR
CAMPAIGN, FEAR THE TURTLE.
AS THE SAYING GOES, THERE'S
NOTHING IN THE MIDDLE OF THE
ROAD BUT YELLOW LINES AND
DEAD ARMADILLOS.
THERE IS NOTHING IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE ROAD BUT
YELLOW LINES AND
DEAD ARMADILLOS.
THEY SAY YELLOW LINES AND
DEAD ARMADILLOS IN THE MIDDLE
OF THE ROAD.
YOU WON UP AND DOWN.
WHAT?
MOVING ON.
A QUICK UPDATE
REGARDING DANBURY, CONNECTICUT.
DUBBED AMERICA'S "HAT CITY"
BY "MEANINGLESS BYGONE
SUPERLATIVES" MAGAZINE.
YOU MAY REMEMBER, A FEW MONTHS
AGO, WE INSULTED THE UNASSUMING
CITY OF DANBURY FOR NO CLEAR
REASON.
AND THE CITIZENS THERE
RESPONDED, WITH MULTIPLE
DANBURIANS INSULTING ME IN
YOUTUBE VIDEOS, AND THE MAYOR
DECLARING THAT HE'D NAME THEIR
SEWAGE PLANT "THE JOHN OLIVER
MEMORIAL SEWER PLANT" BECAUSE
IT'S FULL OF SHIT JUST LIKE ME.
ALL OF WHICH WAS EXCELLENT.
DISAPPOINTINGLY, THE MAYOR THEN
CLAIMED HIS THREAT WAS JUST
A JOKE.
SO TO TRY TO FORCE HIS HAND,
WE OFFERED TO DONATE $55,000 TO
LOCAL CHARITIES ON THE STRICT
CONDITION THEY MADE THE NAME
OFFICIAL.
WELL, THERE HAS BEEN A BIT OF
AN UPDATE.
A CHEEKY BACK AND FORTH
BETWEEN THE CITY OF DANBURY AND
POPULAR SHOW HOST JOHN OLIVER
MAKING A STINK IN THIS CITY.
TONIGHT, IT WAS FRONT AND
CENTER AT THE CITY'S VIRTUAL
COUNCIL MEETING.
THE MAYOR READING SUPPORTIVE
COMMENTS FROM RESIDENTS.
THE COMMUNITY SPIRIT THIS
FEUD HAS GENERATED IS
PRICELESS.
A VOTE GOT PUSHED TO THURSDAY
BUT THE MAYOR TOLD US THE VOTES
ARE THERE.
HE BELIEVES THE FEUD IS CREATING
ANOTHER TOURIST DESTINATION IN
THE STATE.
I'VE GOT SMALL BLEACHERS SET
UP OUTSIDE THE PONDS THAT HOLD
ALL OF THE SOLID WASTE AND YOU
CAN SIT ON YOUR BLEACHER, HAVE
YOUR PICNIC, AND WATCH THE PLANT
OPERATE.
AND IT'LL BE VERY, VERY
EXCITING.
THERE IS A LOT TO LOVE
THERE.
FROM TO THE TOWN'S SEEMING
ENTHUSIASM, TO THE FACT THAT
THE MAYOR SEEMS TO THINK
WATCHING WATER FILTRATION IS
A MUST-SEE THRILL RIDE.
NO ONE ENJOYS SITTING IN
BLEACHERS WATCHING RAW SEWAGE
MOVE AROUND.
JUST ASK ANY FAN OF
THE NEW YORK GIANTS.
IT'S BEEN A ROUGH FEW SEASONS.
BUT THE FACT IS, THINGS HAVE
ESCALATED HERE.
LOCAL BUSINESSES STARTED
A FUNDRAISER SUPPORTING THE
EFFORT, AND HAVE SO FAR RAISED
$45,000 FOR AREA FOOD BANKS.
DANBURY'S LOCAL HOCKEY TEAM HAS
BEEN SELLING SPECIAL HAT TRICKS
T-SHIRTS BENEFITING ALS
CONNECTICUT WITH THE NAME OF
THE CHARACTER I PLAYED IN 2008'S
"THE LOVE GURU."
AND MAYOR MARK IS EVEN OFFERING
TO GIVE PERSONAL TOURS OF THE
SEWER PLANT FOR $500 APIECE...
AGAIN, ALL FOR CHARITY.
IT'S ALL BEEN GOING VERY WELL.
BUT YOU MIGHT HAVE HEARD THERE,
THE VOTE WAS POSTPONED UNTIL
LAST THURSDAY, WHICH IS HOW I
FOUND MYSELF AT HOME, WATCHING
DANBURY CITY COUNCIL MEETINGS ON
ZOOM WITH BATED BREATH.
AND I WILL SAY, SOME MEMBERS
EXPRESSED CONCERNS.
WHILE I APPRECIATE THE HUMOR
DURING A TIME WHEN WE COULD ALL
USE A LAUGH, I'D HAVE TO SAY
THAT I PERSONALLY DON'T FIND
ANYTHING FUNNY ABOUT INSULTING
OUR COMMUNITY, AND LEAST OF ALL,
ABOUT THREATENING VIOLENCE
TOWARDS CHILDREN.
I'M JUST GONNA BE VOTING NO.
YOU KNOW WHAT?
THAT'S FAIR.
I DID INVITE ALL DANBURIANS
TO COME GET A THRASHING FROM ME,
CHILDREN INCLUDED.
ALTHOUGH IN MY DEFENSE, I'M
CLEARLY NO THREAT TO ANYBODY.
I HAVE THE PHYSICAL PRESENCE OF
AL DENTE SPAGHETTI.
IF I WAS WAS A BOXER, MY WEIGHT
CLASS WOULD BE "NOT DETECTED,"
AND MY ENTRANCE MUSIC WOULD BE
NORMA JEAN'S "PLEASE DON'T
HURT ME." I AM FRAGILE.
AND THAT MAN WAS NOT THE ONLY
ONE WITH QUALMS.
I'M REALLY PROUD OF OUR
WASTE TREATMENT PLANT.
ONE OF THE FIRST THINGS I DID
YEARS AGO WHEN I GOT ON THE
COUNCIL, ALONG WITH
COUNCILMAN CHIANESE,
IS ORGANIZE A TOUR,
AND WE TOOK A TOUR OF THE PLANT.
AND I WAS AGOG.
I THOUGHT IT WAS, LIKE, THIS
AMAZING MACHINE THAT TURNS,
YOU KNOW, STUFF YOU DON'T REALLY
WANT ON THE BOTTOM OF YOUR SHOE
INTO SOMETHING THAT YOU CAN
DRINK OR ALMOST DRINK.
SO I, YOU KNOW, WHEN I HEARD WE
WERE NAMING THAT MACHINE THAT'S
INTEGRAL TO THE COMMUNITY AFTER
THIS GUY, I... NO WAY.
GOD, I LOVE
CITY COUNCIL MEETINGS.
WHERE ELSE CAN YOU HEAR SOMEONE
TALK ABOUT THE TIME THEY WERE
STRUCK SPEECHLESS BY
THE SHEER BEAUTY OF
MUNICIPAL WASTE FILTRATION?
ALTHOUGH HE DOES GLOSS PRETTY
QUICKLY OVER THE DIFFERENCE
BETWEEN "WATER YOU CAN DRINK"
AND "WATER YOU CAN ALMOST
DRINK."
YOU CAN ALMOST DRINK A LOT OF
THINGS!
MERCURY, ANTIFREEZE,
MOUNTAIN DEW.
"ALMOST" CAN DO A LOT OF
HEAVY LIFTING.
ALTHOUGH, I AM HAPPY TO SAY
THAT MAN EVENTUALLY VOTED YES,
ALTHOUGH IN DOING SO, SAID HE
HOPED I'D "COME TO TERMS WITH
THE STATEMENTS I MADE
TOWARDS DANBURY."
WHICH I ABSOLUTELY HAVE, AND I
REGRET NOTHING.
BUT LOOK, THE MEETING CULMINATED
IN A NAIL-BITING ROLL-CALL VOTE,
AFTER WHICH, THE RESULTS CAME
IN.
WE HAVE 18 YESES,
ONE ABSTENTION, AND ONE NAY.
CONGRATULATIONS, MR. OLIVER!
YOU NOW HAVE A POOP PLANT NAMED
AFTER YOU. WHOO!
YES!
THAT IS AMAZING.
AND HONESTLY, I DO BELIEVE THAT
I WAS THEIR BEST OPTION.
WHO ELSE WERE THEY GONNA NAME IT
AFTER?
NEIL CAVUTO?
YEAH, HE'S TECHNICALLY FROM
BUT HE ALREADY HAS A SHIT
DANBURY.
FACTORY NAMED AFTER HIM, AND
IT'S CALLED "YOUR WORLD WITH
NEIL CAVUTO."
SO THE RESOLUTION PASSED,
ALTHOUGH THE MAYOR DID HAVE ONE
THAT THEY WOULD MAKE
IT OFFICIAL "ONLY IF THE
COMEDIAN IS PHYSICALLY PRESENT
WHEN THE RIBBON IS CUT."
WHICH, HONESTLY, IS A PRETTY BIG
ASK, BECAUSE DANBURY IS AN
HOUR-AND-A-HALF DRIVE FROM
NEW YORK CITY.
AND THE REASON I KNOW THAT IS
FOR THE FIRST TIME SINCE
WE ENTERED THIS VOID, I LEFT.
AND THIS IS WHAT HAPPENED.
YES, I WENT TO
DANBURY, HOME OF THE
DANBURY RAILWAY MUSEUM, THE
SELF-PROCLAIMED WORLD'S TALLEST
UNCLE SAM, AND NOW, THE SINGLE
GREATEST SEWAGE PLANT IN THE
CONTINENTAL UNITED STATES.
IT WAS EVEN MORE BEAUTIFUL THAN
I'D IMAGINED.
I'D TAKEN ALL NECESSARY
PRECAUTIONS.
NOT JUST BECAUSE OF THE
PANDEMIC, BUT BECAUSE I WAS IN
DANBURY, CONNECTICUT.
MY HEART POUNDED AS I PREPARED
TO MEET MY DESTINY, AND TO A
LESSER EXTENT, MAYOR BOUGHTON.
MR. OLIVER, WELCOME TO THE
GREAT CITY OF DANBURY.
MAYOR MARK, IT IS A
PLEASURE TO BE HERE.
LET'S DO THIS.
ON BEHALF OF ALL THE CITIZENS
OF THE CITY OF DANBURY, WE ARE
PROUD AND HONORED TO NAME THIS
THE JOHN OLIVER MEMORIAL SEWER
PLANT.
YOU READY?
THREE, TWO...
ONE!
YES!
WE DID IT!
MR. MAYOR, IF IT'S OKAY, I WOULD
LOVE TO SAY A FEW WORDS.
ABSOLUTELY.
THERE IS A REASON
THAT THIS SEWER PLANT MEANS SO
MUCH TO ME, AND THAT IS THAT IT
REPRESENTS EVERYTHING THAT WE
NEED THE MOST RIGHT NOW, BECAUSE
THINK ABOUT IT.
THIS PLACE TAKES THE WORST THAT
HUMANITY CAN PRODUCE AND
TRANSFORMS IT INTO SOMETHING
THAT WE CAN LIVE WITH,
AND NOW MORE THAN EVER, THERE IS
SOMETHING INSPIRATIONAL IN THAT.
BECAUSE AT THE END OF THIS
AWFUL, AWFUL YEAR, WHAT COULD BE
MORE IMPORTANT THAN EVIDENCE
THAT IF WE WANT TO,
WE CAN COME TOGETHER, OVERCOME
OUR DIFFERENCES, AND SORT OUR
SHIT OUT?
MR. MAYOR, I COULD NOT BE MORE
PROUD TO HAVE MY NAME ON YOUR
SHIT SORTER.
THANK YOU, DANBURY!
YOU DIDN'T DANBURY THIS UP.
NONE OF YOU ARE DANBURYING THIS
UP.
THAT'S OUR SHOW!
THANK YOU SO MUCH FOR WATCHING!
WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT WEEK!
GOOD NIGHT!
YES!
IT'S HISTORY!
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org