John: HI THERE!
WELCOME TO THE SHOW, STILL
TAKING PLACE IN THIS BLANK VOID,
WHICH MAKES ME LOOK LIKE I'M
IN ONE OF THOSE OLD E-HARMONY
COMMERCIALS, BUT FEATURING
THE CUSTOMERS WHO DIDN'T
FIND LOVE.
AND IT'S BEEN A VERY BUSY WEEK,
DOMINATED BY THE PRESIDENTIAL
CAMPAIGN.
TRUMP HELD MULTIPLE RALLIES
THIS WEEK, INCLUDING ONE IN
ERIE, PENNSYLVANIA, WHERE HE
GAVE A SURPRISINGLY HONEST
SPEECH.
BEFORE THE PLAGUE CAME IN,
I HAD IT MADE.
I WASN'T COMING TO ERIE.
I MEAN, I HAVE TO BE HONEST,
THERE'S NO WAY I WAS COMING.
I DIDN'T HAVE TO.
I WOULD HAVE CALLED YOU AND
SAID, "HEY ERIE, YOU KNOW, IF
YOU HAVE A CHANCE, GET OUT AND
VOTE."
WE HAD THIS THING WON.
John: WOW.
BOLD MOVE THERE TO NEG
A SWING STATE.
BUT I GUESS WE ALL HAD GRAND
DESIGNS FOR THIS YEAR "BEFORE
THE PLAGUE CAME IN."
TRUMP WAS GOING TO CONTINUE
IGNORING ERIE LIKE A PHONE CALL
FROM ONE OF HIS CHILDREN.
LOTS OF PEOPLE WERE GOING TO
SPEND HOLIDAYS WITH THEIR
STILL-ALIVE GRANDPARENTS.
AND I WAS GOING TO CONTINUE MY
43-YEAR STREAK OF NEVER ONCE
SETTING FOOT IN DANBURY,
CONNECTICUT.
IT SEEMS TIME MAKES FOOLS OF ALL
OF US.
BUT YOU CAN SEE WHY
THE PRESIDENT MIGHT BE FEELING
NERVOUS.
THIS MONTH HAS BROUGHT ENOUGH
OCTOBER SURPRISES FOR HIM TO
RENDER THAT TERM COMPLETELY
MEANINGLESS... FROM CONTRACTING
COVID, TO THE MULTIPLE DAMNING
STORIES ABOUT HIS TAX RECORDS,
INCLUDING THE REVELATION HE HAS
A PREVIOUSLY UNKNOWN BANK
ACCOUNT IN CHINA.
AND YET, FOR TRUMP SUPPORTERS,
IT SEEMS ALL OF THAT IS
COMPLETELY OFFSET BY THIS.
THE FBI DOES, IN FACT,
HAVE POSSESSION OF
HUNTER BIDEN'S LAPTOP.
EMAILS ALLEGEDLY FROM
HUNTER BIDEN'S
LAPTOP.
HUNTER BIDEN'S LAPTOP.
AND THEY FOUND THE LAPTOP.
YOU KNOW WHAT THEY CALL THAT?
THE LAPTOP FROM HELL.
John: YES, THE LAPTOP FROM
HELL.
NOT TO BE CONFUSED WITH
THE LAPTOP IN HELL,
WHICH I BELIEVE IS OWNED BY
JEFFREY TOOBIN.
I'M SO SORRY FOR EVERYTHING
THAT YOU'VE SEEN.
IF YOU'RE TRYING TO FIGURE OUT
WHAT THE FUCK THEY'RE TALKING
ABOUT THERE, IT REVOLVES AROUND
EMAILS AND TEXT MESSAGES
SUPPOSEDLY RECOVERED FROM
A LAPTOP BELONGING TO
HUNTER BIDEN.
BUT THERE ARE A LOT OF RED FLAGS
HERE... INCLUDING THE FACT
THE "NEW YORK POST" STORY THAT
BROKE IT WAS REPORTEDLY "WRITTEN
MOSTLY BY A STAFF REPORTER WHO
REFUSED TO PUT HIS NAME ON IT."
AND THE LAPTOP'S CONDUIT TO
THE PRESS IS RUDY GIULIANI, WHO
INTELLIGENCE OFFICIALS FLAGGED
LAST YEAR AS THE TARGET OF A
RUSSIAN INTELLIGENCE OPERATION
TO FEED MISINFORMATION TO TRUMP.
AND GIULIANI'S ABILITY TO SPOT
FRAUDULENT INFORMATION IS,
AT BEST, NOT GREAT.
HE'S SO TECHNOLOGICALLY
ILLITERATE, HE HAS BUTT-DIALED
A REPORTER AND LEFT AN
ACCIDENTAL VOICE MAIL,
MORE THAN ONCE.
HE RECENTLY ACCIDENTALLY
UPLOADED A VIDEO OF HIMSELF
AFFECTING A STEREOTYPICAL
CHINESE ACCENT, AND JUST THIS
WEEK, IT EMERGED HE HAS A CAMEO
IN THE NEW BORAT FILM.
SCREENSHOTS FROM THE MOVIE
WERE PUBLISHED BY VARIETY
IN BRITAIN'S "THE GUARDIAN"
NEWSPAPER.
RUDY GIULIANI IS SEEN HELPING
THE WOMAN TAKE HER MICROPHONE
OFF AND THEN THERE IS A SCENE
WHERE IT APPEARS THAT
RUDY GIULIANI'S HAND GOES DOWN
HIS PANT.
John: YOU KNOW, IT SAYS
SOMETHING ABOUT RUDY'S CHARACTER
THAT THE WEIRDEST PART OF
THE SENTENCE "RUDY GIULIANI GOT
TRICKED, THEN SHOVED HIS HAND
DOWN HIS PANTS IN A HOTEL ROOM
IN FRONT OF A RELATIVE STRANGER"
IS THAT IT DOESN'T END
AT THE WORD "RELATIVE."
BUT THE POINT IS, ANY
INFORMATION THAT GIULIANI'S
NO
PASSING ON SHOULD BE TREATED
WITH EXTREME CAUTION.
AND ALL OF THIS FUNCTIONED
AS A LEAD UP TO THURSDAY'S FINAL
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
SOMETHING EVERYONE WAS DREADING,
AFTER THE FIASCO OF THE FIRST
ONE JUST THREE WEEKS AGO.
AND PERHAPS THAT IS WHY THE
INITIAL REACTION TO THIS WEEK'S
DEBATE WAS ONE OF SLIGHT RELIEF.
THIS WAS AN ACTUAL DEBATE,
I MEAN, AS OPPOSED TO SOME OF
THE OTHER THINGS WE HAVE HAD.
THERE WAS A REAL EXCHANGE.
A SPIRITED BUT CIVIL DEBATE
LAST NIGHT.
FINALLY, A DEBATE.
IT WAS SUBSTANTIVE AND
INFORMATIVE.
NO ONE SET THEMSELVES
ON FIRE IN THE LAST
PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE.
John: YEAH, TRUE.
ALTHOUGH HISTORICALLY, THE BAR
FOR SUCCEEDING AT THESE EVENTS
HAS BEEN A LITTLE HIGHER THAN
"NOBODY BURNS ALIVE."
THIS IS A PRESIDENTIAL DEBATE,
NOT A BEGINNER'S FIRE JUGGLING
CLASS AT THE COMMUNITY CENTER.
AND FOR ANY OTHER CANDIDATE,
THINGS TRUMP SAID ON THAT DEBATE
NO
STAGE WOULD'VE BEEN AN ACT OF
SELF-IMMOLATION.
HE INSISTED WE'RE ROUNDING
NO
THE TURN ON THE CORONAVIRUS,
WHICH WE VERY MUCH ARE NOT.
HE CLAIMED THAT WIND TURBINES
"KILL ALL THE BIRDS,"
WHICH THEY DON'T.
AND ARGUED THAT BIDEN'S CLIMATE
POLICY SUGGESTS, "IF BUILDINGS
HAD NO WINDOWS, IT WOULD BE
A LOVELY THING," WHICH IS JUST
A VERY WEIRD THING TO SAY.
AND THEN THERE WAS THIS.
I AM THE LEAST RACIST PERSON
...I CAN'T EVEN SEE THE AUDIENCE
NO
BECAUSE IT'S SO DARK... BUT I
DON'T CARE WHO'S IN THE AUDIENCE
...I'M THE LEAST RACIST PERSON
IN THIS ROOM.
John: RIGHT.
THAT IS STRANGE FOR
MULTIPLE REASONS.
FIRST, HE'S IMPLYING HIS ANSWER
MIGHT HAVE CHANGED IF THE HOUSE
LIGHTS WERE UP.
"I CAN'T EVEN SEE THE AUDIENCE,
BUT I'M THE LEAST RACIST PERSON
IN THE... OH, HOLD ON, IS THAT
TOM HANKS?
OH, SHIT, HE'S DEFINITELY LESS
RACIST THAN ME, FOR SURE.
BUT I THINK I'M STILL IN
THE TOP TWO."
ALSO, IT'S WORTH NOTING THAT
WHEN HE SAID HE'S THE LEAST
RACIST PERSON IN THE ROOM, THAT
ROOM CONTAINED... AND THIS IS
TRUE... HIS FAMILY.
SO HE'S EFFECTIVELY THROWING
THEM UNDER THE BUS THERE, TOO.
LOOK, WHAT IS REALLY SAD HERE IS
THAT WHEN PEOPLE CLAIM TRUMP WAS
ON HIS "BEST BEHAVIOR"... THAT'S
ACTUALLY TRUE.
BUT HIS BEST BEHAVIOR IS STILL
ABSOLUTELY APPALLING.
BECAUSE EVEN WHEN THE BAR IS
SO LOW AS TO BE VIRTUALLY
NONEXISTENT, LIKE, "DON'T TELL
YOUR SUPPORTERS THAT YOU HATE
THEIR STUPID CITY," OR
"DON'T SAY EVERYONE IN THE
AUDIENCE IS MORE RACIST THAN
YOU, " OR " DON'T HIRE A PERSONAL
NO
ATTORNEY WHO FALLS FOR A BORAT
PRANK 14 YEARS AFTER THE FIRST
MOVIE CAME OUT," THE UNSHAKABLE
FACT IS, UNLESS YOU SET THE BAR
AT "NOBODY CAUGHT FIRE,"
TRUMP WILL ALWAYS FIND A WAY TO
DISAPPOINT.
AND NOW THIS.
Announcer: AND NOW..
NO A MOVING TASTE OF CNBC IS
EXACTLY WHAT YOU THINK IT IS.
ANY MAN WHO REFERENCES THE
CLASSIC "APOCALYPSE NOW" MOVIE
AND THEIR LATEST RESEARCH NOTE
IS OKAY BY US.
THE HORROR, THE HORROR,
CONRAD'S "HEART OF DARKNESS."
"APOCALYPSE NOW."
HE WALKED THROUGH AND NOT
EVEN FLINCHED WITH THINGS
EXPLODING, REMINDS ME OF ROBERT
DUVALL IN "APOCALYPSE NOW."
AGAIN, TRYING TO SPEAK
POSITIVE ABOUT G.E. BECAUSE I AM
A KIND MAN AND I'M A GOOD MAN,
NOT UNLIKE "APOCALYPSE NOW."
I AM A KIND MAN, I'M A GOOD MAN.
THAT IS FROM "APOCALYPSE NOW."
I AM A KIND MAN, I'M A GOOD MAN,
SAID TO ME BY THE WAY, AND
"APOCALYPSE NOW" AT THE END.
I'M A KIND MAN.
JUST LIKE IF YOU HAVE SEEN THE
"APOCALYPSE NOW," I WILL COIN
THIS, SELL EVERYTHING, SO THE
KIDS, SELL THE CAR, SELL THE
HOME, I'M NOT COMING BACK,
"APOCALYPSE NOW."
KIND OF LIKE THE VILLAGE
BURNING WITH NAPALM AND
"APOCALYPSE NOW."
"APOCALYPSE NOW" SITUATION.
HAVE YOU EVER SEEN
"APOCALYPSE NOW"?
MANY TIMES.
John: MOVING ON.
OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT CONCERNS
IMMIGRATION.
IT'S ABSOLUTELY CENTRAL TO THE
AMERICAN STORY, AS IS SOMETIMES
CLUMSILY EXPRESSED IN CARTOONS
LIKE THIS.
THEY HEARD ABOUT A COUNTRY
WHERE LIFE MIGHT LET THEM WIN,
THEY PAID THE FARE TO AMERICA
AND THERE THEY MELTED IN.
LOVELY LADY LIBERTY WITH HER
BOOK OF RECIPES AND THE FINEST
ONE SHE'S GOT IS THE GREAT
AMERICAN MELTING POT.
THE GREAT AMERICAN MELTING POT.
John: OKAY, DEEPLY WEIRD
METAPHOR ASIDE, I WILL SAY THIS:
IF YOU'RE COOKING A BUNCH OF
HUMANS IN A MELTING POT,
DON'T INCLUDE THE ENGLISH.
BELIEVE ME, WE'LL RUIN THE DISH.
WE'RE BLAND AND YET ALSO TOTALLY
OVERPOWERING TO THE PALATE.
WE ARE BASICALLY THE CILANTRO OF
THE HUMAN RACE.
WE'VE TALKED ABOUT IMMIGRATION
REPEATEDLY ON THIS SHOW BUT
TONIGHT, WE'RE GOING TO FOCUS ON
ASYLUM.
IT'S THE LEGAL PROCESS BY WHICH
PEOPLE WHO ARE FLEEING
PERSECUTION, AND MAKE IT TO
THE U.S., CAN APPLY TO STAY
HERE.
AND ASYLUM SEEKERS ARE A GROUP
THAT, IN THEORY, EVERYONE SHOULD
BE ABLE TO SUPPORT... THEY ARE
THE LITERAL HUDDLED MASSES
YEARNING TO BREATHE FREE WHO
THE STATUE OF LIBERTY HAS,
FOR CENTURIES, FRICASSEED.
BUT TRUMP IS FAMOUSLY NOT A FAN.
HE WENT ON ABOUT ASYLUM
AT LENGTH IN THURSDAY'S DEBATE,
AND HE LOVES TO RIFF ABOUT IT
WHENEVER HE GETS IN FRONT
OF A CROWD.
THE ASYLUM PROGRAM IS A SCAM.
SOME OF THE ROUGHEST PEOPLE
YOU'VE EVER SEEN.
PEOPLE THAT LOOK LIKE THEY
SHOULD BE FIGHTING FOR THE UFC.
THEY READ A LITTLE PAGE GIVEN
BY LAWYERS.
I AM VERY FEARFUL FOR MY LIFE.
I AM VERY WORRIED THAT I WILL BE
ACCOSTED IF I WAS SENT BACK
HOME.
OH, GIVE HIM ASYLUM.
HE'S AFRAID.
WE DON'T LOVE THE FACT HE'S GOT
TATTOOS ON HIS FACE.
John: OKAY, THERE'S A LOT TO
UNPACK THERE, STARTING WITH
THE FACT THAT TRUMP SEEMS TO
THINK PEOPLE WITH FACIAL TATTOOS
ARE JUST INHERENTLY SCARY,
SOMETHING DEFINITIVELY DISPROVEN
BY THE EXISTENCE OF POST MALONE.
HE LOOKS LIKE A BUILD-A-BEAR
WHO SPENT TOO MUCH TIME AT
THE TATTOO STATION.
ALSO, AS YOU PROBABLY GUESSED,
THE ASYLUM PROCESS ISN'T
A SIMPLE RECITATION OF MAGIC
WORDS, BY WHICH ALL MANNER OF
FRAUDULENT CLAIMS ARE LET
THROUGH.
NOR IS IT RESPONSIBLE FOR, AS
TRUMP'S OFFICIAL WHITE HOUSE
WEBSITE CALLS IT, "THE BIGGEST
LOOPHOLE TO GAIN ENTRY INTO OUR
GREAT COUNTRY."
THAT IS SIMPLY NOT TRUE.
HISTORICALLY, THE BIGGEST
LOOPHOLE HAS BEEN TO BE
THE PARENTS OF SOMEONE
THAT DONALD TRUMP WISHES WOULD
FUCK HIM.
AND FOR THE RECORD, ASYLUM
SEEKERS ARE NOT ALL TATTOOED
UFC FIGHTERS.
THEY'RE ALSO PEOPLE LIKE BERTA,
WHO FLED HONDURAS AFTER MS-13
GANG MEMBERS TRIED TO FORCE HER
12-YEAR-OLD GRANDDAUGHTER INTO
MARRIAGE.
BERTA REFUSED, THEY THREATENED
TO SET HER ON FIRE, SO SHE AND
HER GRANDDAUGHTER FLED TO
THE U.S.
THEY WERE SEPARATED,
BERTA WAS DETAINED,
AND I'LL LET HER LAWYER PICK
THE STORY UP FROM THERE.
BERTA, MY CLIENT, SHE'S
A 63-YEAR-OLD GRANDMOTHER
WHO LEGALLY ENTERED
THE UNITED STATES.
AND SHE'S FLEEING FOR HER LIFE,
BUT SHE DID IT THE CORRECT WAY.
WHY?
'CAUSE SHE WENT TO THE PORT OF
ENTRY AND BASICALLY TURNED
HERSELF IN.
IT'S NOT LIKE SHE WAS HIDING,
SHE WAS TRYING TO BE SMUGGLED
IN THE TRUNK OF A CAR.
SHE DID IT THE RIGHT WAY.
I'VE BEEN HERE FOR 17 MONTHS.
I'VE BEEN HERE FOR A LONG TIME
ALREADY.
I DON'T KNOW WHY IMMIGRATION
WON'T LET ME LEAVE.
I DON'T OWE ANYTHING.
ONLY BECAUSE I CAME TO ASK FOR
PROTECTION FROM THIS COUNTRY.
John: THAT IS RIDICULOUS.
IF YOU ASKED THE COPS FOR HELP,
AND THEY RESPONDED BY THROWING
YOU INTO DETENTION, YOU'D BE
ABSOLUTELY FURIOUS.
YOU'D PROBABLY ALSO BE BLACK,
BUT LET'S TRY AND TAKE THIS
ONE SYSTEMIC SOCIAL CRISIS
AT A TIME.
AND BERTA'S STORY ISN'T EVEN
A ONE-OFF.
THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION'S
ATTACK ON ASYLUM HAS BEEN
FOCUSED, DEDICATED, AND
DEEPLY RESOURCEFUL.
AND I KNOW THOSE AREN'T
ADJECTIVES YOU'RE USED
TO ASSOCIATING WITH THIS
ADMINISTRATION.
BUT IN THIS ONE AREA, THEY'VE
BEEN TRULY DISCIPLINED ABOUT
BEING TRULY EVIL.
SO TONIGHT, LET'S TALK ABOUT OUR
ASYLUM SYSTEM.
HOW IT'S SUPPOSED TO WORK, AND
JUST A FEW OF THE KEY WAYS THIS
ADMINISTRATION HAS UNDERMINED
IT.
AND LET'S START WITH HOW IT'S
SUPPOSED TO WORK AT OUR BORDER.
IDEALLY, AN ASYLUM SEEKER
PRESENTS THEMSELVES TO ASK
FOR PROTECTION, AND AN OFFICER
PERFORMS A "CREDIBLE FEAR
SCREENING."
IF THERE IS A CHANCE THEY MIGHT
FACE DANGER IF THEY'RE SENT BACK
HOME, THEY'RE ALLOWED TO REMAIN
IN THE U.S. PENDING A DATE IN
IMMIGRATION COURT.
WHICH MAKES SENSE.
WHEN A PERSON SAYS THEIR LIFE'S
AT STAKE, YOU WANT TO ERR ON
THE SIDE OF BELIEVING THEM
WHILE YOU WEIGH THE FACTS OF
THEIR CASE.
IF SOMEONE SAYS "I'M DROWNING,"
YOUR FIRST MOVE SHOULD BE TO
HELP THEM OUT OF THE POOL, NOT
LEAVE THEM IN THERE WHILE YOU
CONVENE A HEARING TO DETERMINE
WHETHER OR NOT THEY'RE A FISH
WHO IS LYING.
NOW YOU SHOULD KNOW, EVEN BEFORE
TRUMP, THE ODDS OF BEING GRANTED
ASYLUM WERE NOT GREAT, WITH
IMMIGRATION ADVOCATES SAYING
LESS THAN HALF OF ALL CLAIMS
ARE GRANTED.
NOW THAT IS PARTLY BECAUSE... AS
WE'VE DISCUSSED BEFORE... MANY
MIGRANTS DON'T HAVE A LAWYER TO
HELP THEM NAVIGATE A COMPLICATED
PROCESS.
AND IT'S PARTLY BECAUSE THE BAR
TO QUALIFY FOR ASYLUM IS HIGH.
YOU HAVE TO BE ABLE TO PROVE
YOU'RE BEING PERSECUTED ON
THE BASIS OF RACE, RELIGION,
NATIONALITY, MEMBERSHIP
IN A SOCIAL GROUP, OR POLITICAL
OPINION.
AND THERE'S ALWAYS GOING TO
BE ROOM FOR INTERPRETATION
THERE.
WHAT QUALIFIES AS MEMBERSHIP IN
A SOCIAL GROUP OR A POLITICAL
OPINION?
FOR INSTANCE, SOMEONE BEING
PERSECUTED FOR CRITICIZING
A DRUG CARTEL MIGHT WELL ARGUE
THAT THEIR CRITICISM IS
POLITICAL IF THEY LIVE
IN A NARCO-STATE.
BUT THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION HAS
TOLD IMMIGRATION JUDGES TO APPLY
THE CRITERIA VERY NARROWLY, AS
THIS ATTORNEY EXPLAINS TO A ROOM
FULL OF ASYLUM SEEKERS.
THE ASYLUM PROCESS DOES NOT
PROTECT EVERYONE.
CASES THAT PERTAIN TO CARTELS OR
GANGS EXTORTING YOU ARE ALMOST
IMPOSSIBLE TO WIN.
UH-HUH?
I HAVE A PROBLEM IN MY
COUNTRY.
I CAN'T GO BACK.
THIS IS VERY COMMON.
THEY ALREADY KILLED FAMILY WHO
DIDN'T PAY.
CRIMINALITY ISN'T PROTECTED.
YOU'RE SAYING WE CAN ONLY
PROVE IT IF WE TURN UP DEAD?
EVEN THEN, IF IT'S NOT
THE RIGHT REASON, IT'S NOT
PROTECTED.
John: WOW.
I DON'T KNOW WHAT'S MORE JARRING
THERE, THAT MAN'S PITCH-BLACK
JOKE ABOUT GETTING MURDERED OR
THE LAWYER TAKING IT AT COMPLETE
FACE VALUE.
"HA, THAT'S VERY FUNNY, BUT
SERIOUSLY, IF YOU COULD DIE
HOLDING DOCUMENTATION THAT YOU
WERE MURDERED FOR YOUR RELIGION,
THAT WOULD ACTUALLY BE A BIG
HELP."
SO THE ASYLUM PROCESS HAS NEVER
BEEN EASY.
BUT THIS ADMINISTRATION HAS MADE
IT ABSOLUTE HELL.
THEIR POLICY OF FAMILY
SEPARATION CAUSED WIDESPREAD
OUTRAGE, BUT THEY'VE DONE SO
MUCH MORE THAN THAT.
AND IT'S WORTH SLOWING DOWN TO
LOOK AT THREE TACTICS THEY'VE
USED IN PARTICULAR.
MIGRANT PROTECTION PROTOCOLS,
"SAFE THIRD COUNTRY AGREEMENTS,"
AND TITLE 42.
AND I KNOW NONE OF THOSE HAVE
THE HARROWING RING OF
"FAMILY SEPARATION," BUT EACH
REPRESENTS ANOTHER CRUEL,
CALCULATED DECISION THAT HAS
LARGELY FLOWN UNDER THE RADAR.
AND LET'S START WITH THE MIGRANT
PROTECTION PROTOCOLS, OR, AS
THEY'RE MORE COMMONLY KNOWN,
THE "REMAIN IN MEXICO" PROGRAM.
VERY BASICALLY, THIS POLICY
FORCES ASYLUM SEEKERS TO WAIT IN
MEXICO FOR THEIR CASES TO FULLY
PLAY OUT IN U.S. IMMIGRATION
COURT RATHER THAN ADMIT THEM TO
SAFETY FIRST.
WE'VE ALREADY DONE THIS TO OVER
67,000 PEOPLE, MANY OF WHOM
WOUND UP IN MAKESHIFT CAMPS
THAT HAVE EMERGED AT THE BORDER.
AND SINCE WE STARTED LIMITING
THE NUMBER EVEN ALLOWED TO ASK
FOR ASYLUM AT THE BORDER EACH
DAY, IN SOME PLACES, THE
MIGRANTS THEMSELVES HAD TO WORK
OUT A SYSTEM FOR WHOSE TURN IT
WAS NEXT.
THE LIST IS A STRANGE THING.
VOLUNTEERS WHO ARE MIGRANTS
THEMSELVES KEEP THEM IN A
NOTEPAD IN THE MEXICAN BORDER
CITY OF TIJUANA.
IT DETERMINES THE ORDER IN WHICH
THE THOUSANDS OF ASYLUM SEEKERS
HERE WILL BE SEEN BY U.S.
OFFICIALS.
NO ONE KNOWS EXACTLY WHO
STARTED IT OR WHEN, BUT IT'S
EVOLVED INTO A SYSTEM TO TRY AND
KEEP ORDER AS THE U.S. HAS
SLOWED UP THE PROCESSING OF
ASYLUM CLAIMS.
John: LOOK, THERE ARE PLENTY
OF THINGS YOU'D EXPECT TO BE
HAND-WRITTEN IN A COLLEGE RULED
NOTEBOOK.
MATH HOMEWORK, SURE.
A LIST OF THE CUTEST BOYS IN
HOMEROOM, NATCH.
JUST AN ABSOLUTE SHITLOAD OF
COOL Ss?
YOU KNOW IT.
WHAT YOU WOULDN'T EXPECT WOULD
BE THE NAMES OF THOUSANDS OF
FAMILIES FOR WHOM THIS SCRAP OF
NOTEBOOK PAPER IS THEIR ONLY
LIFELINE TO SAFETY.
BECAUSE HOW THE FUCK HAVE WE LET
THAT BE THE BEST SYSTEM
AVAILABLE TO THEM?
AND CONDITIONS ON THE BORDER CAN
BE DIRE.
IN FEBRUARY, MORE THAN 2500
MIGRANTS WERE LIVING IN A CAMP
IN MATAMOROS, WHERE THERE WAS
ONLY ONE TOILET FOR EVERY
60 PEOPLE, AND SAFE DRINKING
WATER WAS SCARCE.
AND EVEN PEOPLE WHO DON'T WIND
UP IN THOSE CAMPS CAN BE IN
REAL JEOPARDY.
BECAUSE MIGRANTS IN GENERAL CAN
BE TARGETS FOR CARTELS WHO
REGULARLY KIDNAP AND TRY TO
EXTRACT RANSOM MONEY FROM THOSE
THEY SUSPECT OF HAVING FAMILY IN
THE U.S.
THIS IS DONE SO OFTEN, THERE'S A
WHOLE SYSTEM IN PLACE FOR IT, AS
THIS CARTEL MEMBER EXPLAINS.
WE JUST PULL PEOPLE OFF THE
STREETS, TAKE THEM INTO A SAFE
HOUSE.
WE REACH THEIR FAMILIES IN THE
UNITED STATES TO ASK FOR MONEY.
HOW MUCH MONEY ARE WE TALKING
HERE?
ALL THE WAY FROM $10,000 TO
$20,000 AMERICAN DOLLARS.
WE KNOW THEY CAN AFFORD IT.
THAT'S WHY WE DO WHAT WE DO.
WHAT IF THEY DON'T PAY?
WELL, THEY END UP WHERE THEY
END UP.
John: "THEY END UP WHERE THEY
END UP."
HE'S TALKING ABOUT MURDER
VICTIMS WITH THE SAME CASUALNESS
MOST PEOPLE RESERVE FOR LOST
SOCKS.
AND AS OF MAY, THERE WERE OVER A
THOUSAND PUBLICLY REPORTED CASES
OF MURDER, RAPE, TORTURE,
KIDNAPPING, AND OTHER VIOLENT
ASSAULTS AGAINST ASYLUM SEEKERS
AND MIGRANTS FORCED BY THE U.S.,
COMPLETELY UNNECESSARILY, TO
WAIT IN MEXICO.
IN FACT, KIDNAPPINGS ARE SUCH A
FACT OF LIFE, CARTELS WILL GIVE
SOME KIDNAPPED MIGRANTS A CODE
WORD UPON RELEASE, SO IF THEY'RE
KIDNAPPED AGAIN, THE KEYWORD
WOULD INDICATE THAT THEY'D
ALREADY PAID THE RANSOM.
AND IT'S PRETTY BLEAK WHEN
DRUG CARTELS HAVE A MORE
EFFICIENT SYSTEM FOR KEEPING
TRACK OF ASYLUM SEEKERS THAN
THE U.S. GOVERNMENT.
AND YET DESPITE THE WRECKAGE
THIS ADMINISTRATION HAS CAUSED,
IT'S TRUMPETED ITS "REMAIN IN
MEXICO" PROGRAM AS A GREAT
SUCCESS.
IN FACT, CHAD WOLF... ACTING
SECRETARY OF HOMELAND SECURITY
AND UNDISPUTED CHADDIEST WOLF...
HAS TOUTED IT, USING A PRETTY
WEIRD METRIC.
WHAT WE'RE SEEING IS ABOUT
HALF OF THESE INDIVIDUALS THAT
ARE PUT IN THE PROGRAM NEVER
SHOW UP FOR THEIR COURT
HEARINGS.
SO INDIVIDUALS THAT ARE PUT IN
THIS PROGRAM THAT KNOW THEY DO
NOT HAVE A, AGAIN, A MERITORIOUS
CLAIM, SIMPLY CHOOSE TO WALK
AWAY.
John: OKAY, REAL QUICK...
GET FUCKED, CHAD, YOU HUMAN
RAZOR BURN.
BECAUSE REMEMBER, THESE HEARINGS
ARE MIGRANTS' ONLY SHOT AT
GETTING TO SAFETY.
IT'S EVERYTHING THEY'VE BEEN
WAITING FOR.
AND IF THEY MISS THEIR HEARING,
THEY LOSE THEIR CASE!
SO A PERSON NOT SHOWING UP
IN COURT AFTER YOU FORCE THEM
TO WAIT IN A DANGEROUS AREA,
WITHOUT ADEQUATE SHELTER OR
SUPPORT ISN'T PROOF THEY WERE
TRYING TO CHEAT THE SYSTEM, IT'S
PROOF YOUR SYSTEM IS NOT FUCKING
WORKING!
AND FOR THE RECORD, THE
GOVERNMENT CAN MAKE THESE
HEARINGS PRETTY MS.ABLE.
IT MAY BEAR NO DATE OR
TIME, OR YOUR HEARING MAY BE
SCHEDULED FOR WHEN THE COURTS
AREN'T OPEN, INCLUDING ONE THAT
WAS SCHEDULED AT 1:00 A.M.
IT CAN BE HARD TO KNOW ABOUT ANY
CHANGES TO DATE OF HEARINGS
GIVEN THAT SOME BORDER PATROL
AGENTS FILLING OUT FORMS FOR
MIGRANTS HAVE WRITTEN IN
"FACEBOOK" AS A STREET ADDRESS.
ALL IN ALL, THE GOVERNMENT
SYSTEM IS ABOUT AS EFFECTIVE
AS PAINTING
"MEET US AT THE PLACE" ON
A RACCOON AND THROWING IT
OVER THE WALL INTO MEXICO.
GOOD LUCK GETTING THE
INSTRUCTIONS, AND IF YOU DO,
GOOD LUCK FIGURING OUT HOW TO
FOLLOW THEM.
SO THIS PROGRAM ALL BUT SHUT OFF
THE PATHWAY FOR MANY ASYLUM
SEEKERS TO ENTER THE COUNTRY.
BUT THAT SEEMINGLY WASN'T
ENOUGH, BECAUSE THE
ADMINISTRATION THEN CAME UP WITH
"SAFE THIRD COUNTRY" AGREEMENTS.
BASICALLY, THE U.S. MANAGED
TO FORCE HONDURAS, GUATEMALA,
AND EL SALVADOR TO SIGN UP TO
THIS.
AND IT MEANT THAT WE COULD BAR
MIGRANTS FROM SEEKING ASYLUM
HERE, AND SEND THEM TO APPLY FOR
IT IN THOSE COUNTRIES INSTEAD.
WHICH IS COMPLETELY ABSURD,
SINCE FOR MANY MIGRANTS, THOSE
ARE THE EXACT COUNTRIES THEY'RE
SEEKING ASYLUM FROM.
"OH, YOU'RE FLEEING HONDURAS?
WHY NOT TRY EL SALVADOR!
IT'S RIGHT NEXT DOOR SO YOU CAN
STAY IN TOUCH WITH FAMILY,
FRIENDS, AND THE PEOPLE WHO WANT
TO MURDER YOU!"
AND IF THAT WASN'T BAD ENOUGH,
NONE OF THESE THREE COUNTRIES
HAVE ROBUST ASYLUM SYSTEMS, AS
THE PRESIDENT OF EL SALVADOR
HIMSELF ADMITS.
A MEMBER OF THE PRESIDENT'S
INNER CIRCLE SAID THAT ASYLUM
SEEKERS COULD END UP STAYING IN
EL SALVADOR, THAT THAT COULD
HAPPEN.
IS EL SALVADOR PREPARED FOR
THAT?
WELL, NOT RIGHT NOW.
WE DON'T HAVE ASYLUM CAPACITIES,
BUT WE CAN BUILD THEM.
BUT YOU DON'T HAVE IT NOW.
WE DON'T HAVE IT NOW.
WHEN WE HAVE IT...
AND IF HE SAID, "I CAN THROW
UP A TENT."
A TENT?
THAT'S NOT... THAT'S NOT ASYLUM
CAPACITY.
NO.
John: NO.
NO, IT REALLY ISN'T.
THROWING UP A TENT DOESN'T
INHERENTLY GIVE YOU ASYLUM
CAPACITY.
THERE ARE ONLY TWO THINGS
SHELTER FROM THE ELEMENTS, AND
THE ARENA FOR A SHAME-BASED
BAKING CRUCIBLE WHOSE ONLY PRIZE
IS THE NARROW AVOIDANCE OF
PUBLIC FAILURE.
WHY THE
FUCK DID THE NEW SEASON OF
"THE GREAT BRITISH BAKE-OFF"
MAKE THE FIRST SHOWSTOPPER
CHALLENGE "CELEBRITY CAKE
BUSTS?"
BECAUSE IT GAVE US SQUASHED
FREDDIE MERCURY, SOMETHING
THE BAKER INSISTED WAS
LUPITA NYONG'O, AND A
PHOTO PERFECT DAVID BOWIE.
THAT BAKER DESERVES
A PAUL HOLLYWOOD HANDSHAKE.
THE REST OF YOU NEED TO THINK
ABOUT WHAT YOU'VE DONE.
AND FORCING MIGRANTS TO SIT IN
REFUGEE CAMPS OR SENDING THEM
TO COUNTRIES WITH
NON-FUNCTIONING ASYLUM SYSTEMS
IS COMFORTABLY BAD ENOUGH,
BEFORE YOU GET TO WHAT HAPPENED
EARLIER THIS YEAR, WHEN
THE ADMINISTRATION'S INVOKED
TITLE 42 OF THE U.S. CODE.
AND THAT ISN'T EVEN AN
IMMIGRATION LAW.
IT'S A PROVISION THAT GIVES THE
GOVERNMENT BROAD POWER TO ACT
DURING A PUBLIC HEALTH CRISIS.
AND THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION IS
CURRENTLY CLAIMING THAT, BECAUSE
OF THE PANDEMIC, IT GIVES THEM
THE AUTHORITY TO SHUT DOWN THE
BORDER TO VIRTUALLY ALL
MIGRANTS.
AND NOT JUST THAT... THEY'RE
ALSO CLAIMING THAT IT ALLOWS
THEM TO TAKE ASYLUM SEEKERS
WHO'VE ALREADY MADE IT INTO
THE U.S., AND EXPEL THEM WITH NO
DUE PROCESS WHATSOEVER.
IT IS A TRANSPARENT ATTEMPT TO
EXPLOIT THIS PANDEMIC TO DO WHAT
THEY WANT WITH MIGRANTS...
ALTHOUGH, MARK MORGAN, TRUMP'S
HEAD OF CUSTOMS AND BORDER
PROTECTION, HAS REPEATEDLY
INSISTED THAT NOTHING COULD
BE FURTHER FROM THE TRUTH.
TITLE 42 HAS NOTHING TO DO
WITH IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT.
I'M GONNA SAY THAT AGAIN.
I'VE SAID IT BEFORE.
I'M GONNA CONTINUE TO SAY IT.
TITLE 42 HAS NOTHING TO DO WITH
IMMIGRATION ENFORCEMENT AND
EVERYTHING TO DO WITH
PUBLIC HEALTH.
John: YEAH, MARK, WE'RE AWARE
YOU KEEP SAYING THIS HAS NOTHING
TO DO WITH IMMIGRATION.
BUT A TRUMP OFFICIAL SAYING HIS
ACTIONS HAVE NOTHING TO DO WITH
IMMIGRATION IS ABOUT AS
BELIEVABLE AS COOKIE MONSTER
SAYING HIS ACTIONS HAVE NOTHING
TO DO WITH COOKIES.
BECAUSE OF COURSE THEY DO.
THEY'RE THE THING YOU'RE SO
OBSESSED WITH, IT LITERALLY
MAKES YOU A MONSTER.
AND IT'S A LITTLE HARD TO TAKE
THIS ADMINISTRATION CITING THEIR
DEEP CONCERN ABOUT THE
CORONAVIRUS, EVEN BEFORE YOU
LEARN THAT THE CDC WAS
APPARENTLY FORCED TO ISSUE THE
TITLE 42 ORDER, DESPITE THEIR
OWN SCIENTISTS SAYING THERE WAS
NO EVIDENCE IT WOULD SLOW THE
CORONAVIRUS.
SO THIS CLEARLY HAS NOTHING TO
DO WITH PUBLIC HEALTH AT ALL.
AND IF YOU NEED ANY MORE PROOF,
STEPHEN MILLER... TRUMP'S TOP
IMMIGRATION ADVISER AND WORLD'S
TALLEST MINION... HAS APPARENTLY
BEEN TRYING TO INVOKE TITLE 42
FOR IMMIGRATION PURPOSES LONG
BEFORE COVID.
HE REPORTEDLY PUSHED TO INVOKE
IT TWICE LAST YEAR, ONCE WHEN
AN OUTBREAK OF MUMPS SPREAD
THROUGH IMMIGRATION DETENTION
FACILITIES, AND AGAIN WHEN
BORDER PATROL STATIONS WERE HIT
WITH THE FLU.
IN FACT, USING EMERGENCY
PUBLIC HEALTH POWERS TO CURB
IMMIGRATION WAS APPARENTLY ON
A WISH LIST THAT MILLER CRAFTED
WITHIN THE FIRST SIX MONTHS OF
THE ADMINISTRATION.
INCIDENTALLY, THE REST OF THAT
WISH LIST WAS JUST WHAT LOOKS
LIKE A HAND-DRAWN PICTURE OF
A RIPPED STEPHEN MILLER AND
"MAYBE AN ALL-WHITE REBOOT OF
'HIDDEN FIGURES'?"
CIRCLED THREE TIMES.
AND YOU CAN KIND OF SEE WHY THIS
APPEALS SO MUCH TO MILLER.
BECAUSE INVOKING TITLE 42
HAS BASICALLY CREATED A SHADOW
DEPORTATION SYSTEM THAT MOVES
QUICKLY AND IS ACCOUNTABLE
TO NO ONE.
AND THEY'VE USED IT A LOT.
SINCE MARCH, THERE'VE BEEN
NEARLY 200,000 EXPULSIONS IN
WHICH ASYLUM SEEKERS WERE SENT
BACK WITHOUT SO MUCH AS A COURT
HEARING.
AND THE GOVERNMENT HAS GONE OUT
OF ITS WAY TO AVOID SCRUTINY.
FOR EXAMPLE, UNACCOMPANIED
MINORS ARE USUALLY KEPT IN
SHELTERS, WHERE IMMIGRATION
ATTORNEYS CAN FIND THEM, AND TRY
AND HELP THEM WITH THEIR CASE.
BUT BY CITING PUBLIC HEALTH
CONCERNS, THE GOVERNMENT HAS
INSTEAD BEEN QUIETLY KEEPING
KIDS IN HOTELS, SUPERVISED BY
PRIVATE CONTRACTORS.
AND THE RARE GLIMPSES WE'VE
GOTTEN OF THIS HAVE BEEN
ABSOLUTELY CHILLING.
JUST WATCH AS A CIVIL RIGHTS
ATTORNEY TRIES TO HELP THE KIDS
BUT GETS STOPPED.
ARE YOU POLICE?
YOU CAN'T BE HERE.
CAN I ASK WHO YOU ARE?
DESPERATELY TRYING TO
COMMUNICATE TO CHILDREN, THE
ASSOCIATED PLACE SO THEY ARE
BEING HELD BY THE FOURTH FLOOR
OF THE HILTON IN SUITES HOTEL IN
McALLEN, TEXAS.
IF YOU ARE DETAINED, GIVE ME
HER NAME!
GET OUT OF HERE.
WHO ARE YOU?
DON'T WORRY ABOUT WHO WE ARE.
ARE YOU POLICE?
GET OUT.
GET OUT NOW!
John: WHAT THE FUCK IS
HAPPENING THERE?
ALTHOUGH I AM CURIOUS IF, AFTER
THAT INTERACTION, THOSE MEN FELT
THEY'D SUCCESSFULLY HIDDEN
THE GOVERNMENT'S CHILD PRISON.
"WHEW, THAT WAS A CLOSE ONE!
I GOT A BIT WORRIED WHEN HE
ASKED "WHO ARE YOU," BUT THEN
RANDY SAID, "DON'T WORRY WHO WE
ARE."
NICE SAVE THERE, RANDY!
THAT'S THE LAST TIME ANYONE
ASKS US QUESTIONS ABOUT THIS
MYSTERIOUSLY OFF-LIMITS HOTEL
FLOOR PACKED WITH TERRIFIED
CHILDREN."
NOW, INCIDENTALLY, OUR LAWYERS
ARE INSISTING THAT I HAVE TO
CLARIFY THAT THAT HAMPTON INN
SAID THEY HAD MADE THOSE
BOOKINGS WITHOUT KNOWING WHAT
THEY'D BE USED FOR, AND HAVE
CANCELED THEIR BUSINESS.
BECAUSE THE ENTITY YOU'RE
DEFINITELY ANGRIEST AT RIGHT NOW
IS THE HAMPTON FUCKING INN.
AND WHEN YOU PUT ALL THIS
TOGETHER, THIS ADMINISTRATION
HAS EFFECTIVELY TAKEN AN ASYLUM
SYSTEM THAT WAS ALREADY
IMPERFECT AND SHATTERED IT.
AND THE THING IS, THEY'RE NOW
TRYING TO MAKE THIS DAMAGE
PERMANENT.
BECAUSE ALONG WITH EXTENDING
TITLE 42 INDEFINITELY, THEY'VE
DRAFTED NEW REGULATIONS THAT
WOULD, AMONG OTHER THINGS, MAKE
IT EASIER FOR IMMIGRATION JUDGES
TO REJECT ASYLUM REQUESTS OUT OF
HAND, MAKE IT MORE DIFFICULT,
IF NOT IMPOSSIBLE, TO WIN A CASE
INVOLVING GENDER-BASED VIOLENCE
OR GANG THREATS, AND MAKE IT SO
MIGRANTS ARE REQUIRED TO SUBMIT
COMPLETE ASYLUM APPLICATIONS...
WHICH HAVE TO BE IN ENGLISH, AND
WITH ALL SUPPORTING EVIDENCE...
WITHIN JUST 15 DAYS OF THEIR
FIRST COURT HEARING.
AND THAT IS REGARDLESS OF
WHETHER THEY HAVE A LAWYER.
THE TRUMP ADMINISTRATION'S
ATTACK ON THIS SYSTEM HAS JUST
BEEN RELENTLESS.
AND THERE ARE LIVES AT STAKE
HERE.
REMEMBER BERTA, WHO CAME HERE TO
PROTECT HER 12-YEAR-OLD
GRANDDAUGHTER?
JUST WATCH HER LAWYER UPDATE HER
ON THE OUTCOME OF HER CASE.
WELL, HERE WE ARE.
THE COURT APPEAL WAS REJECTED.
THEY ARE LOOKING FOR ME.
AND THEY WILL KILL ME RIGHT
AWAY.
I DON'T WANT TO...
SO YOU ARE AFRAID?
YES.
I'M SCARED.
John: YEAH, THE GOVERNMENT,
ACTING ON OUR BEHALF, DEPORTED
BERTA BACK TO HONDURAS, WHERE
YOU SHOULD KNOW, SHE ONCE AGAIN
FLED, AND IS CURRENTLY LIVING
IN LIMBO IN MEXICO.
AND THE TRAGIC THING IS, IN SOME
WAYS, SHE'S LUCKIER THAN MANY
ASYLUM SEEKERS.
SHE AT LEAST HAD A LAWYER AND
HER CASE WAS HEARD.
BUT FOR SO MANY, ESPECIALLY NOW,
THERE'S JUST NO TELLING IF OR
WHEN THEY'LL EVEN GET THAT FAR.
AND IF YOU'RE WONDERING, "WELL,
WHAT WE CAN DO ABOUT THIS?"
THERE IS ACTUALLY ONE THING YOU
CAN DO.
YOU CAN VOTE FOR JOE BIDEN.
AND I KNOW THAT SOUNDS
SIMPLISTIC, ESPECIALLY
CONSIDERING THAT OUR IMMIGRATION
POLICY HAS BEEN PRETTY SHITTY
UNDER DEMOCRATIC ADMINISTRATIONS
TOO, LIKE THE ONE JOE BIDEN WAS
IN FOR EIGHT YEARS.
AND I AM NOT SAYING HE'S THE
PERFECT CANDIDATE, FAR FROM IT.
I PERSONALLY FIND HIS OPPOSITION
TO MEDICARE FOR ALL UTTERLY
RIDICULOUS, ESPECIALLY IN
THE MIDDLE OF A PANDEMIC.
ALSO, I THINK AVIATOR GLASSES
SHOULD ONLY BE WORN BY
HOT PILOTS, CUTE BABIES, AND
CUTE BABY PILOTS.
BUT THE FACT IS, A LOT OF OUR
IMMIGRATION POLICY IS SET SOLELY
BY THE EXECUTIVE BRANCH.
AND YOU SHOULD KNOW, BIDEN HAS
EXPLICITLY PROMISED TO END THE
REMAIN IN MEXICO POLICY AND
RESTORE ASYLUM ELIGIBILITY FOR
DOMESTIC VIOLENCE SURVIVORS AND
VICTIMS OF GANG PERSECUTION.
AND THOSE COULD BE
LIFE-SAVING CHANGES.
ONE IMMIGRATION ATTORNEY WE
SPOKE WITH HAS SAID,
"I SPEND HOURS EVERY DAY TELLING
ASYLUM-SEEKERS STUCK IN MEXICO,
"WE WON'T KNOW UNTIL NOVEMBER
THIRD."
THEY CRY.
THEY PRAY.
THEY ASK ABOUT THE LATEST POLLS.
I SHOW MY COUNTDOWN TIMER.
THEY SHOW ME THEIR SCARS."
AND OBVIOUSLY, BIDEN WILL HAVE
TO DO A LOT MORE, AND WE'LL HAVE
TO HOLD HIM TO THE PROMISES HE'S
MADE, BUT WE CAN'T BEGIN
TO FIX THE DAMAGE DONE BY THIS
ADMINISTRATION UNTIL WE REPLACE
THE ADMINISTRATION ITSELF.
IF WE EVEN WANT A SHOT
AT CHANGE, IT'S ON US TO VOTE,
AND THEN ADVOCATE LIKE LIVES
DEPEND ON IT.
BECAUSE THE FACT IS, WE BADLY
NEED AN ASYLUM SYSTEM THAT
WORKS.
AND THAT IS ONE THAT'S BASED ON
COMPASSION, DUE PROCESS, AND OF
COURSE, ULTIMATELY, CANNIBALISM
BY A GIANT GREEN STATUE.
AND NOW THIS.
Announcer: AND NOW, LIKE WE
SAID, THE MOVIE TASTE OF PEOPLE
ON CNBC IS EXACTLY WHAT YOU
THINK IT IS.
A LOT OF THIS IS LIKE "THE
GODFATHER, JUST BUSINESS.
I CALL IT THE GODFATHER THREE
STOCK MARKET.
HOWEVER MUCH INVESTORS WANT TO
GET OUT, THE PRICE STRUCTURE
KEEPS PULLING THE BACK END.
JUST WHEN I THOUGHT I WAS
OUT, THEY ARE PULLING ME BACK
IN.
THAT IS USED A LOT.
"THE GODFATHER."
NO, YOU PULLED ME BACK IN.
I MEAN, FOR AN ABSOLUTELY AWFUL
MOVIE, I MEAN, THAT... THAT
DEFINITELY IS... I MEAN,
COMPARED...
THAT IS AN AWFUL MOVIE?
COMPARED TO G1 AND G2.
SPEAK ANOTHER TIME HAS COME UP
TO CLEAN UP THE SHIP, TO TAKE
CARE OF THE FAMILY BUSINESSES IN
THE "THE GODFATHER."
IT'S KIND OF LIKE
"THE GODFATHER" 3, NOT THAT
IMPORTANT.
AS THEY SAY IN
"THE GODFATHER," THIS IS THE
LIFE WE CHOSE.
I WAS REMINDED BY THE
SOLILOQUY THAT MARLON BRANDO
GIVES ABOUT SONNY SAYING THINGS
YOU SHOULDN'T SAY, HOTHEADED.
IS THAT "ON THE WATERFRONT?"
"ON THE WATERFRONT?"
I DON'T WASH DIANE KEATON
MOVIES BECAUSE HER CHARACTER
ABORTED MICHAEL CORLEONE'S BABY
AND "THE GODFATHER."
I CAN RELATE THAT BACK TO THE
DISNEY SITCOM.
John: THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANK YOU SO MUCH.
WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT WEEK.
GOOD NIGHT.
>>>>oakislandtk
www.opensubtitles.org