♪ ♪
John: HI THERE!
WELCOME TO THE SHOW STILL
TAKING PLACE IN THIS BLANK VOID.
THINK OF IT AS THE INSIDE OF
AN OYSTER, MAKING ME THE PEARL.
WHICH DOES MAKE SENSE... I'M A
SMALL WHITE IRRITANT TO WHICH
SOME PEOPLE HAVE INEXPLICABLY
ASSIGNED VALUE.
THIS WAS A BUSY WEEK, DOMINATED
BY THE DEMOCRATIC NATIONAL
CONVENTION, WHICH HAD TO BE HELD
VIRTUALLY THIS YEAR DUE TO...
Y'KNOW.
AND THIS MEANT THINGS LOOKED
SIGNIFICANTLY DIFFERENT... OR,
AS PEOPLE ON TV PREFERRED TO PUT
THAT:
WE'RE CALLING THIS THE
UNCONVENTIONAL CONVENTION.
AN UNCONVENTIONAL CONVENTION.
I KNOW EVERYONE HAS BEEN
SAYING... IT'S A CLICHE...
AN UNCONVENTIONAL CONVENTION,
AND IT HAS BEEN AN
UNCONVENTIONAL CONVENTION.
John: YEAH, OKAY, WE GET IT.
IT WAS AN "UNCONVENTIONAL
CONVENTION."
THE THING IS, THAT'S ONE OF
THOSE PHRASES THAT SOUNDS LIKE
IT HAS GRAVITY, BUT ACTUALLY
MEANS NEXT TO NOTHING, LIKE
"IT IS WHAT IT IS" OR
"QUIBI EXCLUSIVE."
AND WHILE THE LACK OF ATTENDEES
DID MAKE SOME THINGS AWKWARD,
THERE WERE UPSIDES, TOO.
FOR INSTANCE, THE ROLL CALL OF
DELEGATES WAS DONE VIRTUALLY
THIS YEAR, WITH STATES AND
TERRITORIES FINDING NOVEL WAYS
TO SHOWCASE THEMSELVES.
HAWAII RUBBED THEIR BEACHES IN
EVERYONE'S FACE, PETE BUTTIGIEG
SHOWED OFF WHAT I CAN ONLY
ASSUME IS HIS NEW SOCIAL MEDIA
START-UP, AND THE ENTIRE
POPULATION OF MONTANA TURNED UP.
BUT IT WAS THE STATE OF
RHODE ISLAND THAT STOLE THE SHOW
WITH THIS MOMENT.
RHODE ISLAND, THE OCEAN
STATE.
OUR STATE APPETIZER,
CALAMARI, IS AVAILABLE
IN ALL 50 STATES.
John: YEAH, THAT WAS RHODE
ISLAND'S DEMOCRATIC PARTY
CHAIRMAN PLEDGING DELEGATES
WHILE STANDING NEXT TO
A CALAMARI NINJA.
AND I HAD NO IDEA THAT CALAMARI
WAS RHODE ISLAND'S OFFICIAL
STATE APPETIZER.
IT MIGHT BE THE FIRST THING I'VE
LEARNED ABOUT THAT STATE THAT
I'VE ACTUALLY LIKED.
ASIDE FROM, OF COURSE, THE FACT
THAT IT DOESN'T INCLUDE THE CITY
OF DANBURY, CONNECTICUT.
I'VE SAID IT BEFORE:
FUCK DANBURY!
BABIES, ELDERLY, PETS, BUILDINGS
...ALL OF YOU CAN GO FUCK
YOURSELVES.
IN TERMS OF TONE, THE DNC SPENT
THE WEEK STEERING HARD TOWARD
THE MIDDLE OF THE ROAD.
BECAUSE WHILE, YES, THERE WERE
BRIEF APPEARANCES FROM STARS
LIKE AOC AND STACEY ABRAMS,
A LOT OF TIME WAS GIVEN TO
REPUBLICANS LIKE MEG WHITMAN,
COLIN POWELL, AND JOHN KASICH,
WHO DELIVERED HIS REMARKS
STANDING AT A LITERAL
CROSSROADS.
AND IT'S HARD TO CONVINCE
PROGRESSIVE VOTERS THAT YOU'RE
A FORWARD-LOOKING PARTY WHEN
YOUR CONVENTION FEELS LIKE A
ZOOM CAST REUNION, EXCEPT
THE SHOW IS "THE 2008 RNC."
AS FOR BIDEN, HIS NOMINATION
SPEECH ALSO PLAYED IT SAFE,
SHOWCASING HIS WARMTH AND
HIS EMPATHY.
BUT WHILE HE NAME-CHECKED
BROAD GOALS LIKE "EXPANDING
CHILD CARE" OR "ENDING RACISM,"
THE SPEECH WAS LIGHT ON DETAIL,
AND HEAVY ON LINES LIKE THIS:
THIS WILL DETERMINE WHAT
AMERICA IS GOING TO LOOK LIKE
FOR A LONG, LONG TIME.
CHARACTER IS ON THE BALLOT.
COMPASSION IS ON THE BALLOT.
DECENCY, SCIENCE, DEMOCRACY.
THEY'RE ALL ON THE BALLOT.
John: OKAY, NOW NORMALLY I
WOULD POINT OUT THAT PASSION AND
DECENCY ARE NOT
OPEN AUTHORITARIANISM
INITIATIVES, CONSIDERING
IS ALSO ON THE BALLOT, SURE,
WHAT THE FUCK... ADEQUATE VS.
EVIL.
LET'S GO.
AND I'M HONESTLY NOT SAYING IT'S
A MISTAKE FOR THE DNC TO SPEND
FOUR DAYS POINTING OUT THAT
JOE BIDEN'S NOT DONALD TRUMP.
IT'S A VERY ATTRACTIVE QUALITY.
BUT SPENDING SO MUCH OF THEIR
CONVENTION UNDERSCORING TRUMP'S
UNFITNESS FOR OFFICE MAY'VE BEEN
REDUNDANT, GIVEN THAT TRUMP
SPENT THE ENTIRE WEEK BASICALLY
MAKING THAT CASE FOR THEM,
BY CONTINUING TO SOW DISTRUST
OF VOTING BY MAIL, CALLING FOR
A BOYCOTT OF AN AMERICAN COMPANY
THAT EMPLOYS OVER 60,000
WORKERS, AND REFUSING TO DISAVOW
THE QANON CONSPIRACY THEORY.
BUT AS APPALLING AND
UNSURPRISING AS ALL OF THAT IS,
THE BIGGEST NEWS REGARDING HIM
ACTUALLY GOT BURIED THIS WEEK,
AND IT WAS THIS:
TONIGHT, THE REPUBLICAN-LED
SENATE INTELLIGENCE COMMITTEE
RELEASING ITS FINAL REPORT,
DECLARING THE 2016 TRUMP
CAMPAIGN HAD REPEATED CONTACTS
WITH RUSSIAN OPERATIVES.
John: YEAH, THE SENATE'S
REPORT CONFIRMED TRUMP'S
CAMPAIGN WAS UNCOMFORTABLY CLOSE
TO RUSSIAN INTELLIGENCE.
IT'S SOMETHING WE ALREADY KNEW,
BUT IT IS STILL NICE TO HAVE IT
IN WRITING, LIKE WHEN YOUR DAD
SIGNS A BIRTHDAY CARD WITH
"I LOVE YOU."
SURE, HE MAY NOT BE EMOTIONALLY
READY TO SAY IT OUT LOUD, BUT AT
LEAST HE HAD YOUR MOM SCRIBBLE
IT ON TOP OF GARFIELD'S ASS.
THAT'S NOT NOTHING.
IS IT?
THIS REPORT HAS NEW DETAILS, AND
CITES TRUMP'S FORMER CAMPAIGN
MANAGER, PAUL MANAFORT'S
WILLINGNESS TO SHARE INFORMATION
WITH INDIVIDUALS CLOSELY
AFFILIATED WITH RUSSIAN
INTELLIGENCE AS A GRAVE
COUNTERINTELLIGENCE THREAT.
NOT ONLY THAT, IT DETAILS HOW
ROGER STONE TRIED TO GET
WIKILEAKS TO DROP DAMAGING
EMAILS FROM HILLARY CLINTON'S
CAMPAIGN CHAIR, JUST AS THE
"ACCESS HOLLYWOOD" TAPE
CAME OUT.
AND WHILE TRUMP DENIED KNOWLEDGE
OF STONE'S ACTIVITIES TO
ROBERT MUELLER, THIS REPORT HAS
PUT ONE HELL OF AN ASTERISK
ON THAT.
THE COMMITTEE ASSESSES THAT
TRUMP DID, IN FACT, SPEAK WITH
STONE ABOUT WIKILEAKS ON
MULTIPLE OCCASIONS.
John: YEAH, OF COURSE.
NOT ONLY DID EVERYONE ASSUME
THAT, BUT IT'S IMPOSSIBLE
TRUMP WOULDN'T HAVE REMEMBERED
THAT CONVERSATION.
HOW WOULD ANYONE FORGET TALKING
TO ROGER STONE, A MAN WHO CAN
BEST BE DESCRIBED AS
VISUALLY TOO FUCKING MUCH?
THE BIPARTISAN REPORT... WHICH,
REMEMBER, COMES FROM A
REPUBLICAN-LED SENATE COMMITTEE
...IS A TRULY DAMNING INDICTMENT
OF TRUMP'S CHARACTER,
UNDERSCORING JUST HOW IMPORTANT
THE ELECTION IN NOVEMBER IS.
AND AS MUCH AS THE DNC'S
PLATFORM OF "BIDEN IS NOT TRUMP"
SHOULD BE AN OVERWHELMINGLY
SUCCESSFUL STRATEGY, THE TRUTH
IS TRUMP STILL HAS A VERY REAL
CHANCE AT WINNING RE-ELECTION.
TAKE THAT RHODE ISLAND CALIMARI
CHEF.
"THE WASHINGTON POST" TRACKED
HIM DOWN, AND HE SAID HE'S NOT
SURE IF HE'LL VOTE FOR BIDEN
AT ALL, ADDING, HE DOESN'T
KNOW MUCH ABOUT THE DEMOCRATIC
NOMINEE.
AND IT'S PRETTY FRUSTRATING TO
CLAIM YOU'RE ONLY VAGUELY AWARE
OF BIDEN.
BECAUSE WE'RE TALKING ABOUT A
FORMER VICE PRESIDENT WHO'S BEEN
IN PUBLIC OFFICE FOR NEARLY
50 YEARS, NOT
PENN FUCKING BADGLEY.
AND WHILE YOUR INSTINCTIVE
REACTION MIGHT BE, "HOW THE FUCK
CAN ANYONE STILL BE UNDECIDED?"
THE SAD FACT IS, LOTS OF PEOPLE
STILL ARE.
SO I REALLY HOPE THE DNC'S
STRATEGY THIS WEEK OF WOOING
UNDECIDED VOTERS WITH THE STAR
POWER OF JOHN KASICH AND
MEG WHITMAN PAYS OFF.
BECAUSE IF THE DEMOCRATS JUST
SPENT A WEEK WOOING CONSERVATIVE
WHO ULTIMATELY END
UP VOTING REPUBLICAN, THEN THIS
WILL HAVE TURNED OUT TO BE
A DEPRESSINGLY CONVENTIONAL
CONVENTION.
AND NOW THIS.
Announcer: AND NOW...
YES, IT'S STILL AUGUST, BUT
GUESS WHO'S BACK?
PUMPKIN SPICE SEASON IS
STARTING EARLIER THAN EVER THIS
YEAR.
I FEEL LIKE EVERY YEAR, IT GETS
EARLIER AND EARLIER.
PUMPKIN SPICE SEASON HAS COME
EARLIER AND IS COMING FOR THE
REMAINS OF YOUR FRAGILE PSYCHE!
WE ALL KNOW PUMPKIN SPICE
SEASON, IT IS INEVITABLE.
IS INEVITABLE!
YOU SHALL BE CRADLED IN THE
FRAGMENT PUMPKIN ARMS OF THE
SPICE!
IF YOU WANT TO GO BUY A
PUMPKIN COFFEE, DO IT.
DO IT.
DO IT!
ARE YOU PUMPKIN SPICE?
I'M NOT.
NO, I'M NOT EITHER.
WE JUST WANT THE REGULAR
COFFEE.
YOU CAN'T HAVE IT!
REGULAR COFFEE LIKE THE PRECIOUS
THOUGHTS OF A MARBLE FRIEND IS
NOT LIKE A VIVID MEMORY!
I HAVE NEVER HAD A PUMPKIN
SPICE LATTE.
IT IS REALLY GOOD.
OH, MY GOD, IT IS SO FUCKING
GOOD!
YOU HAVE TO TRY IT!
JILL!
EVERY YEAR, PEOPLE WHO LIKE
PUMPKIN SPICE KIND OF GET MADE
FUN OF.
YES, THEY DO.
2020 HAS BEEN, MIGHT I SAY,
HE DUM DUMPSTER FIRE.
LET THEM HAVE THE PUMPKIN SPICE.
PUMPKIN SPICE IS ALL WE HAVE
LEFT!
John: MOVING ON.
FOR OUR MAIN STORY TONIGHT,
WE THOUGHT WE'D LOOK AT
THE BORDER WALL.
ONE OF THE MORE DEPRESSING
THINGS FROM 2016, TIED WITH THE
REBOOT OF "GILMORE GIRLS CLOSE."
WHO WAS PAUL?
NOT ENOUGH PARIS.
WINDED BOTH OF THESE WOMEN
FORGET?
WHO THE ABSOLUTE FUCK WAS PAUL?
#TeamLoganForLife.
IT WAS THE KEY PROMISE OF
TRUMP'S FIRST CAMPAIGN.
HE TALKED ABOUT IT CONSTANTLY,
EVEN FAMOUSLY MANAGING TO
INADVERTENTLY POINT OUT KEY
FLAWS IN THE IDEA, LIKE THIS:
THERE'S NO LADDER GOING
OVER THAT.
IF THEY EVER GET UP THERE,
THEY'RE IN TROUBLE, BECAUSE
THERE'S NO WAY TO GET DOWN.
MAYBE A ROPE.
John: YEAH, MAYBE A ROPE.
THAT WAS TRUMP, RECOGNIZING IN
REAL TIME THAT HIS SIGNATURE
PLAN COULD BE COMPLETELY UNDONE
BY THICK STRING.
IF THAT CLIP'S FAMILIAR TO YOU,
IT MIGHT BE BECAUSE WE PLAYED IT
IN OUR FIRST PIECE ON THE WALL
FOUR YEARS AGO, WHEN I WAS
APPROXIMATELY 50 YEARS YOUNGER.
AND IN THAT SHOW, WE DISCUSSED
HOW THE WALL SEEMED... IN
ADDITION TO BEING TRANSPARENTLY
RACIST... LIKE IT WAS GOING TO
BE BOTH EXPENSIVE AND POINTLESS.
WELL, I DON'T KNOW IF YOU'VE
NOTICED, BUT TRUMP IS PRESIDENT
NOW, AND HAS SPENT THE LAST
THREE AND A HALF YEARS PUTTING
HIS PLAN INTO ACTION.
IN FACT, JUST BEFORE THE
PANDEMIC, HE WAS REASSURING
ATTENDEES AT A RALLY THAT THINGS
WERE GOING GREAT.
WE'LL SOON BE BUILDING MANY
MANY MILES A WEEK, BUT WE'RE UP
TO OVER 125.
I GUESS, 127 OR 28 MILES OF THIS
SUPER-DUPER WALL, SUPER-DUPER.
John: I'M SORRY,
"THE SUPER-DUPER WALL?"
THAT SOUNDS LESS LIKE A
DESCRIPTION OF BORDER FENCING
AND MORE LIKE THE NAME OF AN
OFF-BRAND PLAY SET RECALLED
BECAUSE IT COLLAPSED ON A BUNCH
OF SMALL CHILDREN.
LISTEN TO ME!
DO NOT BUY "THE SUPER-DUPER
WALL!"
UNLESS YOU WANT TO WIND UP WITH
A PILE OF CRACKED FIBERGLASS AND
A FLATTENED TODDLER.
BUT CLEARLY, THE WALL IS BY NO
MEANS SUPER-DUPER.
AND WHILE WE PREDICTED THE WHOLE
THING WOULD BE A SHAMBLES,
THE EXTENT TO WHICH THAT'S BEEN
TRUE, EVEN WE DIDN'T SEE COMING.
TAKE WHAT HAPPENED JUST THIS
THURSDAY.
STEVE BANNON AND THREE OTHERS
ARE ACCUSED OF DEFRAUDING
HUNDREDS OF THOUSANDS OF PEOPLE
BY PERSONALLY PROFITING OFF
ASCHEME TO RAISE MONEY TO HELP
BUILD PRESIDENT TRUMP'S
BORDER WALL.
John: YEAH, STEVE BANNON,
THE PRESIDENT'S CAMPAIGN MANAGER
AND FORMER CHIEF STRATEGIST,
WAS ARRESTED!
WHICH IS ONE OF THOSE THINGS
YOU KNEW WOULD EVENTUALLY
HAPPEN, BUT ARE PLEASANTLY
SURPRISED THAT IT HAPPENED SO
SOON, LIKE JENNIFER LAWRENCE'S
OSCAR WIN, OR ROGER AILES'
DEATH.
AND THE STORY BEHIND THAT ARREST
IS ABSOLUTELY FASCINATING, AND I
PROMISE WE'LL GET INTO IT LATER
IN THIS PIECE.
BUT WE THOUGHT TONIGHT...
ESPECIALLY AHEAD OF THE RNC
NEXT WEEK... IT'D BE A GOOD TIME
TO GIVE YOU AN UPDATE ON THE
STATUS OF TRUMP'S BORDER WALL.
BECAUSE BEFORE HE TOOK OFFICE,
HE WANTED IT TO DEFINE HIM AS
A PRESIDENT.
AND THAT HAS VERY MUCH HAPPENED,
BUT IN NONE OF THE WAYS
THAT HE INTENDED.
SO LET'S TRY AND BREAK DOWN
A FEW THINGS: WHAT HE'S BUILT,
WHAT DAMAGE IT'S DONE, AND
CRUCIALLY, WHO'S BEEN DOING
SOME OF THE BUILDING.
AND LET'S START WITH WHAT,
EXACTLY, HE HAS BUILT.
BECAUSE FROM THE START, TRUMP
INSISTED THAT HE WANTED A
CONCRETE WALL... SOMETHING MANY
BORDER PATROL AGENTS HAD ADVISED
HIM AGAINST BECAUSE IT WOULD
BLOCK THEIR VIEW OF WHAT WAS
GOING ON BEHIND IT.
YET TRUMP WAS STILL SO INSISTENT
ON IT THAT LESS THAN A YEAR INTO
HIS TERM, THIS HAPPENED.
PRESIDENT TRUMP SAID HE
WANTED A BIG, FAT BEAUTIFUL
WALL.
THESE ARE HIS 30 BY 30 FOOT
OPTIONS.
ONE OF THESE EIGHT CONTESTANTS
COULD SOON STRETCH ACROSS THE
BORDER.
THERE'S A CHANCE THAT ONE OF
THEM GETS... ONE OF THEM GETS
ELECTED, EIGHT OF THEM GET
SELECTED, OR A MIX OF THEIR
CHARACTERISTICS GET SELECTED FOR
CONSTRUCTION.
John: YEAH, TRUMP ESSENTIALLY
ORGANIZED A WALL PAGEANT.
AND LOOK, IF YOU'RE GOING TO
HOLD A WEIRD CONTEST IN THE
MIDDLE OF THE DESERT, AT LEAST
MAKE IT SAUDI ARABIA'S ACTUAL
BEAUTY PAGEANT FOR CAMELS.
A REAL, ANNUAL EVENT WHERE THE
HOTTEST CAMELS ARE EVALUATED ON
THE "FULLNESS OF THEIR LIPS,
HOW GRACEFULLY THEY WALK, AND
THE SIZE OF THEIR HUMPS."
AND YOU MIGHT BE THINKING, "WOW,
IT'S PRETTY PROBLEMATIC TO
OBJECTIFY CAMELS LIKE THAT,"
BUT THE FACT IS, THIS CONTEST IS
ACTUALLY ONE OF THE BIGGEST
SCHOLARSHIP OPPORTUNITIES THEY
HAVE.
AND DO YOU REALLY THINK NOW IS
THE TIME TO ARGUE WE NEED FEWER
CAMELS IN STEM?
OF COURSE NOT.
GET REAL.
BE AN ALLY.
BUT IT'S TRUE.
EIGHT PROTOTYPES WERE BUILT, SO
THEY COULD TEST THEM TO FIGURE
OUT WHICH WOULD WORK BEST.
AND IT DIDN'T GO WELL.
A GOVERNMENT REPORT FOUND EVERY
MOCK-UP WAS "DEEMED VULNERABLE
TO AT LEAST ONE BREACHING
TECHNIQUE," WITH ONE HAVING
THE "POTENTIAL TO IMPACT
THE STRUCTURAL INTEGRITY OF
THE ENTIRE MOCK-UP."
WHICH IS RIDICULOUS.
WE ALL KNOW, THE ONLY WALL THAT
SHOULD BE IN DANGER OF
COLLAPSING IS THE
"SUPER-DUPER WALL!"
I'M SERIOUS... DO NOT BUY THAT
WALL!
IT WILL SQUISH YOUR CHILD
LIKE A PANINI.
SO THE DESIGN THEY ENDED UP
GOING WITH WAS A WALL OF SLATS,
OR BOLLARDS, TOPPED BY A METAL
ANTI-CLIMBING PLATE.
AND TRUMP DID NOT LIKE THAT,
REPORTEDLY TELLING OFFICIALS
"HE THINKS IT'S UGLY."
AND I HAVE TO SAY... HE'S NOT
ACTUALLY WRONG THERE.
I DON'T MEAN TO WALL-SHAME,
BUT IF I HAD A LIST OF HOT
WALLS, THAT ONE WOULDN'T CRACK
THE TOP 30.
THIS STONE WALL?
SCORCHING HOT.
THIS WOODEN ONE?
CALL ME TOMORROW, YOU BIG,
TEASE.
THIS HUMAN WALL?
I THINK WE ALL KNOW I FEEL ABOUT
THAT.
COLLAPSE ON MY CHEST,
YOU IMPENETRABLE BARRIER.
CRUSH MY RIB CAGE, YOU
LOAD-BEARING BEHEMOTH.
BUT THIS BORDER WALL?
NO, THANK YOU.
THAT'S A HARD PASS FROM BOTH ME
AND THE PRESIDENT.
STILL, TRUMP INSISTS THAT
REGARDLESS OF HOW IT LOOKS,
THE IMPORTANT THING IS,
IT WORKS.
WE ACTUALLY BUILT PROTOTYPES
AND WE HAVE, I GUESS YOU COULD
SAY, WORLD-CLASS MOUNTAIN
CLIMBERS.
WE GOT CLIMBERS.
WE HAD 20 MOUNTAIN
CLIMBERS... THAT'S ALL THEY DO,
THEY LOVE TO CLIMB MOUNTAINS.
THEY CAN HAVE IT.
ME, I DON'T WANT TO CLIMB
MOUNTAINS.
BUT THEY'RE VERY GOOD.
AND SOME OF 'EM WERE CHAMPIONS.
AND WE GAVE THEM DIFFERENT
PROTOTYPES OF WALLS.
AND THIS WAS THE ONE THAT WAS
HARDEST TO CLIMB.
John: OKAY, HOLD ON.
THERE'S NO NEED FOR TRUMP TO SAY
"I DON'T WANT TO CLIMB
MOUNTAINS."
THAT WAS... AND I CANNOT STRESS
THIS ENOUGH... ASSUMED.
IF I KNEW NOTHING ELSE ABOUT
DONALD TRUMP, BASED SOLELY ON
HIS APPEARANCE, I'D IMMEDIATELY
MAKE THREE ASSUMPTIONS:
BAD KNEES.
WEIRD DICK.
DOESN'T WANT TO CLIMB MOUNTAINS.
HE'S GIVING ME INFORMATION
I ALREADY HAVE.
AND OBVIOUSLY, THAT CLAIM IS
BULLSHIT, NOT JUST BECAUSE
NOBODY'S BEEN ABLE TO FIND THOSE
CHAMPION CLIMBERS, BUT ALSO
BECAUSE OF THIS:
PRESIDENT TRUMP HAS CALLED
THESE REFURBISHED WALLS
UNCLIMBABLE.
BUT THIS VIDEO POSTED JUST
YESTERDAY ON SOCIAL MEDIA SHOWS
TWO MEN SCALING A REPLACED
PORTION OF THE WALL IN
CALIFORNIA.
John: YEAH, OF COURSE!
YOU DON'T EVEN NEED A ROPE IF IT
CAN FUNCTION LIKE A FIREMAN'S
POLE.
SO TO RECAP WHAT WE'VE LEARNED
ABOUT WALLS SO FAR: FUCKABLE.
DEFINITELY FUCKABLE.
AND VERY MUCH CLIMBABLE.
SO THAT IS WHAT THE WALL
LOOKS LIKE.
THE NEXT QUESTION IS WHERE,
EXACTLY, ARE WE BUILDING IT?
WELL, AS WE POINTED OUT IN OUR
FIRST PIECE, FINDING PLACES
WHERE YOU CAN BUILD THE WALL IS
A BIT OF A CHALLENGE.
UNDER PRESIDENTS CLINTON, BUSH,
AND OBAMA, HUNDREDS OF MILES OF
BORDER BARRIER HAD ALREADY BEEN
CONSTRUCTED, AND MUCH OF THE
REST OF THE BORDER IS ALREADY
COVERED BY NATURAL BARRIERS,
OR IS ON PRIVATE PROPERTY.
SO WHAT TRUMP DID WAS START
BUILDING IN THE PLACES WHERE IT
WAS EASIEST TO DO THAT...
SPECIFICALLY, WHERE BARRIERS
WERE ALREADY IN PLACE.
IN FACT, OF THE 275 MILES OF
NEW WALL TRUMP HAS COMPLETED
TO DATE, ONLY FIVE MILES ARE IN
LOCATIONS WHERE NO BARRIERS
AT ALL PREVIOUSLY EXISTED.
IT MAY BE TEMPTING TO THINK,
"OH, WELL, THEN HE HASN'T DONE
VERY MUCH, HAS HE?"
BUT TRUMP'S ACTING SECRETARY OF
HOMELAND SECURITY, A MAN NAMED
CHAD WOLF, PUSHES BACK ON THAT
CLAIM, HARD.
AND YOU PUT UP WHAT'S BEHIND
US.
THAT'S NOT REPLACEMENT WALL.
THAT IS A NEW WALL.
THAT IS A NEW PHYSICAL
INFRASTRUCTURE.
I JUST... I DON'T... I DON'T
AGREE WITH THE ASSERTION THAT
WE'RE SIMPLY REPLACING WALL.
John: OKAY, FIRST, LET'S DEAL
WITH THE SHEER "CHAD WOLF" -INESS
OF THIS MAN.
IF I LOST ALL OF MY MEMORIES AND
FELL INTO A COMA FOR 30 YEARS,
OPENED MY EYES, AND SAW HIM,
THE FIRST WORDS OUT OF MY MOUTH
WOULD BE, "YOU MUST BE
CHAD WOLF."
HE LOOKS LIKE THE MODEL FOR A
KNOCKOFF "TOP GUN" COSTUME
YOU FIND AT PARTY CITY CALLED,
"TOP FLIGHT FAST PILOT COSTUME:
USA!"
HE LOOKS LIKE HIS PARENTS
STARTED WITH THE NAME
"CHAD WOLF" AND THEN FOUND
A BABY TO MATCH.
BUT HE IS ACTUALLY RIGHT THERE.
THE REPLACEMENT WALL IS
A COMPLETELY NEW PHYSICAL
INFRASTRUCTURE.
I'LL SHOW YOU: HERE'S THE OLD
BARRIER IN A SECTION OF
ARIZONA.
HERE IS THE NEW STRUCTURE.
THOSE ARE VERY DIFFERENT.
CLAIMING THAT THEY'RE THE SAME
BECAUSE THEY'RE TECHNICALLY
BARRIERS IS LIKE CLAIMING THAT
JOHN CENA AND I ARE THE SAME
BECAUSE WE'RE THE EXACT SAME
AGE AND WE'RE BOTH NAMED JOHN.
SURE, YEAH, ON PAPER, THERE ARE
SOME SIMILARITIES.
BUT WHEN YOU COMPARE THE TWO
SIDE BY SIDE, ONE IS GIGANTIC,
AND THE OTHER LOOKS LIKE IT
MIGHT COLLAPSE IF YOU PRESS ON
IT TOO HARD.
BUT, CRUCIALLY, THESE MASSIVE
NEW BARRIERS ARE CAUSING
SIGNIFICANT PROBLEMS, DISRUPTING
ANIMALS' MIGRATORY PATTERNS, AND
SLICING UP PEOPLE'S LAND.
AND THE THING IS, FOR WHAT?
IF THIS IS ABOUT STOPPING DRUGS
OR PEOPLE FROM ENTERING THE
COUNTRY, IT'S WORTH REMEMBERING,
MOST OF THAT HAPPENS THROUGH OUR
PORTS OF ENTRY.
AND EVEN THE DEPARTMENT OF
HOMELAND SECURITY'S OWN
INSPECTOR GENERAL ISSUED
A SCATHING REPORT JUST LAST
MONTH SAYING THE ADMINISTRATION
"DID NOT USE A SOUND METHODOLOGY
TO IDENTIFY AND PRIORITIZE
INVESTMENTS IN AREAS ALONG THE
BORDER THAT WOULD BEST BENEFIT
FROM PHYSICAL BARRIERS."
IN OTHER WORDS, PUTTING WALLS
WHERE WE'VE BEEN PUTTING THEM
JUST DOESN'T MAKE SENSE.
AND IF YOU WANT TO SEE JUST HOW
NONSENSICAL, NEW SECTIONS ARE
CURRENTLY GOING UP ALONG
THE TOP OF THESE JAGGED
MOUNTAINS IN A NATIONAL WILDLIFE
REFUGE, WHICH IS JUST UTTERLY
INSANE.
AND THIS IS COSTING A LOT OF
MONEY.
MEXICO, OBVIOUSLY, IS NOT PAYING
FOR THE WALL.
INSTEAD, WE ARE, AND IN THE
DUMBEST WAY POSSIBLE.
SO FAR TRUMP HAS GARNERED
$15 BILLION OF TAXPAYER MONEY
FOR THE WALL... BUT ONLY
$5 BILLION OF THAT WAS PROVIDED
BY CONGRESS.
TRUMP DECLARED A NATIONAL
EMERGENCY AT THE SOUTHERN BORDER
SO HE COULD TAP INTO PENTAGON
ACCOUNTS FOR THE REST.
THAT REDIRECTION OF FUNDS
DIVERTED MONEY THAT HAD BEEN SET
ASIDE FOR THINGS LIKE REPLACING
AN OVERCROWDED MIDDLE SCHOOL ON
A KENTUCKY MILITARY BASE, OR
REPAIRING A DAYCARE FOR SERVICE
MEMBERS' CHILDREN, WHICH
REPORTEDLY SUFFERED FROM SEWAGE
BACKUPS, FLOODING, MOLD, AND
PESTS.
AND WHEN ASKED TO JUSTIFY
THOSE DECISIONS,
SENATOR LINDSEY GRAHAM HAD
A PRETTY AMAZING RATIONALE.
LET'S JUST SAY FOR A MOMENT
THAT HE TOOK SOME MONEY OUT OF
THE MILITARY CONSTRUCTION
BUDGET.
I WOULD SAY IT'S BETTER FOR
THE MIDDLE SCHOOL KIDS
IN KENTUCKY TO HAVE
A SECURE BORDER.
WE'LL GET THEM THE SCHOOL THEY
NEED, BUT RIGHT NOW, WE'VE GOT
A NATIONAL EMERGENCY ON OUR
HANDS.
John: WOW.
EVERYTHING ABOUT THAT IS BAD.
FROM THE IDEA THAT TRUMP'S
NATIONAL EMERGENCY DECLARATION
WAS JUSTIFIED... WHICH IT
WASN'T.
TO THE IDEA THAT HIS VANITY
PROJECT IS "BETTER FOR MIDDLE
SCHOOL KIDS" THAN A NEW SCHOOL,
WHICH IT'S NOT.
TO THAT TIE, WHICH LOOKS LIKE
A CANDY CANE THAT MELTED ON HIS
SHIRT.
IT LOOKS LIKE THE TIE THAT
SANTA CLAUS WEARS TO
ELF FUNERALS.
IT'S THE WORST THING IN THAT
SHOT, WHICH IS SAYING SOMETHING
BECAUSE THAT SHOT ALSO INCLUDES
LINDSEY GRAHAM.
AND THAT BRINGS US TO OUR FINAL
QUESTION: WHO'S BUILDING THIS?
BECAUSE THE ANSWERS TO THAT ARE
ACTUALLY A LITTLE SURPRISING.
JUST LOOK AT ONE OF THE
COMPANIES THAT WAS INVITED TO
TAKE PART IN THAT AMERICA'S NEXT
TOP WALL IN THE DESERT
COMPETITION,
FISHER SAND & GRAVEL.
THE HEAD OF THE COMPANY,
TOMMY FISHER, KNOWS HOW TO CURRY
FAVOR WITH TRUMP.
HERE HE IS ON LAURA INGRAHAM'S
SHOW, GIVING HIM THE HARD SELL.
IF HE ALLOWS US TO PLAY IN,
OUR TEAM OF FISHER INDUSTRIES TO
PLAY, I GUARANTEE YOU, NO
DIFFERENT THAN TOM BRADY, ONCE
WE GET IN, WE NEVER COME OUT.
AND IF WE DON'T PERFORM,
THE PRESIDENT CAN FIRE US,
AND THAT'S HOW COMFORTABLE AND
CONFIDENT I AM IS WHEN PEOPLE
SEE WHAT WE REALLY OFFER.
I LOVE IT!
I LOVE IT.
I'M NOT TAKING SIDES ON WHICH
PROTOTYPE IS BEST, BUT THIS IS
WHY YOU'RE A GOOD BUSINESSMAN.
John: "I LOVE IT!"
I DIDN'T THINK LAURA INGRAHAM
WAS CAPABLE OF THAT LEVEL OF
DELIGHT, BUT IT TURNS OUT HER
LOVE LANGUAGE IS WHITE MEN
BEGGING FOR ATTENTION.
BECAUSE THAT MAN IS THIRSTY
AS FUCK.
"I'LL WIN FOR YOU, DADDY, JUST
LIKE THAT TOM BRADY YOU LIKE!
AND IF I DON'T, YOU CAN FIRE ME
LIKE YOU USED TO ON TV."
AND THAT WAS, BY NO MEANS,
FISHER'S ONLY APPEARANCE ON FOX.
HE WENT ON THE NETWORK TEN TIMES
TO PRAISE THE PRESIDENT AND SELL
HIS WALL.
AND THESE APPEARANCES SEEMED TO
HAVE AN EFFECT.
BECAUSE WHILE BOTH DHS AND THE
ARMY CORPS OF ENGINEERS ACTUALLY
TURNED DOWN FISHER'S INITIAL
WALL DESIGNS BECAUSE THEY DIDN'T
MEET OPERATIONAL REQUIREMENTS,
FISHER'S COMPANY WAS
NEVERTHELESS ADDED TO A SMALL
LIST OF PRE-APPROVED BIDDERS
THANKS TO PERSONAL PRESSURE FROM
THE PRESIDENT, WHO... ACCORDING
TO ONE OF THE SENATORS FROM
FISHER'S HOME STATE... LIKED
FISHER BECAUSE HE HAD SEEN HIM
ON TELEVISION.
AND OF COURSE HE DID!
TRUMP IS LIKE A SHUT-IN WHO SITS
AT HOME ALL DAY AND ORDERS WHAT
HE SEES ON FOX, BUT INSTEAD OF
ORDERING LEGENDZ XL MALE
ENHANCEMENT PILLS, HE PICKS
COMPANIES TO BUILD A GIANT WALL
ACROSS THE BORDER.
BUT JUST AS WITH BONER PILLS,
YOU SHOULDN'T JUST BUY SOMETHING
BECAUSE YOU SAW IT ON TV.
YOU MIGHT WANT TO AT LEAST
GOOGLE IT FIRST.
BECAUSE FISHER'S COMPANY HAD
A LOT OF OBVIOUS RED FLAGS.
FISHER HAS BEEN HIT WITH
LAWSUITS, ONE FROM THE FEDERAL
GOVERNMENT FOR SEXUAL
DISCRIMINATION IN NEW MEXICO.
IT SETTLED FOR 150 GRAND.
THE COMPANY AND THE FOUNDER'S
SON WERE BOTH ACCUSED OF
TAX FRAUD IN 2009.
THE SON PLEADED GUILTY,
THE COMPANY PAID MORE THAN A
MILLION IN BACK TAXES.
John: WOW.
SO THEY CHEATED TO GET AHEAD,
GOT CAUGHT, AND YET, THEY'RE
STILL AROUND.
THEY REALLY ARE THE TOM BRADY OF
THE CONSTRUCTION INDUSTRY.
BUT WAIT, THERE'S MORE, BECAUSE
OVER THE YEARS, THEY'VE ALSO
RACKED UP AROUND 2,000 VIOLATION
NOTICES FROM CITY, COUNTY,
STATE, AND FEDERAL REGULATORY
BODIES, INCLUDING 469 CRIMINAL
CHARGES FOR VIOLATIONS IN
PHOENIX, WHERE THE COMPANY RAN
AN ASPHALT PLANT... CHARGES ONLY
REDUCED TO CIVIL PENALTIES AFTER
FISHER AGREED TO PERMANENTLY
CLOSE IT.
BUT WAIT... I'M NOT DONE.
LOCAL GOVERNMENTS HAVE REJECTED
THEIR BIDS ON CONTRACTS DUE TO
EVEN MORE SKETCHY DETAILS FROM
THEIR PAST, INCLUDING THE FACT
THE FORMER HEAD OF THEIR FAMILY
OF COMPANIES, FISHER INDUSTRIES,
WAS CONVICTED FOR
CHILD PORNOGRAPHY.
AND SEXUAL HARASSMENT,
TAX FRAUD, FEDERAL VIOLATIONS,
AND CHILD PORNOGRAPHY IS NOT A
GREAT LIST FOR A COMPANY VYING
TO RECEIVE GOVERNMENT MONEY,
IT'S NOT EVEN A GREAT LIST FOR
THE "OZARK" SEASON FOUR WRITER'S
ROOM.
GUYS, GUYS, THAT'S TOO MUCH.
NOT EVEN JASON BATEMAN CAN MAKE
THOSE CRIMES LIKEABLE!
AND YET, FISHER WAS INCREDIBLY
SAVVY ABOUT HOW TO APPEAL TO
TRUMP... NOT JUST WITH HIS
CONSTANT TV APPEARANCES, BUT
ALSO BY HOOKING UP WITH "WE
BUILD THE WALL"... THAT IS THE
NON-PROFIT ORGANIZATION THAT
LED TO STEVE BANNON'S ARREST
ON THURSDAY.
IT WAS FOUNDED BY A VETERAN
NAMED BRIAN KOLFAGE, AND IT TOOK
MONEY FROM INDIVIDUAL DONORS,
WITH THE PROMISE THAT IT WOULD
BUILD NEW SECTIONS OF WALL ON
PRIVATE LAND.
IT EVEN HAD A FUNDRAISING
"WALL-A-THON," FEATURING A STAR
TURN FROM A MAN CALLING HIMSELF
"FOREMAN MIKE":
WE BUILD THE WALL
CONSTRUCTION.
THEY ARE REAL!
WE NEED YOUR HELP.
WE NEED TO GET DONATIONS IN.
WE WANT TO START.
YOU CAN BUY A BOLLARD PANEL.
PUT YOUR NAME ON IT FOR
ETERNITY, CAUSE YOU'RE NOT GONNA
LAST FOREVER.
$5,000.
AND IF YOU CAN'T DO THAT,
GET YOURSELF A BRICK.
IT LASTS FOREVER AS WELL WITH
YOUR NAME, YOUR FAMILY, YOUR
GIRLFRIEND, WHATEVER YOU WANT TO
PUT ON IT.
YOU NEED TO DONATE TODAY.
John: OKAY, THERE'S A LOT TO
DIGEST THERE.
BECAUSE DESPITE WHAT YOU MAY
THINK, "FOREMAN MIKE" IS NOT
A PROMO FOR A NEW WWE CHARACTER
WHOSE SIGNATURE MOVE IS
"THE CHAOTIC SALES PITCH."
IN FACT, HE ISN'T EVEN THE
FOREMAN ON THE PROJECT, JUST AS
"WE BUILD THE WALL CONSTRUCTION"
IS NOT A REAL CONSTRUCTION
COMPANY.
HE'S JUST SOME GUY THEY USE TO
FUNDRAISE, SO HE CAN GRUNT ABOUT
PERSONALIZED BRICKS.
WHICH I DO ADMIT ARE A GREAT
IDEA, BECAUSE WE ALL KNOW THE
BEST WAY TO DETER SOMEONE WHO'S
CROSSING THE BORDER IS FOR THEM
TO SEE THE MESSAGE, "TO THE ONE
AND ONLY KIERSTEN, MAY OUR LOVE
BE AS STRONG AS THIS WALL."
AND AS RIDICULOUS AS THAT MAY
SEEM, "WE BUILD THE WALL" RAISED
$25 MILLION.
AND YET, ACCORDING TO THIS
WEEK'S INDICTMENT, QUITE A BIT
OF THAT MONEY WOUND UP GETTING
REDIRECTED BACK TO BANNON AND
KOLFAGE, WHO... ALONG WITH
OTHERS... WORKED TOGETHER TO
MISAPPROPRIATE HUNDREDS OF
THOUSANDS OF DOLLARS FOR THEIR
OWN PERSONAL BENEFIT.
WITH BANNON ALLEGEDLY USING
MONEY FOR PERSONAL USES AND
EXPENSES, AND KOLFAGE ALLEGEDLY
SPENDING FUNDS ON A LUXURY SUV,
A GOLF CART, JEWELRY, AND
PAYMENTS TOWARD A BOAT.
AND LOOK, BANNON AND KOLFAGE
DENY THOSE CHARGES.
BUT IT DEFINITELY PAINTS THIS
MOMENT FROM THAT "WALL-A-THON"
IN A VERY DIFFERENT LIGHT:
WELCOME BACK, THIS IS
STEPHEN K. BANNON.
WE'RE OFF THE COAST OF
SAN TROPEZ IN SOUTHERN FRANCE IN
THE MEDITERRANEAN, WE'RE ON
THE MILLION-DOLLAR YACHT OF
BRIAN KOLFAGE... BRIAN KOLFAGE,
WHO TOOK ALL THAT MONEY FROM
BUILD THE WALL.
NO, WE'RE ACTUALLY IN
SUNLAND PARK, NEW MEXICO.
John: HA HA HA!
I GET IT!
JOKING ABOUT STEALING PEOPLE'S
MONEY IS FUNNY!
BECAUSE YOU KNOW WHAT THEY SAY,
ALL GREAT JOKES HAVE AN ELEMENT
OF TRUTH IN THEM.
NOW TRUMP WAS ANXIOUS THIS WEEK
TO DISTANCE HIMSELF FROM
"WE BUILD THE WALL," SAYING "I
KNOW NOTHING ABOUT THE PROJECT,"
WHICH IS A LITTLE HARD TO
BELIEVE, BECAUSE HERE'S KOLFAGE
WITH DON, JR., AT AN EVENT WHERE
HE DESCRIBED "WE BUILD THE WALL"
AS "PRIVATE ENTERPRISE AT ITS
FINEST."
AND HERE'S TRUMP ALLY
KRIS KOBACH ON THE GROUP'S OWN
YOUTUBE PAGE, BEING PRETTY
UNEQUIVOCAL ABOUT WHERE THE
PRESIDENT STOOD.
I WAS SPEAKING WITH THE
PRESIDENT AND WE WERE TALKING
ABOUT A VARIETY OF ISSUES, AND
THE TOPIC CAME UP... I MENTIONED
THAT I WAS WORKING WITH WE BUILD
THE WALL, AND HE SAID, WELL, YOU
TELL THE PEOPLE YOU ARE WORKING
WITH THAT THIS PROJECT HAS MY
BLESSING, AND HE WENT FURTHER,
AND HE SAID, I WANT THE MEDIA TO
KNOW THAT THIS PROJECT HAS MY
BLESSING.
HE WAS REALLY MAKING A POINT
THAT HE WAS BEHIND THIS.
John: YEAH, OF COURSE HE WAS!
I'M JUST SURPRISED KOBACH DIDN'T
CONTINUE, "THIS PRESIDENT WANTED
YOU TO KNOW HE'S COMPLETELY
BEHIND THIS WALL SCAM UNTIL IT
FAILS, AND THEN YOU'LL NOT BE
ABLE TO REACH HIM AND HE WON'T
HAVE HEARD OF YOU.
THAT'S JUST HOW THE GUY WORKS."
AND LOOK, TO BE FAIR, SOME OF
THAT $25 MILLION THEY RAISED DID
GO TO CONSTRUCTION.
SPECIFICALLY, THEY SAY THEY GAVE
AROUND $10 MILLION OF IT TO
TOMMY FISHER'S COMPANY, MOST OF
IT TO BUILD THAT PRIVATE WALL
IN NEW MEXICO THAT YOU SAW A GUY
NAMED MIKE BANGING WITH A
HAMMER.
AND THAT WALL DOES APPEAR TO
FEATURE SOME PERSONALIZED
BRICKS, LIKE THIS ONE THAT
KOLFAGE EXCITEDLY PUT ON
INSTAGRAM, WHICH SAYS,
"THICC LATINAS WILL NOT BE
DEPORTED," WHICH IS JUST FUCKING
DISGUSTING.
THE GROUP ALSO HELPED FUND
ANOTHER FISHER WALL, BUILT
DIRECTLY ALONG THE RIO GRANDE,
WHICH FISHER REFERRED TO AS THE
LAMBORGHINI OF WALLS, CLAIMING
THAT, "IT'LL STAND FOR
150 YEARS, YOU MARK MY WORDS."
ALTHOUGH IT SEEMS TO BE CONKING
OUT AROUND 149 YEARS AHEAD OF
SCHEDULE.
A PROPUBLICA AND
"TEXAS TRIBUNE" INVESTIGATION
FOUND EROSION BENEATH
THE FOUNDATION OF A STRETCH OF
WALL IN TEXAS.
THAT STRETCH WAS JUST BUILT IN
JANUARY OF THIS YEAR BY FISHER
SAND AND GRAVEL.
I'M JUST DOING THIS WITH ONE
HAND, NOT EVEN EXERTING MYSELF.
John: OKAY, SO
IT TURNS OUT, IT REALLY IS THE
LAMBORGHINI OF WALLS, IN
THAT AS SOON AS YOU GET NEAR IT,
THE OWNER YELLS, "HEY, PLEASE
DON'T TOUCH THAT, IT'LL LOSE
VALUE AND YOU COULD BREAK IT."
AND WHILE I HAVE TO TELL YOU,
FISHER'S ATTORNEY HAS TOLD
REPORTERS THAT EROSION IS A
NORMAL PART OF NEW CONSTRUCTION,
AND THAT IF THERE ARE ISSUES
THAT COME UP, THEY WILL ADDRESS
THAT.
EXPERTS SAID THAT IT WAS
CONCERNING AND THAT
SEGMENTS OF THE STRUCTURE COULD
TOPPLE INTO THE RIVER IF NOT
FIXED.
SO, TO RECAP: FISHER SAND &
GRAVEL IS A COMPANY WITH A
CHECKERED PAST THAT PARTNERED
WITH A SHADY NONPROFIT WHOSE
BACKERS ARE NOW UNDER INDICTMENT
FOR SKIMMING MONEY FOR THEIR OWN
USES, IN ORDER TO HAVE A FOREMAN
WHO'S NOT THE ACTUAL FOREMAN
HELP BUILD A WALL THAT LOOKS
LIKE IT MAY EITHER COLLAPSE
OR GET PUSHED OVER.
AND IF YOU KNOW ANYTHING ABOUT
THIS ADMINISTRATION, IT WILL NOT
SURPRISE YOU TO LEARN THAT
FISHER HAS NOW WOUND UP WITH
OVER $2 BILLION DOLLARS IN
BORDER-BUILDING CONTRACTS.
THEY'RE ONE OF THE BIGGEST
CONTRACTORS THE GOVERNMENT HAS
HIRED FOR THIS PROJECT.
AND THE THING IS, SHOULD TRUMP
BE RE-ELECTED, ALL OF THIS IS
ONLY GOING TO ACCELERATE... IN
FACT, HIS ADMINISTRATION SEEMS
TO BE STEPPING UP ITS EFFORTS,
ATTEMPTING TO TAKE PRIVATE LAND
BY FILING MORE EMINENT DOMAIN
LAWSUITS DURING THE PANDEMIC
THAN AT ANY OTHER TIME IN HIS
PRESIDENCY.
AND THEY'RE ALSO USING A
PROVISION TUCKED INTO
THE REAL ID ACT OF 2005, GIVING
THE ADMINISTRATION THE POWER TO
WAIVE ALL LEGAL REQUIREMENTS
NECESSARY TO CONSTRUCT THE WALL.
AND THAT MEANS IT'S NOT BOUND
BY ENVIRONMENTAL OR CULTURAL
HERITAGE PROTECTION LAWS, WHICH
HAS ENABLED THEM TO PLOW THROUGH
NATIVE AMERICAN COMMUNITIES,
WITH DEVASTATING EFFECTS.
CONSTRUCTION CREWS IN
SOUTHERN ARIZONA CONDUCTED
CONTROLLED BLASTS EARLIER THIS
YEAR ALONG MONUMENT HILL.
FIRE IN THE HOLE.
THE SAME DAY OF THE
DETONATIONS IN FEBRUARY, THE
TOHONO O'ODHAM TRIBE'S CHAIRMAN
SAT BEFORE CONGRESS.
IT'S HARD TO SEE THE BLASTING
THAT YOU SHOWED ON THE VIDEO
TODAY.
THAT AREA IS HOME TO OUR
ANCESTORS.
AND BY BLASTING AND DOING WHAT
WE SAW TODAY, HAS TOTALLY
DISTURBED... TOTALLY, FOREVER
DAMAGED OUR PEOPLE.
John: THAT'S HORRIBLE.
AS THAT MAN TOLD CONGRESS, "FOR
US, THIS IS NO DIFFERENT THAN
DHS BUILDING A 30-FOOT WALL
ALONG ARLINGTON CEMETERY OR
THROUGH THE GROUNDS OF THE
NATIONAL CATHEDRAL."
AND I'D LIKE TO THINK THAT'S
SOMETHING TRUMP KNOWS WOULD BE
WRONG, BUT WHO KNOWS, GIVEN THAT
HE HAD PEOPLE TEARGASSED SO HE
COULD STAND OUTSIDE A CHURCH,
HOLDING A BIBLE WITH AN
EXPRESSION LIKE IT JUST FUCKED
HIS WIFE.
AND THE DEVASTATION CAUSED BY
THIS WALL WAS COMPLETELY
PREDICTABLE.
I KNOW THAT, BECAUSE WE
LITERALLY PREDICTED IT.
AND BELIEVE ME,
THIS IS THE LAST THING I
WANTED TO SAY I TOLD YOU SO ON.
I'D MUCH RATHER HAVE SAID THAT
ABOUT THE FACT I KNEW PETE AND
ARIANA WEREN'T GOING TO MAKE IT
OR THAT A CROCKPOT WOULD BE THE
KILLER ON "THIS IS US," OR THE
FACT THAT I KNEW THE BABADOOK
WAS GAY AS SOON AS I SAW HIM.
C'MON, GUYS... THE HAT!
BUT EVEN I DIDN'T SEE SOME OF
THIS COMING... FROM THE
POINTLESSNESS OF A BEAUTY
CONTEST IN THE DESERT, ALL THE
WAY THROUGH A SKETCHY CHARITY
SELLING PERSONALIZED BRICKS.
ALL OF THIS WAS STUPIDER THAN
EVEN I THOUGHT WAS POSSIBLE.
BECAUSE THE FACT IS, THIS WALL
IS NOT A FUNCTIONAL BARRIER.
IF IT'S ANYTHING, IT'S A FUCKING
MONUMENT TO TRUMP.
WHICH ACTUALLY MAKES SENSE.
BECAUSE WE KNOW THAT HE'S
COMPLETELY OBSESSED WITH HIS
LEGACY.
TRUMP REPORTEDLY EVEN ASKED
SOUTH DAKOTA'S GOVERNOR HOW HE
COULD BE ADDED TO
MOUNT RUSHMORE.
AND WHILE THAT IS CLEARLY NOT
GOING TO HAPPEN... FOR ONE
THING, IT'S IMPOSSIBLE TO CARVE
STONE INTO WHATEVER FUCKING
SHAPE HIS HAIR IS... HE ALSO
DOESN'T NEED IT.
BECAUSE THIS IS HIS MONUMENT.
AND THERE'S PERHAPS NOTHING MORE
EMBLEMATIC OF HIS PRESIDENCY
THAN THIS WALL: IT'S
DESTRUCTIVE, POINTLESS,
INEFFECTIVE, RACIST, WEAK, AND
SOMETHING THE DAMAGES OF WHICH
WE'RE GOING TO BE DEALING WITH
FOR A VERY LONG TIME.
THAT'S OUR SHOW.
THANKS SO MUCH FOR WATCHING.
WE'LL SEE YOU NEXT WEEK,
GOOD NIGHT.
Subtitles Diego Moraes(oakislandtk)
www.opensubtitles.org
♪ ♪